<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-08-29T21:20:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="rmrp">https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/150081</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Sarampo - uma velha doença infantil a relembrar</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Measles - an old children's disease to remember</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Custódio, Marta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Strecht, Tânia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zelinová, Jana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marques, Anabela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Measles. Outbreak. Vaccine, MMR. Vaccination</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sarampo. Surtos de Doenças. Vacina SCR. Vacinação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O sarampo é uma doença viral grave e altamente contagiosa. O vírus do sarampo é um vírus de ARN, cadeia simples, do gênero Morbillivirus, da família Paramyxoviridae, transmitido pelas vias aéreas, através de gotículas de aerossóis ou por contato direto com secreções respiratórias de indivíduos infectados. A infecção é adquirida pelo contato dessas gotículas com a mucosa do trato respiratório ou conjuntiva. Em 2005, a Organização Mundial de Saúde estabeleceu que o objetivo para a erradicação do sarampo na Região Europeia seria até 2010 mas, apesar das medidas adotadas pelos diversos países, o sarampo ressurgiu, com 10271 casos relatados somente em 2013 em 30 estados da União Europeia, com mais de 91% deles na Alemanha, Itália, Holanda e Reino Unido. No início de 2017, Portugal foi ameaçado por um surto de sarampo, relatando nos primeiros cinco meses do ano 31 casos confirmados, 20 (65%) em adultos (com idade igual ou superior a 18), dos quais 45% (13) foram em profissionais de saúde. Face a este surto de sarampo ter tantos casos em adultos, os autores decidiram fazer uma breve revisão, tentando relembrar uma infeção antiga, não tão conhecida pelos médicos mais jovens e que pode ser esquecida na abordagem de um doente adulto. Os autores salientam igualmente que o vírus do sarampo pode virtualmente ser erradicado, pois existe uma vacina eficaz e não existe na natureza nenhum reservatório para o vírus, além dos humanos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Measles is a serious, highly contagious viral disease. The measles virus is a single-stranded, RNA virus of the genus Morbillivirus within the family Paramyxoviridae, transmitted by air, through droplets of aerosols or by direct contact with respiratory secretions of infected individuals. The infection is acquired through the mucosa of respiratory tract or conjunctiva. In 2005, the World Health Organization established that measles eradication in the European Region should be achieved by 2010, but despite the measures adopted by the various countries, measles re-emerged, with 10271 cases reported only in 2013 in 30 states of European Union, with more than 91% of them in Germany, Italy, Netherland and United Kingdom. In the beginning of 2017, Portugal was threatened with a measles outbreak, reporting in the first five months of the year 31 confirmed cases, 20 (65%) of them in adults (18 or older), of which 45% (13) were in health professionals. Because this measles outbreak had so many cases in adults, the authors decided to make a brief review, trying to remember an old infection, not so well known by younger doctors, and that can be overlooked in the approach of the adult patients. The authors also point out that measles virus could virtually be eradicated as there is an effective vaccine and there is no reservoir in nature for the virus other than humans.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-09-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150081</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v51i1p69-74</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 No. 1 (2018): jan./fev./mar.; 69-74</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 Núm. 1 (2018): jan./fev./mar.; 69-74</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 51 n. 1 (2018): jan./fev./mar.; 69-74</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150081/147156</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/150085</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Síndrome de Wilson: relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Wilson´s Disease: a case report</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silvério, Alessandra dos Santos Danziger</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Couto, Thaís dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Juliana Marília Pereira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Wilson's Diseas. Cooper. Hepatolenticular Degeneration. Penicillamine.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doença de Wilson. Cobre. Degeneração hepatolenticular. Penicilamina.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objectives: This report describes a rare genetic disorder, called Wilson’s Disease, inherited in an autosomal recessive form, with symptoms very easily confused with other diseases. The underlying cause of the clinical manifestations is the accumulation of copper in various compartments of the human body, especially in places such as liver, brain, kidneys and corneas, due to mutations in the ATP7B gene encoding Cu + 2 ATPase, a copper carrier protein which is located in the Golgi complex of hepatocytes. Liver changes may present as chronic hepatitis, cirrhosis and, more rarely, fulminant hepatitis. Neurological changes are variable, predominantly extrapyramidal symptoms, tremors, dystonia, dysarthria, mood changes, and psychiatric symptoms, if not treated, progressive decrease in intellectual capacity. One of the most extraordinary characteristics of this syndrome is the great variability of phenotypic manifestations in patients who have the same mutation. In the diagnosis of Wilson’s disease, several biochemical parameters are analyzed: serum ceruloplasmin, serum copper, urinary excretion of copper and hepatic copper concentration. In addition, an ophthalmologic examination is performed with Kayser-Fleischer rings observation. In order to complement and facilitate the diagnosis, genetic studies can be performed, since the symptoms and laboratory abnormalities can often be associated with other diseases. Treatment is based on the use of copper chelating drugs. D-penicillamine is the drug of choice, despite the risk of neurological worsening in up to 50% of patients and the various side effects associated with its use. Trientin and tetrathiomolybdate are alternative drugs, the latter being chosen for individuals with neurological symptoms. Zinc is indicated for asymptomatic or maintenance therapy. Early treatment prevents serious complications. Case report: A 14-year-old patient from Poço Fundo-MG sought medical attention because of frequent episodes of facial paralysis, especially in the mandibular region, leading to dysphagia and dysphonia, as well as irritability and gait abnormalities. She underwent magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), which showed “symmetrical signal changes in the bilaterally striatum, with signs of edema of the caudate nuclei and caudate nuclei, and atrophy of the pale globes.” In view of the family history of Wilson’s syndrome, a differential diagnosis was performed, by serum concentration of ceruloplasmin and serum and urinary copper, which showed typical changes in Wilson’s syndrome and ocular biomicroscopy, which verified the presence of the Kayser-Fleischer ring. The patient did not present previous liver disease, showing that the disease does not always present as expected, and reflects the difficulty in establishing an early diagnosis that may prevent the emergence of the first symptoms. All patients with Wilson’s syndrome require multidisciplinary care since it is a disease that can significantly affect various organs and systems.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivos: Este relato descreve um distúrbio genético raro, denominado de Síndrome de Wilson, herdado em caráter autossômico recessivo, com sintomas muito facilmente confundidos com outras doenças. A causa básica responsável pelas manifestações clínicas é o acúmulo de cobre em diversos compartimentos do organismo humano, especialmente em locais como fígado, cérebro, rins e córneas, devido a mutações no gene ATP7B que codifica a Cu+2 ATPase, uma proteína transportadora de cobre que está localizada no complexo de Golgi dos hepatócitos. As alterações hepáticas podem se apresentar como hepatite crônica, cirrose e, mais raramente, hepatite fulminante. As alterações neurológicas são variáveis, predominando os sintomas extrapiramidais, tremores, distonia, disartria, alterações de humor, sintomas psiquiátricos e, se não tratada, diminuição progressiva da capacidade intelectual. Uma das características mais extraordinárias dessa síndrome é a grande variabilidade de manifestações fenotípicas em pacientes que possuem a mesma mutação. No diagnóstico da doença de Wilson são analisados diversos parâmetros bioquímicos, sendo eles: ceruloplasmina sérica, cobre sérico, excreção urinária de cobre e concentração hepática de cobre. Além disso, realiza-se exame oftalmológico com a observação de anéis de Kayser – Fleischer. A fim de complementar e facilitar o diagnóstico podem ser realizados estudos genéticos, visto que muitas vezes os sintomas e alterações laboratoriais podem estar associados a outras doenças. O tratamento baseia-se no uso de drogas quelantes do cobre. A Dpenicilamina é a droga de escolha, apesar do risco de piora neurológica em até 50% dos pacientes e dos diversos efeitos colaterais associados ao seu uso. Trientina e tetratiomolibdato são drogas alternativas, sendo a última escolhida para indivíduos com sintomas neurológicos. O zinco tem indicação em assintomáticos ou em terapia de manutenção. O tratamento precoce evita graves complicações. Relato de caso: Paciente de 14 anos de idade, natural de Poço Fundo-MG, procurou atendimento médico por apresentar episódios frequentes de paralisia facial, principalmente na região mandibular, que levava à disfagia e disfonia, além de irritabilidade e anormalidades na marcha. Foi submetida ao exame de ressonância magnética que mostrou “alteração de sinal simétrica nos corpos estriados bilateralmente, com sinais de edema dos putâmens e núcleos caudados, e atrofia dos globos pálidos. Diante do histórico familiar para a síndrome de Wilson, foi realizado o diagnóstico diferencial, por meio da concentração de sérica de ceruloplasmina e cobre sérico e urinário, que mostraram alterações típicas da síndrome de Wilson e a biomicroscopia ocular que constatou a presença do anel de Kayser-Fleischer. Conclusões: Ainda há um longo caminho a ser seguido no que se diz respeito ao diagnóstico precoce da Síndrome de Wilson. Nesse caso, a paciente não apresentou hepatopatia pregressa. Isso mostra que a doença nem sempre se apresenta da forma esperada, e reflete a dificuldade de estabelecer um diagnóstico precoce que possa impedir o surgimento dos primeiros sintomas. Todos os portadores da síndrome de Wilson necessitam de atendimento multidisciplinar, por se tratar de uma doença que pode afetar de forma significativa vários órgãos e sistemas.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-09-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150085</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v51i1p75-81</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 No. 1 (2018): jan./fev./mar.; 75-81</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 Núm. 1 (2018): jan./fev./mar.; 75-81</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 51 n. 1 (2018): jan./fev./mar.; 75-81</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150085/147157</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/150087</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Reação cutânea paradoxal com tratamento com infliximabe</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Paradoxical skin reaction with infliximab treatment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fernandes, Larissa Starling de A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martinez, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lupi, Omar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Ricardo Barbosa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martins, Carlos José</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>D'`Acri, Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Psoriasis. Inflximab. anti-TNF. Paradoxical Reaction. Inflammatory Bowel Diseases.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Psoríase. Infliximabe. anti-TNF. Reação Paradoxal. Doenças Inflamatórias Intestinais.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Considering the increased utilization of anti-TNF medications in the treatment of inflammatory and autoimmune diseases, dermatologists should be aware of the possible adverse skin reactions. We describe a case of inverted psoriasis due to the use of infliximab used in the treatment of inflammatory bowel disease.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Com o aumento do uso de anti-TNF no tratamento de doenças inflamatórias e auto-imunes, os dermatologistasdevem estar conscientes da possibilidade de reações cutâneas adversas. Apresentamos umcaso de psoríase invertida devido ao uso de infliximab utilizado no tratamento da doença inflamatóriaintestinal.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-09-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150087</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v51i1p82-86</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 No. 1 (2018): jan./fev./mar.; 82-86</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 Núm. 1 (2018): jan./fev./mar.; 82-86</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 51 n. 1 (2018): jan./fev./mar.; 82-86</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150087/147158</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/150092</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Refl.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Uma experiência exitosa de meio século da Universidade de São Paulo junto à comunidade</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">A successful experience of half a century of the University of São Paulo with the community</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ferraz, Ivan Savioli</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Del Ciampo, Luiz Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Community-Institutional Relations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Universities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Primary Health Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Teaching</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Research</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Extensão Comunitária</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidades</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atenção Primária</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ensino</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pesquisa</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Extension is inseparable from university activities and a key link between academia and the community. The participation of the university in health care to the community may represent one of the most visible and at the same time sensitive aspects of university extension. The work of the University of São Paulo (USP) at the Community Social Medical Center “Vila Lobato” (CSMC "Vila Lobato") has been a successful experience of half a century in the community attended by this primary health care unit of Ribeirão Preto. Undergraduate students of both Medicine and Nutrition and Metabolism courses from Ribeirão Preto Medical School-USP (RPMS-USP) and also resident physicians from Clinics Hospital of RPMS-USP have provided health care to the local population. Undergraduate students from other schools from USP at Ribeirão Preto (dentistry, nursing and psychology) have also worked at the CSMC "Vila Lobato". Several research projects on health were carried out and many others has been developed in the unit, benefiting the community. This experience of half a century of USP with the CSMC “Vila Lobato” is a successful model in extension and it not only should be recognized in a genuine way in the academic institutions but also stimulated.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A extensão constitui-se em parte indissociável das atividades universitárias e elo fundamental da interface da academia com a comunidade. A participação da universidade na assistência à saúde da comunidade talvez represente uma das faces mais visíveis e, ao mesmo tempo, sensíveis da extensão universitária. A atuação da Universidade de São Paulo (USP) no Centro Médico Social Comunitário “Vila Lobato” (CMSC “Vila Lobato”) tem se constituído em uma experiência exitosa de meio século junto à comunidade servida por esta unidade básica de saúde de Ribeirão Preto. Alunos de graduação do curso de medicina e de nutrição e metabolismo da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto-USP (FMRP-USP) e, também, médicos residentes do Hospital das Clínicas da FMRP-USP têm prestado assistência à saúde à população local. Alunos de graduação de outras unidades do Campus de Ribeirão Preto da USP (odontologia, enfermagem e psicologia) também atuam no CMSC “Vila Lobato”. Inúmeros projetos de pesquisa na área da saúde foram e continuam sendo desenvolvidos na unidade, beneficiando a comunidade. A experiência de meio século da USP junto ao CMSC “Vila Lobato” constitui-se em modelo bem-sucedido de extensão universitária, devendo não somente ser reconhecido de forma genuína no meio acadêmico, mas também, estimulada.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-07-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150092</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v52i1p1-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. 1 (2019): jan./fev./mar.; 1-6</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. 1 (2019): jan./fev./mar.; 1-6</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. 1 (2019): jan./fev./mar.; 1-6</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150092/154317</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/150287</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:00:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeito do extrato aquoso de Cordyline Dracaenóides Kunth na cicatrização de lesões cutâneas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effect of aqueous extract of Cordyline Dracaenóides Kunth in wound healing of skin lesions</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kerppers, Ivo Ilvan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kerppers, Flavio Klinpovous</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Kesia Maria Mangoni Gonçalves dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cordeiro, Maria Elvira Ribeiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pereira, Mario César da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Wound Healing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Collagen</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Plant</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cicatrização</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Colágeno</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Planta</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Method of study: This is an experimental, randomized study. Introduction: The healing process is a dynamic set of important tissue changes involving inflammation and chemotaxis. Cordyline Dracaenoides Kunth, popularly known as Uvarana, is a plant that contributes to the healing process. Objective: In this context, this work aimed to verify the effects of the aqueous extract of Uvarana on the healing process. Method: The sample consisted of 42 Rattus norvegicus, Wistar rats divided into four experimental groups: Negative Control Group, Positive Control Group, Uvarana Group, and Fármaco Group, subdivided in 3 and 7 days. The animals were anesthetized with 80 mg/kg Ketamine and 15 mg/kg Xylazine and then placed in a ventral decubitus position on a surgical plank, after which a dorsal region tricotomy was performed and with a scalpel blade was made a 10mm incision. After the incision, wound closure was performed with nylon thread number 5.0. Results: It was observed that in the group in which the aqueous extract of Uvarana was applied, there was a regeneration of the epidermis with presence of crust, the dermal tissue presented inflammatory cells, the hypodermis had intense inflammation, the epidermis became thicker on the seventh day and the dermis presented regenerative collagen cells and scar closure. Conclusion: Based on this study, it can be concluded that the aqueous extract of Uvarana is a very effective method in the treatment of cutaneous lesions and has the capacity to accelerate the healing process.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Método de estudo: trata-se de um estudo experimental, randomizado. Introdução: O processo de cicatrização é um conjunto dinâmico de alterações teciduais importantes que envolve inflamação e quimiotaxia. A Cordyline Dracaenóides Kunth, conhecida popularmente como Uvarana, é uma planta que contribui com o processo de cicatrização. Objetivo: Nesse contexto, o objetivo desse trabalho foi verificar os efeitos do extrato aquoso de Uvarana no processo cicatricial. Método: A amostra foi composta por 42 ratos da raça Rattus norvegicus, Wistar, divididos em quatro grupos experimentais: Grupo Controle Negativo, Grupo Controle Positivo, Grupo Uvarana e Grupo Fármaco, subdivididos em 3 e 7 dias. Os animais foram anestesiados com 80 mg/kg de Ketamina e 15 mg/kg de Xilazina e, em seguida, foram posicionados em decúbito ventral sobre uma prancha cirúrgica. Após isso, foi realizada a tricotomia da região dorsal e com uma lâmina de bisturi, foi feita uma incisão de 10 mm. Após a incisão, foi realizado o fechamento da ferida com fio de nylon número 5.0. Resultados: Observou-se que, no grupo em que foi aplicado o extrato aquoso de Uvarana, houve uma regeneração da epiderme com presença de crosta, o tecido dérmico apresentou células inflamatórias, a hipoderme teve intensa inflamação, a epiderme ficou mais espessa ao sétimo dia e a derme apresentou células regenerativas de colágeno e fechamento da cicatriz. Conclusão: Com base nesse estudo, pode-se concluir que o extrato aquoso de Uvarana é um método bastante eficaz no tratamento de lesões cutâneas e tem a capacidade de acelerar o processo de cicatrização.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-12-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150287</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v52i4p267-275</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. 4 (2019): out./nov./dez.; 267-275</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. 4 (2019): out./nov./dez.; 267-275</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. 4 (2019): out./nov./dez.; 267-275</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150287/158401</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/150431</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:00:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Acessos cirúrgicos combinados para tratamento de fraturas em assoalho orbital e lâmina papirácea: relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Combined surgical accesses for treatment of fractures in the orbital floor and lamina papyracea: case report</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Verônica Cristine Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Streit-Junior, Rosalvo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Araújo, Juliana da Luz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Queiroz, Elisa Vasconcelos de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Krier, Felipe Carneiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Parreira, Diderot Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Durães, Rodrigo Tamietti</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Orbital Fractures</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Transconjunctival Access</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Transcaruncular Access</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fraturas Orbitárias</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acesso Transconjuntival</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acesso Transcaruncular</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A região orbitária é bastante suscetível a traumas, visto que apresenta uma posição exposta, além de ser composta por ossos frágeis. Quando indicada, é preciso intervenção cirúrgica para preservar a função visual e harmonia facial do paciente. Os acessos transconjuntival e transcaruncular são descritos na literatura como formas seguras, rápidas, funcionais e esteticamente benéficas para a abordagem ao assoalho orbitário e lâmina papirácea. Sobre os materiais biocompatíveis utilizados, a placa de titânio é inabsorvível e permite fixação interna rígida, sendo moldada às curvaturas naturais dos ossos, com baixo risco de infecção. As folhas de polietileno poroso são polímeros inertes e não absorvíveis que facilitam o crescimento de tecido e reduzem as chances de rejeição. Nesse relato de caso, evidencia-se paciente masculino, 28 anos, vítima de traumatismo facial após prática esportiva que apresentou fratura de assoalho e parede medial orbitária direita, sendo indicada reconstrução orbitária com acessos transconjuntival e transcaruncular para fixação de placa de titânio em assoalho da órbita direita e de folhas de polietileno poroso em lâmina papirácea à direita, respectivamente.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The orbital region is quite susceptible to trauma, since it has an exposed position, besides being composed of fragile bones. When indicated, surgical intervention is required to preserve the patient's visual function and facial harmony. Transconjunctival and transcaruncular accesses are described in the literature as safe, fast, functional and aesthetically beneficial for the approach to the orbital floor and papyraceous lamina. On the biocompatible materials used, the titanium plate is inabsorbable and allows rigid internal fixation, being shaped to the natural curvatures of the bones, with low risk of infection. Porous polyethylene sheets are inert and nonabsorbable polymers that facilitate tissue growth and reduce the chances of rejection. In this case report, a 28-year-old male patient, a victim of facial trauma after sports practice, presented a fracture of the floor and the right orbital medial wall, and orbital reconstruction was indicated with transconjunctival and transcaruncular accesses for fixation of titanium plate in the floor of the right orbit and porous polyethylene sheets in papyracea leaf on the right, respectively.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-07-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150431</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v52i1p54-59</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. 1 (2019): jan./fev./mar.; 54-59</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. 1 (2019): jan./fev./mar.; 54-59</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. 1 (2019): jan./fev./mar.; 54-59</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150431/154318</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/150568</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:00:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Acute hepatic failure as presentation of Non Hodgkin lymphoma</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Insuficiência hepática aguda como apresentação de linfoma não-Hodgkin</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jesus, Gustavo Nobre de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Anselmo, Mónica Palma</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Inês</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Quadros, Catarina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, João Madeira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meneses, João</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Victorino, Rui Maria Manoel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Acute Hepatic Failure</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Immunosuppression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Falência Hepática Aguda</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Linfoma não-Hodgkin</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Imunossupressão</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Acute hepatic failure (AHF) consists of a sudden appearance of coagulopathy and hepatic encephalopathy in a patient with no previous hepatic disease. &amp;nbsp;Although the liver is the most affected organ in cancer dissemination, AHF is rare and appears essentially in cancer terminal stages. Even rarer is AHF as an initial finding of cancer. We present a case of a 39 year-old HIV positive patient in whom AHF was the initial manifestation of a non-Hodgkin lymphoma.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Insuficiência Hepática Aguda (IHA) consiste no aparecimento súbito de coagulopatia e encefalopatia hepática em doente sem doença hepática prévia. Embora o fígado seja afectado por metastização, a IHA costuma ser incomum e surgir apenas nos estadios terminais da doença. Apesar de a IHA ser uma forma rara de apresentação de neoplasias, tem sido observada em neoplasias hematológicas, nomeadamente na doença de Hodgkin e linfoma não-Hodgkin difuso de grandes células, B especialmente em doentes imunossuprimidos. É relatado um caso de um doente de 39 anos, vírus da imunodeficiência humana (VIH) 1 postivo, cuja manifestação inaugural de um linfoma não-Hodgkin foi IHA.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-12-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150568</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v52i4p339-342</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. 4 (2019): out./nov./dez.; 339-342</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. 4 (2019): out./nov./dez.; 339-342</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. 4 (2019): out./nov./dez.; 339-342</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150568/158399</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/150582</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-14T18:21:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Incidência de near miss neonatal em uma maternidade de médio porte do Nordeste Brasileiro</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Incidence of neonatal near miss in a midsize maternity in the Northeast Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cantalice, Anajás da Silva Cardoso</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Karlla Kellyane Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Lucian Batista de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neonatology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Intensive Care Units, Neonatal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Indicators of Morbidity and Mortality</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Near Miss, Healthcare</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neonatologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Unidades de Terapia Intensiva Neonatal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Indicadores de Morbimortalidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Near Miss</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Verificar a incidência de near miss neonatal (NMN), indicador de “quase morte” por complicações pré ou pós-natais, em uma maternidade de médio porte no Nordeste brasileiro. Modelo do estudo: Coorte retrospectiva, com abordagem indutiva e procedimentos descritivos. Metodologia: Analisou-se prontuários de nascidos no mês de janeiro de 2016, identificando-se os casos de NMN conforme os seguintes critérios: idade gestacional &amp;lt; 32 semanas, recém-nascido (RN) que necessitou de manobra de reanimação ou deprimido, peso ao nascimento &amp;lt; 1500 g, necessidade de cuidados em unidade de terapia intensiva neonatal (UTIN), necessidade de ventilação mecânica, escore de Apgar no 1º e 5º minutos &amp;lt;&amp;nbsp;7. Para verificar a associação entre as variáveis maternas e o diagnóstico de NMN, foi utilizado o teste t de Student. Resultados: Foram avaliados 120 RN. Dentre eles, 26 nascidos de parto normal e 94 de parto cesáreo. A média de idade materna foi de 26,61 (±7,9). A maioria das genitoras apresentava doenças cardiovasculares (71,7%) e 70,8% pré-natal com número de consultas inferior a sete. Identificou-se uma incidência de 30% de NMN, sendo a maioria do sexo masculino (55%). A taxa de internação na UTIN foi de 17,5%. O menor número de filhos vivos e médias superiores de partos cesáreos apresentaram associação significativa (p &amp;lt; 0,05) com o NMN. Conclusão: O indicador de NMN apresentou uma elevada incidência, mesmo em hospital de referência para gestação de alto risco, sendo um método de grande relevância para avaliação e prevenção de morbidades graves do RN.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Verifying the incidence of neonatal near miss (NNM), an indicator of "near-death" due to pre or postnatal complications, in a medium-sized maternity hospital in the Northeast of Brazil. Study model: retrospective cohort, with an inductive approach and descriptive procedures. Method: Birth charts were analyzed during January 2016, and NNM cases were identified according to the following criteria: gestational age &amp;lt; 32 weeks, newborn (NB) requiring resuscitation or depressed maneuver, birth weight &amp;lt; 1500 g, need for care in a neonatal intensive care unit (NICU), need for mechanical ventilation, Apgar score at 1 and 5 minutes ≤ 7. To verify the association between maternal variables and NMN diagnosis the Student's t-test was used. Results: 120 NB were evaluated. Among them, 26 born of normal birth and 94 of cesarean delivery. The mean maternal age was 26.61 (± 7.9). The majority of the mothers had cardiovascular diseases (71.7%) and 70.8% had a prenatal visit with several consultations below seven. An incidence of 30% of NNM was observed, most of them male (55 %). The hospitalization rate in the NICU was 17.5%. The lower number of live children and higher mean cesarean births had a significant association (p &amp;lt;0.05) with the NNM. Conclusion: The NNM indicator presented a high incidence, even in a reference hospital for a high-risk pregnancy, being a highly relevant method for the evaluation and prevention of severe morbidity in the NB.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-04-27</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i1p1-7</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 1 (2020): jan./fev./mar.; 1-7</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 1 (2020): jan./fev./mar.; 1-7</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 1 (2020): jan./fev./mar.; 1-7</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150582/160354</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Anajás da Silva Cardoso Cantalice, Karlla Kellyane Alves Carvalho, Lucian Batista de Oliveira</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/150661</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:00:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Mortality prognostic factors associated with SAPS 3 and APACHE II in elderly patients admitted in intensive care unit</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores prognósticos associados ao SAPS 3 e APACHE II em pacientes idosos admitidos em unidade de terapia intensiva</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lucena, Marcus Vinícius Ferraz de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos-Veloso, Marcelo Antônio Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Xavier, Geylson Rodrigo dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Inácio Borges</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moraes, Felipe de Castro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lucena, Renata Amorim de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lucena, Letícia Amorim de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Markman Filho, Brivaldo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Sandro Gonçalves de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Prognostic Factors</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Mortality</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Elderly</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Intensive Care Unit</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">SAPS 3</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">APACHE II</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores Prognósticos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Mortalidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idosos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Unidade de Terapia Intensiva</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">SAPS 3</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">APACHE II</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study design: a descriptive, prospective cohort study. Objectives: identify the risk factors associated with SAPS 3 and APACHE II score to improve mortality prediction in elderly admitted in the intensive care unit (ICU). Methodology: a cohort study with 174 elderly patients admitted in ICU from July 2016 to June 2017. The primary independent variables analyzed were: presence of stress hyperglycemia, the need for invasive mechanical ventilation (IMV), acute renal failure, level of consciousness and use of vasopressors. The outcomes studied were death and hospital discharge. Results: ICU and hospital mortality were 17.8% and 29.8%, respectively. The multivariate analysis of factors associated with hospital death not contemplated in the obtaining of SAPS 3 demonstrated that IMV, Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) and Mean Arterial Pressure (MAP) &amp;lt;70 mmHg improved the prediction of mortality. The Hosmer-Lemeshow test (p=0.472) and area under ROC curve=0.80 (CI95%:0.731-0.872) confirmed, respectively, an appropriate calibration and acceptable-to-excellent discriminatory power for this model. IMV and COPD were also factors associated with the APACHE II score in prediction of mortality with appropriated calibration (p=0.471) and acceptable-to-excellent discriminatory power (area under ROC curve=0.80 [CI95%:0.730-0.868]). Conclusion: IMV, COPD, and MAP &amp;lt;70 mmHg were associated with SAPS3 and APACHE II to predict mortality in elderly admitted to ICU.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo de estudo: estudo descritivo, coorte prospectiva. Objetivos: identificar os fatores de risco associados ao escore SAPS 3 e APACHE II para melhorar a predição de mortalidade em idosos internados em unidade de terapia intensiva (UTI). Metodologia:&amp;nbsp;estudo de coorte com 174 idosos internados em UTI no período de julho de 2016 a junho de 2017. As principais variáveis ​​independentes analisadas foram: presença de hiperglicemia de estresse, necessidade de ventilação mecânica invasiva (VMI), insuficiência renal aguda, nível de consciência e uso de vasopressores. Os desfechos estudados foram morte e alta hospitalar. Resultados: A mortalidade na UTI e hospitalar foi de 17,8% e 29,8%, respectivamente. A análise multivariada de fatores associados à morte hospitalar não contemplada na obtenção do SAPS 3 demonstrou que a VMI, Doença Pulmonar Obstrutiva Crônica (DPOC) e Pressão Arterial Média (PAM) &amp;lt;70 mmHg melhoraram a predição de mortalidade. O teste de Hosmer-Lemeshow (p = 0,472) e a área sob curva ROC = 0,80 (IC95%: 0,731-0,872) confirmaram, respectivamente, calibração adequada e poder discriminatório aceitável a excelente para este modelo. VMI e DPOC também foram fatores associados ao escore APACHE II na predição de mortalidade com calibração adequada (p = 0,471) e poder discriminatório aceitável-a-excelente (área sob curva ROC = 0,80 [IC95%: 0,730-0,868]). Conclusão: VMI, DPOC e PAM &amp;lt;70 mmHg foram associados ao SAPS3 e ao APACHE II para predizer mortalidade em idosos internados em UTI.&amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-12-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150661</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v52i4p277-285</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. 4 (2019): out./nov./dez.; 277-285</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. 4 (2019): out./nov./dez.; 277-285</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. 4 (2019): out./nov./dez.; 277-285</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/150661/158318</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/151046</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Encefalopatia por deficiência de glut-1: relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Encephalopathy by glut-1 deficiency: case report</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Simões, Renato Arantes Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nabhan, Thaís</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Delatore, Lara Godela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gazola, Roberta Molinari</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Albuquerque, Regina Celia Ajeje Pires de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fernandes, Debora de Cassia Tomaz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epilepsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Diet, Ketogenic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Glucose Transport Proteins, Facilitative</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epilepsia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dieta Cetogênica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Proteínas Facilitadoras de Transporte de Glucose</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Importância do problema: A síndrome da deficiência do transportador de glicose tipo 1 (GLUT1DS), descrita pela primeira vez por De Vivo em 1991, é causada por um deficitário transporte de glicose na barreira hematoencefálica e astrócitos por mutações&amp;nbsp;na maioria das vezes&amp;nbsp;de novo&amp;nbsp;heterozigóticas no gene SLC2A1, responsável pela codificação do transportador de glicose tipo 1 (GLUT-1). Esta mutação limita a disponibilidade de glicose cerebral levando a sua deficiência energética, sendo o mecanismo gerador de suas manifestações clínicas. Os&amp;nbsp;sintomas sugestivos são convulsões,&amp;nbsp;atraso no desenvolvimento,&amp;nbsp;microcefalia, hipotonia, espasticidade e complexas alterações no movimento consistindo de ataxia e distonia. Em pacientes GLUT1DS, substratos energéticos alternativos são de fundamental importância. Inúmeros trabalhos recomendam a utilização da dieta cetogênica de maneira imperiosa como mecanismo padrão ouro de tratamento. Esta, nos primeiros anos de vida em pacientes com GLUT1DS, garante um melhor resultado cognitivo e melhora nos aspectos psicomotores. Comentários: A GLUT1DS por ser uma doença de recente descoberta, poucos casos descritos na literatura, características clínicas heterogêneas e falta substancial de casuística é muitas vezes subdiagnosticada. Neste sentido, critérios de suspeição e algoritmos diagnósticos se fazem necessários. Desta maneira, o objetivo deste artigo é chamar a atenção da comunidade médica brasileira a essa síndrome com vistas a incrementar seu diagnóstico e melhorar o prognóstico de epilepsias de difícil controle.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Glut-1 deficiency syndrome (GLUT1DS), first described by De Vivo in 1991, is caused by a deficient glucose transport in the blood brain barrier and astrocytes by mutations mostly de novo heterozygous in the SLC2A1 gene encoding the glucose transporter type 1 (GLUT-1). This mutation limits the availability of cerebral glucose leading to energy deficiency, being the mechanism that generates its clinical manifestations. The suggestive symptoms are convulsions, developmental delay, microcephaly, hypotonia, spasticity, and complex changes in movement consisting of ataxia and dystonia. In GLUT1DS patients, alternative energy substrates are of fundamental importance. Numerous studies recommend the use of the ketogenic diet in an imperative manner as a gold standard treatment method. This, in the first years of life in patients with GLUT1DS, guarantees a better cognitive result and improvement in psychomotor aspects. Because GLUT1DS is a disease of recent discovery, few cases described in the literature, heterogeneous clinical features and substantial lack of casuistry is often underdiagnosed. Due to this, suspicion criteria and diagnostic algorithms become necessary. Thus, the purpose of this article is to draw the attention of the Brazilian medical community to this syndrome with a view to increasing its diagnosis and improving the prognosis of difficult-to-control epilepsy.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-07-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151046</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v52i1p65-71</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. 1 (2019): jan./fev./mar.; 65-71</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. 1 (2019): jan./fev./mar.; 65-71</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. 1 (2019): jan./fev./mar.; 65-71</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151046/154320</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/151302</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:00:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Diagnóstico intraoperatório de paraganglioma retroperitoneal em massa abdominal: relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Intraoperative diagnosis of retroperitoneal paraganglioma in abdominal mass: case report</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Macêdo, Anna Flávia Magalhães Castrillon de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Camila Fernandes Álvares da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gomes, Ricardo da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Evandro Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Coutinho, Sandra Lucia Branco Mendes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Paraganglioma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Retroperitoneal Paraganglioma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pheochromocytoma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Differential Diagnosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paraganglioma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paraganglioma Retroperitoneal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Feocromocitoma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diagnóstico Diferencial</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study design: case report; Relevance of the Problem: we herein report the case of a 40-year-old male patient, presented with pain in the left lumbar region for six months, with no palpable masses in the region and no retroperitoneal masses detected upon abdominal ultrasonography. The diagnostic investigation revealed, through Computed Tomography scans of the abdomen, an image of retroperitoneal lesion attached medially to the aorta artery, with the presumed diagnosis of Retroperitoneal Sarcoma and, consequently, indication for surgical treatment. During the intraoperative period, the patient presented adrenergic symptoms, which ceased after complete resection of the lesion and ligation of part of the tumor adhesions to the retroperitoneum. The biopsy revealed a Retroperitoneal Paraganglioma. The aforementioned case study illustrates the importance of including Paraganglioma as a differential diagnosis of retroperitoneal tumors, given its rarity, difficult diagnosis, and clinical importance. Comments: Paragangliomas, often called extra-adrenal pheochromocytomas, are rare, mostly benign, catecholamine-producing tumors originating from Autonomic Nervous System and neural crest cells1. The classic symptoms of these tumors, due to secretory capacity, include palpitations, headaches, and diaphoresis, associated with Arterial Hypertension (AHT).</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: relato de caso; Importância do Problema: O presente relato de caso tem como objetivo relatar o caso de paciente do sexo masculino, 40 anos, com quadro de dor em região lombar esquerda há seis meses, sem massas palpáveis e sem achados de massas retroperitoneais à Ultrassonografia de abdome. A investigação diagnóstica constatou, através de Tomografia Computadorizada de abdome, imagem de lesão retroperitoneal acoplada medialmente à artéria aorta, com suposto diagnóstico de Sarcoma Retroperitoneal e, por conseguinte, indicação de tratamento cirúrgico. Durante o período intraoperatório, o paciente apresentou sintomas adrenérgicos, que cessaram após a ressecção completa da lesão e ligadura de parte das aderências do tumor ao retroperitônio. A biópsia evidenciou se tratar de um Paraganglioma Retroperitoneal. A partir do estudo de caso supracitado, é possível perceber a importância de incluir o Paraganglioma como diagnóstico diferencial de tumores retroperitoneais, em consequência de sua raridade, difícil diagnóstico e importância clínica. Comentários: Os Paragangliomas, frequentemente chamados de feocromocitomas extra-adrenais, são tumores raros, na sua maioria benignos, produtores de catecolaminas, com origem em células provenientes do Sistema Nervoso Autônomo e das células da crista neural.1 A sintomatologia clássica desses tumores, em função da capacidade secretora, inclui palpitações, cefaleias e diaforese, associados a Hipertensão Arterial (HTA).</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-12-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151302</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v52i4p343-347</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. 4 (2019): out./nov./dez.; 343-347</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. 4 (2019): out./nov./dez.; 343-347</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. 4 (2019): out./nov./dez.; 343-347</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151302/158400</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/151363</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:00:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="es-ES">Método INTERMED para pacientes con trastornos mentales: revisión integrativa de la literatura</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Método INTERMED para pacientes com transtornos mentais: revisão integrativa da literatura</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The INTERMED method for patients with mental disorders: integrative literature review</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Reigota, Sabrina Martins</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Azevedo-Marques, João Mazzoncini de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Camila Almeida de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Camargo, Lisa Laredo de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zanetti, Ana Carolina Guidorizzi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Nursing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Psychiatric Nursing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Mental Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Mental Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Integrality in Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Delivery of Health Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Nursing Assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Diagnosis of Health Situation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Enfermagem</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Enfermagem Psiquiátrica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde Mental</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos Mentais</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Integralidade em Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Assistência à Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação em Enfermagem</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diagnóstico da Situação de Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: Revisão integrativa da literatura. Objetivo: Analisar evidências científicas disponíveis na literatura sobre a utilização do método INTERMED pela equipe multidisciplinar em pacientes com transtornos mentais. Metodologia: A seleção de artigos foi realizada nas bases de dados National Library of Medicine (PubMed), American Psychological Association (PsycINFO), Literatura Latino-Americana e do Caribe em Ciências da Saúde (LILACS) e Scientific Eletronic Library Online (SciELO). Resultados: Ao final, cinco estudos concentrados entre 2000 e 2008, foram selecionados para análise. Os artigos analisados mostraram que o método INTERMED teve resultados positivos na identificação de pacientes que precisam de cuidados complexos, o que direcionou a realização de intervenções psiquiátricas rápidas que diminuíram o tempo de permanência no ambiente hospitalar, o número de internações melhorou a qualidade de vida dos pacientes e, consequentemente, diminuiu custos com a saúde. Conclusão: Os estudos analisados mostraram que há poucas evidências sobre o tema investigado. O método INTERMED tem boa aplicabilidade junto a outros instrumentos e foi eficaz na identificação de pacientes que precisam de cuidados complexos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study design: Integrative literature review. Purpose: Analyzing the scientific evidence available in the literature about the use of the INTERMED method by the multidisciplinary team in patients with mental disorders. Method: The selection of articles was performed using the National Library of Medicine (PubMed), American Psychological Association (PsycINFO), Latin American and Caribbean Literature in Health Sciences (LILACS) and Scientific Electronic Library Online (SciELO). Results: Five studies, published between 2000 and 2008, were selected for analysis. The data analyzed highlights that the INTERMED method had positive results in the identification of patients who needed complex care, which led to the implementation of rapid psychiatric interventions that reduced the length of staying in the hospital environment, the number of hospitalizations, improved the quality of life of the patients and consequently decreased health costs. Conclusion: We may affirm that there is little evidence on the subject investigated. The INTERMED method has good applicability with other instruments and has been effective in identifying patients who need complex care.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-07-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151363</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v52i2p136-143</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. 2 (2019): abr./maio/jun.; 136-143</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. 2 (2019): abr./maio/jun.; 136-143</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. 2 (2019): abr./maio/jun.; 136-143</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151363/154849</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/151547</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:00:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Vaginal Schwannoma: report of a rare clinical case</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Schwannoma vaginal: a propósito de um caso clínico raro</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Aidos, Joana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Sónia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Raposo, Joana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Teresa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martins, Nuno Nogueira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martins, Francisco Nogueira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Schwannomas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Tumors</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Peripheral Nerves</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Schwannomas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tumores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Nervos Periféricos</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Schwannomas do trato genital feminino são extremamente raros. São tumores geralmente benignos e a excisão simples é o tratamento adequado. Neste artigo descreve-se o caso de uma mulher de 57 anos com schwannoma vaginal, além de uma revisão resumida da literatura sobre schwannomas no trato genital feminino. A excisão completa foi realizada e o estudo histológico confirmou o diagnóstico de schwannoma vaginal. Devido à sua possibilidade de ocorrer, mesmo num cenário de incidência muito baixa, os schwannomas não devem ser excluídos do diagnóstico diferencial de massas vaginais.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Schwannomas of the female genital tract are extremely uncommon. They are usually benign, and simple excision is the adequate treatment. The case of a 57-year-old woman with a cellular schwannoma of the vagina is described, in addition to a summarized literature review of schwannomas in the female genital tract. Complete excision was performed, and the histological report confirmed to be a vaginal schwannoma. Due to its possibility to occur, even if in a very low incidence scenario, schwannomas should not be excluded from the differential diagnosis of a vaginal mass.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-07-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151547</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v52i2p156-159</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. 2 (2019): abr./maio/jun.; 156-159</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. 2 (2019): abr./maio/jun.; 156-159</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. 2 (2019): abr./maio/jun.; 156-159</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151547/154892</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/151588</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:00:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Paroxysmal non-kinesigenic dyskinesia: case report</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Discinesia paroxística não cinesiogênica: relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Delatore, Lara Godela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Simões, Renato Arantes Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gazola, Roberta Molinari</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Albuquerque, Regina Celia Ajeje Pires de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fernandes, Débora de Cássia Tomaz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Dyskinesias</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Movement Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Anticonvulsants</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Chorea</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Caffeine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Clinical Diagnosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Discinesias</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos dos Movimentos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Anticonvulsivantes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Coreia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cafeína</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diagnóstico Clínico</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: Relato de caso.&amp;nbsp;Importância do problema e comentários: A discinesia paroxística não cinesiogênica é um tipo de discinesia paroxística. É caracterizada por movimentos involuntários unilaterais ou bilaterais, do tipo coreico, distônico, balístico ou misto. É uma desordem rara e o diagnóstico precoce é crucial para seu tratamento e melhoria na qualidade de vida do indivíduo. O presente estudo relata um caso de Discinesia Paroxística Não Cinesiogênica e seus achados clínicos, além de apresentar breve revisão da literatura.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study type: Case report.&amp;nbsp;Relevance and comments: Paroxysmal non-kinesigenic dyskinesia is a type of paroxysmal dyskinesia. It is characterized by involuntary unilateral or bilateral movements, of the choreic, dystonic, ballistic or mixed type. It is a rare disorder and the early diagnosis is crucial for the treatment and improvement of the individual's quality of life. The present report illustrates a case of paroxysmal non-kinesigenic dyskinesia and clinical findings, as well as a brief review of the literature.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-07-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151588</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v52i2p150-155</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. 2 (2019): abr./maio/jun.; 150-155</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. 2 (2019): abr./maio/jun.; 150-155</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. 2 (2019): abr./maio/jun.; 150-155</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151588/154851</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/151774</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:00:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiological profile of hypospadia in the Bragantina region of the estate of São Paulo, Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil epidemiológico da hipospádia na região Bragantina do estado de São Paulo, Brasil</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Conrado, Marco Aurélio Veiga</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Conrado, André Luiz Veiga</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Cibele</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silvestre, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Izzo, Pedro</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hypospadias</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Malformations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Bragança Paulista</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hipospadia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Malformações</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Bragança Paulista</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study model: a Prevalence study. Objective: Evaluating the epidemiological profile of hypospadias cases assisted in the Hospital São Francisco na Providência de Deus of the Universidade São Francisco (HUSF), Bragança Paulista, Brazil, in the last 10 years (2007-2017), relating the types of hypospadias with associated malformations and age at the first corrective surgery. Methodology: A survey of hypospadias cases assisted between 2007 and 2017 in HUSF was carried out with patients from the Bragantina region of the state of São Paulo. The types of hypospadias were related to the associated malformations. The following data were collected from the medical records: type of hypospadias, age at first surgery, ultrasound imaging, ethnicity, place of birth, associated malformation. Data were statistically analyzed using Chi-squared, F-test and Kruskal-Wallis tests. Results: In 1401 pediatric assistances, it was found 45 cases of hypospadias with a prevalence of 0.7/1000 births. From the total, 29 cases were classified as distal, six cases of medium, and 10 cases as proximal types [F-test (2.8)=5.552, P=0.003, χ2=9.3117, P=0.009]. Cases of distal hypospadias had 16 associated malformations, and for medial and proximal types there were seven associated malformations in each one (KW=3.322, P=0.19). The largest number of cases was surgically corrected between three and four years of age. Conclusion: Distal hypospadias were the most prevalent in the Bragantina region in the last 10 years. It was also observed that the age at first surgery is in disagreement with the range proposed for the corrective approach of hypospadias.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo de estudo: Estudo de prevalência. Objetivo do estudo: Avaliar o perfil epidemiológico dos casos de hipospádia atendidos no Hospital São Francisco na Providência de Deus da Universidade São Francisco (HUSF), Bragança Paulista/SP nos últimos 10 anos (2007-2017), relacionando os tipos de hipospádia com as malformações associadas e idade à primeira cirurgia corretiva. Metodologia: Foi realizado um levantamento de casos de hipospádia atendidos entre 2007 e 2017 no HUSF, com pacientes oriundos das cidades da Região Bragantina do estado de São Paulo. Os tipos de hipospádia foram relacionados com as malformações associadas. Foram pesquisados nos prontuários: tipo de hipospádia, idade à primeira cirurgia, laudo de exame ultrassonográfico, etnia, local de nascimento e malformação associada. Os dados foram analisados estatisticamente utilizando os testes Qui-quadrado, teste F e de Kruskal-Wallis. Resultados: Em 1401 atendimentos pediátricos no período avaliado, foram encontrados 45 casos de hipospádia com prevalência igual a 0,7/1000 nascidos vivos. Do total de casos, 29 foram classificados como do tipo distal, seis casos de hipospádia média e 10 casos do tipo proximal [F-test (2,8)=5,552; P=0,003; χ2=9,3117; P=0,009]. Nos casos de hipospádia distal, foram detectadas 16 malformações associadas e, nos tipos média e proximal, foram observadas sete malformações associadas em cada uma (KW=3,322, P=0,19). O maior número de casos foi abordado cirurgicamente no intervalo entre os três e quatro anos de idade. Conclusão: A hipospádia distal foi a mais prevalente, com idade à primeira cirurgia em desacordo com o intervalo proposto para a correção da hipospádia.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-11-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151774</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v52i3p171-177</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. 3 (2019): jul./ago./set.; 171-177</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. 3 (2019): jul./ago./set.; 171-177</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. 3 (2019): jul./ago./set.; 171-177</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151774/157425</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/151880</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Agenesia do lobo direito hepático: um achado incomum nos exames de diagnóstico por imagem</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Agenesis of the right hepatic lobe: an unusual finding in imaging diagnostic exams</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Queiroz, Rodolfo Mendes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Urbano, Cristina Jorge</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Fernanda Catib Costa Pires de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mello, Denise Fabri Rezende Engracia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Queiroz, Michela Gomes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nery, Breno</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Abdala, Ronaldo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bernardes-Filho, Fred</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Diagnostic Imaging</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Liver</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Agenesis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hypertension, Portal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hepatectomy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diagnóstico por Imagem</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fígado</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Agenesia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hipertensão Portal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hepatectomia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Hepatic lobar agenesis is an uncommon condition observed in 1/19000 autopsies and may be more rare in the case of the right lobe, with close to 40 cases reported in the literature. Its diagnosis is based on the non-identification of the hepatic duct, the corresponding portal and hepatic veins. We describe a case of right hepatic lobe agenesis as found in abdominal imaging in a 63-year-old woman with chronic diffuse abdominal discomfort and laboratory findings of a slight elevation of liver enzymes.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A agenesia lobar hepática é uma condição incomum, observada em 1/19000 autopsias e podendo ser mais rara em se tratando do lobo direito, com números próximos de 40 casos relatados na literatura. O seu diagnóstico se baseia na não identificação do ducto hepático, das veias hepática e portal correspondentes. Descrevemos um caso de uma agenesia do lobo direito hepático como achado em exames de imagem abdominais em uma mulher de 63 anos com queixa de desconforto abdominal difuso crônico e apresentando laboratorialmente discreta elevação das enzimas hepáticas.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-07-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151880</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v52i1p60-64</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. 1 (2019): jan./fev./mar.; 60-64</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. 1 (2019): jan./fev./mar.; 60-64</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. 1 (2019): jan./fev./mar.; 60-64</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/151880/154319</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/152008</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:EDT</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Frei exemplo é o melhor educador</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ballejo, Gustavo</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-11-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152008</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v51i2p87-88</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 No. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 87-88</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 Núm. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 87-88</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 51 n. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 87-88</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152008/148795</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/152010</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Association between self-efficacy and sociodemographic and clinical variables in patients with Diabetes Mellitus</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Associação entre autoeficácia e variáveis sociodemográficas e clínicas em pacientes com Diabetes Mellitus</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nascimento, Renata Aparecida do</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pedrosa, Rafaela Batista dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Trevisan, Danilo Donizetti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Maria Helena de Melo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>São-joão, Thais Moreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Roberta Cunha Matheus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Diabetes Mellitus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Self Efficacy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cross-Sectional Studies</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Nursing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diabetes Mellitus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Autoeficácia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudos Transversais</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Enfermagem</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Model of study: A cross-sectional study was conducted. Objective: to evaluate the association between self-efficacy and socio-demographic and clinical variables in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM). Method: The sample was composed by 111 patients with T2DM in use of insulin, in primary health care units and outpatient setting in the southeast region of São Paulo state, Brazil. Sociodemographic data were gathered using validated questionnaire and clinical data were obtained from medical and health records. Self-efficacy was assessed by the Brazilian version of Insulin Management Diabetes Self-Efficacy Scale (IMDSES). The data were submitted to descriptive and comparative analyses using Mann-Whitney and Kruskal-Wallis to verify association between socio-demographic/clinical variables and self-efficacy. Results: Self-efficacy was associated with schooling level and presence of comorbidities, such as coronary artery disease, dyslipidemia, obesity, peripheral arterial disease and peripheral neuropathy. Conclusion: The findings provide support to the design some specifics interventions aimed at improving the selfefficacy of patients with T2DM on insulin use.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: Foi conduzido um estudo transversal. Objetivo: verificar a associação entre autoeficácia e variáveis sociodemográficas e clínicas em pacientes com diabetes mellitus. Métodos: A amostra foi composta por 111 pacientes com diabetes mellitus tipo 2 em uso de insulina em unidade básica de saúde e em ambulatório de hospital universitário da região sudeste do Estado de São Paulo, Brasil. Os dados sociodemográficos foram coletados usando questionário validado e os dados clínicos foram obtidos dos prontuários do hospital e da unidade básica de saúde. A medida da autoeficácia foi obtida por meio da aplicação da Insulin Management Diabetes Self-Efficacy Scale – IMDSES. Para verificar a associação entre as variáveis sociodemográficas / clínicas e a autoeficácia foram utilizados os testes de Mann-Whitney e Kruskal-Wallis. Resultados: A autoeficácia foi associada à escolaridade, presença de comorbidades e complicações do DM, como doença arterial coronária, obesidade, doença arterial periférica e neuropatia periférica. Conclusão: Os achados subsidiam o delineamento de intervenções para otimizar a autoeficácia em pacientes com diabetes mellitus em uso de insulina.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-11-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v51i2p112-120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 No. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 112-120</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 Núm. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 112-120</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 51 n. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 112-120</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152010/148797</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/152013</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Propriedades psicométricas da versão brasileira “Escala de auto-eficácia no manejo da insulina” em pacientes com diabetes mellitus tipo 2</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Psychometric performance of the Brazilian version the “Insulin Management Diabetes Self-Efficacy Scale” for patient with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pedrosa, Rafaela Batista dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Trevisan, Danilo Donizetti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nascimento, Renata Aparecida do</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>São-João, Thaís Moreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Maria Helena de Melo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Roberta Cunha Matheus</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Self Efficacy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Validation Studies</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Nursing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Questionnaires</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Psychometric Properties</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diabetes Mellitus Tipo 2</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Autoeficácia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudos de Validação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Enfermagem</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Questionários</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Propriedades Psicométricas</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo de estudo: estudo de validação. Objetivo: Avaliar o desempenho psicométrico da versão brasileira “Escala de Auto-eficácia no manejo da insulina” - IMDSES. Metodologia: A confiabilidade (consistência interna - α Cronbach), a validade convergente e a validade de critério foram avaliadas. Os dados foram coletados de 127 pacientes com diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2) em uso de insulina por meio da aplicação de instrumentos sociodemográficos e clínicos e as versões brasileiras “Summary of Diabetes Self-Care Activities Measures” - SDSCA and the IMDSES. Resultados: Observou-se “efeito de teto” no domínio da insulina. A confiabilidade foi confirmada em todos os domínios do IMDSES obtendo pontuação total satisfatória (α=0,87). A validade convergente de constructo foi confirmada por correlações negativas significativas de magnitude moderada a fraca entre os escores dos domínios do IMDSES e os escores de domínio da SDSCA. A validade de critério foi parcialmente confimada por correlação de magnitude fraca entre o domínio de Gerenciamento Geral e o escore total do IMDSES e níveis de hemoglobina glicada (r=0.22; p=0.02). Conclusão: A versão brasileira do IMDSES apresentou medidas psicométricas satisfatórias e pode ser útil para avaliar a efetividade das intervenções de enfermagem que visam otimizar a autoeficácia do paciente com DM2 no manejo do tratamento.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Model of study: Validation study. Objective: To evaluate the psychometric performance of the Brazilian version of the Insulin Management Diabetes Self-Efficacy Scale - IMDSES. Methodology: Reliability (internal consistency - Cronbach’s α), convergent and criterion validity were assessed. Data were gathered from 127 patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) in use of insulin through the application of sociodemographic and clinical instruments and the Brazilian versions of the Summary of Diabetes Self-Care Activities Measures - SDSCA and the IMDSES. Results: It was observed “ceiling effect” in Insulin domain. Reliability was confirmed in all IMDSES domains and Total Score (α=0.87). The convergent construct validity was supported by significant negative moderate to weak magnitude correlations between the scores of IMDSES domains and the scores of SDSCA domains. Criterion validity was partially supported by the weak magnitude correlation between the General Managements domain and the Total Score of IMDSES and serum levels of glycated hemoglobin (r=0.22; p=0.02). Conclusion: The Brazilian version of IMDSES presented satisfactory psychometric measures and may be useful to evaluate the effectiveness of nursing interventions aimed at optimizing the selfefficacy of the T2DM patient in the management of his treatment.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-11-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152013</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v51i2p121-130</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 No. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 121-130</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 Núm. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 121-130</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 51 n. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 121-130</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152013/148798</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/152015</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Daily and social activities influence the quality of life of renal chronic patients in hemodialysis</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividades diárias e sociais influenciam a qualidade de vida de pacientes renais crônicos em hemodiálise</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva Filho, Antonio Batista da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Xavier, Camila dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Carolina Guilherme dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Corá, Luiza Franco</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fonseca, Marcela Machado</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Denadai, Amanda Silveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira-Paim, Kennio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fonseca, Fernanda Machado</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Kidney Diseases</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Renal Dialysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Comorbidity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doença Renal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diálise Renal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Comorbidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: This study aimed to evaluate the physical and social factors that influence the quality of life of patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD) on hemodialysis (HD). Study Design: Descriptive and cross-sectional. Methods: There were 149 patients with CKD routinely submitted to HD that answered a questionnaire adapted (Medical Results Survey; SF-36) about the presence of symptoms during and after the HD sessions, main diseases concomitant, and the presence of factors that influence the quality of life. Results: According to the multivariate analysis, the presence of symptoms after the HD contributes to a decrease in the quality of life (p=0.04). However, emotional well-being was positively associated with social activities (p=0.01). The daily activities and the absence of concomitant diseases are associated with good health and, therefore, a better quality of life for patients with CKD (p&amp;lt;0.05). Patients with chronic diseases such as hypertension and diabetes should be better observed, since such illnesses are always associated with renal dysfunction. Conclusion: The results of the present study demonstrate that the chronic renal patients should be inserted into social environments and should perform daily activities despite the limitations of the treatment since an active lifestyle contributes positively to their well-being and quality of life.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: O objetivo deste estudo foi avaliar os fatores físicos e sociais que influenciam a qualidade de vida de pacientes com doença renal crônica (DRC) em hemodiálise (HD). Modelo de estudo: Descritivo e transversal. Métodos: Foram incluídos 149 pacientes com DRC rotineiramente submetidos a HD que responderam ao questionário adaptado (Medical Results Survey; SF-36) sobre a presença de sintomas durante e após as sessões de HD, principais doenças concomitantes e presença de fatores que influenciam a qualidade de vida. Resultados: De acordo com a análise multivariada, a presença de sintomas após a HD contribui para uma diminuição da qualidade de vida (p=0,04). Entretanto, o bem-estar emocional foi positivamente relacionado com as atividades sociais (p=0,01). As atividades diárias e a ausência de doenças concomitantes estão associadas com uma boa saúde e assim, a uma melhor qualidade de vida dos pacientes com DRC (p&amp;lt;0,05). Pacientes com doenças crônicas como hipertensão e diabetes devem ser melhor acompanhados, uma vez que, estas doenças estão constantemente associadas a disfunção renal. Conclusão: Os resultados do presente estudo demonstram que os pacientes crônicos renais devem ser inseridos no ambiente social e devem realizar atividades cotidianas, apesar das limitações do tratamento, uma vez que um estilo de vida ativo contribui positivamente para a melhora da qualidade de vida.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-11-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152015</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v51i2p131-137</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 No. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 131-137</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 Núm. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 131-137</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 51 n. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 131-137</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152015/148799</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/152016</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Acute intermittent porphyria with complications arising from late diagnosis in a pediatric patient</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Porfiria aguda intermitente com complicações decorrentes do diagnóstico tardio em paciente pediátrico</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cunha, Gabriel Veloso</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Suziane Soares</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Luana Cicília Sousa da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fontes, Tânia Maria de Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Luciano Máximo da</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Porphyria, Acute Intermittent</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Renal Insufficiency</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemodialysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Porfiria Aguda Intermitente</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Insuficiência Renal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemodiálise</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A porfiria é uma doença rara, decorrente da deficiência enzimática associada à biossíntese do grupamento heme. O objetivo deste relato é descrever um caso de crise porfirêmica aguda intermitente em um paciente de 15 anos, que evoluiu rapidamente com tetraplegia e insuficiência renal crônica terminal, além de distúrbios neuropsiquiátricos. Representa uma entidade de difícil diagnóstico devido à inespecificidade dos achados clínicos. À admissão a creatinina era de 6,44 mg/dL e a uréia de 103 mg/dL. Déficit neurológico importante e insuficiência renal crônica são complicações raras, decorrentes do diagnóstico e tratamento tardio. É fundamental que o tratamento seja iniciado imediatamente após o diagnóstico, devido não somente à morbidade a curto-médio prazo, mas também aos possíveis efeitos deletérios permanentes.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Porphyria is a rare disease, consequence of enzymatic deficiencies associated with heme group biosynthesis. The aim of this report is to describe a case of acute intermittent porphyria crisis in a 15-year-old patient who progressed rapidly with tetraplegia and chronic terminal renal failure, as well as severe neuropsychiatric disorders. It represents an entity of difficult diagnosis due to the lack of specificity of the clinical findings. At admission, creatinine was 6.44 mg / dL and urea was 103 mg / dL. Significant neurological deficit and chronic renal failure are rare complications, arising from late diagnosis and treatment. A greater degree of clinical suspicion is fundamental that treatment be started immediately after diagnosis, due not only to short-term morbidity but also to possible deleterious permanent effects.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-11-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152016</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v51i2p153-156</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 No. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 153-156</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 Núm. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 153-156</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 51 n. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 153-156</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152016/148800</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/152017</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Kaposi sarcoma in a patient with HIV: case report</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Sarcoma de Kaposi em paciente portador de HIV: relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wagner, Amanda Kloster</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tozo, Jéssica Priscila</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Abreu, Marilda Aparecida Mllanez Morgado de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wedy, Glaucia Ferreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sarcoma, Kaposi</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Herpesvirus 8, Human</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">AIDS Serodiagnosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sarcoma de Kaposi</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Herpesvirus Humano 8</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sorodiagnóstico da AIDS</dc:subject>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-11-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152017</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v51i2p157-161</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 No. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 157-161</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 Núm. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 157-161</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 51 n. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 157-161</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152017/148801</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/152024</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Surgical margins of dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans: case report and literature review</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Margens cirúrgicas no dermatofibrossarcoma protuberans: relato de caso e revisão da literatura</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Câmara, Eduardo R. Z.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Toledo, Tricie Kobylko de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Toledo, Otávio Alberto Kobylko de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eckhardt, Antonio C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alves, Alessandro A. B. R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Araújo, Marcelo S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Jadivan L.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Dermatofibrosarcoma Protuberans</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Skin Neoplasms</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Myocutaneous Flap</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Margins, Surgical</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dermatofibrossarcoma protuberante</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neoplasias Cutâneas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Retalho Miocutâneo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Margens Cirúrgicas</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Introduction: Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans (DFSP) is a rare dermal fibrohistiocytic tumor that affects the skin, accounting for 1% of soft tissue sarcomas and representing less than0.1% of all malignancies. The main characteristic of this type of tumor is a high rate of local recurrence after surgical excision. Deciding the proper surgical margin for complete resection is a challenge. Case report: 24 year-old, shows a reddish vegetative asymptomatic tumor on the left shoulder. She has a positive family history of DFSP in the lower limb. The definitive histopathological report confirmed Dermatofibrossarcoma protuberans. Discussion: The histological feature of the tumor is the presence of tentacle type projections of neoplastic cells in the periphery extending through the subcutaneous tissue to the muscular fascia. Of course, the most important factor for local control is the achievement of free surgical margins. Excision through Mohs micrographic surgery is a great option in regions where wide excision is not desirable, as in the face. The standard margin in most pf the literature is 3 cm resected to the muscular fascia, and it can be reduced to 2 cm in places where the extensive excision impairs the conformation of the site, as in the face.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: O dermatofibrossarcoma protuberante (DFSP) é um tumor fibrohistiocítico de origem dérmica raro, que acomete a pele, representando 1% dos sarcomas de partes moles e menos de 0,1% de todas malignidades. A principal característica deste tipo de tumor é a sua elevada taxa de recidiva local após excisão cirúrgica. Decidir a margem cirúrgica adequada para a ressecção completa é um desafio. Relato de caso: 24 anos, apresenta lesão tumoral vegetante avermelhada no ombro esquerdo, assintomática. Possui história familiar positiva de DFSP em membro inferior. O laudo histopatológico definitivo confirmou Dermatofibrossarcoma protuberans. Discussão: A característica histológica do tumor é a presença de projeções tipo tentáculos de células neoplásicas na periferia que se estendem através do tecido subcutâneo até a fáscia muscular. Certamente, o fator de maior importância para o controle local é a obtenção de margens cirúrgicas livres. A excisão através da cirurgia micrográfica de Mohs é uma ótima opção em regiões onde a excisão ampla não é desejável, como na face. A margem padrão estabelicida em grande parte da literatura é de 3 cm com ressecção até a fáscia muscular, podendo ser diminuida para 2 cm em locais em que a excisão ampla prejudique a conformação do local, como na face</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-11-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152024</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v51i2p162-165</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 No. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 162-165</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 Núm. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 162-165</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 51 n. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 162-165</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152024/148802</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/152027</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Refl.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Evolução da neurociência comportamental nos últimos 50 anos. Foco no sistema de defesa e na neurotransmissão</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evolution of behavioral neuroscience during the last 50 years. Focus on the defense system and neurotransmission.</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Graeff, Frederico Guilherme</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Defense Reactions</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Serotonin</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Animal Models; Anxiety /Panic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Anxiety; Human Experimentation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Magnetic Resonance Imaging</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Panic Disorder</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reações de Defesa</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Serotonina.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelos Animais; Ansiedade/Pânico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ansiedade; Experimentação Humana</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Imagem por Ressonância Magnética</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtorno de Pânico</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The evolution of Behavioral Neuroscience along the last 50 years is presented on the basis of the research work carried out by the author and his coworkers. The main line of investigation reported deals with the role of serotonin in the regulation of defense reactions that are related to the emotions anxiety, fear and panic, as well as to the respective pathologies: generalized anxiety disorder, phobias and panic disorder. The key brain structures for anxiety – amygdala, hippocampus and insula – are localized in the forebrain, whereas those related to fear and panic – hypothalamus and periaqueductal gray matter (PAG) – are placed in the diencephalon and brain stem. The role of the defense reactions to proximal danger – immobility, flight and fight – that are related to panic attacks are highlighted. The results obtained in animal models of anxiety and panic, as well as in humans, including experimental anxiety tests and morphometric and functional neuroimaging are reported, and their implications for the knowledge of the pathophysiology of panic disorder and its pharmacological treatment are discussed.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A evolução da Neurociência Comportamental nos últimos 50 anos é apresentada em função das pesquisas desenvolvidas pelo autor e colaboradores na área de Neuropsicofarmacologia. A principal linha de investigação relatada aborda o papel da serotonina na regulação das repostas de defesa, que estão relacionadas com as emoções ansiedade, medo e pânico, bem como com as respectivas patologias: transtorno de ansiedade generalizada, fobias e pânico. As estruturas cerebrais críticas para a ansiedade – amígdala, hipocampo e ínsula – estão localizadas no cérebro anterior, enquanto que as relacionadas com o medo e o pânico – hipotálamo e matéria cinzenta periaquedutal (MCP) – situam-se no diencéfalo e no tronco cerebral. Dá-se ênfase ao papel da MCP nas reações a ameaças proximais – imobilidade , fuga e luta – que estão relacionadas com ataques de pânico. São relatados resultados obtidos em modelos animais de pânico e em experimentação com seres humanos, incluindo testes de ansiedade experimental e neuroimagem morfométrica e funcional, cujas implicações para o conhecimento da fisiopatologia do transtorno de pânico e seu tratamento farmacológico são discutidas.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-11-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v51i2p89-111</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 No. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 89-111</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 Núm. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 89-111</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 51 n. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 89-111</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152027/148803</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/152029</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:01:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificação da obesidade infantil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Classification of childhood obesity</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nogueira-de-Almeida, Carlos Alberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mell, Elza Daniel de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro, Graziela Aparecida N. de Almeida</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Carla Cristina João N. de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Falcão, Mário Cícero</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rêgo, Carla Maria Barreto da Silva de Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Obesity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Classification</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Adolescent</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Insulin Resistance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pediatric Obesity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Obesidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Adolescente</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Resistência à Insulina</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Obesidade Pediátrica</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Importance of the Problem: obesity in childhood and adolescence is currently considered a serious public health problem with a growing prevalence worldwide. Objective: to update the classification of child and adolescent obesity originally published in 2004, incorporating the new scientific evidence. Methods: a review of the Scientific Literature that addressing etiopathogenic factors of obesity, in order to improve the previously published classification including the new scientific knowledge. Results: a classification that suggests as the first strategy the definition of the presence of peripheral resistance to insulin and then suggests the division into four subgroups of obesity: syndromic, epigenetic, induced (endocrinological, neurological, sleep disorders, drugs and infectious agents) and classical (somatic and psychosocial). Conclusion: this classification could help the clinicians to make decisions and to personalize the treatment.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Importância do Problema: A obesidade na infância e na adolescência é considerada, atualmente, grave problema de saúde pública com prevalência crescente em todo o mundo. Objetivo: atualizar a classificação da obesidade infantojuvenil publicada originalmente em 2004, incorporando as novas evidências científicas. Métodos: revisão da Literatura Científica que abordou os fatores etiopatogênicos da obesidade, buscando-se aprimorar a classificação anteriormente publicada incluindo os novos conhecimentos científicos. Resultados: apresentação de uma classificação que sugere como primeira estratégia a definição da presença de resistência periférica à insulina e, a seguir, sugere a divisão em quatro subgrupos de obesidade: sindrômica, epigenética, induzida (endocrinológica, neurológica, distúrbios do sono, fármacos e agentes infecciosos) e clássica (somática e psicossocial). Conclusão: a classificação permite auxiliar o clínico na tomada de decisões e na individualização do tratamento.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-11-22</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152029</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v51i2p138-152</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 No. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 138-152</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 51 Núm. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 138-152</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 51 n. 2 (2018): abr./maio/jun.; 138-152</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/152029/148804</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2022-08-30T21:20:40Z" completeListSize="1467" cursor="1150">60501c1da0cc32835b57727ed246c52e</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
