<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-08-29T21:20:25Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="rmrp">https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47569</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Profile of users in an emergency care</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil de usuários em um serviço de pronto atendimento</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gomide, Mariana Figueiredo Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pinto, Ione Carvalho</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gomide, Daniela Martorano Pires</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zacharias, Fabiana Costa Machado</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atenção Primária à Saúde. Acesso aos Serviços de Saúde. Serviços Médicos de Emergência.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Primary Health Care. Health Services Accessibility. Emergency Medical Services</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo deste estudo foi identificar o perfil de usuários atendidos no pronto atendimento (PA) de umdistrito do município de Ribeirão Preto - SP. Estudo quantitativo sobre usuários que procuraram o PAentre janeiro a junho de 2009. Foram caracterizados quanto ao sexo, faixa etária, horário, dia da semanae mês de maior procura, justificativa da procura, conduta e encaminhamentos realizados. Dos 45.771atendimentos realizados, foi selecionada amostra com 330 fichas de atendimento pela técnica deamostragem aleatória. Desta amostra, 57% dos usuários eram do sexo feminino e 63,3% são usuáriosentre 20 a 50 anos. Os meses de maior procura foram março, abril e maio e 70,7% dos atendimentosocorreram durante o dia. Em 20% das justificativas tiveram o relato de dor. Em 77,2% das condutasestão a terapia medicamentosa e 26,3% a solicitação de exames. Entre as diversas justificativas paraa procura pelo PA estão as potencialidades deste serviço na forma de alta densidade tecnológica.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The objective of this study was to identify the profile of users treated in emergency care of a district ofRibeirao Preto - SP. Quantitative Study users seeking the emergency care between January to June 2009.Were characterized by sex, age, time, day of week and months of peak demand, demand justification,conduct and referrals. Of the 45,771 visits made, was selected a sample of 330 medical records byrandom sampling technique. Of these, 57% of users were female and 63.3% are users between 20 and50 years. The months of greatest demand were in March, April and May and 70.7% of cases occurredduring the day. In 20% of justifications were reports of pain. In 77,2% of the ducts are drug therapy and26.3% test ordering. Among the many justifications for the search by the emergency care are the potentialof this service in the form of high-density technology.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47569</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i1p31-38</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 1 (2012); 31-38</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 1 (2012); 31-38</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 1 (2012); 31-38</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47569/51298</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47570</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Bacterial contamination in computers keyboards used in university hospital of northeastern Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Contaminação bacteriana em teclados de computadores utilizados em hospital universitário do nordeste do Brasil</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Anderson G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Viveiros, Mariana A. W. B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barroso, Ivoneide M. O.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cavalcante, Alessandra P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopez, Ana M. Q.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Computadores. Contaminação de Equipamentos. Controle de Infecções. Infecção Hospitalar.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Computer. Equipment Contamination. Infection Control. Cross Infection.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The technological advance allows the insertion of computers in the hospital environment, being neededto the execution of tests, record the patient information or doctor's personal use. Thirtyone samples ofcomputer keyboards from the Hospital "Professor Alberto Antunes", at the Federal University of Alagoas,Brazil (UFAL), were subjected to microbiological analysis in the period from February to June 2011. Thecolonies that were isolated were subsequently morphologically and biochemically analyzed, including by&#160;automated method (VITEK®). Among the sectors monitored, the following bacteria were detected:Acinetobacter baumannii (Obstetrical Clinic), Pseudomonas stutzeri (General Medicine and Maternity),P. oryzihabitans (Pediatrics), Enterobacter cancerogenus (Chemotherapy Sector), E. cloacae (NeonatalIntensive Care Unit), Enterococcus faecium (Oncology Nursing Sector), Sphingomonas paucimobilis(Ophtalmology Sector) and &#160;Rhizobium radiobacter (rooming). From these, &#160;P. oryzihabitans, E.cancerogenus and S. paucimobilis showed resistance to antibiotics commonly recommended. Therefore, the hospital computer keyboards can play in the spread of pathogens and should be part of theroutine disinfection of the hospital. Cover with protective film and the adoption of preventive measuressuch as hand washing are important.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O avanço tecnológico permitiu a inserção dos computadores no ambiente hospitalar, sendo necessários na solicitação de exames, registro de informações dos pacientes ou para uso pessoal dos médicos.Trinta e um teclados de computadores do Hospital Universitário Professor Alberto Antunes/UFAL foramsubmetidos a análises microbiológicas no período de fevereiro a junho de 2011. As colônias isoladasdas amostras foram analisadas morfobioquímicamente, inclusive por método automatizado (VITEK®).Entre os setores monitorados, foram detectadas as seguintes bactérias: Acinetobacter baumanii (Clí-nica Obstétrica), Pseudomonas stutzeri (Clínica Médica e Maternidade), &#160;P. oryzihabitans (Pediatria),Enterobacter cancerogenus (Setor de Quimioterapia), E. cloacae (UTI Neonatal), Enterococcus faecium(Enfermaria do Setor Oncológico), Sphingomonas paucimobilis (Setor Oftalmológico) e &#160;Rhizobiumradiobacter (Alojamento Conjunto). Destas, P. oryzihabitans, E. cancerogenus e S. paucimobilis apresentaram resistência a antimicrobianos comumente recomendados. Portanto, os teclados de computadores hospitalares podem atuar na disseminação de patógenos, devendo fazer parte da rotina dedesinfecção do ambiente hospitalar. A cobertura com película protetora e a adoção de medidas preventivas como a lavagem das mãos são de grande importância.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47570</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i1p39-48</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 1 (2012); 39-48</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 1 (2012); 39-48</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 1 (2012); 39-48</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47570/51299</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47571</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effect of different dose of leucine on glycogen reserves from denervated skeletal muscle of rats</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeito de diferentes doses de leucina sobre as reservas glicogênicas da musculatura esquelética desnervada de ratos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro, Carolina Barbosa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Borin, Sergio Henrique</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Carlos Alberto da Silva Alberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Denervação. Glicogênio. Leucina</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Denervation. Glycogen. Leucine.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The aim of this study was to investigate the action of different doses of leucine on the dynamics ofglycogen reserves of denervated skeletal muscle of rats. Wistar rats aged 3 to 4 months, weighingbetween 200 and 300g being kept under controlled conditions Biotery. The animals were divided intoexperimental group called control (C), denervated (D) treated with amino acid leucine in three doses5nm(CL5), 1.25 mM (CL1,25) and 0.30mM(CL0,30), denervated treated with 0.30mM(DL0,30). Supplementation was performed by gavage and denervation was performed by sectioning the sciatic nerve. Theanalysis of the content of glycogen was performed on samples of the soleus(S), gastrocnemius white(GW)and red(GR). The muscle was lower in S glycogen (-33% and -42,8%), both in CL1,25 and CL5 andincreased in a dose CL0,30(+38%), possibly due to act upon this low dose of insulin secretagogue,promoting an increase in the rate of glucose uptake by peripheral tissues (11,2± 0,3%/min C x 14,16 ±0,2%/min CL0,30). The glycogen's GW and GR presented themselves in small groups CL1,25 (-32,6%)and CL5 (-44,8%) compared to C, however, the group CL0,30 no difference was observed in C. Therewas also decreased in group D (26% S; 35% GW; 28,5% GR) if compared to C. Conclusion: High dosesof leucine may compromise the formation of muscle glycogen and 0.30mM was shown to be effectiveeven when the muscle at rest</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo do estudo foi investigar o efeito de diferentes doses de leucina sobre as reservas glicogênicasdo músculo esquelético de ratos desnervados. Foram utilizados 36 ratos Wistar com 3 a 4 meses,pesando entre 200 e 300g sendo mantidos em condições controladas de bioterismo. Os animais foramdistribuídos em grupo experimentais denominados controle(C); desnervados(D); tratados comaminoácido leucina em três doses 5mM(CL5); 1,25mM(CL1,25) e 0,30mM(CL0,30); desnervado tratadocom 0,30mM(DL0,30). A suplementação da leucina foi feita por gavagem e a desnervação foi realizadapela secção do nervo isquiático. As análises do conteúdo de glicogênio foram realizadas em amostrasdos músculos sóleo(S), gastrocnemio branco(GB) e vermelho(GV). O músculo S apresentou reduçãono glicogênio tanto em CL5(-42,8%) quanto em CL1,25(-33%) e aumento na dose CL0,30(+38%). Épossível que a baixas doses de leucina tenham estimulado a secreção de insulina, promovendo aumento na velocidade de captação de glicose pelos &#160;tecidos periféricos de 11.2±0,3%/min C para14,16±0,2%/min no grupo tratado com CL0,30. O glicogênio do GB e GV apresentou-se reduzido nosgrupos CL5(-44,8%) e CL1,25(-32,6%) comparado ao C; no entanto, no grupo CL0,30 não foi observadodiferença em relação ao Grupo C. Observou-se ainda diminuição do glicogênio no grupo D(26% S; 35%GB; 28,5% no GV) e no DL0,30(35,6% GB e 65% no GV) em comparação com C. Conclusão: Altas dosesde leucina podem comprometer a formação de glicogênio muscular e 0,30mM mostrou-se efetivamesmo estando o músculo em repouso.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47571</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i1p58-65</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 1 (2012); 58-65</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 1 (2012); 58-65</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 1 (2012); 58-65</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47571/51300</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47572</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Grupal Rehabilitation: Expectations and perceptions of people with visual disabilities</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação Grupal: Expectativas e percepções de portadores de deficiência visual</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Monteiro, Mayla M. B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Montilha, Rita de Cássia I.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação. Portadores de Deficiência Visual. Saúde de Grupos Específicos.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation. Visually Impaired Persons. Health of Specific Groups.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Purpose: Check characteristics, expectations and perceptions of the visually impaired, participants ofthe rehabilitation process group. Methods: There was descriptive study according to questionnaire throughthe interview not probability sample of people with visual impairments of 12 years and more, users ofrehabilitation service group the Centre for Studies Rehabilitation and Research in "Prof. Dr. Gabriel Port"(CEPRE/FCM/UNICAMP). Two instruments were used, one early in the process of rehabilitation andanother at the end. Results: The samples were composed of 26 and 14 users respectively, the differencebetween the two samples was due to some dropouts in the process of rehabilitation, or difficulty of&#160;access to users. All users who answered the second questionnaire also responded to the first. For userscharacteristics of the sample, the breakdown by sex was equal (50.0%) male and female. The LowVision was the type of disability presented by the majority (76.9%), with diabetic retinopathy the mostmentioned (47.3%). Most users said he expected that rehabilitation would help to ease the daily life(73.1%). Among the perceptions concerning emphasizing the process of rehabilitation is the improvement in activities of daily living (33.2%). For perceptions about the rehabilitation group has been held inthe majority (71.4%) of users said it felt good therapeutic strategy. Conclusion: Users have to be satisfiedwhen asked about the rehabilitation process in which they were inserted, so this process of rehabilitationgroup can meet the expectations of the user regarding this process.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivos: Verificar características, expectativas e percepções de deficientes visuais, participantes deprocesso de reabilitação grupal. Métodos: Realizou-se estudo descritivo aplicando-se questionário pormeio de entrevista à amostra não probabilística de pessoas com deficiência visual, de 12 anos e mais,usuários de serviço de reabilitação grupal do Centro de Estudos e Pesquisas em Reabilitação "Prof. Dr.Gabriel Porto" (CEPRE/FCM/UNICAMP) Foram aplicados dois instrumentos, um no início do processode reabilitação e outro no final. Resultados: As amostras foram compostas por 26 e 14 usuários respectivamente, a diferença entre as duas amostras foi devido a algumas desistências no decorrer do processo de reabilitação, ou dificuldade de acesso aos usuários. Todos os usuários que responderam aosegundo questionário também responderam ao primeiro. Em relação às características dos usuáriosda amostra, a distribuição por sexo foi igual (50,0%) do sexo masculino e feminino. A Baixa Visão foi otipo de deficiência apresentada pela maioria (76.9%), sendo a retinopatia diabética a causa maismencionada (47,3%). A maioria dos usuários declarou que esperava que a reabilitação fosse auxiliar afacilitar o cotidiano (73,1%). Entre as percepções referentes ao processo de reabilitação destacou-se amelhora nas atividades da vida diária (33,2%). Em relação às percepções acerca da reabilitação tersido realizada em grupo a maioria (71,4%) dos usuários declarou que achou boa esta estratégiaterapêutica. Conclusão: Os usuários mostraram-se satisfeitos quando questionados sobre o processode reabilitação no qual estavam inseridos, portanto este processo de reabilitação grupal conseguesuprir as expectativas dos usuários referentes a este processo.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47572</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i1p66-77</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 1 (2012); 66-77</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 1 (2012); 66-77</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 1 (2012); 66-77</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47572/51301</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47573</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Nível de atividade física de portadores de diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2) em comunidade carente no Brasil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Level of physical activity of carriers of diabetes mellitus tipo 2(DM2) in a poor community in Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Modeneze, Dênis Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vilarta, Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Maciel, Érika da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sonati, Jaqueline Girnos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Marcos Eduardo Sales Nunes de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Boccaletto, Estela Marina Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diabetes Mellitus Tipo 2. Planos e Programas de Saúde. Atividade Física.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Diabetes Mellitus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Type 2. Health Programs and Plans. Motor Activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: Estudo transversal observacional. Objetivo: O objetivo deste trabalho foi identificar onível de atividade física de indivíduos portadores de diabetes mellitus, pertencentes às comunidadescarentes. Métodos: Foram entrevistados 101 indivíduos portadores de diabetes tipo 2, de ambos ossexos com média de idade de 63,6 anos (± 11,4), participantes de uma associação municipal dediabéticos, no período de maio a junho de 2009. As variáveis coletas foram nível de atividade física, coma aplicação do Questionário Internacional de Atividade Física forma curta (IPAQ), variáveis demográficas, socioeconômicas e de saúde com aplicação de questionário estruturado. Resultados: Observouse que a maioria era do sexo feminino, casada, aposentada, baixo nível socioeconômico e poucaescolaridade. 87,3% referiram pelo menos uma comorbidade, prevalecendo hipertensão arterial (64%),problemas na coluna (38%) e artrose (31%). Quanto à prática de atividade física, o grupo estudadoapresentou elevados níveis (21,8% Muito Ativos e 65,3% Ativos). Conclusão: Os sujeitos do estudoapresentaram elevados níveis de atividade física onde os homens relataram participação significativamente maior na prática da caminhada do que as mulheres, relação que se inverte nas atividadesmoderadas e vigorosas onde as mulheres se destacaram. Porém o bom escore detectado pelo instrumento não minimiza a importância de se desenvolver programas com atividades físicas orientadas eespecíficas a esta população.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study Model: It was done an observational and analytical study with a cross-sectional design. Objective:This study focuses on assessing the level of physical activity and verifying if it is related to socioeconomicaspects and health conditions of Diabetes Mellitus type 2 sufferers in a poor community. Methods: Aconsecutive sampling was carried out with 101 individuals, both male and female, average age being63.6 (±11.4 years), and the majority of whom were female, married, retired, lowly educated, and belonging to a low socioeconomic level. The following variables were collected: level of physical activity, with theapplication of the International Questionnaire of Physical Activity (IPAQ), demographic variables, socioeconomic aspects and health conditions with application of a structured questionnaire. Results: Addingthe practice of physical activity, the studied group presented high levels (21,8% Very Active and 65,3%Active).Statistical analyses of independent variables suggest an important correlation between age,habit of verifying glycemia, and education level, being level of physical activity the dependent variable.Conclusion: In a view of the correlations observed, in additional of the limitations imposed by the disease, it is highly important that actions on health education be taken amidst professionally operatedsupport groups to help DM sufferers. These actions should include orientations for self care and frequentphysical activities, respecting each community's social and cultural contexts, and local living conditionsas well.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47573</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i1p78-86</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 1 (2012); 78-86</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 1 (2012); 78-86</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 1 (2012); 78-86</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47573/51302</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47580</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Tabagismo, alcoolismo em pacientes que frequentam um serviço de fisioterapia do Sistema Único de Saúde</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Smoking, alcohol use in patients attending in the physiotherapy service at the Health System</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bertanha, Dalila</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ruffino Netto, Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tabagismo. Alcoolismo. Drogas. Abuso de Substâncias Psicoativas. Fisioterapia.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Smoking. Alcoholism. Drugs. Substance-Related Disorders. Physical Therapy Specialty.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Model of the study: This is an epidemiological, descriptive, model survey and with a quantitative approach.Objective: The objective of this research is to analyze the epidemiological profile of patients attending inthe Center for Physicaltherapy Oscar Pires de Andrade, who is in the city of Itapira-SP and estimate thepercentage of the use to tobacco, alcohol and other drugs in the population studied.Methods: Through interviews, the instruments were applied: Socio - Demographic Questionnaire andthe Percentage of Smokers in Itapira Physiotherapy Center, Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence(FTND) questionnaire and the Alcohol, Smoking and Substance Involvement Screening Test (ASSIST)V.3.0. The interviews so taken with patients who attend physiotherapy service at the National HealthSystem (SUS), the city of Itapira-SP, in the months July-August 2010. The percentage of smokers is 17%,the median age of smokers is 48 years and 51% are female,the most (89%) reported smoking onlycigarettes commercialized, the median number of cigarettes smoked per day is 10 and the median timethat the person used the tobacco is 30 years. Half the smokers were classified according to the FTND, asvery low and low nicotine dependence, the mean score of the FTND is 4.1. About the use of psychoactivesubstances in life, tobacco (70%), alcohol (91%) and marijuana (14%) were the most frequently mentioned substances. Tobacco (31%) and alcohol (31%) were the most commonly mentioned to receivebrief intervention according to the ASSIST questionnaire.Conclusions: The legal drugs like alcohol and tobacco, are public health problems. It is important to worka prevention of psychoactive drugs in the Physicaltherapy services.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: Trata-se de um estudo epidemiológico, descritivo, modelo inquérito, com uma abordagem metodológica quantitativa.Objetivo: O objetivo desta pesquisa é analisar o perfil epidemiológico, dos pacientes que frequentam oCentro de Fisioterapia Oscar Pires de Andrade, que se encontra na cidade de Itapira SP e estimar aporcetagem do uso do tabaco, álcool e outras drogas, na pupolação estudada.Métodos: Por meio de entrevistas foram aplicados os instrumentos: Questionário Sócio - Demográficoe sobre a Porcentagem de Tabagistas no Centro de Fisioterapia de Itapira-SP; Teste de Fagerströmpara a Dependência à Nicotina (FTND); e o Questionário Alcohol, Smoking and Substance InvolvementScreening Test (ASSIST) V.3.0. As entrevistas forma feitas com os pacientes que frequentam o serviçode fisioterapia do Sistema Único de Saúde (SUS), da cidade de Itapira-SP, nos meses de julho a agostode 2010.Resultados: Foram entrevistados 217 pacientes, a média de idade dos entrevistados é 50 anos, maioria são do sexo feminino (63, 13%), a moda de anos de escolaridade é 11 anos e a mediana cinco.Lombalgia, cervicalgia e tendinite representaram juntos 50% dos encaminhamentos para fisioterapia.A porcentagem de fumantes é 17%, a média de idade dos pacientes fumantes é 48 anos e 51% são dosexo feminino, a maioria (89%) relatou fumar apenas cigarros comercializados, a mediana do númerode cigarros fumados por dia é 10 e a mediana de tempo que o indivíduo usou o tabaco é 30 anos. Ametade dos tabagistas foram classificados, de acordo com o FTND, como muito baixa e baixa dependência à nicotina, a média do escore do FTND é de 4,1. Sobre o uso de substâncias psicoativas na vida,o tabaco (70%), álcool (91%) e maconha (14%) foram as substâncias mais citadas. O tabaco (31%) e oálcool (31%) foram as drogas mais mencionadas para receber intervenção breve de acordo com oQuestionário ASSIST.Conclusões: As drogas legais como o álcool e o tabaco, são problemas de saúde pública. É importantetrabalhar a prevenção de drogas psicoativas, nos serviços de fisioterapia.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47580</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i1p87-95</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 1 (2012); 87-95</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 1 (2012); 87-95</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 1 (2012); 87-95</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47580/51303</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47582</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:PV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Academic student leagues. The merit and reality</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Ligas acadêmicas estudantis. O médico e a realidade</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Santana, Ana Carolina Delazia Albuquerque</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i1p96-98</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 1 (2012); 96-98</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 1 (2012); 96-98</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 1 (2012); 96-98</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47582/51313</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47584</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:PV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisioterapeuta, fisioterapia e transplante hepático</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Physiotherapist, physiotherapy and liver transplantation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Augusto, Viviane dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i1p99-101</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 1 (2012); 99-101</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 1 (2012); 99-101</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 1 (2012); 99-101</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47584/51324</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47585</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:NTIS</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Resumos de Dissertações de Mestrado e Teses de Doutorado apresentadas na Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto - USP de outubro a dezembro de 2011</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Editor, O</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47585</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i1p102-156</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 1 (2012); 102-156</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 1 (2012); 102-156</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 1 (2012); 102-156</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47585/51326</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47592</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.+Em.+ped.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carlotti, Ana Paula Carvalho Panzeri</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47592</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i2p157-157</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 2 (2012); 157-157</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 2 (2012); 157-157</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 2 (2012); 157-157</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47592/51332</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47593</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.+Em.+ped.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Systematic approach to the seriously ill or injured child: pediatric assessment</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Reconhecimento das situações de emergência: avaliação pediátrica</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Matsuno, Alessandra Kimie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Emergências. Avaliação Pediátrica. Sinais Clínicos. Insuficiência Respiratória. Choque</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Emergencies. Pediatric Assessment. Clinical Signs. Respiratory Failure. Shock.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este texto apresenta uma revisão da avaliação pediátrica nas situações de emergência. A avaliaçãopediátrica sistemática permite o reconhecimento eficiente e rápido de sinais de insuficiência respirató-ria e/ou choque. O reconhecimento e o tratamento precoce dos pacientes nestas situações são fundamentais à prevenção da insuficiência cardiopulmonar e da parada cardíaca em crianças.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This paper presents a review of the pediatric assessment in emergency situations. Systematic pediatricassessment is a quick and efficient way to recognize signs of respiratory failure and/or shock. Earlyrecognition and treatment in a timely manner are essential to the prevention of cardiopulmonary insufficiency and cardiac arrest in children.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47593</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i2p158-167</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 2 (2012); 158-167</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 2 (2012); 158-167</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 2 (2012); 158-167</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47593/51333</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47594</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:14Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.+Em.+ped.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Respiratory failure in children</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Insuficiência respiratória aguda na criança</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Matsuno, Alessandra Kimie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Insuficiência Respiratória. Criança. Serviço Hospitalar de Emergência. Dispositivos de Liberação de Oxigênio.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Respiratory Failure. Child. Emergency Service</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hospital. Oxygen Delivery Devices.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This paper presents a review of the definition, pathophysiology and management of respiratory distressand failure in children, and emphasizes the most appropriate devices for oxygen delivery. Children aremore susceptible to severe respiratory problems, which are leading causes of pediatric emergencyroom demand. Prompt recognition and effective management of respiratory problems are essential toimprove outcome of these patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este texto apresenta uma revisão da definição, da fisiopatologia e do manejo das emergências respiratórias e da insuficiência respiratória aguda na criança, enfatizando os dispositivos mais adequados deliberação de oxigênio. As crianças são mais suscetíveis aos problemas respiratórios graves, sendoestes, causas importantes de procura pela sala de emergência em pediatria. O reconhecimento precoce e o início rápido de tratamento são pontos fundamentais para o melhor desfecho desses pacientes.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47594</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i2p168-184</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 2 (2012); 168-184</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 2 (2012); 168-184</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 2 (2012); 168-184</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47594/51334</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47595</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.+Em.+ped.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Mechanical ventilation in children</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Ventilação mecânica em crianças</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carmona, Fabio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ventilação Mecânica. Pediatria. Insuficiência Respiratória.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ventilation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Mechanical. Pediatrics. Respiratory Failure.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O presente artigo apresenta ao leitor as principais indicações de ventilação mecânica assistida emcrianças e as principais modalidades existentes, além de trazer orientações para o ajuste dos parâmetros iniciais de ventilação de acordo com a indicação e listar as principais complicações relacionadasà ventilação mecânica e seu tratamento imediato.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The present article presents to the reader the main indications for mechanical ventilation in children andthe most common modalities; it also gives orientation for the initial ventilator settings according to theindication, and lists the main ventilation-related complications and their immediate treatment.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47595</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i2p185-196</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 2 (2012); 185-196</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 2 (2012); 185-196</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 2 (2012); 185-196</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47595/51335</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47596</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:12Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.+Em.+ped.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Shock in children</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Choque em crianças</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carlotti, Ana Paula Carvalho Panzeri</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Choque. Criança. Diagnóstico. Ressuscitação Hídrica. Suporte Hemodinâmico.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Shock. Child. Diagnosis. Fluid Resuscitation. Hemodynamic Support.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este texto apresenta uma revisão da definição, classificação, fisiopatologia e tratamento inicial dosdiversos tipos de choque na criança. O reconhecimento precoce e o tratamento agressivo do choque emtempo oportuno são essenciais à prevenção da parada cardiorrespiratória e à melhora do desfecho.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This paper presents a review of the definition, classification, pathophysiology and initial management ofthe different types of shock in children. Early recognition and aggressive treatment of shock in a timelymanner are essential to the prevention of cardiopulmonary arrest and outcome improvement.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47596</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i2p197-207</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 2 (2012); 197-207</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 2 (2012); 197-207</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 2 (2012); 197-207</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47596/51336</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47597</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:12Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.+Em.+ped.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Vascular access</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Acesso vascular</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carlotti, Ana Paula Carvalho Panzeri</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acesso Venoso Periférico. Acesso Vascular Intraósseo. Acesso Venoso Central. Criança.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Peripheral Venous Access. Intraosseous Vascular Access. Central Venous Access. Child.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This paper describes the priorities of vascular access in different clinical situations, the indications,contraindications, and complications of various types of vascular access, and the techniques for obtaining a peripheral venous, intraosseous and central venous access.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este texto aborda as prioridades de acesso vascular de acordo com o contexto clínico, as indicações,contraindicações e complicações dos diversos tipos de acesso vascular, e as técnicas de obtenção doacesso vascular periférico, intraósseo e central.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47597</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i2p208-214</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 2 (2012); 208-214</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 2 (2012); 208-214</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 2 (2012); 208-214</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47597/51337</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47598</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.+Em.+ped.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Arrhythmias in children</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Arritmias na criança</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Matsuno, Alessandra Kimie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Arritmias. Criança. Emergências. Tratamento.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Arrhythmias. Child. Emergencies. Therapeutics</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This paper presents a review of mechanisms, epidemiology, diagnosis and treatment of major arrhythmiasin children. If unrecognized and untreated, arrhythmias in children may lead to life-threatening hemodynamic instability. Therefore, early recognition and immediate treatment of these patients in the emergency department are essential.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este texto apresenta uma revisão dos mecanismos, da epidemiologia, do diagnóstico e do tratamentodas principais arritmias na criança. As arritmias na criança se não reconhecidas e não tratadas adequadamente podem levar a repercussões hemodinâmicas potencialmente fatais. Portanto, são imprescindíveis o reconhecimento precoce e o tratamento imediato desses pacientes na sala de emergência.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47598</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i2p215-222</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 2 (2012); 215-222</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 2 (2012); 215-222</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 2 (2012); 215-222</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47598/51338</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47599</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.+Em.+ped.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Cardiac arrest in children</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Parada cardíaca em crianças</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Matsuno, Alessandra Kimie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Parada Cardíaca. Criança. Diagnóstico. Tratamento.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cardiac Arrest. Child. Diagnosis. Therapeutics.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This paper presents a review of the epidemiology, causes, diagnosis and management of cardiac arrestin children. In contrast to adults, cardiac arrest in children rarely results from a primary cardiac andsudden cause. It’s usually due to respiratory failure and/or shock. Therefore, early recognition of theseconditions and prompt treatment may prevent cardiac arrest and improve outcome of these patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este texto apresenta uma revisão da epidemiologia, das causas, do diagnóstico e do manejo da paradacardíaca em crianças. Ao contrário do adulto, a parada cardíaca súbita de origem cardíaca é um eventoraro na criança. Geralmente, é causada por insuficiência respiratória e/ou choque. Portanto, o reconhecimento precoce e o tratamento imediato destas condições podem evitar a parada cardíaca e melhoraro desfecho desses pacientes.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47599</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i2p223-233</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 2 (2012); 223-233</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 2 (2012); 223-233</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 2 (2012); 223-233</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47599/51339</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47600</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.+Em.+ped.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Trauma resuscitation</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Ressuscitação no trauma</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carlotti, Ana Paula Carvalho Panzeri</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismo Múltiplo. Avaliação Primária. Avaliação Secundária. Lesões Crânio-encefálicas.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Multiple Trauma. Primary Survey. Secondary Survey. Head Injury.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This paper discusses the initial assessment and systematic management of the pediatric trauma victim,as well as the peculiarities of resuscitation of head injured children.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este texto aborda a avaliação inicial e o manejo sistematizado da criança vítima de trauma, assim comoas particularidades da ressuscitação no trauma crânio-encefálico.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47600</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i2p234-243</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 2 (2012); 234-243</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 2 (2012); 234-243</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 2 (2012); 234-243</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47600/51340</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47601</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.+Em.+ped.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">A clinical approach to acid-base disorders</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Abordagem clínica dos distúrbios do equilíbrio ácido-base</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carlotti, Ana Paula Carvalho Panzeri</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidose Metabólica. Acidose Respiratória. Alcalose Metabólica. Alcalose Respiratória. Distúrbios Mistos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Metabolic Acidosis. Acidosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Respiratory. Metabolic Alkalosis. Alkalosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Respiratory. Mixed Disorders.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This paper presents a clinical approach to disorders of acid-base balance. A proper interpretation of theacid-base status requires knowledge of the clinical setting integrated with laboratory results. The pHvalue determines the primary disorder: metabolic or respiratory acidosis, if the pH is less than 7.40;metabolic or respiratory alkalosis, if the pH is greater than 7.40. If the anion gap is greater than 20 mEq/L, a metabolic acidosis is present regardless of the pH value or plasma bicarbonate concentration.Absence of the expected compensatory response to a primary disorder indicates the presence of amixed disorder.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este texto apresenta uma abordagem clínica dos distúrbios do equilíbrio ácido-base. A interpretaçãoapropriada do estado ácido-base requer o conhecimento do quadro clínico integrado aos resultadoslaboratoriais. O valor do pH determina o distúrbio primário: acidose metabólica ou respiratória, se o pHfor menor que 7,40; alcalose metabólica ou respiratória, se o pH for maior que 7,40. Se o ânion gap formaior que 20 mEq/L, há acidose metabólica, independente dos valores do pH ou da concentraçãoplasmática de bicarbonato. A ausência da resposta compensatória esperada a determinado distúrbioprimário indica a presença de um distúrbio misto.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47601</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i2p244-262</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 2 (2012); 244-262</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 2 (2012); 244-262</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 2 (2012); 244-262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47601/51341</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47602</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:NTIS</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Resumos de Dissertações de Mestrado e Teses de Doutorado apresentadas na Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto - USP de janeiro a março de 2012</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Editor, O</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47602</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i2p263-301</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 2 (2012); 263-301</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 2 (2012); 263-301</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 2 (2012); 263-301</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47602/51342</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47604</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Determinants of blood pressure in type 2 diabetic subjects with high occurrence of inadequate glycemic control</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Determinantes da pressão arterial em diabéticos tipo 2 com alta ocorrência de controle glicêmico inadequado</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Codogno, Jamile Sanches</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fernandes, Rômulo Araújo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Freitas Júnior, Ismael Forte</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Monteiro, Henrique Luiz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividade Física. Diabetes Mellitus. Pressão Arterial. Dieta.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Activity. Diabetes Mellitus. Blood Pressure. Diet.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study design: Association studyObjective: To analyze the association between different biological/behavioral risk factors and bloodpressure in a sample of type 2 diabetes mellitus patients with poor glycemic control. Methods: A sampleof 121 type 2 diabetic patients was selected in the Public Healthcare System in a middle size Braziliancity. Blood pressure was measured using an aneroid device, previously calibrated. Six determinants ofblood pressure were taken into count: age, hypoglycemic agents, general obesity, abdominal obesity,eating behaviors and physical activity level. Results: The type 2 diabetic patients presented mean age of60.1±8.9 years-old and, at least, one risk factor. Eating behaviors (ORadj= 0.31 [0.12-0.75]) and sportspractice (ORadj= 0.12 [0.02-0.75]) constituted protective factors associated with lower systolic blood pressure. On the other hand, age was positively associated with high systolic blood pressure (ORadj= 3.81[1.39-10.38]). Patients with 5-6 risk factors, presented higher values of systolic and (F= 3.857; p= 0.011[post hoc with p= 0.039]), diastolic blood pressure (F= 4.158; p= 0.008 [post hoc with p= 0.036]) andincreased occurrence of hypertension (p= 0.010). Conclusion: Our findings indicate that, behavioralvariables were important determinants of blood pressure in type 2 diabetic patients with poor glycemiccontrol and clustering of behavioral and biological risk factors increase the hypertension occurrence.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: Estudo de associaçãoObjetivo: Analisar a associação entre diferentes fatores de risco biológicos/comportamentais e pressãoarterial in uma amostra de diabéticos do tipo 2 com pobre controle glicêmico. Métodos: Uma amostra de121 diabéticos tipo 2 foi selecionada no sistema público de uma cidade brasileira de porte médio.Pressão arterial foi aferida usando um aparelho aneroide previamente calibrado. Seis determinantes dapressão arterial foram considerados: idade, hipoglicemiantes, obesidade geral, obesidade central, hábitos alimentares e atividade física. Resultados: Os diabéticos apresentaram média de idade de 60,1±8,9anos e ao menos um fator de risco. Hábitos alimentares (ORadj= 0.31 [0.12-0.75]) e prática esportiva(ORadj= 0.12 [0.02-0.75]) constituíram fatores de proteção associados a menor pressão arterial. Poroutro lado, idade foi positivamente associada com alta pressão arterial sistólica (ORadj= 3.81 [1.39-10.38]).Pacientes com 5-6 fatores de risco apresentaram maiores valores sistólicos (F= 3,857; p= 0,011 [post hoccom p= 0,039]) e diastólicos (F= 4,158; p= 0,008 [post hoc com p= 0,036]) e maior ocorrência de hipertensão (p= 0,001). Conclusão: Nossos achados indicam que variáveis comportamentais foram importantesdeterminantes de pressão arterial em pacientes com pobre controle glicêmico e a agregação de fatorescomportamentais e biológicos aumentaram a ocorrência de hipertensão.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47604</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i1p49-57</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 1 (2012); 49-57</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 1 (2012); 49-57</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 1 (2012); 49-57</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47604/51344</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47663</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Hormonal regulation of food intake: A brief review</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Regulação hormonal na ingestão alimentar: um breve relato</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Maior, Alex Souto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hormônios. Neurônios Orexígenos e Anorexígenos. Ingestão Alimentar. Neurônios/ classificação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hormones. Orexigen and Anorexigen Neurons. Food Intake. Neurons/classification.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The purpose of a literature review was to explain about the hormonal regulation and neural control of thefood intake and body weight. The ingestion of macronutrients, the energy cost of food and hormonesynthesis that increases the activity of the orexygenic and anorexygenic neurons are determinative factors in the regulation of the food intake and body weight. The leptin, insulin and peptide YY increaseactivity of the anorexygenic neurons POMC/CART. However, the ghrelin increases activity of the orexygenicneurons NPY/AgRP. These hormones crossing the barrier hematoencephalic and binds to specificsreceptors in the hypothalamic arcuate nucleus. These mechanisms show to the complexity of the foodintake control and all the involved centers in the search for the energy homeostasis.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo deste trabalho de revisão foi dissertar sobre a regulação hormonal da ingestão alimentar e dopeso corporal. A ingestão de macronutrientes, o gasto energético e o balanço entre a síntese de hormô-nios que aumentam a atividade dos neurônios orexígenos e anorexígenos são fatores determinantesna regulação da ingestão alimentar e no controle do peso corporal. Os hormônios leptina, insulina e opeptídeo YY são grandes potenciadores da atividade dos neurônios anorexígenos POMC/CART. Poroutro lado, a ação da grelina aumenta a atividade dos neurônios orexígenos NPY/AgRP. Estes hormônios sintetizados perifericamente atravessam a barreira-hemato-encefálica e se ligam aos seus receptores no núcleo arqueado hipotalâmico com o objetivo de regular a ingestão alimentar e controlar obalanço energético. Estes mecanismos revelam a complexidade do controle do balanço energético etodos os centros envolvidos na busca pela homeostase energética</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47663</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i3p303-309</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 3 (2012); 303-309</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 3 (2012); 303-309</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 3 (2012); 303-309</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47663/51403</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47664</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Health status profile of climacteric women</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil do estado de saúde de mulheres climatéricas</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Roberta D.S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Flávia G.D.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Tatiana P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Viegas, Riana L.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Faria, Angélica</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Suen, Vivian M. M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Navarro, Anderson M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Iannetta, Renata</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nonino, Carla B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marchini, Julio S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Iannetta, Odilon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Climatério. Menopausa. Hipertensão. Diabetes Mellitus. Dislipidemias. Obesidade.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Climacteric. Menopause. Hypertension. Diabetes Mellitus. Dyslipidemias. Obesity.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: Estudo retrospectivo com análise de dados de prontuário.Objetivo: O presente estudo teve por objetivo verificar a freqüência de obesidade, diabetes mellitus,hipertensão arterial e dislipidemia em um grupo de mulheres climatéricas.Metodologia: Estudo das primeiras pacientes atendidas no Ambulatório do Climatério (ACLI) do Departamento de Ginecologia e Obstetrícia da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto -USP, no período de1983 a 2007. De fevereiro a abril de 2008 foram coletados dados de peso, estatura, Índice de MassaCorporal (IMC), grupo biológico, diagnóstico de hipertensão, diabetes e dislipidemia.Resultados: De 1983 a 2007, 400 pacientes tiveram seguimento no Ambulatório (ACLI), e 272 apresentavam seus prontuários com os dados do presente estudo devidamente registrados. Dessas 272pacientes, foram selecionadas 628 consultas, sendo que, portanto, em média, cada mulher teve trêsretornos. Estas mulheres tinham idade mínima de 29 e máxima de 80 anos, com IMC mediano acimade 25 kg/m2. O diagnóstico de diabetes, hipertensão e dislipidemia foi detectado em, respectivamente:32%, 68% e 54% dos casos.Conclusão: Mulheres climatéricas atendidas em um hospital de nível de atendimento terciário apresentaram um aumento do IMC e da prevalência de doenças crônicas não transmissíveis com o passar dotempo, o que faz urgir um olhar mais atento dos profissionais de saúde a esse grupo populacional.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study design: Retrospective analysis of medical records.Purpose: This study aimed to determine the prevalence of obesity, diabetes mellitus, hypertension anddyslipidemia in a group of climacteric women.Methods: Study of the first patients treated at the Menopause Clinic (ACLI), Department of Obstetrics andGynecology, School of Medicine of Ribeirão Preto (USP), from 1983 to 2007. Data on weight, height, BMI,biological group, diagnosis of hypertension, diabetes and dyslipidemia was collected from February/2008 until April/2008.Results: From 1983 until 2007, 400 patients were followed up, and 272 had their records registered. Ofthese 272 patients, 628 were selected queries, and therefore, on average, each woman had threereturns. Women over the age of 29 and maximum of 80 years and median BMI above 25kg/m². Theprevalence of diabetes, hypertension and dyslipidemia was respectively 32%, 68% and 54%. The prevalence of NCDs and BMI was higher for the later groups.Conclusion: Climacteric women treated at a hospital level care center showed a worsening of the BMIand the prevalence of noncommunicable chronic diseases over time, which is urging a closer look athealth professionals in this population group.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i3p310-317</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 3 (2012); 310-317</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 3 (2012); 310-317</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 3 (2012); 310-317</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47664/51404</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47665</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevalência de infecções urinárias em pacientes atendidos pelo sistema único de saúde e sua suscetibilidade aos antimicrobianos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Prevalence of urinary infections in patients served by the national health system and their suscetibility to antibiotics</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Beraldo-Massoli, Mariana Casteleti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nardi, Caroline Peters Pigatto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Makino, Lilian Cristina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schocken-Iturrino, Ruben Pablo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Urina. Resistência Microbiana a Antibióticos. Relações Hospedeiro-Patógeno</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Urine. Drug Resistence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Microbial. Host-Pathogen Interactions.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">As infecções do trato urinário são comuns tanto nosocomial quanto na comunidade. As principaisbactérias comumente envolvidas são bastonetes Gram-negativos ou cocos Gram- positivos. Tratamentos inadequados destas infecções agravam o problema de resistência antimicrobiana. O presentetrabalho teve como objetivo determinar a frequência dos patógenos causadores de infecção urinária empacientes atendidos em postos de saúde da região de Jaboticabal, SP, no período de janeiro a abril de2009, bem como conhecer o perfil de suscetibilidade antimicrobiana das espécies bacterianas isoladas. Foram analisadas 84 uroculturas positivas nos meios CLED e MacConkey e, de acordo com ascaracterísticas morfológicas, as mesmas foram identificadas por provas bioquímicas direcionadas. Asmulheres apresentaram-se mais susceptíveis às infecções do trato urinário em 88% das amostras. AEscherichia coli foi a bactéria predominante em 62% das amostras, seguida de Enterobacter sp. (9%),Klebsiella pneumoniae, Staphylococcus saprophyticus e Staphylococcus sp com 6% cada, Proteusmirabilis (5%), Streptococcus sp (2,4%), Staphylococcus aureus e Streptococcus do grupo D com 1,2%cada e Klebsiella oxytoca com 1%. A faixa etária de pacientes mais acometidos foi a de 13 a 40 anoscorrespondendo a 43% dos pacientes com infecção do trato urinário (ITU) atendidos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The urinary tract infections are common in both nosocomial and community. The main bacteria commonly involved are Gram-negative or Gram-positive cocci. Inadequate treatment of these infections exacerbates the problem of antimicrobial resistance. This study aimed to determine the frequency of pathogens causing urinary tract infection in patients from clinics in Jaboticabal, SP, from January to April 2009,as well as to know the antimicrobial susceptibility of bacterial species isolated. Eighty four urine cultureswere analysed on MacConkey and CLED means and, according to the morphological characteristics,they were identified by biochemical directed. Women were more susceptible to urinary tract infections in88% of the samples. Escherichia coli bacteria was predominant in 62% of the samples, followed byEnterobacter sp. (9%), Klebsiella pneumoniae, Staphylococcus saprophyticus, and Staphylococcus spwith 6% each, Proteus mirabilis (5%), Streptococcus sp (2.4%), Staphylococcus aureus and Streptococcus D at 1.2% each and Klebsiella oxytoca 1%. The age group most affected patients was 13 to 40 yearsold, accounting for 43% of patients with urinary tract infection (UTI) treated.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47665</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i3p318-321</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 3 (2012); 318-321</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 3 (2012); 318-321</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 3 (2012); 318-321</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47665/51405</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/47670</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:06:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores de risco cardiovascular em estudantes da Faculdade de Ciências Médicas de Campina Grande</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Cardiovascular risk factors in students from the health Sciences Center - Campina Grande - Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mascena, Guilherme Veras</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cavalcante, Manuela Stefania Barros</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marcelino, Gustavo Brasil</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Holanda, Samara Aquino</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brandt, Carlos Teixeira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores de Risco / Sistema Cardiovascular. Estudantes/Universidades. Atividade Física. Universidades.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Risk Factors / Cardiovascular System. Students /Universities. Physical Activity. Universities.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Background: Research related to cardiovascular risk factors among college students is essential, considering their roles in society.Purpose: To assess the cardiovascular risk factors among students of the Health Sciences of a University of Campina Grande.Materials and methods: We conducted a study involving 234 university students with mean age of 23.2± 3.9 years. Students were interviewed, obtained the anthropometric data and measured blood pressure.Continuous variables were expressed as means and standard deviations, while categorical variables bytheir frequencies. We used the Student t test to identify differences between means. The chi-square testwas used to assess differences between frequencies. The level of significance was p &amp;lt;0.05. The studywas approved by the Ethics Committee.Results: The majority (161 to 68.8%) of students were female. The medical school accounted for thelargest number (150 - 64.1%) of undergraduates surveyed. The courses of physiotherapy and nursingrespectively accounted for 17.9% of students enrolled in the study. Most (53.4%) of parents had completed college. Sedentary lifestyle was reported by 123 (52.6%) students. The prevalence of overweightand obesity was 43.6%. Hypertension (HBP) was observed in 37 (15.8%) students, however, in only five(14.7%) the disease was under control.Conclusion: The prevalence of: overweight / obesity and physical inactivity were high (± 40%) and areassociated with hypertension.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Fundamento: Pesquisa relacionada a fatores de risco cardiovascular entre universitários é essencial,considerando seus papéis na sociedade.Objetivos: Avaliar os fatores de risco cardiovascular entre estudantes da área de saúde de uma Universidade de Campina Grande.Materiais e métodos: Foi realizado estudo envolvendo 234 universitários com média das idades de23,2 ± 3,9 anos. Os estudantes foram entrevistados, foram obtidos os dados antropométricos e aferidaa pressão arterial. As variáveis contínuas foram expressas por suas médias e desvios padrão, enquanto as categóricas por suas freqüências. Foi usado o teste t de Student visando identificar diferençasentre médias. O teste do qui-quadrado foi utilizado para avaliar diferenças entre freqüências. O nível designificância foi p &amp;lt; 0,05. O estudo foi aprovado no Comitê de Ética.Resultados: A maioria (161 - 68,8%) dos universitários foi do sexo feminino. O curso de medicinarespondeu pelo maior número (150 - 64,1%) de graduandos pesquisados. Os cursos de fisioterapia eenfermagem responderam respectivamente por 17,9% dos alunos incluídos no estudo. A maioria (53,4%)dos pais dos alunos tinha curso superior completo. Sedentarismo foi relatado por 123 (52,6%) alunos.A prevalência de sobrepeso e obesidade foi de 43,6%. Hipertensão arterial sistêmica (HAS) foi verificadaem 37 (15,8%) estudantes; todavia, em apenas cinco (14,7%) a doença estava sob controle.Conclusão: As prevalências de: sobrepeso/obesidade e sedentarismo foram altos (±40%) estandoassociados à HAS.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47670</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v45i3p322-328</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 No. 3 (2012); 322-328</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 45 Núm. 3 (2012); 322-328</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 45 n. 3 (2012); 322-328</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/47670/51410</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2022-08-30T21:20:25Z" completeListSize="1467" cursor="800">6ad854a8a54b3e4dbaa7b21fdcde02b7</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
