<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-08-29T21:20:53Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="rmrp">https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/184783</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-26T15:31:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:TEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">University extension in virtual spaces: strategies for the development of physical therapy teachers and students at the Federal University in Minas Gerais (UFMG)</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Extensão universitária na interface virtual: estratégias de aprimoramento docente e discente do curso de fisioterapia da Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Fabiane Ribeiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Érica de Matos Reis</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vaz, Daniela Virgínia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação continuada</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pandemia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Covid-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Continuing education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pandemic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Covid-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A pandemia causada pelo COVID-19, em 2020, resultou no esvaziamento das salas de aula como estratégia de distanciamento para a controle da disseminação do vírus. As universidades, através de seus gestores e docentes, buscaram maneiras de viabilizar a continuidade das atividades acadêmicas pautando-se na cooperação, solidariedade e inovação. Foi imprescindível buscar aprimoramentos para desenvolver o processo de aprendizagem no formato de Ensino Remoto Emergencial (ERE). Neste cenário, a extensão universitária cumpriu um importante papel. Este trabalho relata o processo de criação dos projetos Aprimoramento Docente para Ensino Superior da Fisioterapia (ADES-FIT) eAprimoramento Discente para o Ensino Superior (ADES Jr.), seus objetivos e atividades realizadas. Acredita-se que iniciativas pautadas na colaboração e com o envolvimento ativo para o aprendizado possam ressignificar as experiências no contexto da universidade.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">During the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020, classrooms were emptied to ensure social distancing as a strategy to decrease the spread of the virus. University managers and professors looked for means to continue academic activities through cooperation, solidarity, and innovation. Fast skill building was needed to make remote learning feasible. In this scenario, university extension played an important role. This paper reports on creating and adapting two extension projects to support teachers&amp;amp;#39; and students&amp;amp;#39; skill-building for remote learning, the projects&amp;amp;#39; objectives, and the activities carried out. We believe that collaborative initiatives based on active learning can give new meaning to university activities during challenging times.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-08-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/184783</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2021.184783</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 No. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-184783</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 Núm. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-184783</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 54 n. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-184783</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/184783/175272</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Fabiane Ribeiro Ferreira, Érica de Matos Reis Ferreira, Daniela Virgínia Vaz</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/184784</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-26T15:31:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:TEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">FMRP unified for a better semester: narratives of a pact that celebrates human values and collective commitments during the Covid-19 pandemic</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">FMRP unida por um semestre melhor: narrativas de um pacto que celebra valores humanos e compromissos coletivos durante a pandemia da Covid-19</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Panúncio-Pinto, Maria Paula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Flauzino, Rodrigo Humberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferraz, Victor Evangelista de Faria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bollela, Valdes Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação superior</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Crise sanitária</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pandemia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ensino remoto</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estratégias de enfrentamento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Covid-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Higher education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health crisis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pandemic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Remote education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Coping strategies</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Covid-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A pandemia da COVID-19 impactou a educação superior de diversas formas, demandando criatividade e resiliência no seu enfrentamento. Além dos novos desafios, o cenário induzido pela crise sanitária também agudizou problemas pré-existentes, principalmente no que se refere às relações humanas dentro da universidade, à equidade no acesso a recursos educacionais e à capacitação para o desenvolvimento profissional, qualidade de vida e o cuidado com as pessoas, entre tantos outros desafios. Nesse contexto, em busca de respostas para os problemas apresentados, diferentes centros e comissões da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto da Universidade de São Paulo (FMRP-USP) se uniram e propuseram a celebração do Pacto “FMRP: UNIDA POR UM SEMESTRE MELHOR”. O Pacto foi proposto para reafirmar os valores da instituição, fortalecer as relações e a rede de suporte às pessoas e aos processos, minimizar o estresse e o impacto na saúde e bem-estar de estudantes, funcionários e professores. O objetivo deste relato é apresentar os termos e condições que tornaram o Pacto possível, como estratégias utilizadas para sua execução, ações integradas de diferentes setores, comunicação qualificada visando responder às necessidades da comunidade acadêmica. O pacto promoveu ações para garantir acesso a recursos para ensino e aprendizagem, capacitação profissional e cuidado nas relações interpessoais e entre os diferentes setores da instituição. O Pacto nasceu no contexto da pandemia e chamou atenção para a necessidade constante de aprimorarmos nossas relações, de investir no diálogo e na integração. Já não se trata de ações para “um semestre melhor”, mas de compromissos e valores que reafirmamos e devem seguir conosco seja qual for o contexto e situação.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The COVID-19 pandemic impacts on higher education in several ways, demanding creativity, and resilience in facing it. In addition to the new challenges, the scenario induced by the health crisis has also aggravated pre-existing problems, especiallywith regard to human relations within the university, equity in access to educational resources and training for professional development, quality of life and caring for people, among many other challenges. In this context, in search for answers to the challenges presented, different FMRP centers and committees came together and proposed the celebration of the Pact &amp;amp;quot;FMRP: UNIFIED FOR A BETTER SEMESTER&amp;amp;quot;. The Pact was proposed to reaffirm the institution&amp;amp;#39;s values, strengthenrelationships and support network, minimize stress and the impact of this new reality on the health and well-being of students, staff and teachers. The purpose of this report is to present the terms and conditions that made the Pact possible, thestrategies used for its execution, with integrated actions from different sectors, qualified communication, responding to the needs of the academic community. The purpose of this report is to present the terms and conditions that made the Pactpossible, the strategies used for its execution, with integrated actions from different sectors, qualified communication, responding to the needs of the academic community. The pact has enabled actions to guarantee access to resources for teaching and learning, professional training and care, in addition to strengthening interpersonal relationships and between different sectors of the institution. The Pactwas born in the context of the pandemic, but it calls our attention to the constant need to improve our relations, to invest in dialogue and integration. We are no longer dealing with actions for “a better semester”, but with commitments and values that wewill continue to reaffirm.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-08-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/184784</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2021.184784</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 No. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-184784</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 Núm. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-184784</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 54 n. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-184784</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/184784/175273</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Maria Paula Panúncio-Pinto, Rodrigo Humberto Flauzino, Victor Evangelista de Faria Ferraz, Valdes Roberto Bollela</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/184799</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-26T15:31:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:TEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Remote Education in times of pandemic: the experience of the Pontifícia Universidade Católica de São Paulo (PUC-SP)</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Ensino Remoto em tempos de pandemia: a experiência da Pontifícia Universidade Católica de São Paulo (PUC-SP)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mello, Julia Brum de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sampaio Neto, Luiz Ferraz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Geraldini, Alexandra Fogli Serpa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cesaretti, Mário Luís Ribeiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Distance learning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Faculty development</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medicine undergraduate student</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Problem based learning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Covid-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação a distância</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Capacitação de professores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudantes de medicina</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Aprendizagem baseada em problemas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Covid-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Pontifícia Universidade Católica de São Paulo é uma universidade comunitária. Em março de 2020, o distanciamento/isolamento social ocasionado pela pandemia da SARS-CoV-2 impôs diversos desafios a serem enfrentados, relacionados à migração do ensino presencial para o ensino remoto/ capacitação tecnológica (e pedagógica) do corpo docente, suporte aos estudantes, capacitação tecnológica do corpo funcional e adequação da infraestrutura de tecnologia da informação. Neste trabalho trataremos da capacitação docente. Embora não existisse uma estrutura de desenvolvimento docente institucionalizada, um grupo de docentes envolvidos nas diversas capacitações que vinham sendo promovidas desde 2017 pela instituição, por iniciativa da Pró-Reitoria de Graduação, foi responsável pela capacitação do conjunto de docentes da Universidade para uso das plataformas institucionais. Também foram criados treinamentos individuais para atender às necessidades dos docentes. Superada a primeira fase de familiarização com as plataformas, a etapa seguinte foi suscitar, no corpo docente, a necessidade de qualificação das atividades remotas, por meio do uso de metodologias inovadoras de ensino. A necessidade de manutenção do ensino remoto levou à ampliação do grupo de docentes responsáveis pelo apoio às atividades remotas. Mais ainda, monitores pós-graduandos (mestrandos e doutorandos) dos diferentes cursos da universidade foram selecionados para auxiliar os docentes, de forma individualizada, para que fizessem o uso apropriado de estratégias de ensino e as plataformas tecnológicas. No curso de Medicina da PUC-SP, que tem em seu cerne o uso de estratégias ativas de ensino e aprendizagem, com exceção de parte das atividades práticas, todas foram realizadas remotamente. A adaptação das tutorias da aprendizagem baseada em problemas foi satisfatória. Um dos aprendizados mais significativos foi o trabalho colaborativo docente para a realização de avaliações somativas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The Pontifícia Universidade Católica de São Paulo (PUC-SP) is a community university. In March 2020, the social distancing caused by the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic imposed several challenges to be faced related to the migration from classroom teaching to remote teaching: technological (and pedagogical) training of the teaching staff, support for students, training of the staff and the adequacy of the Information technology infrastructure. In this work, we will deal with faculty development. Although there was no institutionalized faculty development structure, a group of teachers involved in the various training courses promoted since 2017 by the institution, under the Deanery of Undergraduate coordination, was responsible for training to help teachers to use theinstitutional platforms. Individual training was also proposed to meet specific needs. Following the first bare step of familiarization with the platforms, the next phase was to raise the need for qualification of remote activities in the teaching staff through innovative teaching methodologies. Maintaining remote education led to the expansion of the group of teachers responsible for supporting remote activities. Furthermore, post-graduate (masters and doctoral students) acted as monitors from the different courses of the university. They were selected to assist teachers individually to make the appropriate use of teaching strategies and technological platforms. In the PUC-SP undergraduate medical course, which has at its core the use of active teaching andlearning strategies, except for part of the practical activities, all were carried out remotely. The adaptation of the problem-based learning tutorials was satisfactory. One of the most significant apprenticeships was the collaborative teaching work for carrying out summative assessments.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-08-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/184799</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2021.184799</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 No. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-184799</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 Núm. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-184799</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 54 n. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-184799</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/184799/175201</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Julia Brum de Mello, Luiz Ferraz Sampaio Neto, Alexandra Fogli Serpa Geraldini, Mário Luís Ribeiro Cesaretti</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185275</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-20T14:17:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:TEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Liver transplantation. A twenty-year anniversary worthy celebration</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Martinelli, Ana de Lourdes Candolo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva Junior, Orlando de Castro e</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transplante de fígado</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fígado</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Celebração digna</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Liver</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Liver Transplantation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Worthy celebration</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">In the middle of the Covid-19 pandemic, we celebrate the 20th anniversary of the creation of the Institutional Program of Liver Transplantation, with emphasis on the first transplant performed during the first year of this century. We OCSJr and ALCM are currently retired, but we are obviously attached in an affective manner both to their colleagues and to the FMRP-USP institution. We believe that there are plenty of reasons to celebrate this anniversary. &amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-12-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185275</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2021.185275</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 No. 3 (2021); e-185275</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 Núm. 3 (2021); e-185275</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 54 n. 3 (2021); e-185275</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185275/178597</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Orlando de Castro e Silva Jr, Ana de Lourdes Candolo Martinelli</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185299</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-04T11:30:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="es-ES">La Relación entre dermatitis atópica y síntomas depresivos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The relation between atopic dermatitis and depressive symptoms</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A relação entre dermatite atópica e sintomas depressivos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Passos Junior, Marcelo Alcântara de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Farias, Alécio Vinícius Sá Gomes e</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Antunes, Gean dos Reis</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Marcos Vinicius Maceno e</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fernandes, Tânia Rita Moreno de Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Atopic eczema</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Atopic dermatitis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Depression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Depressive symptoms</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Eczema atópico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dermatite atópica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Depressão</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sintomas depressivos</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">ABSTRACT Atopic dermatitis (AD) is characterized by chronic itching, presenting with fluctuating evolution, resulting in sleep disorders and social stigmatization due to the presence of visible and recurrent lesions, that might become progressively lichenified. Factors such as those mentioned and others associated, such as incapacity for work, lack of concentration throughout the day and isolation have profound impacts on the patient's mental health, resulting in low self-esteem, depression and frustration. In addition, it is known that AD is essentially an inflammatory disease. And, recent studies demonstrate the role of inflammatory cytokines in the development of depressive syndromes, therefore may be a causal correlation between the conditions by inflammatory pathways. Objectives: This systematic literature review aimed to analyze a relationship between atopic dermatitis and depressive symptoms, identifying mechanisms responsible for this connection. Methods: The research was carried out between 11/17/2020 and 11/18/2020 following the PRISMA model and using PUBMED, Virtual Health Library (VHL) - IBECS, LILACS and CUMED - and EMBASE databases. Keywords “Depression” and “Atopic Eczema”, along with its MeSh and DECS terms, were used and associated using the Boolean method. Inclusion criteria were defined as articles that are clinical or observational trials involving a group of patients with atopic dermatitis and a control group, which could be constituted by the group with atopic dermatitis itself, however, after an intervention. The depressive symptoms had to be measured by scales or, at least, the criteria for diagnosis of depressed syndrome must have been established. Results: In the end, fifteen studies remained, which were classified among those that compare treatments and their outcomes related to depression and AD, those that propose AD as an aggravator of depressive symptoms, those that propose depressive symptoms as an aggravating factor for AD and those that bring statistical analysis without clearly establishing where the causality relation resides. Conclusion: Several studies have presented a relationship between the condition of AD and depressive symptoms in distinct pathways, or analyzing AD as an aggravating factor for depressive symptoms or vice-versa. From this perspective, there may be a cyclical bidirectional causality, in which constant positive feedback generates worsening of both conditions until the adequate approach is taken, highlighting the importance of the multidisciplinary propaedeutics for these patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Resumo: O quadro da dermatite atópica (DA) é caracterizado por prurido crônico de evolução flutuante, que pode resultar em distúrbios no padrão de sono e em estigmatização social devido à presença de lesões visíveis e recidivantes, as quais tendem a se tornar progressivamente liquenificadas. Fatores como os já citados e outros associados, como incapacidade laboral, falta de concentração ao longo do dia e isolamento apresentam-se como profundos impactantes para a saúde mental do paciente, podendo resultar em baixa autoestima, depressão e frustração. Além disso, sabe-se que a DA é uma doença essencialmente inflamatória, ao mesmo tempo em que estudos recentes demonstram papel de citocinas no desenvolvimento de síndromes depressivas, podendo haver correlação causal entre os quadros por vias inflamatórias. Objetivos: Essa revisão sistemática de literatura objetivou analisar a relação entre dermatite atópica e sintomas depressivos, identificando possíveis mecanismos responsáveis por essa ligação. Métodos: A busca foi feita entre 17/11/2020 e 18/11/2020 seguindo o modelo PRISMA e utilizando as bases PUBMED, Biblioteca Virtual em Saúde (BVS) - IBECS, LILACS e CUMED - e EMBASE. As palavras-chave “Depression” e “Atopic Eczema”, em conjunto com seus termos MeSh e DECS, foram utilizadas e associadas através do método booleano. Critérios para inclusão foram definidos como artigos que são ensaios clínicos ou observacionais envolvendo grupo de pacientes com dermatite atópica e grupo controle, que pôde ser constituído pelo próprio grupo com dermatite atópica, porém, após intervenção. Os sintomas depressivos precisavam ser medidos por escalas ou terem critérios para diagnóstico de síndrome depressiva estabelecidos. A seleção foi feita por todos os autores de forma independente, sendo discordâncias solucionadas por consenso. Resultados: Ao final, quinze estudos restaram, os quais foram classificados entre aqueles que comparam tratamentos e seus desfechos relacionados à depressão e DA, aqueles que propõem DA como agravante de sintomas depressivos, aqueles que propõem sintomas depressivos como agravantes da DA e aqueles que trazem análises estatísticas sem estabelecer claramente onde reside a relação de causalidade entre os dois quadros. Conclusões: Diversos estudos mostraram a existência de relação entre o quadro de DA e sintomas depressivos em vias distintas, tanto analisando a DA como agravante de sintomas depressivos como vice-versa. A partir dessa perspectiva, é possível que haja uma causalidade bidirecional cíclica, na qual um constante feedback positivo gera piora de ambos os quadros até que a abordagem adequada seja tomada, evidenciando a importância da propedêutica multidisciplinar para esses pacientes.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-05-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185299</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.185299</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 1 (2022); e-185299</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 1 (2022); e-185299</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 1 (2022); e-185299</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185299/181511</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185299/181510</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Marcelo Alcântara de Passos Junior, Alécio Vinícius Sá Gomes e Farias, Gean dos Reis Antunes, Marcos Vinicius Maceno e Silva, Tânia Rita Moreno de Oliveira Fernandes</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185347</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-26T15:31:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:INTR</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação remota em Tempos de Pandemia da Covid-19: desafios e aprendizados</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bollela, Valdes Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-08-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185347</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2021.185347</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 No. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-185347</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 Núm. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-185347</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 54 n. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-185347</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185347/175191</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Valdes Roberto Bollela</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185512</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-04T11:30:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Sociodemographic, clinical, epidemiological and care aspects of children and adolescents treated for retinoblastoma in Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Aspectos sociodemográficos, clínicos, epidemiológicos e assistenciais de crianças e adolescentes atendidos por retinoblastoma no Brasil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="es-ES">Aspectos sociodemográficos, clínicos, epidemiológicos y asistenciales de niños y adolescentes tratados por retinoblastoma en Brasil: un estudio transversal</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bochi, Gabriela Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Alicia Natali Ferreira da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Messias, Maria Izabel Pereira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Melo, Jessica Luanda Lemos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sawada, Namie Okino</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Fabiana Lucio de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nascimento, Murilo César do</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Retinoblastoma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Adolescent</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Family</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Eye Neoplasms</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Retinoblastoma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Adolescente</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Família</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neoplasias Oculares</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Introduction: Retinoblastoma greatly impacts the affected children and adolescents and their families. Epidemiological approaches to this form of cancer in Brazil are scarce, and this gap motivated this study. Objectives: This study aimed to describe the sociodemographic, clinical, epidemiological, and care characteristics of children and adolescents treated for retinoblastoma in Brazil and analyze whether there is any association between them. Methods: It is a cross-sectional, descriptive-analytical study, carried out with accompanying family members of children and adolescents treated for retinoblastoma in Brazil, sampled by snowball sampling, via a web survey, based on a semi-structured questionnaire elaborated by the authors, shared on social media. Results: The children and adolescents were represented by 129 accompanying family members from the five largest regions of Brazil. Low education level, housewifery, and low family income were associated with exclusive care provided by the Unified Health System, while low family income was associated with the use of ocular prosthesis post retinoblastoma. Conclusion: The identified odds ratio indicated the importance of family members’ sociodemographic aspects for the clinical, epidemiological and care outcomes of the children and adolescents treated. Public healthcare services were the most used for oncology care, which endorses the relevance of the Unified Health System for children, adolescents, and their family members who have been impacted by retinoblastoma in the country.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: O retinoblastoma impacta sobremaneira as crianças, adolescentes e familiares acometidos. Abordagens epidemiológicas sobre tal câncer no Brasil são escassas, lacuna esta que motivou este trabalho. Objetivos: Os objetivos desse estudo foram descrever as características sociodemográficas, clínica, epidemiológicas e assistenciais de crianças e adolescentes atendidos por retinoblastoma no Brasil e analisar se existe associação entre tais características. Métodos: Tratou-se de um estudo transversal, descritivo-analítico, realizado com acompanhantes familiares de crianças e adolescentes atendidos por retinoblastoma no Brasil, amostrados por snowball sampling, via web survey, a partir de um roteiro autoral semiestruturado, compartilhado em mídias sociais. Os dados foram analisados por meio de estatística descritiva e inferencial, com o auxílio do software Statistical Package for the Social Sciences. Resultados: As crianças e os adolescentes foram retratados por 129 acompanhantes familiares das cinco grandes regiões brasileiras. A escolaridade baixa, a ocupação do lar e a baixa renda familiar dos respondentes associaram-se ao atendimento exclusivo pelo Sistema Único de Saúde, sendo que a baixa renda familiar também associou-se ao uso de prótese ocular pós retinoblastoma. Conclusões: As razões de chances identificadas sinalizaram para a importância dos aspectos sociodemográficos dos familiares para os desfechos clínicos-epidemiológicos-assistenciais das crianças e dos adolescentes atendidos. Os serviços públicos foram os mais utilizados para a assistência oncológica, o que endossa a relevância do Sistema Único de Saúde para as crianças, adolescentes e familiares impactados pelo retinoblastoma no país.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-05-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185512</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.185512</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 1 (2022); e-185512</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 1 (2022); e-185512</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 1 (2022); e-185512</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185512/181521</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Gabriela Silva Bochi, Alicia Natali Ferreira da Silva, Maria Izabel Pereira Messias, Jessica Luanda Lemos Melo, Namie Okino Sawada, Fabiana Lucio de Oliveira, Murilo César do Nascimento</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185554</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-26T15:31:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:TEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">From emergency remote teaching to quality blended learning: our view from the Institute of Biosciences at University of São Paulo (IB-USP)</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Do ensino remoto emergencial ao ensino híbrido no curso de Ciências Biológicas: a nossa visão a partir do Instituto de Biociências da Universidade de São Paulo (IB-USP)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chow, Fungyi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Calixto, Cristiane Paula Gomes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mello, Marco Aurelio Ribeiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação à distância</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação remota</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ensino online</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ensino híbrido</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tecnologia educacional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">COVID-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Distance education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Remote learning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Online teaching</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Blended learning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Educational techonology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">COVID-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A formação de biólogos baseia-se fortemente em um currículo presencial, incluindo inúmeras atividades práticas de laboratório e campo. Essa estrutura foi abruptamente abalada pela pandemia em 2020, forçando-nos a uma mudança para o ensino remoto emergencial (ERE). Sobrevivemos e nos adaptamos. Agora é hora de refletirmos com calma sobre a nossa prática docente. Que tal aproveitar o que aprendemos no calor da batalha e pensar em uma futura evolução do ERE para o ensino híbrido no curso de Ciências Biológicas do IB-USP? Assim como ocorre evolução biológica e cultural, é natural que a nossa prática docente e o processo de ensino-aprendizagem também evoluam. Cometemos erros e acertos, e as nossas experiências oferecem uma oportunidade de abraçar o processo de adaptação e evoluir. É importante ressaltar que o hibridismo em um curso de Ciências Biológicas, por definição, não envolve abolir experiências práticas presenciais que fomentem habilidades e competências fundamentais para a atuação profissional de biólogos. Não defendemos aqui uma migração integral para a educação a distância (EAD) ou os cursos abertos online em massa (MOOC), mas a incorporação de aprendizados e ferramentas obtidos durante o ERE. O ensino híbrido, além de valorizar significado e contexto, pode facilitar que cada aluno estabeleça o seu próprio ritmo de estudo. Ele permite ao estudante um papel ativo na aprendizagem autônoma e na exploração de novos conteúdos, dentro de limites de organização e prazos de aprendizado. Isso pode ainda aumentar o aproveitamento das atividades práticas de laboratório e campo, e de outras que são mais produtivas em modo presencial. O ensino híbrido, com boa parte do conteúdo passada de forma remota, torna a experiência de aprendizagem mais agradável e possibilita a construção do conhecimento de forma mais colaborativa, ativa e integrativa. É notório que estamos enfrentando um dos maiores desafios da nossa era. Felizmente, temos a oportunidade de unir as nossas experiências e aumentar a eficiência do processo ensino- aprendizagem, assim como promover uma maior inclusão e acolhimento nas nossas turmas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The training of biologists is strongly based on a face-to-face curriculum, including numerous hands-on laboratory and field activities. This structure was abruptly changed by the 2020 pandemic, forcing us to move to emergency remote teaching (ERT). We survived and adapted, and we can now seize the opportunity to reflect on our teaching practices. Howabout we take advantage of what we learned in the heart of the battle and think about adopting the blended learning approach in the course of Biological Sciences at IB-USP? Just as biological and cultural evolution occur; it is only natural that our teaching practices and the teaching-learning processes also evolve. We had hits and misses with ERT, and theseexperiences allowed us to embrace adaptation, transforming our teaching practices. Surely,adopting the blended learning approach in a biology course, by definition, does not involve abolishing hands-on activities that foster fundamental skills and competences of the professional biologist. Therefore, we do not advocate here for a full migration to distance education (DE) or massive open online courses (MOOC), but rather to the incorporation ofeducational technology tools, used during the ERT, within traditional place-based teaching methods. Crucially, blended learning has the potential to improve teaching practices in higher education courses. For example, it allows each student to become an autonomous learner where they can establish their own pace of study and take an active role in the exploration of new content. As a consequence, this can increase student performance in hands-on laboratory and field activities, and other activities that are more productive in person. In blended learning, most of the content is passed on remotely, making the learning experience more enjoyable and enabling the construction of knowledge in a more collaborative, active and integrated way. In summary, it is clear that we are facing one of the greatest challenges of our era but, fortunately, we have the opportunity to combine ourexperiences and improve our teaching practices, while promoting social acceptance and inclusive classrooms.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-08-24</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185554</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2021.185554</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 No. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-185554</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 Núm. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-185554</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 54 n. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-185554</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185554/175307</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Fungyi Chow, Cristiane Paula Gomes Calixto, Marco Aurelio Ribeiro Mello</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185559</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-26T15:31:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:TEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Desenvolvimento Docente para educação remota emergencial em 2020: a experiência da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto da Universidade de São Paulo (FMRP-USP)</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Faculty Development for Emergency Remote Education in 2020: the experience at Ribeirão Preto School of Medicine, University of São Paulo (FMRP-USP)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carmona, Fábio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bollela, Valdes Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação a distância</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Aprendizagem online</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Teleducação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Escolas para Profissionais de Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Covid-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Education distance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Online learning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Teleducation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Schools health occupations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Covid-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">After the suspension of face-to-face classes in 2020, due to the Covid-19 pandemic, it was necessary to provide emergency remote education for thousands of students at all levels of education in Brazil. No one was prepared to face such a challenge. Due to the lack of familiarity with technology-mediated education strategies, the only available at that, this situation soon brought to light signs of fatigue and stress among teachers and students. It was also noticeable the need, on the part of teachers, of training to take advantage of the existing resources for remote education at the university. The energy expended for the preparation of classes, activities, and assessments in the context of remote education was enormous and it would be necessary to acquire basic skills to keep the teaching-learning and assessment processes of students happening and with good quality. These signs and requests for help on the part of teachers and students began to become evident at the end of May 2020 at the Ribeirão Preto Medical School of the University of São Paulo (FMRP-USP). Students complained about content overload, overlapping and disorganization of the activities proposed for the virtual environment, and were very anxious about the assessments they would have at the end of the semester. On the other hand, we saw insecure teachers offering online activities, unsure of how to take care of various aspects, such as: recording attendance, engaging students in online classes and, most importantly, student assessment. In short, how to use remote education resources, starting from little or almost no previous experience? In this context, the Center of Faculty Development for Teaching (CDDE) of FMRP-USP assesses the needs of teachers and proposes a training focused on the use of the USP e-Disciplines platform, according to the basic principles of good education and student assessment. For those teachers with greater expertise in remote education, we conducted two complete courses using hybrid teaching based on the remote flipped classroom strategy. For a more novice audience or for those who would not be able to dedicate themselves to the complete course, we provided personalized help. This is the experience that we present in this article and that will serve as a basis for the necessary adaptations to face the education challenge during and after the most acute phase of the Covid-19 pandemic.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Após a suspensão das aulas presenciais em 2020, devido à pandemia da Covid-19, foi necessário viabilizar educação remota emergencial para milhares de estudantes de todos os níveis do ensino no Brasil. Quase ninguém estava preparado para enfrentar um desafio desta grandeza. Por conta da falta de familiaridade com as estratégias de educação mediada por tecnologia, única modalidade de ensino disponível naquele momento, essa situação logo trouxe à tona sinais de fadiga e estresse entre professores e estudantes. Era perceptível também a necessidade, por parte dos professores, de treinamento para apropriarem-se dos recursos existentes na universidade para a educação remota. A energia dispendida para preparação das aulas, atividades e avaliações no contexto da educação remota era enorme e seria necessário adquirir competências básicas para manter os processos de ensino-aprendizagem e avaliação dos estudantes acontecendo e com boa qualidade.&amp;nbsp; Estes sinais e pedidos de ajuda, por parte dos professores e estudantes, começam a ficar evidentes no final de maio de 2020 na Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto da Universidade de São Paulo (FMRP-USP). Estudantes reclamavam de sobrecarga de conteúdo, sobreposição e desorganização das atividades propostas para o ambiente virtual e estavam muito ansiosos com a avaliação que teriam ao final do semestre. Por outro lado, víamos professores inseguros para oferecerem atividades online, ou em dúvida sobre como cuidar de vários aspectos, tais como registro de frequência, participação ativa nas aulas, e, principalmente, avaliação do estudante. Enfim, como utilizar recursos de educação remota, partindo de pouca ou quase nenhuma experiência prévia? Neste contexto, o Centro de Desenvolvimento Docente para o Ensino (CDDE) da FMRP-USP identifica as necessidades dos docentes e propõe um treinamento voltado para a plataforma e-Disciplinas da USP, assegurando os princípios básicos de boa educação e avaliação dos estudantes. Daí nasce o módulo básico de educação remota para profissões da saúde, que busca atender docentes com diferentes necessidades na FMRP-USP. Para aqueles professores com maior expertise em educação a distância, realizamos dois cursos completos empregando o ensino híbrido a partir da estratégia da sala de aula invertida, mas de maneira remota (remote flipped classroom). Para um público mais iniciante ou que não teria condições de se dedicar ao curso completo, disponibilizamos ajuda personalizada. Esta é a experiência que apresentamos neste artigo e que servirá de base para adequações necessárias para o enfrentamento do desafio da educação durante e após a fase mais aguda da pandemia da Covid-19.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-08-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185559</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2021.185559</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 No. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-185559</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 Núm. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-185559</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 54 n. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-185559</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185559/175202</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Fábio Carmona, Valdes Roberto Bollela</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185857</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-04T10:58:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Associação entre o diagnóstico de COVID-19 e a classe econômica, raça/cor da pele e distanciamento social em universitários brasileiros</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Association between COVID-19 diagnosis and economic class, race/skin color and social distancing in Brazilian university students</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva Júnior, André Eduardo da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Macena, Mateus de Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pureza, Isabele Rejane de Oliveira Maranhão</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Ana Debora Santos de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Praxedes, Dafiny Rodrigues Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Florêncio, Telma Maria Toledo de Menezes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Clemente, Ana Paula Grotti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bueno, Nassib Bezerra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">SARS-CoV-2</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Economic status</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ethnicity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Race</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">SARS-CoV-2</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Status econômico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Grupos étnicos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores raciais</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Purpose: To determine the association between diagnosis of COVID-19 and the economic class, race/skin color, and adherence to social distancing in Brazilian university students. Methods: This is a nationwide cross-sectional study carried out with online questionnaires applied to Brazilian university students, at 94 universities in the public and private education network. Self-reported age, sex, economic class data, race/skin color, COVID-19 diagnosis, and adherence to social distancing measures were collected. Results: 5,984 individuals were evaluated. No significant association was found between the diagnosis of COVID-19 and economic class and race/skin color in the multivariable analysis. However, we observed that there were significant associations between the diagnosis of COVID-19 and partial adherence to social distancing, with leaving home only for going to work (PR: 1.35; 95% CI: 1.10–1.66; p &amp;lt; 0.01) and with non-adherence to social distancing (PR: 1.96; 95% CI: 1.29–2.97; p &amp;lt;0.01). Conclusion: The diagnosis of COVID-19 was associated with age, non-adherence and partial adherence to social distancing measures in Brazilian university students, but was not associated with race/skin color and economic class.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Verificar a associação entre o diagnóstico de COVID-19 e a classe econômica, raça/cor da pele e adesão às medidas ao distanciamento social em universitários brasileiros. Métodos: Estudo transversal, de abrangência nacional, realizado com universitários brasileiros. Foram coletados dados autorreferidos de idade, sexo, classe econômica, raça/cor, diagnóstico do COVID-19 e adesão às medidas de distanciamento social. Resultados: 5.984 indivíduos foram avaliados. Não foi encontrada associação significativa entre o diagnóstico de COVID-19, a classe econômica e raça/cor na análise multivariável. Observamos que houve associações significativas entre o diagnóstico de COVID-19 e adesão parcial ao distanciamento social (RP: 1,35; IC 95%: 1.10–1.66; p &amp;lt; 0,01) e com a não adesão ao distanciamento social (RP: 1,96; IC95%: 1.29–2.97; p &amp;lt; 0,01). Conclusão: O diagnóstico de COVID-19 foi associado à idade, não adesão e adesão parcial às medidas de distanciamento social em universitários brasileiros, mas não se associou à raça/cor e classe econômica.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185857</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2021.185857</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 No. 4 (2021); e-185857</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 Núm. 4 (2021); e-185857</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 54 n. 4 (2021); e-185857</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185857/180452</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 André Eduardo da Silva Júnior, Mateus de Lima Macena, Isabele Rejane de Oliveira Maranhão Pureza, Ana Debora Santos de Oliveira, Dafiny Rodrigues Silva Praxedes, Telma Maria Toledo de Menezes Florêncio, Ana Paula Grotti Clemente, Nassib Bezerra Bueno</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185988</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-04T11:30:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Anthropometric markers of abdominal adiposity and its relation to dyslipidemia and insulin resistance among overweight/obese schoolchildren and adolescents</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcadores antropométricos de adiposidade abdominal e sua relação com dislipidemia e resistência à insulina em escolares e adolescentes com sobrepeso/obesidade</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nogueira-de-Almeida, Carlos Alberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferraz, Ivan Savioli</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ued, Fábio da Veiga</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Ane Cristina Fayão</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Maria Eduarda Nogueira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Biella, Diego</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Del Ciampo, Luiz Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Obesity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Insulin resistance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Dyslipidemia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Waist circumference</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Anthropometry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Obesidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dislipidemia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Circunferência da cintura</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Antropometria</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Resistência à insulina</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: to assess the relationship between anthropometric indicators and laboratorial markers of cardiovascular risk in overweight/obese children and adolescents, in order to verify whether any anthropometric indicator has a better potential for use in screening cardiovascular risk in the population. Method: retrospective cross-sectional study enrolling 237 individuals aged 7 to 18 years.&#160; Body mass index (BMI), waist circumference (WC), waist circumference/height index (WC/H), glucose, HOMA-IR, total cholesterol (TC), LDL, HDL, triglycerides and TC/HDL and LDL/HDL indexes were obtained. Associations between anthropometric and laboratory markers were tested in contingency tables using the chi-square test. Correlations were tested by Spearman's correlation. Results: higher WC (Freedman cutoffs) was associated with lower levels of HDL and higher score in the TC/HDL and LDL/HDL indexes, but, using +2 z-scores as the cutoff, there were associations with low HDL and higher HOMA-IR. WC/H indicator (0.5 cutoff) was not associated with any of the outcomes, but, using +2 z-scores, an association was found with HOMA-IR. Z-scores of WC, WC/H and BMI showed positive correlation with HOMA-IR, TC/HDL and HOMA-IR, respectively. Negative correlations were found between WC and WC/H z-scores with HDL. WC and WC/H z-score were related to changes in HDL and HOMA-IR. Conclusions: there seems to be an advantage in using WC alone as a possible predictor of dyslipidemia and insulin resistance in children and adolescents. It is not possible to state that WC, WC/H or BMI measurements differ in their abilities to identify Brazilian children and adolescents with risk factors for cardiovascular diseases. &#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: avaliar a relação entre indicadores antropométricos e marcadores laboratoriais de risco cardiovascular em crianças e adolescentes com sobrepeso / obesidade, a fim de verificar se algum indicador antropométrico tem melhor potencial para uso no rastreamento de risco cardiovascular na população. Método: estudo transversal retrospectivo com 237 indivíduos com idades entre 7 e 18 anos. Índice de massa corporal (IMC), circunferência da cintura (CC), índice de circunferência da cintura / altura (CC / H), glicose, HOMA-IR, colesterol total (CT), LDL, HDL, triglicerídeos e índices CT/HDL e LDL/HDL foram obtidos. As associações entre marcadores antropométricos e laboratoriais foram testadas em tabelas de contingência por meio do teste do qui-quadrado. As correlações foram testadas pela correlação de Spearman. Resultados: CC mais elevado (pontos de corte de Freedman) foi associado a níveis mais baixos de HDL e maior pontuação nos índices TC/HDL e LDL/HDL, mas, usando +2 escores z como ponto de corte, houve associações com HDL baixo e HOMA-IR mais alto. O indicador CC/H (0,5 ponto de corte) não foi associado a nenhum dos desfechos, mas, usando +2 escores z, foi encontrada associação com o HOMA-IR. Os escores Z de CC, CC/E e IMC mostraram correlação positiva com HOMA-IR, TC/HDL e HOMA-IR, respectivamente. Correlações negativas foram encontradas entre CC e escores z de CC/H com HDL. CC e escore z de CC/H foram relacionados a mudanças em HDL e HOMA-IR. Conclusões: parece haver vantagem em usar a CC isoladamente como possível preditor de dislipidemia e resistência à insulina em crianças e adolescentes. Não é possível afirmar que as medidas de CC, CC/E ou IMC diferem na capacidade de identificar crianças e adolescentes brasileiros com fatores de risco para doenças cardiovasculares.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-05-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185988</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.185988</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 1 (2022); e-185988</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 1 (2022); e-185988</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 1 (2022); e-185988</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/185988/181524</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Carlos Alberto Nogueira-de-Almeida, Ivan Savioli Ferraz, Fábio da Veiga Ued, Ane Cristina Fayão Almeida, Maria Eduarda Nogueira de Almeida, Diego Biella, Luiz Antonio Del Ciampo</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/186048</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-07-04T13:51:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ENS</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="es-ES">La Medicina Intensiva y el Intensivista: de 1850 hasta 2021</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A medicina intensiva e o intensivista: de 1850 a 2021</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Intensive care medicine and the intensivist: from 1850 to 2021</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Filho, Luiz Alberto Cerqueira Batista</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Caraccio, Gabriela de Castro Damasceno</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Intensive care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Critical care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">COVID-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Historical aspects</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina Intensiva</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="es-ES">Cuidados criticos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="es-ES">COVID-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="es-ES">Historia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina intensiva</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cuidados críticos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">COVID-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">História</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ventilação mecânica</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Medicina Intensiva ganhou destaque no anos de 2020 e 2021 devido à pandemia por COVID-19. Trata-se de uma especialidade recente, e ainda pouco conhecida por muitos médicos e pelo público. Este artigo faz uma perspectiva histórica, desde o surgimento das primeiras áreas para observação de pacientes graves no século XIX, até o presente, com o impacto da pandemia, e as perspectivas futuras.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Intensive Care Medicine gained prominence in 2020 and 2021 due to the COVID-19 pandemic. It is a recent medical specialty, which many physicians and the public know little about. This article makes a historical perspective, from the emergence of the first areas for observation of critically ill patients in the nineteenth century to the present, to the impact of the pandemic and its consequences.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-07-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/186048</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.186048</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 2 (2022); e-186048</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 2 (2022); e-186048</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 2 (2022); e-186048</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/186048/183961</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Luiz Alberto Cerqueira Batista Filho, Gabriela de Castro Damasceno Caraccio</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/186687</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-07-04T13:51:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevalência da sensibilização a Malassezia spp. em pacientes adultos portadores de dermatite atópica e psoríase e sua correlação com a gravidade das doenças</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Prevalence of sensitization to Malassezia spp. in adults with atopic dermatitis and psoriasis and its correlation with disease severity.</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Souto, Luciana de Araújo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Fabio Brito dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida-Paes, Rodrigo de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lupi, Omar</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Immunoglobulin E</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Malassezia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Atopic dermatitis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Dosage</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Imunoglobulina E</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Malassezia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dermatite atópica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dosagem</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Fundamentos: Dermatite atópica (DA) e psoríase apresentam similaridades clínicas e fisiopatológicas. Objetivos: Avaliar a frequência da sensibilização a Malassezia spp. em adultos portadores de DA e psoríase e correlacionar à gravidade dos quadros clínicos. Métodos: De janeiro de 2016 a agosto de 2017, conduziu-se um estudo observacional em indivíduos adultos onde foram realizadas dosagem de IgE específica anti-Malassezia spp. e raspados das lesões para cultura micológica. Testes paramétricos ou não paramétricos foram utilizados para análise. Resultados: Nos 20 portadores de DA, a mediana da idade foi 29 anos. O valor médio do Scoring Atopic Dermatitis foi 45,35 ± 18,32. A mediana de IgE específica anti-Malassezia spp. foi 0,63 kU/l. M. furfur e M. sympodialis foram isolados. A análise de correlação não-paramétrica de Spearman não mostrou correlação entre a sensibilização à Malassezia spp. e a gravidade. Nos 36 pacientes com psoríase, foram obtidas as seguintes medianas: idade 61 anos, comprometimento de superfície corpórea 22% e IgE específica anti-Malassezia spp. 0,00 kU/l. Houve identificação de M. furfur e Malassezia spp. Limitações do estudo: O número reduzido de participantes dificultou a avaliação da sensibilização por IgE a Malassezia spp. Não houve uniformidade nos locais de coleta dos raspados cutâneos. Medicamentos tópicos não foram suspensos anteriormente ao exame micológico, prejudicando o isolamento dos fungos. Conclusões: Sensibilização a Malassezia spp. apenas ocorreu nos portadores de DA. O teste de IgE específica anti-Malassezia spp. não se mostrou um marcador de gravidade para a DA neste grupo.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Fundamentals: Atopic Dermatitis (AD) and Psoriasis (PS) share clinical and physiopathological similarities. Objective: Determine the prevalence of sensitization to Malassezia spp. in adults with AD and PS and its correlation with disease severity. Methods: A cross-sectional study was carried out from January 2016 to August 2017 with adults. Malassezia spp.-specific IgE dosages were measured, and skin scrapings for fungal culture performed. Parametric or nonparametric tests were used for analysis. Results: Median age of the 20 participants with AD was 29 years old, and the mean SCORAD was 45.35 ± 18.32. Malassezia spp.- specific IgE median dosage was 0.63 kU/l. M. furfur and M. sympodialis were isolated. Spearman’s nonparametric correlation analysis showed no correlation between sensitization to Malassezia spp. and disease severity. The median age of the 36 participants with PS was 61 years old, the median body surface area affected was 22%, and Malassezia spp.-specific IgE median dosage was 0.00 kU/l. M. furfur and Malassezia spp. were identified. Study limitations: Assessing the sensitization to Malassezia spp. was difficult due to the reduced number of participants in the study. Furthermore, there was no uniformity in the location to collect skin scrapings. The use of topical medication was not suspended before collecting skin specimens for mycological examination, therefore interfering with fungal isolation. Conclusion: Sensitization to Malassezia spp. was only detected in the AD sample. Malassezia spp.-specific IgE test did not prove to be a marker for disease severity in our AD sample.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-07-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/186687</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.186687</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 2 (2022); e-186687</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 2 (2022); e-186687</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 2 (2022); e-186687</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/186687/184008</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Luciana de Araújo Souto, Fabio Brito dos Santos, Rodrigo Almeida-Paes, Omar Lupi</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/187329</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-04T11:30:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Five oriented tasks in manual skills of a baby child with obstetric brachial plexus palsy</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Cinco tarefas direcionadas nas habilidades manuais de uma criança com paralisia braquial obstétrica</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Paula Reis da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gerzson, Laís Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Carla Skilhan de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia do plexo braquial neonatal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Plexo braquial</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neonatal brachial plexus palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Brachial plexus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physiotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A lesão do plexo braquial (PB) durante o parto é denominada paralisia braquial obstétrica (PBO). É uma anormalidade que ocorre na extremidade superior do corpo, em consequência de um estiramento excessivo das raízes neurais do PB. Toda habilidade motora que a criança com PBO adquirir será dificultada pela deficiência na movimentação de um membro superior (MS), repercutindo em suas experimentações motoras. Para modificar seu comportamento motor, a terapia por tarefas direcionadas pode contribuir na função do MS afetado, pois a mesma caracteriza-se com um protocolo de exercícios funcionais, que ainda há escassez em pesquisas voltados a esta morbidade. O objetivo do estudo foi avaliar o efeito de uma intervenção motora através de cinco tarefas direcionadas sobre as habilidades manuais do membro superior de uma criança com PBO, bem como sua função motora grossa. A criança do estudo tinha 17 meses, com PBO à esquerda, com fraqueza de abdução de ombro, rotação externa, flexão de cotovelo e queda do punho. Realizou 24 sessões de fisioterapia com tarefas direcionadas por 45 minutos, três vezes por semana. Para classificar o grau de severidade do MSE, foi utilizado o Manual Ability Classification System (MACS). A Medida da Função Motora Grossa (GMFM-66) mediu quantitativamente aspectos motores e estáticos e o Sistema de Classificação da Função Motora Grossa (GMFCS) foi utilizado para determinar qual nível melhor representou as habilidades e limitações na função motora grossa da criança. As tarefas direcionadas foram baseadas no modelo do protocolo de terapia por contensão induzida (TCI), sendo: achar a surpresa; colher laranja; encaixar elástico de cabelo; pescaria de tampinhas; empilhar blocos. Nas avaliações pós-intervenção, o MACS demonstrou melhora no nível das tarefas de achar a surpresa, colher laranja e pescaria de tampinhas, mas manteve-se igual no nível das atividades de encaixar os elásticos e empilhar os blocos. O GMFM-66 obteve aumento do escore final e o GMFCS manteve-se no nível I. O GMFM-66 apresentou melhora de 4,99% ao final da intervenção. As atividades de achar a surpresa; colher laranjas e pescaria de tampinhas obtiveram melhora na classificação no nível do MACS quando comparadas à avaliação inicial. Os achados evidenciam melhor recrutamento muscular, com refinamento nos movimentos de flexão de cotovelo; supinação do antebraço e rotação externa (RE) de ombro.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Brachial plexus (BP) injury during labor is called obstetric brachial palsy (OBP). It is an abnormality that occurs in the upper extremity of the body due to excessive stretching of the neural roots of the BP. Every motor skill that the child with OPB acquires will be hampered by the deficiency in the movement of an upper limb (MS), impacting his motor experimentation. To modify their motor behavior, task-directed therapy can contribute to the function of the affected upper limb, because it is characterized by a protocol of functional exercises, which is still scarce in researches aimed at this morbidity. The objective of the study was to evaluate the effect of a motor intervention by means of five directed tasks on the manual skills of the upper limb of a child with OBP, as well as on his gross motor function. The child in the study was 17 months old, with left OBP, with weakness of shoulder abduction, external rotation, elbow flexion and wrist drop. He underwent 24 physiotherapy sessions with directed tasks for 45 minutes, three times a week. The Manual Ability Classification System (MACS) was used to classify the degree of severity of the MSE. The Gross Motor Function Measure (GMFM-66) quantitatively measured motor and static aspects and the Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS) was used to determine which level best represented the abilities and limitations in the child's gross motor function. The targeted tasks were based on the model of the Induced Constraint Therapy (ICT) protocol, being: find the surprise; orange spoon; hair elastic fitting; fishing for bottle caps; stacking blocks. In the post-intervention assessments, the MACS showed improvement in the tasks of finding the surprise, orange spoon, and fishing for lids, but remained the same in the level of the activities of fitting the rubber bands and stacking the blocks. The GMFM-66 obtained an increase in the final score and the GMFCS remained at the level I. The GMFM-66 showed a 4.99% improvement at the end of the intervention. The activities finding the surprise, picking oranges, and fishing for bottle caps showed an improvement in the MACS level classification compared to the initial assessment. The findings show better muscle recruitment, with refinement in elbow flexion movements, forearm supination and external rotation (ER) of the shoulder.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-05-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/187329</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.187329</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 1 (2022); e-187329</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 1 (2022); e-187329</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 1 (2022); e-187329</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/187329/181513</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/187329/181512</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Paula Reis da Silva, Laís Rodrigues Gerzson, Carla Skilhan de Almeida</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/187684</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-04T11:30:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Alterações morfológicas em leucócitos de pacientes com infecção aguda por SARS-CoV-2, Amazônia, Brasil.</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Morphological changes in leukocytes of acute SARS-CoV-2 infection patients, Amazon, Brazil.</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brito Junior, Lacy Cardoso de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Rayeli Thaisse Pinheiro da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Paixão, Ana Paula Silveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pereira, Vanessa Ingrid Cardoso</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Roberta Isabella Senna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gomes, Rafaelli de Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pinto, Andresa Correa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Azevedo, Murilo Chermont</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Coronavirus infections</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">SARS vírus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">COVID 19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Monocytes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Lymphocytes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neutrophils</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Clinical pathology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Infecções por coronavírus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">COVID 19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">SARS-CoV-2</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Monócitos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Linfócitos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neutrófilos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Patologia clínica</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">INTRODUÇÃO. A pandemia pelo novo coronavírus (SARS-CoV-2) trouxe muitas incertezas sobre quais parâmetros laboratoriais seriam mais adequados durante a evolução da COVID 19. OBJETIVOS. Correlacionar os resultados do hemograma (HGM), da relação neutrófilos/linfócitos (R N/L), da proteína C reativa (PCR) e dos achados morfológicos de indivíduos diagnosticados com infecção por SARS-CoV-2 através de Reação em Cadeia da Polimerase em Tempo Real (RT-PCR) em um laboratório particular de Belém, Pará, no período de março a setembro de 2020. MATERIAIS E MÉTODOS. Estudo retrospectivo com 30 indivíduos, de ambos os sexos, qualquer idade e queixa clínica, de origem domiciliar ou hospitalar que realizaram HGM, PCR e RT-PCR para COVID 19 até o 8o dia de infecção. As alterações morfológicas foram analisadas após a seleção das lâminas desses pacientes. RESULTADOS. Amostra composta por 15 homens e 15 mulheres, com idades entre 7 e 92 anos. Desses, 12/30 indivíduos estavam em domicílio e 18/30 internados. As principais queixas foram febre, mal-estar geral, diarreia e desconforto respiratório. O estudo estatístico mostrou a existência de relação de dependência direta entre os aumentos da R N/L, PCR e necessidade de internação (p=0,0005). A análise morfológica mostrou neutrófilos hipossegmentados com granulações tóxicas, monócitos vacuolizados e linfócitos reativos com citoplasma basofílico. CONCLUSÃO. Nossos resultados associam os níveis intermediários e elevados da R N/L com o aumento de PCR e a gravidade da doença, porém, sem relação com os achados morfológicos em neutrófilos, linfócitos e monócitos que foram comuns a todos os pacientes diagnosticados até o 8o dia de infecção.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">INTRODUCTION. The pandemic for the new coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) brought many uncertainties about which laboratory parameters would be most suitable during the evolution of COVID 19. OBJECTIVES. Correlate the results of the blood count (BC), the neutrophil/lymphocyte ratio (N/LR), the C-reactive protein (CRP) and morphological findings of individuals diagnosed with SARS-CoV-2 infection through Polymerase Chain Reaction in Real Time (RT-PCR) in a private laboratory in Belém, Pará, from March to September 2020. MATERIALS AND METHODS. Retrospective study with 30 individuals, of both sexes, any age and clinical complaint, of home or hospital origin who underwent BC, CRP and RT-PCR for COVID 19 until the 8th day of infection. Morphological changes were analyzed after selecting the slides for these patients. RESULTS. Sample composed of 15 men and 15 women, aged between 7 and 92 years. Of these 12/30 individuals were at home and 18/30 were hospitalized. The main complaints were fever, malaise, diarrhea and respiratory distress. The statistical study showed a direct dependency relationship between increases in N/LR, CRP and the need for hospitalization (p = 0.0005). Morphological analysis showed hyposegmented neutrophils with toxic granulations, vacuolated monocytes, and reactive lymphocytes with basophilic cytoplasm. CONCLUSION. Our results associate intermediate and elevated levels of N/LR with increased CRP and disease severity, however, unrelated to the morphological findings in neutrophils, lymphocytes and monocytes that were common to all patients diagnosed up to the 8th day of infection.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-05-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/187684</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.187684</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 1 (2022); e-187684</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 1 (2022); e-187684</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 1 (2022); e-187684</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/187684/181540</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Lacy Cardoso de Brito Junior, Rayeli Thaisse Pinheiro da Silva, Ana Paula Silveira Paixão, Vanessa Ingrid Cardoso Pereira, Roberta Isabella Senna Ferreira, Rafaelli de Souza Gomes, Andresa Correa Pinto, Murilo Chermont Azevedo</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/187865</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-04T11:30:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">COVID-19 and obesity: difficulties faced by patients in the preoperative period for bariatric surgery</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">COVID-19 e obesidade: dificuldades enfrentadas por pacientes em pré-operatório para cirurgia bariátrica</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Alves Júnior, Antônio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Julia Maria Salgado</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leal , Roberta Kayane Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nepomuceno, Aline Lima de Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alves, Maria Rosa Melo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cirurgia bariátrica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Obesidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">COVID-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Bariatric surgery</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Obesity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">COVID-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: A obesidade é uma doença crônica que apresenta risco à saúde e está associada a formas graves da Covid-19. Durante a pandemia, pode haver o surgimento mais acentuado de dificuldades psicológicas nesses pacientes. Objetivo: avaliar possíveis impactos durante o enfrentamento da pandemia em pacientes no pré-operatório para cirurgia bariátrica. Método: Estudo transversal e descritivo, de abordagem qualitativa, com dados coletados através de entrevista semiestruturada. Amostra composta por pacientes em pré-operatório para cirurgia bariátrica. Foram previamente estabelecidos três grandes eixos temáticos e após a transcrição das entrevistas as respostas foram analisadas e classificadas em categorias. Resultados: Foram entrevistados 17 pacientes em pré-operatório para cirurgia bariátrica, sendo dez do sexo feminino e sete do sexo masculino. A média de idade dos participantes foi de 36,7 ± 13,6 anos e o índice de massa corporal médio foi de 43,9 ± 8,4 kg/m2. Os pacientes apresentaram dificuldades em seguir o protocolo nutricional e realizar atividades físicas, importantes na preparação para a cirurgia bariátrica. O momento vivido durante a pandemia da Covid-19 trouxe sequelas principalmente no emocional dos entrevistados. Conclusão: É importante manter assiduamente o acompanhamento por equipes multiprofissionais para esses pacientes durante a pandemia, mesmo que remotamente, a fim de melhorar a gestão da sua saúde física e mental no pré-operatório da cirurgia bariátrica.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Introduction: Obesity is a chronic disease that poses health risks and is associated with severe forms of COVID-19. During the COVID-19 pandemic, psychological difficulties may emerge more often in obese patients. Objective: to evaluate possible impacts when coping with the pandemic in patients in the preoperative period for bariatric surgery. Method: A cross-sectional descriptive study with a qualitative approach and data collected through semi-structured interviews. The sample was composed of patients in the preoperative period for bariatric surgery. Three main thematic axes were previously established, and after transcribing the interviews, the answers were analyzed and classified into categories. Results: Seventeen patients in the preoperative period for bariatric surgery were interviewed, 10 females and 7 males. The mean age of participants was 36.7 ± 13.6 years, and the mean body mass index was 43.9 ± 8.4 kg/m2. The patients had difficulties in following the nutritional protocol and performing physical activities, which are important in preparing for bariatric surgery. The moment experienced during the COVID-19 pandemic caused sequels, particularly emotional ones, in the interviewees. Conclusion: It is important to maintain frequent monitoring by multidisciplinary teams for these patients during the pandemic, even if remotely, to improve the management of their physical and mental health in the preoperative period of bariatric surgery.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-05-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/187865</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.187865</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 1 (2022); e-187865</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 1 (2022); e-187865</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 1 (2022); e-187865</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/187865/181515</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/187865/181514</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Antônio Alves Júnior, Julia Maria Salgado Carvalho, Roberta Kayane Silva Leal , Aline Lima de Oliveira Nepomuceno, Maria Rosa Melo Alves</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/188023</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-07-04T13:51:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da qualidade de vida em pacientes com doença inflamatória intestinal</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Assessment of quality of life in patients with inflammatory bowel disease</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Yutani Koseki, Ives Alexandre</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marciano Neto, João Hélio Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Campanher, Djeison Mikael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nunes, Simoni Euzébio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Araujo, Daniel Brito de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bueno, Elza Cristina Miranda da Cunha</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ulcerative rectocolitis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Crohn’s disease</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Depression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Retocolite ulcerativa</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doença de Crohn</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Depressão</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A doença inflamatória intestinal (DII) é um distúrbio inflamatório crônico do trato gastrointestinal ocorrendo principalmente na faixa etária jovem socioeconomicamente ativa. Tanto o curso recorrente-remitente dos sintomas quanto a cronicidade da doença impactam a qualidade de vida (QoL) dos pacientes. Objetivo: avaliar a qualidade de vida de pacientes com DII em um serviço terciário. Métodos: estudo transversal de pacientes atendidos no ambulatório de DII da Universidade Federal de Pelotas no período de janeiro a novembro de 2020, com coleta de dados clínicos e laboratoriais. A atividade de doença foi avaliada pelo Crohn’s Disease Activity Index para os casos de Doença de Crohn e escore de Mayo para os casos de retocolite ulcerativa e QoL por meio do Inflammatory Bowel Disease Questionnaire (IBDQ). Resultados: a presença de história de depressão resultou em impacto significativo na QoL (p = 0,005) e principalmente nos domínios sintomas sistêmicos (p = 0,04), social (p &amp;lt; 0,001) e emocional (p = 0,008). Em relação à atividade da doença, evidenciado significância estatística nos domínios sintomas intestinais (p &amp;lt; 0,001) e qualidade global (p &amp;lt; 0,001). Conclusão: há evidências de que os pacientes com história de depressão e não remissão da DII apresentam maior impacto na qualidade de vida avaliados pelo IBDQ.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) is a chronic inflammatory disorder of the gastrointestinal tract, occurring mainly in the young, socioeconomically active age group. Both the recurrent-remitting course of symptoms and the chronicity of the disease impact patients’ quality of life (QoL). Objective: determine the contributing factors associatedwith QoL in IBD patients in a tertiary service. Methods: a cross-sectional study of patients seen at the IBD outpatient clinic of the Federal University of Pelotas from January to November 2020, with clinical and laboratory data collection. Disease assessment was performed using Crohn’s Disease Activity Index for Crohn’s disease and Mayo score for ulcerative colitis and quality of life through the Inflammatory Bowel Disease Questionnaire (IBDQ). Results: the presence of a history of depression resulted in a significant impact on the overall QoL (p = 0.005) andmainly in the systemic symptoms (p = 0.04), social (p &amp;lt;0.001), and emotional (p = 0.008) domains. Regarding disease activity, statistical significance was evidenced in the intestinal symptoms domain (p &amp;lt;0.001) and overall QoL (p &amp;lt;0.001). Conclusion: a history of psychiatric illness and IBD disease activity were predictors of poorer QoL assessed by the IBDQ.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-07-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/188023</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.188023</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 2 (2022); e-188023</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 2 (2022); e-188023</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 2 (2022); e-188023</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/188023/184010</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Ives Alexandre Yutani Koseki, João Hélio Alves Marciano Neto, Djeison Mikael Campanher; Simoni Euzébio Nunes; Daniel Brito de Araujo, Elza Cristina Miranda da Cunha Bueno</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/188343</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-07-04T13:51:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Ectopic Third Molar in the Mandibular Notch</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Terceiro Molar Ectópico em Incisura Mandibular</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ishii, Jessica Tiemi Ribeiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Batista, Jonas Dantas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gondo, Roberto Massayoshi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Melo, Plínio Eduardo Celiac de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Clovis Martins</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rocha, Flaviana Soares</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terceiro molar</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Erupção ectópica de dente</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Mandíbula</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Molar third</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Tooth eruption ectopic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Mandible</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Dentes ectópicos são frequentemente encontrados, entretanto, terceiros molares inferiores ectópicos são incomuns, com etiologia obscura e pouco descritos na literatura pertinente. Sua localização já foi relatada nas regiões condilar, subcondilar, incisura mandibular, ângulo e borda inferior da mandíbula. Devido à importância do planejamento terapêutico, manejo adequado e variedade das manifestações clínicas desta condição, este trabalho teve como objetivo relatar um caso clínico de terceiro molar inferior ectópico na região de incisura mandibular, com radiolucência aumentada ao redor da coroa, em um paciente do gênero masculino, de 28 anos e sem sintomatologia. Acompanhamento radiográfico pode ser indicado, no entanto, em pacientes sintomáticos ou com alterações patológicas associadas, a extração deve ser considerada. Diante disso, o tratamento de escolha foi a extração do dente 38 sob anestesia geral, por via intraoral, tendo em vista a posição dentária, radiolucência e morbidade associadaà cirurgia. O tecido mole circundante foi enviado para análise anatomopatológica. O paciente evoluiu sem intercorrências durante avaliação pós-operatória.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Ectopic teeth are frequently found, however, ectopic lower third molars are uncommon, with obscure etiology and little described in the pertinent literature. Its location has been reported in the condylar, subcondylar, mandibular notch, angle and lower edge of the mandible. Due to the importance of therapeutic planning, adequate managementand variety of clinical manifestations of this condition, this study aimed to report a clinical case of an ectopic lower third molar in the region of the mandibular notch, with increased radiolucency around the crown, in a male gender pacient, 28 years old and without symptoms. Radiographic follow-up may be indicated, however, in symptomatic patients or patients with associated pathological changes, extraction should be considered. Therefore, thetreatment of choice was the extraction of tooth 38 under general anesthesia, intraorally approach, considering the dental position, radiolucency and morbidity associated with the surgery. The surrounding soft tissue was sent for anatomopathological analysis. The patient evolved uneventfully during the postoperative evaluation.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-07-05</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/188343</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.188343</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 2 (2022); e-188343</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 2 (2022); e-188343</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 2 (2022); e-188343</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/188343/183956</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/188343/183955</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Jessica Ishii, Jonas Dantas Batista, Roberto Massayoshi Gondo, Plínio Eduardo Celiac de Melo, Clovis Martins Silva, Flaviana Soares Rocha</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/189515</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-04T11:30:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil clínico-epidemiológico de usuários de saúde submetidos à Intervenção Coronária Percutânea</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Clinical-epidemiological profile of health users who have undergone a Percutaneous Coronary Intervention</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="es-ES">Perfil clínico-epidemiológico de los usuarios de salud sometidos a Intervención Coronaria Percutánea</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Arce, João Pedro Sperluk</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Liliane Gonçalves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Paulo Emilio Botura</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eggres, Danielen Antunes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tanaka, Ana Karina Silva da Rocha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lana, Letice Dalla</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Intervenção coronária percutânea</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doenças cardiovasculares</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Angioplastia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Percutaneous coronary intervention</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cardiovascular diseases</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Angioplasty</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Background: Coronary artery disease represents the condition with the highest prevalence worldwide. The treatment of this disease is through Percutaneous Coronary Intervention (PCI). Aiming: To outline the clinical epidemiological profile of health users who have undergone PCI, in a Hospital in the state of Rio Grande do Sul. Methods: Exploratory research, with a quantitative approach carried out on 188 medical records of health users who were submitted to elective or emergency PCI, with the use of stents or not in the year 2018. Values of p &amp;lt;0.05 represented significant statistical differences. Results: Users with a diagnosis of unstable angina (n = 16; 17.8%), diagnostic symptoms of unstable angina (n = 61; 67.8%) and a diagnosis of angina pectoris (n = 52; 57.8%) presented significantly more likely to be submitted to the PCI in elective way (p &amp;lt;0.001). Users diagnosed with Acute Myocardial Infarction - AMI (n = 59; 60.2%) and symptoms with evolution greater than 24 hours (n = 30; 30.6%) and less than 24 hours (n = 24; 24.5%), with dyslipidemia (n = 38; 38.8%) and who underwent catheterization on the same day (n = 87; 88.8%) are significantly more likely to perform emergency surgery (p &amp;lt;0.05). In addition, the data showed that the diagnosis of unstable angina potentiates new cardiomyopathies (n = 9, 47.4%; p &amp;lt;0.001) and restenosis (n = 5; 26.3%; p = 0.002). Conclusion: It is necessary to create strategies to strengthen the Health Care Network (HCN) with actions for prevention, promotion and rehabilitation to health, aiming quality in diagnosis, treatment and rehabilitation. &#160; &#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: A doença arterial coronariana representa a afecção de maior prevalência mundial. O tratamento desta doença se dá pela intervenção coronária percutânea (ICP). Objetivo: Delinear o perfil clínico-epidemiológico dos usuários de saúde submetidos à ICP em um Hospital do estado do Rio Grande do Sul. Métodos: Pesquisa exploratória, de abordagem quantitativa realizada em 188 prontuários de usuários de saúde submetidos à ICP eletiva ou de urgência com uso de stent ou não no ano de 2018. Valores de p&amp;lt; 0,05 representaram diferenças estatísticas significativas. Resultados: Usuários com diagnóstico de angina instável (n=16; 17,8%), sintomas diagnósticos de angina instável (n= 61; 67,8%) e diagnóstico de angina pectoris (n=52; 57,8%) apresentaram significativamente maior probabilidade de serem submetidos à ICP em caráter eletivo (p&amp;lt;0,001). Usuários com diagnóstico para infarto agudo do miocárdio (n=59; 60,2%) e sintomatologia com evolução maior que 24 horas (n=30; 30,6%) e menor que 24 horas (n=24; 24,5%), com dislipidemia (n=38; 38,8%) e que fizeram cateterismo no mesmo dia (n=87; 88,8%) são significativamente mais propensos a realizar cirurgia de urgência (p&amp;lt;0,05). Além disso, os dados evidenciaram que o diagnóstico de angina instável potencializa novas cardiomiopatias (n=9, 47,4%; p&amp;lt;0,001) e reestenose (n=5; 26,3%; p= 0,002). Conclusão: É necessário criar estratégias para fortalecer a Rede de Atenção à Saúde (RAS) com ações de prevenção, promoção e reabilitação à saúde, visando a qualidade no diagnóstico, tratamento e reabilitação. &#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="es-ES">Introdución: La enfermedad de las arterias coronarias representa la afección más prevalente en todo el mundo. El tratamiento de esta enfermedad es mediante intervención coronaria percutánea (ICP).Objetivo: Esbozar el perfil clínico-epidemiológico de los usuarios de salud sometidos a ICP en un Hospital del estado de Rio Grande do Sul.Métodos: Investigación exploratoria con abordaje cuantitativo realizada en 188 registros clínicos de usuarios de salud sometidos a ICP electiva o urgente con o sin stent en 2018. Valores de p &amp;lt;0.05 representaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas.Resultados: Los usuarios diagnosticados de angina inestable (n = 16; 17,8%), síntomas diagnósticos de angina inestable (n = 61; 67,8%) y diagnosticados de angina de pecho (n = 52; 57,8%) presentaron significativamente más probabilidades de someterse a ICP en de forma electiva (p &amp;lt;0,001). Usuarios diagnosticados de infarto agudo de miocardio (n = 59; 60,2%) y síntomas con evolución superior a 24 horas (n = 30; 30,6%) y menor de 24 horas (n = 24; 24,5%)), con dislipidemia (n = 38; 38,8%) y que se sometieron a cateterismo el mismo día (n = 87; 88,8%) tienen significativamente más probabilidades de someterse a una cirugía de emergencia (p &amp;lt;0,05). Además, los datos mostraron que el diagnóstico de angina inestable potencia nuevas miocardiopatías (n = 9, 47,4%; p &amp;lt;0,001) y reestenosis (n = 5; 26,3%; p = 0,002).Conclusión: Es necesario crear estrategias para fortalecer la Red de Atención a la Salud (RAS) con acciones de prevención, promoción y rehabilitación de la salud, con atención a la calidad en el diagnóstico, tratamiento y rehabilitación.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-05-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/189515</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.189515</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 1 (2022); e-189515</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 1 (2022); e-189515</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 1 (2022); e-189515</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/189515/181546</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 João Pedro Sperluk Arce, Liliane Gonçalves Oliveira, Paulo Emilio Botura Ferreira, Danielen Antunes Eggres, Ana Karina Silva da Rocha Tanaka, Letice Dalla Lana</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/189716</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-07-04T13:51:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="es-ES">Xantomatosis cerebrotendínea: una enfermedad rara y multisistémica aún poco conocida. ¿Cuándo debemos sospechar?</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Cerebrotendine xantomatose: a rare and multisystemic disease still little known. When should we suspect?</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Xantomatose cerebrotendínea: uma doença rara e multissistêmica ainda pouco conhecida. Quando devemos suspeitar?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gouvea, Elisa Gutman</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Francisco Ramon Canale</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sales, Deborah Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Rayanne da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hammerle, Mariana Beiral</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pires, Karina Lebeis</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neurology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neuromuscular diseases</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neurodegenerative diseases</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rare diseases</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="es-ES">enfermedades neuromusculares raras</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="es-ES">neurología</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="es-ES">enfermedades neuromusculares</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="es-ES">enfermedades neurodegenerativas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neurologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doenças neuromusculares</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doenças neurodegenerativas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doenças raras</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Cerebrotendinous Xanthomatosis (CTX) is a multisystemic rare autosomal-recessive congenital disease of biliary acid metabolism that leads to accumulation of cholesterol intermediates in several tissues. The main presentation of the disease is the progressive and irreversible neurological damage that begins in childhood and evolves with severe neurological dysfunction in adulthood. The patients also can present with characteristic non-neurological symptoms, such as tendinous xanthomas, cataracts beginning in childhood and chronic infantile diarrhea. In Brazil, there is no medical treatment for the disease. The main therapeutic approach to slow the progression of the disease is the multidisciplinary follow-up with the aim of improving the quality of life. Even though the symptoms begin in childhood, most patients take an average of 16 years to receive the diagnosis, at which stage neurological damage is already extensive and therapeutic approaches are no longer effective. In this study it is reported a case of a 47-years-old female patient with CTX that started her symptoms in childhood, with neurological worsening at the age of 38 and diagnosis at 44, a phase in which neurodegeneration was already severe and irreversible. Laboratory tests and Magnetic Resonance Imaging indicated characteristic alterations of the disease. It is important to have CTX as a differential diagnosis in the presence of a progressive, wide and varied neurological picture, associated with tendinous xanthomas and other specific signs and symptoms. Because it is a chronic and degenerative disease, early diagnosis is essential to establish measures to improve the quality of life.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Xantomatose cerebrotendínea (XCT) é uma doença congênita autossômica recessiva rara multissistêmica do metabolismo do ácido biliar que leva ao acúmulo de intermediários do colesterol em diversos tecidos. A principal manifestação da doença é o acometimento neurológico progressivo e irreversível, que inicia na infância e evolui com disfunção neurológica grave na fase adulta. Sintomas não neurológicos característicos como xantomas tendíneos, cataratas de início na infância e diarreia crônica infantil também podem estar presentes. No Brasil, não existe terapia medicamentosa para a doença. A principal abordagem terapêutica para retardar a progressão do quadro é o acompanhamento multidisciplinar com o objetivo de melhorar a qualidade de vida. Apesar dos sintomas iniciarem na infância, a maioria dos pacientes demora em média 16 anos para receber o diagnóstico, fase na qual o dano neurológico já é extenso e as abordagens terapêuticas não são mais eficazes. Neste estudo é relatado o caso de paciente de 47 anos com XCT que iniciou os sintomas na infância, com piora neurológica aos 38 anos e diagnóstico aos 44 anos, fase na qual a neurodegeneração já era grave e irreversível. Os testes laboratoriais e Imagem de Ressonância Magnética indicaram alterações características da doença. Ressalta-se a importância de ter a XTC como diagnóstico diferencial na presença de um quadro neurológico progressivo, amplo e variado, associado com xantomas tendíneos e outros sinais e sintomas específicos. Por tratar-se de doença crônica e degenerativa, o diagnóstico precoce é essencial para que se possa instituir medidas que melhorem a qualidade de vida.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="es-ES">Xantomatosis cerebrotendínea (XCT) es una enfermedad congénita autosómica recesiva rara multisistémica del metabolismo del ácido biliar que conduce a la acumulación de intermedios de colesterol en diversos tejidos.&amp;nbsp;La principal manifestación de la enfermedad es el acometimiento neurológico progresivo e irreversible, que comienza en la infancia y evoluciona con disfunción neurológica grave en la fase adulta.&amp;nbsp;Los síntomas no neurológicos característicos como xantomas tendíneos, cataratas de inicio infantil y diarrea crónica infantil también pueden estar presentes.&amp;nbsp;En Brasil, no existe terapia medicamentosa para la enfermedad.&amp;nbsp;El principal enfoque terapéutico para retrasar la progresión del marco es el acompañamiento multidisciplinario con el objetivo de mejorar la calidad de vida. A pesar de que los síntomas comienzan en la infancia, la mayoría de los pacientes tardan 16 años en recibir el diagnóstico, fase en la que el daño neurológico ya es extenso y los enfoques terapéuticos ya no son eficaces.&amp;nbsp;En este estudio es relatado el caso de paciente de 47 años con XCT que inició los síntomas en la infancia, con empeoramiento neurológico a los 38 años y diagnóstico a los 44 años, fase en la cual la neurodegeneración ya era grave e irreversible.&amp;nbsp;Las pruebas de laboratorio e imágenes de resonancia magnética indicaron cambios características de la enfermedad.&amp;nbsp;Se resalta la importancia de tener la XTC como diagnóstico diferencial en presencia de un cuadro neurológico progresivo, amplio y variado, asociado con xantomas tendíneos y otros signos y síntomas específicos. Por tratarse de enfermedad crónica y degenerativa, el diagnóstico precoz es esencial para que se puedan instituir medidas que mejoren la calidad de vida.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-07-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/189716</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.189716</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 2 (2022); e-189716</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 2 (2022); e-189716</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 2 (2022); e-189716</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/189716/183988</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/189716/183987</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Elisa Gutman Gouvea, Francisco Ramon Canale Ferreira, Deborah Santos Sales, Rayanne da Silva Souza, Mariana Beiral Hammerle, Karina Lebeis Pires</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/189735</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-26T15:31:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:TEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O futuro da Educação na Universidade: avanços possíveis e necessários</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The future of higher Education: how to move forward</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carmona, Fabio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cesaretti, Mário Luís Ribeiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Anamaria Siriani de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bollela, Valdes Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Capacitação de Professores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação em Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tecnologia Educacional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Relações Interpessoais</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde do Estudante</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Covid-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Teacher Training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Educational Technology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Interpersonal Relations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Student Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Covid-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este artigo traz uma reflexão sobre transformações possíveis e necessárias, a partir das experiências vividas por docentes, estudantes e instituições de ensino ao longo do ano de 2020, na medida em que sobreviviam, aprendiam e se adaptavam à pandemia da COVID-19. Não resta dúvidas de que a maneira de ensinar deverá estar alicerçada em conhecimentos pedagógicos, práticas colaborativas, na tecnologia educacional, infraestrutura de informática e práticas avaliativas que favoreçam a aprendizagem, através do feedback e da interação mais próxima entre aprendiz e professor. O futuro aponta para o ensino híbrido que deve auxiliar os estudantes a alcançarem a competência para a prática profissional. O desenvolvimento de habilidades interpessoais será fundamental, em especial na formação de profissionais da área da saúde. A oferta de oportunidades para o desenvolvimento docente e a estruturação de comunidades de prática para a aprendizagem colaborativa também serão essenciais. A maior flexibilização dos currículos e a mediação tecnológica do processo de ensino e aprendizagem devem favorecer intercâmbios e a internacionalização das instituições de ensino.&amp;nbsp; Deste modo, tanto o ensino de graduação, pós-graduação lato e stricto-sensu tende a ampliar seu escopo e deixará de ficar circunscrito aos seus nichos de origem, expandindo-se para a realização de convênios nacionais e internacionais. Os espaços universitários e os momentos presenciais deverão estar adaptados a nova realidade, que permita ao estudante a aquisição de competências clínicas e relacionais essenciais e que requerem atividades presenciais em cenários da prática profissional. Na área da saúde garantir estes momentos de formação seguirá como um requisito fundamental, assim, as salas de aula, os laboratórios e os campos de estágios devem ser seguros, permitindo uma orientação e supervisão direta por parte dos docentes e preceptores. Além disso, será necessário reafirmar que não existe dilema entre a formação de profissionais da saúde e a segurança do paciente, como houve a partir da suspensão das atividades práticas da maioria dos estudantes dos cursos da saúde no Brasil. Formar profissionais da saúde, num contexto de emergência sanitária, tem importância equivalente a cuidar de pessoas em qualquer cenário. Isso vale também para o acesso a equipamentos de proteção individual e a vacinas. Os desafios estão lançados e as possibilidades de avanço emergem e precisam ser aproveitadas a partir de um trabalho coeso entre gestores universitários, corpo docente, técnico administrativo e discentes.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This article reflects on possible and necessary transformations, based on the experiences lived by teachers, students, and educational institutions throughout the year 2020, as they survived, learned and adapted to the COVID-19 pandemic. Teaching should be based on pedagogical evidence, collaborative practices, educational technology, supported by computer infrastructure and evaluative practices that foster learning, through feedback and a closer interaction between learner and teacher. The direction pointed in the future includes and is based on blended education to help students to achieve competence for professional practice. The development of interpersonal skills will be fundamental, especially in the training of health professionals. Offering opportunities for faculty development and creating communities of practice for collaborative learning will also be essential. The greater flexibility of curricula and the technological mediation of the teaching and learning process should favor exchanges and the internationalization of institutions. In this way, both undergraduate, graduate and stricto-sensu education tends to expand its scope and will no longer be limited to its original niches, expanding to national and international agreements. University spaces and face-to-face moments will be adapted to a new reality, which allows the student to acquire essential clinical and relational skills, and which require activities in the professional practice settings. In the HPE, ensuring these training moments will continue to be a fundamental requirement. Thus, classrooms, laboratories and internship fields must be safe, allowing direct guidance and supervision by teachers and preceptors. It is possible and probable that, for a long time, it will still be necessary to maintain some social distance, use of personal protective equipment, hand and environment hygiene so that students are not deprived of these experiences during their training. In the health area, it will be necessary to reaffirm that there is no dilemma between the training of health professionals and patient safety, as we experienced with the interruption of most practical activities in the HPE undergraduate courses in Brazil, during the first semester of 2020. Training health professionals, in a context of a health &amp;amp; sanitary emergency, is equivalent to caring for people in any context or setting. It is the same if we are talking about access to personal protective equipment or access to vaccines. The challenges are launched and the possibilities for advancement emerge and need to be taken advantage of from a cohesive work between university managers, faculty, administrative staff and students.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-08-20</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/189735</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2021.189735</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 No. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-189735</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 Núm. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-189735</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 54 n. Supl 1 (2021): Suplemento 1 - Simpósio Educação Remota Epidemia; e-189735</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/189735/175206</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Fabio Carmona, Mário Luís Ribeiro Cesaretti, Anamaria Siriani de Oliveira, Valdes Roberto Bollela</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/190763</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-07-04T13:51:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Simultaneous occurrence of dentigerous cyst and compound-complex odontoma causing dental impaction</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Ocorrência simultânea de cisto dentígero e odontoma composto-complexo causando impacção dentária</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brazão-Silva, Marco Tullio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guimarães, Douglas Magno</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Laranjeira, Anamaria de Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Andrade, Valdir Cabra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Danillo Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Odontoma composto-complexo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cisto dentígero</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diagnóstico diferencial</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tumores odontogênicos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Compound-complex odontoma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Dentigerous cyst</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Differential diagnosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Odontogenic tumors</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The present work illustrates and discusses this disease that represents the most common odontogenic tumor in clinical practice, the Odontoma. However, an unusual variation of the same is included here in the literature, characterizedby the exams as a form of compound-complex odontoma additionally causing dentigerous cyst formation and dental impaction. The unusual case occurred in a 21-year-old woman, complaining of missing the tooth 23. The details of the exams allowed the visualization of compound and complex areas in the lesion, cystic formation and dental impaction. The histopathological findings confirmed the diagnosis of the Odontoma, and the interpretation with the set of other exams led to the final diagnosis of Compound-complex odontoma with dentigerous cyst. The present case highlights the need for early removal of Odontoma due to the possibility of developing cysts, compromising adjacent structures, in addition to its growth potential already reported in the literature.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O presente trabalho ilustra e discute essa doença que representa o tumor odontogênico mais comum da prática clínica, o Odontoma. Para tal, apresenta um caso clínico com imagens clínicas e radiográficas esclarecedoras dos aspectos dessa doença, bem como discussão a partir de revisão narrativa de literatura direcionada para a caracterização da doença. Relata-se o caso de um odontoma composto-complexo, uma forma incomum de odontoma, mas que mantém os demais aspectos usuais, sendo uma mulher de 21 anos com lesão radiopaca em maxila detectada devido à não erupção do 23. A remoção cirúrgica seguiu a partir de acesso anterior na maxila e o exame histopatológico mostrou os aspectos típicos de um Odontoma composto e complexo juntos. Independentemente da variante, nota-se que o Odontoma é quase sempre indolente, porém requer cuidados de remoção precoce devido à possibilidade de crescimento, de desenvolvimento de cistos e comprometimento de estruturas adjacentes devido a sua localização e possibilidade de crescimento.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-07-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/190763</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.190763</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 2 (2022); e-190763</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 2 (2022); e-190763</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 2 (2022); e-190763</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/190763/184030</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/190763/184029</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Marco Tullio Brazão-Silva, Douglas Magno Guimarães, Anamaria de Lima Laranjeira, Valdir Cabra Andrade, Danillo Costa Rodrigues</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/190854</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-05-04T11:30:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="es-ES">Predictores del resultado de la Prueba de Provocación Oral en Alergia a las Proteínas de la Leche de Vaca: in natura vs. alimentos procesados</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Predictors of the outcome of the Oral Food Challenge for Cow’s Milk Protein Allergy: raw vs. processed foods</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores preditores do desfecho do Teste de Provocação Oral na Alergia à Proteína do Leite de Vaca: in natura vs. alimentos processados</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Leitão, Lia Maria Bastos Peixoto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Janáira Fernandes Severo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Motoyama, Paula Vitória Pereira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Teixeira Filho, Manuel Sampaio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nogueira, Hildênia Baltasar Ribeiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bessa, Olivia Andrea Alencar Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Allergy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hypersensitivity to milk</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Children</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Alergia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hipersensibilidade a leite</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objectives: To describe the population of children with IgE-mediated CMPA tolerant to processed or raw CMP in the OFC, comparing their clinical, epidemiological and laboratory characteristics and evaluating the possible predictors of outcomes associated with these different presentations of CMP. Methods: Cross-sectional study carried out in an allergy clinic of a tertiary hospital in Fortaleza, Ceará. Data collection was carried out between October 2018 and September 2019. The questionnaire was filled out with epidemiological, clinical and laboratory data found in the medical records. The total sample was composed of 49 children with IgE-mediated CMPA tolerant to processed or raw foods in the OFC. Results: The comparison of the clinical and epidemiological characteristics of populations tolerant to raw foods vs. processed (respectively) showed similarities, such as the predominance of the male gender (60% vs. 57.9%); mixed ethnicity (73.3% vs. 68.4%); delivery at term (80% vs. 77 .8%); no complications during pregnancy (58.3% vs. 80.0%) or childbirth (70% vs. 78.9); mean maternal age (32 years vs. 35 years); level of education of the mothers &#160;(complete high school - 43.3% vs. 47.4%); age of onset of CMPA symptoms between 1 and 6 months (76.7% vs. 68.4%); exclusive breastfeeding for 4 to 6 months (60% vs. 68.45%); family history of food allergy (73% vs. 68.4%); and respiratory (38.9% vs. 35.7%) and food allergies (38.9% vs. 35.7%) as the main allergic comorbidities. Regarding laboratory data, most protein fractions had values ≤ 10 kU/L in both groups. It was found that maternal age (p = 0.006) and age of introduction of formula (p = 0.020) were statistically significant in the group of patients tolerant to processed foods. Conclusions: It was observed that maternal age (p = 0.006) and age of introduction of formula (p = 0.020) were statistically significant in the group of patients tolerant to processed foods. Laboratory data were proportionally distributed across the two groups, with a higher frequency of values lower than or equal to 10 kU/L for all CMP fractions, with no statistical significance between the groups. Similar population studies in IgE-mediated CMPA populations are important to better characterize this phenotype and optimize diagnostic tools and treatment protocols. The role of baked therapy is also noteworthy, as it helps patients to develop tolerance to different presentations of CMP more quickly, improving their quality of life.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivos: Descrever uma população de crianças com alergia à proteína do leite de vaca (APLV) IgE mediada, submetidas ao teste de provocação oral (TPO) com alimentos processados vs. in natura, e comparar características clínico-epidemiológicas e laboratoriais, avaliando preditores de desfecho ao uso dessas diferentes apresentações de proteína. Métodos: Estudo transversal ambulatorial de alergia em hospital terciário em Fortaleza, Ceará. A coleta dos dados foi realizada entre outubro de 2018 a setembro de 2019. O questionário foi preenchido com os dados epidemiológicos, clínicos e laboratoriais encontrados no prontuário; amostra total de 49 crianças, com APLV IgE mediada tolerantes ao TPO com alimentos processados ou in natura. Resultados: Na comparação das características clinico-epidemiológicas das populações tolerantes a alimentos in natura vs. processados (respectivamente), a maioria apresentou dados semelhantes, como sexo masculino (60% vs. 57,9%), etnia parda (73,3% vs. 68,4%), idade gestacional a termo (80% vs. 77,8%), sem intercorrências durante a gestação (58,3% vs. 80,0%) ou parto (70% vs. 78,9), média de idade materna (32 anos vs. 35 anos), escolaridade materna (ensino médio completo - 43,3% vs. 47,4%), idade de início dos sintomas de APLV entre 1 e 6 meses (76,7% vs. 68,4%), aleitamento materno exclusivo entre 4 e 6 meses (60% vs. 68,45%), histórico de alergia familiar alimentar (73% vs. 68,4%), sendo as principais comorbidades alérgicas as respiratórias (38,9% vs. 35,7%) e alimentares (38,9% vs. 35,7%). Em relação aos dados laboratoriais, a maioria das frações de proteína no grupo tolerante a alimentos in natura e a alimentos processados apresentou valores ≤ 10 kU/L. Foi constatado que a idade materna (p = 0,006) e a idade de introdução de fórmula complementar (p = 0.020) se correlacionam de forma estatisticamente significante no grupo de pacientes tolerantes a alimentos processados. Conclusões: Foi observado que a idade materna (p = 0,006) e a idade de introdução de fórmula complementar (p=0.020) se correlacionam de forma estatisticamente significante no grupo de pacientes tolerantes alimentos processados. Os dados laboratoriais seguiram distribuição proporcionais entre os dois grupos, com maior frequência de valores ≤ 10 kU/L para todas as frações de proteína do leite de vaca, sem significância estatística. Estudos populacionais semelhantes em populações APLV IgE mediada são importantes caracterizando melhor esse fenótipo e otimizar ferramentas diagnósticas e protocolos de tratamento. Destaca-se também o papel da terapia baked, que auxilia na aquisição de tolerância a diferentes apresentações da PLV de forma mais breve, melhorando, portanto, a qualidade de vida desses pacientes.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-05-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/190854</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.190854</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 1 (2022); e-190854</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 1 (2022); e-190854</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 1 (2022); e-190854</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/190854/181517</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/190854/181516</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Lia Maria Bastos Peixoto Leitão, Janáira Fernandes Severo Ferreira, Paula Vitória Pereira Motoyama, Manuel Sampaio Teixeira Filho, Hildênia Baltasar Ribeiro Nogueira, Olivia Andrea Alencar Costa Bessa</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/191143</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-07-04T13:51:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Magnitude dos casos de tuberculose notificados em um município: perfil epidemiológico e fatores de risco, uma descrição temporal</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Magnitude of tuberculosis cases notified in a municipality: epidemiological profile, risk factors and comorbidities, a temporal description</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Arantes da Cunha, João Pedro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marques, Ana Maria Campos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cunha, Maria Eduarda Arantes da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Bruna Martins de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Tuberculosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Public health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tuberculose</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epidemiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde pública</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: A tuberculose permanece entre as doenças infecciosas mais prevalentes em todo o mundo, os fatores de risco incluem fatores sociodemográficos e comorbidades como consumo de álcool, diabetes mellitus, uso de drogas lícitas e ilícitas e HIV. Esta pesquisa teve como objetivo estimar a incidência de casos de tuberculose e descrever o perfil epidemiológico de todos os casos notificados ao Sistema Nacional de Agravos de Notificação do município de Campo Grande/MS, correlacionando com a literatura nacional e internacional. Métodos: Trata-se de um levantamento transversal de dados que analisou todos os casos notificados em um período de 6 anos. Resultados: Houve predomínio do sexo masculino (80,3%). A faixa etária mais acometida correspondeu aos indivíduos em idade ativa (20 a 59 anos), com 84% do total de dados. O tabagismo foi o problema de saúde mais prevalente (27%), seguido pelo uso de substâncias psicoativas, alcoolismo e coinfecção HIV/Aids. Conclusões: Os dados obtidos apontam para a necessidade de avaliar o tratamento diretamente observado (TDO) na capital, dada a alarmante taxa de adesão. Cerca de 33% dos casos de tuberculose foram diagnosticados em hospitais, corroborando a hipótese de diagnóstico tardio, a qual alavanca a necessidade de ações de saúde sobre a temática.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Background: Tuberculosis remains among the most prevalent infectious diseases worldwide, Risk factors include sociodemographic factors and comorbidities such as alcohol consumption, diabetes mellitus, the use of legal and illegal drugs and HIV. This research aimed to estimate the incidence of tuberculosis cases and describe the epidemiological profile of all tuberculosis cases reported to the National System of Notifiable Diseases in the city of Campo Grande/MS, correlating with national and international literature. Methods: This is a cross-sectional survey of secondary data that analyzed all cases reported in the city from January 2014 to December 2019. Results: There was a predominance of males (80.3%). The most affected age group corresponded to individuals of working age (20 to 59 years), with 84% of the total data. As for comorbidities, 70.5% had at least one. Smoking was the most prevalent health issue (27%), followed by the use of psychoactive substances, alcohol consumption and HIV/Aidsco-infection (13.8%). Diabetes was the lowest rated disease, with 5,4%. Conclusions: The data obtained points to the need to assess the directly observed treatment (DOT) in the capital, given the alarming rate of adherence od 3.8%. About one third of tuberculosis cases were diagnosed in hospitals, supporting the hypothesis of delayed diagnosis, which leverages the need for health actions on the subject.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-07-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/191143</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.191143</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 2 (2022); e-191143</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 2 (2022); e-191143</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 2 (2022); e-191143</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/191143/184009</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 João Pedro Arantes da Cunha, Ana Maria Campos Marques, Maria Eduarda Arantes da Cunha, Bruna Martins de Souza</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/191222</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-07-04T13:51:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Ansiedade e insegurança em estudantes de medicina no internato: o impacto da pandemia da COVID-19</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Anxiety and insecurity in medical interns: the impact of the pandemic COVID-19</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dziedzic, Daphne Moreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dell’Agnelo, Gabriela Silvestre</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schindler Junior, Emerson</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lindstron, Olavo Andreucci</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Andrade, Fabiana Antunes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nisihara, Renato</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">COVID-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pandemia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudantes de medicina</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde mental</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ansiedade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">COVID-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pandemic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical students</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Mental health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Anxiety</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Objetivou-se avaliar a ansiedade de estudantes de medicina – internos e identificar mudanças em relação à perspectiva sobre a profissão durante o período pandêmico no Brasil, entre novembro de 2020 e fevereiro de 2021. Métodos: Trata-se de um estudo transversal descritivo no qual os estudantes internos responderam a um questionário de pesquisa online. A avaliação foi realizada por meio do questionário validado General Anxiety Disorder Scale (GAD-7). Resultados: Participaram 162 estudantes, com média de idade de 24,9 anos, maioria do sexo feminino (66,7%); 83,3% tiveram a opção de retornar ao atendimento prático. Destes, 35% afirmaram ter tido contato com pacientes suspeitos para COVID-19 e 13% tiveram teste positivo para COVID-19. Os escores do GAD-7 mostraram que 37% apresentaram sintomas de ansiedade leve, 22,8% moderado, e 6,8% grave. Um escore GAD-7 positivo para TAG foi encontrado em 29,6% deles. A ansiedade associou-se significativamente (p = 0,013) ao questionamento da escolha da Medicina como profissão.Conclusões: Encontramos alta frequência de internos com sintomas de ansiedade, superior à observada em estudos semelhantes anteriores à pandemia. Além disso, os acadêmicos com ansiedade foram os que mais questionaram a escolha da profissão.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Purpose: We aimed to assess anxiety among medical interns and to identify changes regarding their perspective about the profession during the pandemic period in Brazil, between November 2020 and February 2021. Methods: This is a cross-sectional descriptive study which medical interns answered an online survey questionnaire. The assessment was performed using the validated questionnaire General Anxiety Disorder Scale (GAD-7).Results: 162 responses were collected, mean age of 24.9 years, majority female (66.7%); 83.3% had the option of returning to practical assistance. Among these, 35% claimed to have had contact with suspects COVID-19 patients and 13% had a positive test for COVID-19. GAD-7 scores showed that 33.4% were qualified as “Normal”, while mild (37%), moderate (22.8%) or severe symptoms of anxiety (6.8%). A GAD-7 score positive for TAG was found in 29.6% of them. Anxiety was significantly associated (p=0.013) with questioning the choice of Medicine as a profession. Conclusions: We found a high frequency of interns with symptoms of anxiety, higher compared to similar studies prior to the pandemic. In addition, medical interns with anxiety were the ones who most questioned the choice of profession.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-07-06</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/191222</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2022.191222</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 No. 2 (2022); e-191222</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 55 Núm. 2 (2022); e-191222</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 55 n. 2 (2022); e-191222</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/191222/184013</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Daphne Moreira Dziedzic, Gabriela Silvestre Dallgnelo, Emerson Schindler Junior, Olavo Andreucci Lindstron, Fabiana Antunes Andrade, Renato Mitsunori Nisihara</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2022-08-30T21:20:53Z" completeListSize="1467" cursor="1425">655e497f005cc0e96b208b76f35e0223</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
