<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-08-29T21:20:37Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="rmrp">https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127449</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Pneumomediastino espontâneo, síndrome de Hamman, relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Spontaneous pneumomediastinum, Hamman syndrome: case report</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Coelho Júnior, Luilson Geraldo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Figueiredo, Estevão Tavares de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Haesbaert, Cristian Machado</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pneumomediastino</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Diagnostic. Mediastinal Emphysema. Diagnosis. Computed Tomography</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diagnóstico de Pneumomediastino. Enfisema Mediastínico. Diagnóstico. Tomografia Computadorizada</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Pneumomediastinum is defined as free air or gas within the mediastinum, and in case of spontaneous pneumomediastinum there is no evidence of trauma, invasive procedures or previously diagnosed lung diseases. Spontaneous emphysema is a rare condition at urgent care centers. Hammam’s syndrome or spontaneous pneumomediastinum is more frequent in young adults. The more frequent symptoms are chest pain and dyspnea. Hammam’s sign, a pathognomonic sign of mediastinal emphysema, is a crunching, rasping sound, synchronous with heartbeat, heard over the precordium. Pneumomediastinum is diagnosed with the aid of chest X-rays and chest CT scans. It is usually a benign self-limited condition. Treatment is conservative and symptom alleviating. The purpose of this study was to describe a case of Hammam’s syndrome and the importance of clinical evaluation and early diagnosis of this disease</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O pneumomediastino caracteriza-se pela presença de ar no mediastino, sendo que no espontâneo não há evidências de traumatismo, iatrogenia ou pneumopatias prévias. O surgimento de enfisema espontâneo é uma situação rara nos serviços de urgência. A Síndrome de Hamman ou pneumomediastino espontâneo é mais frequente em adultos jovens. Os sintomas mais frequentes são dor torácica e dispneia. A presença de crepitação à ausculta cardíaca, denominado por sinal de Hamman é patognomônico. O diagnóstico é estabelecido por exames de imagem, como a radiografia torácica e a tomografia computadorizada do tórax. É uma enfermidade autolimitada e de evolução benigna na maioria dos casos. O tratamento é conservador e visa aliviar os sintomas. O objetivo do presente trabalho é descrever um caso de Síndrome de Hamman e demonstrar a importância da avaliação clínica e diagnóstico precoce dessa enfermidade</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127449</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v49i6p574-577</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 49 No. 6 (2016); 574-577</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 49 Núm. 6 (2016); 574-577</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 49 n. 6 (2016); 574-577</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127449/124603</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127450</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">An unusual presentation of Epstein-Barr Virus induced hepatitis in a 15-month-old child</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Apresentação incomum de hepatite induzida por Epstein-Barr Virus em criança de 15 meses de idade</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tofani, Gabriel B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Tadeu S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Irffi, Gustavo P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Valle, Daniela C. S. M. do</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Herpesvirus Humano 4. Criança. Hepatite</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Herpesvirus 4</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Human. Child. Hepatitis</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: We report an atypical case of hepatitis in an infant that could be helpful to physicians of various specialties, as it demonstrates an atypical clinical and laboratorial manifestation of a disease not so common at that age and that could have gone undiagnosed. Case Description: A 15-month-old female, immunocompetent patient was referred to the hospital with a 3-day history of fever, vomiting, and diarrhea. The patient presented with alternation between sleepiness and irritation associated with rapid increase in serum liver enzymes levels, but no jaundice. Neurologic evaluation showed no meningeal signs and no encephalic morphological abnormalities were observed in a cranial CT scan. Treatment consisted of symptomatic medication and daily evaluation for signs of hepatic encephalopa- thy or bleeding. A serological panel showed negative IgM but positive IgG reactivity against Cytomega- lovirus (CMV) and IgM and IgG negative immunoreactivity against HAV. She was not tested for Hepatits B (HBV) or Hepatits C (HCV). Positive immunoreactivity against the Epstein-Barr virus capsid antigen (EBV VCA) IgM and negative reactivity against IgG, indicated a diagnosis of EBV-induced acute hepatitis. The patient was discharged asymptomatic after 11 days, with decreasing serum liver enzymes levels. A 15-day follow up evidenced complete remission of symptoms and normalized laboratory tests. Comments: Hepatic involvement in infections by Epstein-Barr Virus is common, presenting with moderate and transient increase in liver enzymes. It can go undetected and resolve spontaneously, while clinical manifestations of hepatitis are infrequent. In this report, we present an unusual case of a pediatric patient with hepatitis induced by EBV infection, along with a review of the literature. According to our search, no other EBV-induced hepatitis case reports have been published involving an immunocompetent patient under 2 years of age</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Este relato de uma hepatite em um paciente pediátrico pode trazer benefícios para médicos de diversas especialidades, pois ele demonstra um quadro clínico e laboratorial atípicos de uma doença não tão comum nessa faixa etária e que poderia não ter sido diagnosticada. Descrição do Caso: Uma paciente, de 15 meses de idade, foi referenciada ao hospital com história de 3 dias de febre, vômitos e diarréia. A paciente apresentava alternância entre sonolência e irritação associada com rápida elevação das enzimas hepáticas, mas sem icterícia. Ao exame neurológico não foram evidenciados sinais meníngeos e a tomografia computadorizada de crânio não apresentou altera- ções. O tratamento consistiu em medicação sintomática junto à avaliação diária dos sinais de encefalopatia hepática ou sangramentos. O painel sorológico foi de IgM negativo e IgG positivo para Citomegalovirus (CMV) e IgM e IgG negativos para Anti-HAV. Em contraste, encontrou-se no soro IgM Imunorreativa contra o antígeno do capsídeo do vírus Epstein-Barr (EBV VCA), o que confirmou um diagnóstico de hepatite pelo EBV. A paciente recebeu alta hospitalar assintomática após 11 dias de internação, com declínio dos valores séricos das transaminases. Um acompanhamento após 15 dias da alta evidenciou completa remissão dos sintomas. Comentários: O envolvimento do fígado com infecções pelo vírus Epstein-Barr é comum, apresentando elevações moderadas e transitórias das enzimas hepáticas. Ela pode não ser detectada e ser autolimitada, enquanto manifestações hepáticas são infrequentes. Nesse relato de caso, é apresentado um quadro pediátrico atípico de um paciente que desenvolveu hepatite induzido pela infecção por EBV, além de uma revisão na literatura. De acordo com nossa busca, nenhum outro caso de hepatite induzida por EBV foi publicado envolvendo um paciente imunocompetente com idade inferior a 2 anos</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v49i6p578-582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 49 No. 6 (2016); 578-582</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 49 Núm. 6 (2016); 578-582</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 49 n. 6 (2016); 578-582</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127450/124604</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127452</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Tuberous sclerosis associated with autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease: Case report about of the TSC2/PKD1 contiguous gene syndrome</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Esclerose tuberosa associada à doença renal policística autossômica dominante: Relato de caso clínico sobre a síndrome do gene contíguo TSC2/PKD1</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Queiroz, Rodolfo M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gomes, Michela P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Valentin, Marcus V. N.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Miyake, Cecília H.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Abud, Lucas G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Marcio de Castro e</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Tuberous Sclerosis. Chronic Kidney Disease. Polycystic Kidney</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Autosomal Dominant</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Esclerose Tuberosa. Doença Crónica Renal. Rim Policístico Autossômico Dominante</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">We present a case of a young woman with chronic kidney disease, with a history of seizures, episodes of spontaneous pneumothorax and left nephrectomy. The retrospective study of the image exams showed liver, kidney and lung cysts; in addition to cortical tubers and subependymal nodules in the brain. The pathologic evaluation of kidney surgically removed characterised adult renal polycystic disease. The clinical review also with these tests revealed the diagnosis of tuberous sclerosis, and autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease, suggesting contiguous gene syndrome TSC2/PKD1</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Relatamos o caso de mulher jovem portadora de doença renal crônica, com antecedentes de crises convulsivas, episódios de pneumotórax espontâneos e nefrectomia à esquerda. O estudo retrospectivo dos seus exames de imagem evidenciaram cistos hepáticos, renais e pulmonares; além de túberes corticais e nódulos subependimários no encéfalo. A avaliação anatomopatológica do rim removido cirurgicamente caracterizou doença policística renal do adulto. A revisão clínica em conjunto com esses exames revelou o diagnóstico de esclerose tuberosa e doença renal policística autossômica dominante, sugerindo síndrome do gene contíguo TSC2/PKD1</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-08</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127452</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v49i6p583-586</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 49 No. 6 (2016); 583-586</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 49 Núm. 6 (2016); 583-586</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 49 n. 6 (2016); 583-586</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127452/124605</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127533</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:EDT</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O Diagnóstico dos transtornos mentais</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Juruena, Mario Francisco</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127533</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50isupl1.p1-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 1-2</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 1-2</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 1-2</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127533/124628</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127534</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Art.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Psychotherapies: introductory concepts for healthcare students</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Psicoterapias: conceitos introdutórios para estudantes da área da saúde</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Osório, Flávia de Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mendes, Ana Irene Fonseca</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pavan-Cândido, Caroline da Cruz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Uanda Cristina Almeida</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Psicoterapia. Técnicas. Psicoterapia de Grupo. Psicoterapia Psicodinâmica. Terapia Comportamental Cognitiva</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Psychotherapy. Techniques. Psychotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Group. Psychotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Psychodynamic. Behavior Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cognitive</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The psychotherapies can be defined as method of as therapeutic procedures based on different theoretical and technical concepts, conceived to help the patient to cope with his/her emotional, cognitive and behavioral problems. The present study aims are: a) to review the main technical and theoretical concepts associated with psychotherapy, especially those based on psychoanalytic/psychodynamic and cognitive-behavioral theoretical concepts and, b) to discuss some peculiarities of the psychotherapy of groups. This material is intented to be used as a reference to beginners students of this field of knowledge as well as others specialties of the health-related context</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">As psicoterapias podem ser definidas como métodos de tratamento, embasados em diferentes conceitos teóricos e técnicos, que visam influenciar o paciente e auxiliá-lo na modificação de problemas de ordem emocional, cognitiva e comportamental Objetiva-se apresentar: a) os principais conceitos técnicos e teóricos associados às psicoterapias, com destaque àquelas baseadas nos conceitos teóricos psicanalí- ticos/ psicodinâmicos e cognitivo-comportamentais, e b) algumas especificidades da psicoterapia de grupo. Pretende-se que este material possa servir como referência a alunos iniciantes da área, bem como a outros de diferentes áreas correlatas do contexto da saúde</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127534</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50isupl1.p3-21</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 3-21</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 3-21</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 3-21</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127534/124629</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127535</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Art.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Psicofarmacoterapia para o clínico geral</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Pharmacotherapy for general practitioners</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Baes, Cristiane von Werne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Juruena, Mário Francisco</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pharmacotherapy. Psychopharmacology. General Practitioners. Mental Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Farmacoterapia. Psicofarmacologia. Clínicos Gerais. Transtornos Mentais</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo deste artigo é introduzir o aluno de graduação na área da saúde, em especial o aluno de Medicina, no campo da psicofarmacoterapia para o tratamento dos transtornos mentais. Para isso, serão revisados os principais psicofármacos utilizados na atualidade, seus mecanismos de ação, suas indica- ções e contra-indicações, seus efeitos colaterais, oferecendo ainda diretrizes para o seu uso na prática clínica diária</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The objective of this article is to introduce the graduate students of healthcare courses, especially medical students, into the psychopharmacotherapy field for the treatment of mental disorders. To this aim, we performed a comprehensive review of the main psychoactive drugs used today, their mechanisms of action, indications and contraindications, side effects. We also provided guidelines for their use in daily clinical practice</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127535</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50isupl1.p22-36</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 22-36</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 22-36</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 22-36</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127535/124630</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127536</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Art.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos relacionados a traumas e a estressores</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Trauma and stressor-related disorders</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Martins-Monteverde, Camila Maria Severi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Padovan, Thalita</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Juruena, Mario Francisco</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Trauma. Stressful Events. Stress. Emotional Stress. Battered Child Syndrome. Trauma and Stressor Related Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Trauma. Eventos Estressantes. Estresse. Estresse Emocional. Síndrome da Criança Maltratada. Transtornos Relacionados a Trauma e a Estressores</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Trauma and Stressor-Related Disorders are psychiatric conditions related to exposure to a traumatic or stressful event, resulting in significant psychological distress social, professional and other relevant areas of the individual’s life. The clinical presentation of these disorders is characterized by symptoms of anxiety and fear, anhedonia, dysphoria, externalizations of anger, aggressiveness and dissociative symptoms. According to the 5th edition of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5), the diagnostic categories included in this spectrum are Reactive Attachment Disorder, Disinhibited Social Engagement Disorder, Posttraumatic Stress Disorder, Acute Stress Disorder and Adjustment Disorders. The objective of this review is to introduce the debate on clinical conceptualization and therapeutic guidelines of Trauma and Stressor-Related Disorders, directing professional’s choice for proper therapeutic practices related to such diagnostic categories. Also, the authors discuss the consequences of early life stress (traumatic situations that occur in childhood and adolescence) in adulthood</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Os Transtornos relacionados a traumas e a estressores são quadros psiquiátricos relacionados a exposi- ção a um evento traumático ou estressante, resultando em sofrimento psicológico relevante, prejuízo social, profissional e em outras áreas importantes da vida do indivíduo. A apresentação clínica de tais transtornos é caracterizada por sintomas de ansiedade e de medo, anedonia, disforia, externalizações da raiva, agressividade e sintomas dissociativos. De acordo com a 5ª edição do Manual Diagnóstico e Estatístico de Transtornos Mentais (DSM-5), as categorias diagnósticas inclusas nesse espectro são Transtorno de Apego Reativo, Transtorno de Interação Social Desinibida, Transtorno de Estresse PósTraumático, Transtorno de Estresse Agudo e os Transtornos de Adaptação. O objetivo desta revisão é introduzir o debate sobre a conceituação clínica e as diretrizes terapêuticas dos Transtornos Relacionados a Traumas e a Estressores, direcionando a escolha do profissional pelas práticas terapêuticas adequadas relacionadas a tais categorias diagnósticas. Além disso, os autores discutem as consequências do Estresse Precoce (situações traumáticas ocorridas na infância e adolescência) na vida adulta</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127536</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50isupl1.p37-50</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 37-50</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 37-50</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 37-50</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127536/124631</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127538</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Art.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Características básicas do transtorno de ansiedade generalizada</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Basic features of generalized anxiety disorder</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zuardi, Antonio W.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtorno de Ansiedade Generalizada</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos de Ansiedade. Terapia Comportamental Cognitiva. Preocupação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Generalized Anxiety Disorder. Anxiety Disorders. Behavior Therapy.Cognitive. Worry</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este texto é dirigido à alunos de graduação com o objetivo de caracterizar o Transtorno de Ansiedade Generalizada (TAG) com ênfase em seu diagnóstico e tratamento. O TAG é um dos transtornos psiquiá- tricos mais subdiagnosticados. Caracteriza-se por preocupação persistente e excessiva acompanhada de sintomas físicos relacionados a hiperatividade autonômica e a tensão muscular. Apresenta comorbidade frequente com depressão e outros transtornos de ansiedade. A abordagem psicoterápica, num sentido amplo, deve ser prioritária no tratamento desse distúrbio e o tratamento farmacológico, quando indicado, não deve ser a única opção terapêutica</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This text is addressed to medical undergraduate students with aim to characterize Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD) with emphasis on diagnosis and treatment. GAD is one of the most psychiatric disorders under-diagnosed. The main characteristic of GAD is persistent and excessive worry accompanied by physical symptoms related to autonomic hyperactivity and muscle tension. The comorbidity with depression and other anxiety disorders is frequently. The psychotherapeutic approach, in a wide sense, must be a priority in the treatment of this disease and, when indicated, the pharmacological treatment should not be the only therapeutic option</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127538</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50isupl1.p51-55</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 51-55</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 51-55</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 51-55</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127538/124632</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127539</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Art.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Basic features of panic disorder</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Características básicas do transtorno do pânico</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zuardi, Antonio W.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Panic Disorder. Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors. Anxiety Disorders. Panic Attacks</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtorno de Pânico. Inibidores da Recaptação de Serotonina. Transtornos de Ansiedade. Ataques de Pânico</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The aim of this paper is to characterize the Panic Disorder (PD) with an emphasis on diagnosis and treatment. PD is one of the anxiety disorders, characterized by recurrent panic attacks accompanied by a persistent preoccupation with additional attacks and maladaptive behavioral changes (American Psychiatric Association – DSM-V). Its etiology is not known, but should involve an interaction of genetic, developmental and environmental factors that result in changes in the functioning of some brain areas. The pharmacological treatment of choice is with the use of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors, which has a latency of 20 for 30 days for the beginning of the therapeutic effect</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo é caracterizar o Transtorno do Pânico (TP) com ênfase em seu diagnóstico e tratamento. O TP é um dos transtornos de ansiedade, caracterizado por ataques de pânico recorrentes acompanhados por uma persistente preocupação com ataques adicionais e alterações mal adaptativas do comportamento (Associação Americana de Psiquiatria - DSM-V). Sua etiologia ainda não é conhecida, mas deve envolver uma interação de fatores genéticos, de desenvolvimento e ambientais que resultam em altera- ções no funcionamento de algumas áreas cerebrais. O tratamento farmacológico de primeira escolha é com o uso de antidepressivos inibidores seletivos da recaptação de serotonina, os quais apresentam uma latência de 20 a 30 dias para o início do efeito</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127539</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50isupl1.p56-63</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 56-63</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 56-63</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 56-63</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127539/124633</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127540</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Art.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Diagnosis of unipolar and bipolar depressions and their specifiers</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Diagnóstico de depressões unipolares e bipolares e seus especificadores</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Menezes, Itiana Castro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Juruena, Mário Francisco</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Depressão. Depressão Unipolar. Depressão Bipolar</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Depression. Depression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Unipolar. Depression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Bipolar</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Depression is a common, recurrent and chronic disease with a high prevalence in the world population. It is a disease that affects the individual organism as a whole, affecting, in addition to mood, cognitive, neuroendocrine and physiological functions, impairing personal, social and laboral well-being. Depression is multifactorial (intrinsic and extrinsic etiology) and heterogeneous, because in addition of being unipolar or bipolar, there are specifiers (subtypes) of depression, each containing particuliarities in symptomathology. This review aimed to present the unipolar and bipolar depressions, as well as some of their specifiers, with their characteristics, diagnostic criteria, epidemiology, associated comorbidities and etiology; also presenting the importance of being done and how we can make the differential diagnosis between unipolar and bipolar depressions</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Depressão é um doença comum, recorrente e crônica, que acomete o organismo do indivíduo como um todo, afetando o humor, as funções cognitivas, neuroendócrinas e outros sistemas do organismo, prejudicando o bem-estar pessoal, social e laboral. A depressão é multifatorial (etiologia intrínseca e extrínseca) e heterogênea, pois, além de unipolar ou bipolar, existem especificadores (subtipos) de depressão, cada um contendo particulares em sua sintomatologia. A presente revisão visa abordar as depressões unipolares e bipolares, assim como alguns de seus especificadores, apresentando suas características, crité- rios diagnósticos, epidemiologia, comorbidades associadas e etiologia; também apresentando a importância de ser feito e como pode ser feito o diagnóstico diferencial entre as depressões unipolares e bipolares</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127540</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50isupl1.p64-71</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 64-71</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 64-71</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 64-71</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127540/124634</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127541</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Art.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtorno bipolar: uma revisão dos aspectos conceituais e clínicos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Bipolar disorder: a review of conceptual and clinical aspects</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bosaipo, Nayanne Beckmann</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Borges, Vinícius Ferreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Juruena, Mario Francisco</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Bipolar Disorder. Depression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Bipolar. Manic-Depressive Psychosis. Manic Disorder</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtorno Bipolar. Depressão Bipolar. Psicose</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Maníaco-Depressiva. Transtorno Maníaco</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Esta revisão tem o objetivo de introduzir aspectos históricos, epidemiológicos e etiológicos do transtorno bipolar, além de apresentar a caracterização e curso da doença e algumas questões relativas ao diagnóstico, tratamento e prognóstico. O Transtorno Bipolar (TB) é caracterizado por graves alterações de humor, que envolvem períodos de humor elevado e de depressão intercalados por períodos de remissão. O transtorno se diferencia em dois tipos principais: o Tipo I, em que ocorrem episódios de mania, e o Tipo II, em que a elevação do humor é mais branda e breve, caracterizando episódios de hipomania. O conceito de espectro bipolar amplia a classificação do TB, incluindo padrões clínicos e genéticos. O TB é uma doença comum, que atinge cerca de 30 milhões de pessoas no mundo, afetando homens e mulheres de modo diferente. As causas do TB incluem uma interação de fatores genéticos e ambientais, distinguindo-o como um transtorno complexo e multideterminado. O diagnóstico segundo os critérios do DSM-5 envolve a identificação de sintomas de mania ou hipomania e da avaliação do curso longitudinal da doença. A depressão é geralmente o quadro mais comum e persistente entre os pacientes bipolares. Embora não existam sintomas específicos que distinguem a depressão unipolar da depressão bipolar, foram encontradas características clínicas típicas de cada manifestação (e.g., perfil dos sintomas, história familiar, e curso da doença). O diagnóstico precoce e o tratamento dos episódios agudos de humor melhoram significativamente o prognóstico. O tratamento de primeira escolha é com medicamentos estabilizadores de humor, anticonvulsivantes e antipsicóticos atípicos. A combinação de medicamentos com intervenções psicossociais tem se mostrado efetiva. Não obstante, o uso de antidepressivos em monoterapia não é recomendado</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This review aims to introduce historical, epidemiological and etiological aspects of bipolar disorder, also to present the characterization and course of the disease, as well as some issues related to the diagnosis, treatment and prognosis. Bipolar disorder (BD) is characterized by severe mood disturbances, involving periods of elevated mood and depression intercalated with periods of remission. The disorder is distinguished into two main types: Type I, in which episodes of mania occur; and Type II, in which mood elevation is milder and briefer, characterizing episodes of hypomania. The concept of bipolar spectrum extends the classification of BD, including clinical and genetic patterns. BD is a common disease that strikes about 30 million people worldwide, affecting men and women differently. The causes of BD include the interaction of genetic and environmental factors, distinguishing it as a complex and multidimensional disorder. The diagnosis according to DSM-5 involves the identification of mania or hypomania symptoms and the longitudinal evaluation of the disease course. Depression is usually the most common and persistent condition among bipolar patients. Although there are no specific symptoms that distinguish unipolar depression from bipolar depression, typical clinical features of each manifestation were found (e.g., symptom profile, family history, and disease course). Early diagnosis and the treatment of acute mood episodes significantly improve the prognosis. The first choice treatment involves mood stabilizers, anticonvulsants and atypical antipsychotics. The combination of medication with psychosocial interventions has been proved effective. However, the use of antidepressant monotherapy is not recommended</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127541</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50isupl1.p72-84</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 72-84</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 72-84</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 72-84</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127541/124635</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127542</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Art.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos da personalidade</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Personality disorders</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mazer, Angela K.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Macedo, Brisa Burgos D.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Juruena, Mário Francisco</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Personality Disorders. Borderline Personality Disorder. Suicide. Physician-Patient Relations</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos da Personalidade. Transtorno da Personalidade Borderline. Suicídio. Relações Médico-Paciente</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Personality disorders are psychological patterns of difficult diagnosis that require careful evaluations from mental health professionals. The physician-patient relationship is a crucial condition for the management of these disorders. On this view it must be important guide undergraduate students from health care areas through the existence of such a category of disorders. This article consists of a descriptive review aiming at clarifying the definition of personality disorders; furthermore discuss historical, physiological and epidemiological aspects. On this publication will be reviewed some particularities from diagnostic comorbidity, course and treatment of these disorders. The management of individuals with borderline personality disorder will be emphasized in this publication due to increased seek from this public for mental health care units</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Os Transtornos da personalidade são padrões psicológicos de difícil diagnóstico que exigem uma avaliação criteriosa por parte do profissional da saúde mental. A relação médico-paciente também se configura como fator de extrema importância para o manejo destes quadros. Dentro deste contexto, é imprescindível orientar os alunos das áreas de graduação em saúde sobre a existência de tal categoria de transtornos. O presente artigo consiste em uma revisão descritiva, que busca elucidar a definição de transtornos da personalidade; além de discorrer sobre aspectos históricos, nosológicos e epidemiológicos. Nesta publicação ainda serão revisadas as particularidades referentes ao diagnóstico, as comorbidades, ao curso e tratamento destes transtornos. O enfoque maior será no manejo de indivíduos com transtorno da personalidade borderline, dada a maior procura destes por unidades de atendimento psiquiátrico</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127542</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50isupl1.p85-97</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 85-97</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 85-97</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 85-97</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127542/124636</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/127543</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Art.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Psychiatric emergencies: psychomotor agitation management and suicide risk assessment</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Emergências psiquiátricas: manejo de agitação psicomotora e avaliação de risco suicida</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Del-Ben, Cristina Marta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sponholz-Junior, Alcion</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mantovani, Célia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Faleiros, Maria Clara de Morais</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Gabriel Elias Correa de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guapo, Vinicius Guandalini</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marques, João Mazzoncini de Azevedo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Emergency Medicine. Psychiatry. Psychiatric Department</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hospital. Diagnosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Differential. Psychomotor Agitation. Suicide</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina de Emergência. Psiquiatria. Unidade Hospitalar de Psiquiatria. Diagnóstico Diferencial. Agitação Psicomotora. Suicídio</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The objective of this article is to present guidelines and assessment protocols of frequently observed conditions in the context of psychiatric emergencies, namely, management of agitation and evaluation of suicide risk. The peculiarities of the interaction between psychiatric emergency and mental health services and the differential diagnosis of first-episode psychosis are briefly presented. Based on scientific evidence associated with our clinical experience, we discuss the skills and competencies needed for the management of emergencies in psychiatry, with emphasis on psychiatric interview techniques, attitudinal/ behavioral approach and pharmacological interventions</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo deste artigo é a apresentação de diretrizes e protocolos de avaliação de condições frequentemente observadas em contexto de emergências psiquiátricas, a saber; manejo de agitação psicomotora e avaliação de risco suicida. As peculiaridades da interação entre serviços de emergências psiquiá- tricas e rede de saúde mental e do diagnóstico diferencial de primeiro episódio psicótico também são brevemente discutidas. Com base em evidências científicas associadas à experiência clínica dos autores, são apresentadas as habilidades e competências necessárias para o manejo de emergências em psiquiatria, com ênfase em técnicas de entrevista psiquiátrica, abordagem atitudinal/comportamental e intervenções farmacológicas</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127543</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50isupl1.p98-112</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 98-112</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 98-112</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. supl.1 (2017): Suplemento Temático: Psiquiatria I; 98-112</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/127543/124637</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/134993</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação do rastreamento do câncer do colo do útero e sua periodicidade em um município de Santa Catarina</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Assessment of cervical cancer screening and its periodicity in a city of Santa Catarina state</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Trindade, Griselda B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Manenti, Sandra A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Simões, Priscyla W.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Madeira, Kristian</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neoplasias do Colo do Útero. Esfregaço Vaginal. Sondas de DNA de HPV. Epidemiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Uterine Cervical Neoplasms. Vaginal Smears. DNA Probes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">HPV. Epidemiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: Estudo de Prevalência. Objetivo do estudo: Conhecer a prevalência dos resultados alterados dos exames preventivos para câncer do colo do útero e a sua regularidade na coleta. Metodologia: Estudo observacional, transversal e retrospectivo. Foram estudadas 3.425 mulheres usuárias do Sistema Único de Saúde e 9.436 exames citopatológicos de novembro de 2003 a janeiro de 2014. Resultados: A mediana da idade foi de 35 anos (25,0 - 46,0, percentil 25 a 75%). No primeiro exame citopatológico, 2,7% das mulheres apresentaram alterações em células epiteliais. As Células escamosas atípicas de significado incerto (ASC-US) (n=54; 1,7%) e as lesões intra-epiteliais de baixo grau (LIEBG) (n=24; 0,7%) foram as mais frequentes. Ao longo do período observado houveram 87 novas alterações citopatológicas, totalizando 173 exames alterados em 9.436 analisados. Quanto a regularidade, 58,5% pacientes repetiram a segunda coleta. Conclusões: Houve um perfil predominante de mulheres jovens, sendo o diagnóstico de ASC-US o mais frequente. A flora bacteriana mais frequente foi Lactobacillus principalmente em mulheres jovens</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study Model: Prevalence Study. Study objective: To determine the prevalence of the abnormal cervical cancer screening test (PAP) and regularity in repeat it. Methods: An observational, cross-sectional and retrospective study. 3,425 women, users of the Brazilian Unified Health System, and 9,436 cytopathology, conducted from November 2003 to January 2014, were studied. Results: The median age was 35 years (25.0 to 46.0, 25 to 75% percentile). In the first PAP, 2.7% of women examined had alterations in epithelial cells. The atypical squamous cells of uncertain significance (ASC-US) (n = 54; 1.7%), and low-grade intraepithelial lesion (LSIL) (n = 24; 0.7%) were the most frequent alterations found. During the observed period, 87 new abnormal PAPs were found, totalling 173 altered tests in 9436 analysed. Regarding regularity of test, 58.5% patients repeated the second PAP. Conclusions: There was a preferential profile of young women, and the diagnosis of ASC-US was the most frequently found. Lactobacillus, especially in young women, was the main bacterial flora</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/134993</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50i1p1-10</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 1-10</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 1-10</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 1-10</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/134993/130839</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/134996</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da qualidade de vida de praticantes de ginástica laboral</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of quality of life of gymnastics practitioners</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Corrêa, Thânia R. M. F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cintra, Mariana M. M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Paulino, Tony P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Renata C. R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Resende e Silva, Débora T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ginástica laboral. Qualidade de Vida. Questionário SF-36</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Labor Gymnastics. Quality of Life. SF-36 Questionnaire</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: A qualidade de vida (QV) de trabalhadores vem sendo alvo de pesquisas há algum tempo no Brasil. Sendo assim verifica-se a necessidade de avaliar QV e parâmetros antropométricos de participantes, funcionários e estagiários, de instituição de ensino que realizaram a prática da ginástica laboral com o objetivo de melhorar sua rotina diária de trabalho. Material e Métodos: Foi realizada ginástica laboral para os participantes e a versão brasileira do questionário SF-36 foi aplicada, além disto, foram avaliados peso e altura e calculado o índice de massa corporal (IMC). Resultados: Foram avaliados 21 indivíduos, sendo 19% masculinos e 81% femininos, com idade média de 35,47±12,90 anos. A amostra tinha média de peso de 63,26±5,80 gramas e média de 1,64±3,90 centímetros de altura e foi calculado o IMC, e obteve-se média de 23,25±2,90. Os aspectos motores, emocionais, além dos sociais e mentais têm determinantes no aspecto que influenciam a QV dos praticantes demonstrando que a realização de tal atividade, mesmo que em um período curto (três meses) parece trazer influências benéficas no cotidiano do praticante de tal atividade, pois a maioria dos entrevistados relatam boa saúde física e emocional, e sem prejuízos de suas atividades laborais. Conclusões: Os participantes estão satisfeitos e motivados com a liberdade de expressão, participações em decisões e satisfação com a QV no trabalho, sendo assim com o conhecimento do grau de satisfação dos trabalhadores, instituições podem ajuda a direcionar estratégias de prevenção, orientação e suporte dos seus trabalhadores, afim de proporcionar um ambiente saudável de trabalho. Observou-se que a prática de ginástica laboral contribui para estes resultados</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Introduction: Quality of life (QOL) of workers has been the subject of research for some time in Brazil. Therefore, there is the need to assess QOL and anthropometric parameters of participants, employees and trainees, teaching institution that carried out the practice of gymnastics in order to improve their daily work routine. Methods: gymnastics was held for the participants and the Brazilian version of the SF-36 questionnaire was applied were assessed height and weight and calculated body mass index (BMI). Results: A total of 21 subjects, 19% male and 81% female, mean age 35.47 ± 12.90 years. The sample had an average weight of 63.26 ± 5.80 grams and average of 1.64 ± 3.90 cm in height and calculated BMI, and obtained an average of 23.25 ± 2.90. The engines, emotional aspects, as well as social and mental are determinants in the aspect that influence QOL of practitioners demonstrating that the performance of such activity, even in a short period (three months) seems to bring beneficial influences on practicing everyday in such activity because the majority of respondents reported good physical and emotional health, and without prejudice to their work activities. Conclusions: Participants are satisfied and motivated with freedom of expression, participation in decisions and satisfaction with QOL at work, so with knowledge of the degree of employee satisfaction, institutions can help to direct prevention strategies, guidance and support of its employees in order to provide a healthy working environment. It was found that practicing gymnastics contributes to these results</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/134996</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50i1p11-17</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 11-17</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 11-17</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 11-17</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/134996/130840</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/135042</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Quality of life of hypertensive and diabetic elderly in an outpatient clinic</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de vida de idosos hipertensos e diabéticos em um serviço ambulatorial</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Esteves, Marlene</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vendramini, Silvia H. F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Maria de Lourdes S. G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brandão, Vânia Z.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Soler, Zaida A. S. G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lourenção, Luciano G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso. Qualidade de Vida. Doença Crônica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged. Quality of Life. Chronic Disease</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: Estudo populacional descritivo, de corte transversal. Objetivo: Avaliar a qualidade de vida de pacientes idosos hipertensos e diabéticos em um ambulatório de um hospital universitário no interior do Estado de São Paulo, Brasil. Metodologia: Estudo realizado em um ambulatório de Geriatria, em São José do Rio Preto, envolvendo 62 pacientes idosos com pressão arterial elevada e/ou diabetes mellitus, atendidos no período de dezembro de 2009 a fevereiro de 2010. Os dados foram coletados com o WHOQOL-OLD, analisados com o Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS) software, com testes Mann-Whitney e Kruskal-Wallis não paramétricos e correlação de Pearson, o nível de significância foi ajustado para um valor de p&amp;lt;0,05. Resultados: 38 (61,3%) idosos eram hipertensos e 23 (37,1%) diabéticos. A idade dos idosos foi de 67±7 (média, DP). Houve prevalência do sexo feminino (58 %), ensino fundamental (87,1%), casados (56,5%), profissões ligadas ao setor de serviços (56,4%), renda de 1 salário mínimo (66,1%) e morando com esposo(a) (58,1%). O maior escore mediano (75,0) foi encontrado nas facetas "Atividades passadas, presentes e futuras", "Participação social", "Morte e morrer" e "Intimidade". A faceta "Autonomia" apresentou o menor escore, correspondendo a 62,5. Os idosos hipertensos tiveram escore inferior aos diabéticos na faceta do "Funcionamento Sensório" (62,2 vs. 73,6, respectivamente). Conclusão: Os idosos apresentaram qualidade de vida inferior na faceta "Autonomia" e melhor qualidade para as facetas "Atividades passadas, presentes e futuras", "Participa- ção social", "Morte e morrer" e "Intimidade". Não houve diferença na qualidade de vida entre diabéticos ou hipertensos, exceto por tendência a menor "Funcionamento do sensório" entre os hipertensos</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Model of study: The study design was a populational, cross-sectional and descriptive. Objective: To evaluate the quality of life of high blood pressure and diabetic elderly outpatients of a teaching hospital in the interior of Sao Paulo State, Brazil. Methodology: The study was done in a Geriatrics Outpatient Service in São José do Rio Preto, involved 62 elderly patients with high blood pressure and/or diabetes mellitus treated in the period from December 2009 to February 2010. The data were collected with the WHOQOL-OLD, analyzed with the Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS) software, with tests Mann-Whitney, Kruskal-Wallis non-parametric and Pearson's correlation; the level of significance was set to a value of p&amp;lt;0.05. Results: A total of 38 elderly patients studied (61.3%) have high blood pressure, and 23 (37.1%) were diabetics. The age was 67±7 (mean, SD). Characteristics of the sample studied were: female (58.1%), elementary school (87.1%), married status (56.4%), professions linked to the sector of services (56.4%), the income of 1 minimum wage (66.1%) and living with the spouse (58.1%). The highest median score (75.0) was found in the facets "Past, present and future" "Activities", "Social participation", "Death and dying" and "Intimacy". The facet "Autonomy" showed the lowest scoring of 62.5. The elderly with high blood pressure had a lower score compared to patients with diabetes in "Sensory Functioning" facet (62.17 versus 73.64, respectively). Conclusion: The elderly showed a lower quality of life in the "Autonomy" and best quality for facets: "Past, present and future", "Activities", "Social participation", "Death and dying" and "Intimacy". There was not difference in the quality of life among elderly with diabetes and high blood pressure patients, except for a tendency to lower "Sensory Functioning" facet in high blood pressure patients</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135042</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50i1p18-28</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 18-28</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 18-28</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 18-28</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135042/130889</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/135043</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Analysis of access and care among PMAQ-AB results and users satisfaction of emergency department: similarities and differences</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Análise do acesso e acolhimento entre os resultados do PMAQ-AB e a satisfação dos usuários do pronto atendimento: semelhanças e diferenças</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gomide, Mariana Figueiredo Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pinto, Ione Carvalho</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zacharias, Fabiana Costa Machado</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferro, Denise</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Primary Health Care. Patient Satisfaction. Health Services Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atenção Primária à Saúde. Satisfação do Usuário. Avaliação de Serviços de Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivou-se identificar semelhanças e diferenças da satisfação do usuário com a Atenção Primária à Saúde (APS) nas dimensões de acesso e acolhimento a partir dos atendimentos não urgentes no ProntoAtendimento (PA) de Ribeirão Preto-SP com os resultados do Programa de Melhoria do Acesso e da Qualidade da Atenção Básica (PMAQ-AB), cuja avaliação no município de Ribeirão Preto-SP percorreu em período concomitante. Estudo quantitativo realizado nas unidades de PA dos cinco Distritos de Saúde do município. Participaram do estudo 514 usuários que receberam ao menos um atendimento na APS nos seis meses que antecederam a pesquisa. Utilizou-se o intrumento EUROPEP - European Task Force on Patient Evaluation of General Practice Care e diário de campo como fontes de dados. Amparouse nos resultados das dimensões de acesso e acolhimento da avaliação do PMAQ para identificar semelhanças e diferenças entre o que os usuários do presente estudo reportaram. No recrutamento dos sujeitos percebeu-se que muitos não obtiveram atendimento médico na APS nos últimos seis meses justificando a dificuldade em conseguir vaga e quando adoecem e precisam procuram o PA. Tem-se que 12,7% foram atendidos no mesmo dia que procuraram a APS. Dos 87,3% que não foram atendidos no mesmo dia, o tempo médio de espera entre o dia do agendamento e o dia da consulta na APS foi 58 dias, 42,4% dos usuários responderam “ruim” sobre a facilidade em marcar uma consulta. Os resultados convergem com os resultados do PMAQ-AB que sinalizaram baixo desempenho para o acolhimento à demanda espontânea. Porém, a boa avaliação do PMAQ-AB no quesito agendamento de consultas divergiu com os resultados deste estudo em que foi constante a queixa pela demora no agendamento de consultas. Conclui-se que os usuários atendidos nos PAs em Ribeirão Preto-SP não reconhecem a APS como fonte regular de cuidado, o que pode interferir na não adesão a esses serviços de forma contínua, resultando na busca por serviços de urgência e emergência para tratar agravos que poderiam ser resolvidos na APS</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The objective was to identify similarities and differences about user satisfaction with Primary Health Care (PHC) in the dimensions of access and care from non-urgent care in emergency care (EC) in Ribeirão Preto-SP with the National Program Evaluation Improving Access and Quality of Primary Care (PMAQ-AB), whose evaluation in Ribeirão Preto happened in same period. It was a quantitative study in the PA units of the five Health Districts.The study included 514 users who received at least one appointment in the PHC in the six months preceding the survey. We used the EUROPEP instrument - European Task Force on Patient Evaluation of General Practice Care and diary as data sources. It was based on the results of the dimensions of access and host PMAQ assessment to identify similarities and differences between what users of this study reported. During recruitment of users we realized that many did not receive medical care in PHC in the last six months justifying the difficulty in getting vaccancy and when they get sick and need to look for EC. We have that 12.7% were treated on the same day that sought to PHC. Of the 87.3% that have not met the same day, the average waiting time between the day of marking and the day of appointment on the PHC was 58 days, 42.4% of users answered "bad" about the ease in making an appointment. The results converge with PMAQ-AB results signaled underperforming to host the spontaneous demand. However, the good evaluation of PMAQ-AB in the category marking appointment diverged with the results of this study it was constant complaint by the delay in scheduling appointments. We conclude that users seen in EC in Ribeirão Preto-SP not recognize PHC as a regular source of care, which may interfere with non-adherence to these continuous service, resulting in the search for urgent and emergency services to treat injuries that could be resolved in the PHC</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135043</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50i1p29-38</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 29-38</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 29-38</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 29-38</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135043/130890</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/135044</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Incidência da pneumonia associada à ventilação mecânica em unidade de terapia intensiva</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Incidence of ventilator-associated pneumonia in intensive care unit</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mota, Écila C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Silvânia P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silveira, Beatriz R. M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Patrick L. N.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Adriana C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pneumonia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ventilator-Associated. Intensive Care Units. Cross Infection. Patient safety</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pneumonia Associada à Ventilação Mecânica. Unidades de Terapia Intensiva. Infecção Hospitalar. Segurança do Paciente</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To evaluate the incidence of ventilator-associated pneumonia in intensive care unit (ICU). Method: A retrospective cohort study, was carried in a university hospital. Univariate analyzes were performed using the chi-square test or Fisher’s exact test for categorical variables, and nonparametric Mann-Whitney test for numerical variables. Results: In a period of 24 months, 190 patients were admitted in the ICU, and 90.5% of them used mechanical ventilation. The incidence of ventilatorassociated pneumonia (VAP) was 23.2%, being notified in 100% of the patients who used the mechanical ventilation; the incidence density of VAP was 32.4/1000 ventilator days and the overall mortality associated with VAP was 72.7%. There was a positive association between the occurrence of pneumonia and the period of hospitalization in the intensive care unit &amp;gt; 15 days (RR: 7.29), time of mechanical ventilation &amp;gt; 10 days (RR: 11.33), and reintubation (RR: 6.31). Conclusion: pneumonia is considered a high morbidity condition in the intensive care unit. Thus, it is necessary to implement effective measures for quality and safety on the care of critically ill patients</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: avaliar a incidência da pneumonia associada à ventilação mecânica em unidade de terapia intensiva (UTI). Método: trata-se de um estudo de coorte retrospectivo desenvolvido em um hospital universitário. Análises univariadas foram realizadas por meio do teste Qui-quadrado ou teste exato de Fisher para variáveis categóricas e teste não paramétrico de Mann-Whitney para variáveis numéricas. Resultados: Durante 24 meses foram admitidos 190 pacientes na UTI, desses, 90,5% utilizaram Ventilação Mecânica (VM). A incidência de pneumonia associada à VM foi de 23,2%, sendo notificada em 100% dos pacientes que utilizaram VM; a densidade de incidência foi de 32,4/1000 ventiladores/dia e a taxa de mortalidade global dos pacientes com pneumonia foi de 72,7%. Houve associação positiva entre a ocorrência de pneumonia e o tempo de internação &amp;gt;15 dias (RR: 7,29), o tempo de VM &amp;gt;10 dias (RR: 11,33) e reintubação (RR: 6,31). Conclusão: a pneumonia foi considerada como uma doença de alta morbidade na Unidade de Terapia Intensiva. Torna-se necessário a implantação de medidas efetivas para qualidade e segurança no cuidado de pacientes críticos</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135044</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50i1p39-46</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 39-46</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 39-46</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 39-46</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135044/130891</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/135045</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:12Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Gest.+Org.+Sa%C3%BAde</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Descrição de prática para a gestão da farmácia hospitalar</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Description of hospital pharmacy management practice</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pereira, Laura M. V.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Abramovicius, Alexandra C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ungari, Andrea Q.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Heloisa B. D.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Aragon, Davi C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Andre L.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Forster, Aldaisa C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Services. Pharmacy Service</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hospital. Quality Management. Indicators</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Serviços de Saúde. Serviço de Farmácia Hospitalar. Gestão da Qualidade. Indicadores</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Health institutions, particularly hospitals, are characterized as complex structures that need managers with a global view of the institution and its relations with the external environment. The hospital pharmacy is a strategic unit, which cooperates with the institutional management and integrates the multiprofessional team in the process related to the acquisition, provision and control of essential inputs for the inpatient care process. The objective in this study is to demonstrate the applicability, in the context of hospital-based health, of a performance measuring system at the pharmacy. Method: A descriptive and longitudinal study was undertaken on the evolution of the key indicator Absence Rate of Standardized Drugs in inpatient care between March 2004 and December 2013. This indicator was employed to monitor the impact of changes the Pharmacy Division has been implementing, as the first step of the pharmaceutical care cycle in the model of the process-based managed approach at a public university hospital. Qualitative data collection methods were used, including observation and documentary analysis, as well as quantitative data collection. Results: After the application of the model, one point of change in the key performance indicator was detected in the tenth month, when the process-based management model was implemented at the pharmacy. Conclusions: The process-based management approach was effective for the hospital pharmacy. The premise adopted is that the administrative changes (interferences), focused on the improvement of the processes and the selection and monitoring of indicators, influence the processes, reducing the variability and improving the quality</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">As instituições de saúde, especialmente hospitais, são caracterizadas como estruturas complexas que precisam de administradores com uma visão global da instituição e de suas relações com o ambiente externo. A farmácia hospitalar é uma unidade estratégica, que colabora com a administração institucional e integra a equipe multiprofissional no processo que tange a aquisição, provisão e controle de insumos essenciais para o processo do atendimento do paciente internado. Este estudo tem como objetivo demonstrar a aplicabilidade, no contexto da saúde hospitalar, de um sistema de medição de desempenho da farmácia. Método: Trata-se de um estudo descritivo, longitudinal, sobre a evolução do indicador chave Taxa de Falta de Medicamentos Padronizados na assistência do paciente internado, no período de março de 2004 a dezembro de 2013. Esse indicador foi empregado para monitoramento do impacto de mudanças que a Divisão de Farmácia vem implementando, como primeira etapa do ciclo de assistência farmacêutica dentro do modelo da abordagem de gestão por processos, em um hospital público universitário. Foram usados métodos de coleta de dados qualitativos, incluindo a observação e análise documental, bem como coleta de dados quantitativos. Resultados: Após a aplicação do modelo, um ponto de mudança no indicador chave de desempenho, foi detectado no 10º mês, quando o modelo de gestão baseado em processo foi implementado na farmácia. Conclusões: A abordagem de gestão baseada em processos foi eficaz para a farmácia hospitalar. A premissa adotada é que as mudanças administrativas (interferências), com foco na melhoria dos processos e seleção e acompanhamento de indicadores, têm influencia sobre os processos, reduzindo a variabilidade e melhoria da qualidade</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135045</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50i1p66-75</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 66-75</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 66-75</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 66-75</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135045/130892</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/135046</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:PV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O adolescente e a puericultura</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Adolescent and puericulture</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Del Ciampo, Luiz Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Del Ciampo, Ieda Regina Lopes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Adolescente. Medicina do Adolescente. Atenção Primária à Saúde. Prevenção de Doenças</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Adolescent. Adolescent Medicine. Primary Health Care. Disease Prevention</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A partir do século XIX a adolescência passa a despertar grande interesse na sociedade em virtude do processo de desenvolvimento econômico, científico e social, o que impulsiona a criação de serviços de saúde direcionados ao atendimento dos indivíduos na segunda década de vida. Este artigo apresenta um breve histórico da Puericultura, da consolidação da Hebiatria e destaca a importância dos programas de atendimento em atenção básica à saúde do adolescente. Apoiado em alguns textos clássicos sobre o tema, procurou-se traçar um paralelo com os pioneiros programas de atendimento em puericultura para as crianças no sentido de incentivar as ações de prevenção de agravos e promoção da saúde dos adolescentes em nível primário, como estratégia para garantir boas condições de vida</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">From the nineteenth century, adolescence becomes aroused great interest in the society due to the process of economic, scientific and social development, which drives the creation of health services directed to the care of the people in the second decade of life. This article presents a brief history of Puericulture, the consolidation of Hebiatria and highlights the importance of services in an adolescent primary health care. Supported in some classic texts on the subject, it drew a parallel with the pioneer's paediatric health programs, to encouraging the actions of prevention and promotion of adolescent health at the primary level as a strategy to ensure healthy living conditions</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135046</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50i1p76-81</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 76-81</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 76-81</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 76-81</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135046/130893</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/135047</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Bócio retroesternal – incidência de câncer</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Retrosternal Goiter – Cancer Incidence</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pinheiro, Thiago Cerizza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Scandiuzzi, Maissa Marçola</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, André Afonso Nimtz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alcadipane, Fernando Antônio Maria Claret</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Iwakura, Ricardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Monazzi, Bruno Vallim</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Freitas, Luiz Carlos Conti de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Thyroid Gland. Retrosternal Goiter</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cancer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tireóide. Bócio Retroesternal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Câncer</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O bócio retroesternal é uma afecção rara da glândula tireóide, que acomete principalmente mulheres acima de 60 anos, caracterizada por tireóide aumentada de tamanho, peso e volume, que invade a cavidade torácica total ou parcialmente. A não realização do ato cirúrgico tem sido preconizada em alguns casos como forma alternativa de melhoria da qualidade de vida, sobretudo em pacientes idosos assintomáticos. Todavia, existe uma incidência de câncer nos bócios retroesternais, associado a um índice maior de complicações, que justifica a abordagem cirúrgica precoce, principalmente em pacientes jovens, mesmo que assintomáticos. Este trabalho resulta de um relato de caso e revisão de literatura, sobre bócio retroesternal e incidência de câncer em uma paciente de 62 anos, submetida a tireoidectomia total, com achados histopatológicos de pós operatório, de carcinoma papilífero, carcinoma folicular e adenoma folicular. Esses achados nos alerta para a possibilidade de incidência de câncer nesses pacientes, devendo ser aventado o tratamento cirúrgico precoce</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The retrosternal goiter is a rare thyroid gland disease, which mainly affects women over 60 years, characterized by increased thyroid size, weight and volume, which invades the thoracic cavity. Failure to perform the surgery has been recommended in some cases as an alternative way of improving the quality of life, especially in asymptomatic elderly patients. However, there is an incidence of cancer in retrosternal goiters associated with a higher rate of complications, justified the early surgical approach, especially in young patients, even if asymptomatic. This work results from a case report and literature review on retrosternal goiter and cancer incidence in a 62-year-old patient submitted total thyroidectomy with histopathologic findings after surgery, papillary carcinoma, follicular carcinoma and follicular adenoma. These findings alerts us to the possibility of cancer incidence in these patients, recommending in such cases, early surgical treatment</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135047</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50i1p47-52</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 47-52</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 47-52</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 47-52</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135047/130894</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/135049</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Remissão parcial e simultânea da nefrite e da anemia hemolítica autoimune em paciente com lúpus após terapia com agente biológico: relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Partial and simultaneous remission of nephritis and autoimmune hemolytic anemia in patients with lupus after treatment with biological agent: a case report</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fernandes, Marcus I.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Figueiredo, Evania C. Q. de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fernandes, Maria Angelina C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dantas, Camila M. F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Ítalo E. L.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Lupus Erythematosus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Systemic. Lupus Nephritis. Rituximab. Anemia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemolytic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Autoimmune</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lúpus Eritematoso Sistêmico. Nefrite Lúpica. Rituximab. Anemia Hemolítica Autoimune</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is a chronic inflammatory disease, systemic, of unknown cause and autoimmune nature. It features variable prognosis, depending on the affected organ or system. The renal impairment is the condition most often related to morbidity and mortality. This manuscript aims to contribute to the further evidence that early diagnosis of lupus associated with quickly aggressive therapy could increase the success outcome rate. Also, immediate recognition of therapeutic failures and change the treatment strategy must be applied. In this regard, a new therapeutic option seems to be the biological drug rituximab described in this study and which it is emphasised because of its possible and still supposed ability to act as a rescue agent for nephritis and hemolytic lupus anaemia, simultaneously, with effectiveness and safety. This article presents the case of female lupus patient with both severe refractory hematologic disorder and renal impairment, which had an evolution of the simultaneous restoration of urine output, and clinical and laboratory improvement of autoimmune anaemia after rituximab administration. The persistence of renal damage could not be ruled out, so the response to treatment was considered to be partial</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O Lúpus Eritematoso Sistêmico (LES) é uma doença inflamatória crônica, sistêmica, de causa desconhecida e de natureza autoimune. Apresenta prognóstico variável, dependente do órgão ou sistema acometido, sendo o comprometimento renal uma das condições mais frequentemente relacionadas à morbimortalidade. O presente manuscrito propõe-se a contribuir como mais um indício de que o diagnóstico precoce e a terapia agressiva inicial, no lúpus, elevam sobremaneira o índice de sucesso clinico. Falhas no tratamento devem ser reconhecidas de imediato, com rápida mudança de estratégia, quando necessário. Neste sentido, uma nova opção terapêutica parece ser o agente biológico rituximab, descrito neste estudo e para o qual é dada ênfase devido à sua possível e ainda suposta capacidade de atuar como agente de resgate para a nefrite e para a anemia hemolítica lúpicas, simultaneamente, com efetividade e segurança. Apresenta-se o caso de paciente lúpica com acometimento renal e hematológico grave e refratário, que evoluiu simultaneamente com restabelecimento do débito urinário e melhora clínico-laboratorial da anemia autoimune após administração de rituximab, resposta considerada parcial, posto que a existência de dano renal persistente não pode ser descartada</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135049</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50i1p53-57</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 53-57</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 53-57</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 53-57</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135049/130895</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/135050</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Tem.+Ens.+Med.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The approach intersectoral for medical education in primary health care</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A abordagem da intersetorialidade para o ensino médico em atenção primária</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Forster, Aldaísa C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Janise B. B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Nereida Kilza da Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Galati, Priscila Mina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Farche, Renata</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação Médica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ação Intersetorial. Atenção Primária à Saúde. Determinantes Sociais da Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical. Intersectorial Action. Primary Health Care. Social Determinants of Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Introduction: The process of creating the Unified Health System (SUS) as one health care model more humanized, comprehensive, effective and decisive has intersectorality as one of its tools for transformation. However, there are few articles that address the intersectoral approach in the context of medical education and organization of practices, especially in primary care. Objective: Bring forth the concept of intersectionality and the principle of community orientation in the organization of practices in the reality of family health staffs, under the SUS. Method: Analysis of documents held to discuss the concept of intersectionality in the work of authors of Primary Health Care (PHC), the official documentation of the Ministry of Health and selected publications on intersectionality. It also discussed the community orientation in the given actions of Primary Health Care in the perception of the physician and the family health staffs in Brazil. It described the evolution of the former Family Health Program to the Family Health Strategy as reorganization model of PHC in the SUS and in the education scenario of the Family Health Units (FHU) involved in the Ribeirão Preto Medical School - University of São Paulo in the period from 1999 to 2014. Results: Official and scientific documentation consulted showed advance of changes in family health services, such as the PHC model of organization in the country. The setting of FHU oriented to PHC has contributed to the adaptation of medical training and health professionals in this area. Final Considerations: Nevertheless, perceiving the potential of intersectoral and practices geared towards the community in the health paradigm change, there is plenty to do in the broad sense of intersectionality comprising addressing the social determinants of health in local integrated plan</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: O processo de criação do Sistema Único de Saúde (SUS) como um modelo de atenção à saúde, mais humanizado, abrangente, eficaz e resolutivo tem a intersetorialidade como um de seus instrumentos para a transformação. No entanto, há escassez de artigos que abordem a intersetorialidade no contexto da educação médica e da organização das práticas, principalmente na atenção primária. Objetivo: Trazer à luz o conceito de intersetorialidade e o princípio da orientação comunitária na organização das práticas na realidade das equipes de saúde da família, no âmbito do SUS. Método: Análise documental realizada para discutir o conceito de intersetorialidade na obra de autores da Atenção Primária à Saúde (APS), na documentação oficial do Ministério da Saúde e em publicações selecionadas sobre a intersetorialidade. Discutiu-se também a orientação comunitária nas ações prestadas de APS segundo a percepção do médico e da equipe de saúde da família, no Brasil. Foi descrita a evolução do antigo Programa de Saúde da Família para a Estratégia de Saúde da Família como modelo de reorganização da atenção primária à saúde no SUS e no cenário de ensino das Unidades de Saúde da Família (USF) ligadas à Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto- Universidade de São Paulo, no período de 1999 a 2014. Resultados: A documentação oficial e científica consultada mostrou avanço das transformações nos serviços de Saúde da Família, como modelo de organização da APS no país. O cenário das USF orientado para a APS vem contribuindo para a adequação da formação médica e dos profissionais de saúde nessa área. Considerações finais: Não obstante, percebendo-se as potencialidades das práticas intersetoriais e orientadas para a comunidade na mudança do paradigma da saúde, há muito o que fazer no sentido amplo da intersetorialidade, que compreende a abordagem dos determinantes sociais da saúde no planejamento integrado local</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-02-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135050</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50i1p58-65</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 58-65</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 58-65</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. 1 (2017): jan./fev.; 58-65</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135050/130896</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/135087</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Socioeconomic and gestational determinants of birth weight of term infants</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Determinantes socioeconômicos e gestacionais do peso ao nascer de crianças nascidas a termo</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Moreira, Mônica Évelim Figueiredo Horta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Cristiane Leila</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Freitas, Ronilson Ferreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Macêdo, Mariana Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lessa, Angelina do Carmo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Peso ao Nascer. Saúde da Criança. Fatores Socioeconômicos. Gestação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Birth Weight. Child Health. Socioeconomic Factors. Pregnancy</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To identify the social and gestational factors associated with birth weight of full-term newborns. Methods: A cross-sectional study was conducted between September 2004 and July 2005. The information was obtained through the Statement of Live Birth and subsequent home visit after the child’s birth. Results: The mean birth weight in the sample was 3,146 (± 375 grams), and the incidence of low birth weight was 7.5%. In the multivariate analysis female children, maternal age less than 19 years, smoking during pregnancy and greater overcrowding in the home were associated with significantly lower mean birth weight. The most significant difference was seen among children whose mothers were smokers, with a mean birth weight less than 258grs compared to nonsmoking mothers (p = 0.001). Jointly, these factors accounted for 16% of the variation in birth weight. Conclusion: Greater investment in primary care is required, in an attempt to reduce the number of adolescent pregnancies and smoking during pregnancy, among other factors relevant to the health of the newborn</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Identificar os fatores sociais e gestacionais associados ao peso ao nascer de crianças nascidas a termo. Métodos: Trata-se de estudo transversal realizado entre setembro de 2004 e julho de 2005. As informações foram obtidas por meio da Declaração de Nascidos Vivos e de visita domiciliar subsequente ao nascimento da criança. Resultados: O peso médio ao nascer na amostra estudada foi de 3,146 (±375 g), sendo que a incidência de nascidos vivos com baixo peso ao nascer foi de 7,5%. Observou-se, na análise multivariada, que crianças do gênero feminino, idade materna inferior a 19 anos, o hábito de fumar durante a gestação e maior aglomeração de pessoas no domicílio associaramse significantemente com menor média de peso ao nascer. A diferença mais expressiva ocorreu entre as crianças cujas mães eram tabagistas, com uma média de peso dessas crianças menor que 258grs quando comparadas com mães não tabagistas (p=0,001). De forma conjunta, esses fatores responderam por 16% da variação do peso ao nascer. Conclusão: Considera-se necessário maior investimento na atenção básica, na tentativa de reduzir o número de gestantes adolescentes e do hábito de fumar durante a gestação, dentre outros fatores relevantes para a saúde do recém-nascido</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-04-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135087</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50i2p83-90</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. 2 (2017): mar./abr.; 83-90</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. 2 (2017): mar./abr.; 83-90</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. 2 (2017): mar./abr.; 83-90</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135087/130921</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/135088</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:02:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Asma: perfil da população infantil atendida na UBS Vitória Régia, Sorocaba/SP</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Asthma: profile of infant population at the Health Center of Vitória Régia, Sorocaba</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sorio, Gabriella N.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Edelmuth, Stephanie V. C. L.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Utiyama, Thaís O.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Janie M. de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Asthma. Health Profile. Health Centers. Sex Distribution. Breast Feeding</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Asma. Perfil de Saúde. Centro de Saúde. Distribuição por sexo. Aleitamento Materno</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Introduction: Asthma is a chronic inflammatory disease of the airways that not only constitutes a public health issue, but also compromises the development of children affected by the condition. Its multifactorial origin suggests that the association of certain factors, such as low maternal education, passive smoking, inadequate hygiene and immunization and limited breast-feeding, causes higher asthma incidence. Study design: descriptive study. Aims of the study: to determine the profile and factors associated to the asthmatic children participating in the Asthma Control Program at the Health Center of Vitória Régia, Sorocaba/SP. Methods: Descriptive study conducted with the infant population of the Asthma Control Program, composed of 42 children. Children between 5 and 7 years old were included in the study and, as an exclusion criterion, children whose responsible did not agree to participate in the research. During the period of October 2014 to April 2015 questionnaires were applied to the responsible for the participating minor, after signature of a written informed consent. The collected data were analyzed by multivariate statistics. Results: Results indicated that the participating children are majorly male (66.7%), without history of intrauterine exposure to tobacco(89,7%) or passive smoking (69,2%), and received exclusive breast-feeding (92,3%) until approximately 5 months of age. The majority of children did not present diarrhea or respiratory infections in the first year of life and were not diagnosed with rhinitis and/or eczema. However, we verified that most infants have family history of asthma and/ or atopy. The factorial analysis showed that the first three factors describe 80,71% of the variability of the sample. Statistically, the variables gender, animal presence, rhinitis and/or eczema diagnosis and breastfeeding stand out in the description of the studied population. Conclusions: We concluded that the findings of this study are, in many of the analyzed items, compatible with current literature. Variables such as gender and animal presence were consistent with findings from other studies, even considering the convenience sample. Regarding breastfeeding and its duration, the results contradict some scientific references, reinforcing that conclusions are conflicting in this aspect. Despite many studies that refer a beneficial effect of breastfeeding on the prevention of asthma, this variable was strongly associated to the analyzed sample. The application of a multivariate analysis allowed the identification of the variables most relevant to this group, among the main existing risk factors for asthma</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: A asma, uma doença inflamatória crônica das vias aéreas, além de ser um problema de saúde pública no Brasil, compromete o desenvolvimento dos indivíduos jovens afetados. Sua etiologia poligênica leva a crer que a associação de determinados fatores, como baixa escolaridade materna, tabagismo no domicílio, higiene e imunização inadequados e menor período de amamentação exclusiva, gera maior incidência da patologia. Objetivos do estudo: traçar o perfil e os fatores associados às crianças portadoras de asma acompanhadas na UBS Vitória Régia, município de Sorocaba (SP). Modelo de estudo: Estudo descritivo. Metodologia: Estudo realizado com a população infantil atendida no Programa de Controle da Asma, composta por 42 crianças. Foram incluídas as crianças maiores de 5 anos e menores de 7 anos, e como critério de exclusão, as crianças cujos responsáveis não concordaram em participar do estudo. Durante o período de outubro de 2014 a abril de 2015 foram aplicados questionários aos responsáveis pelo menor participante, após assinatura do TCLE, em seu domicílio. Os dados foram analisados pela Estatística Multivariada. Resultados: As crianças participantes são majoritariamente do sexo masculino (66,7%), sem exposição ao tabagismo na gestação (89,7%) ou no domicílio (69,2%), tendo recebido amamentação exclusiva (92,3% das crianças) até cinco meses de vida em média. A maioria dessas crianças não apresentou diarreia e/ou infecção respiratória no primeiro ano de vida e não teve diagnóstico de rinite e/ou eczema; no entanto, verificou-se que a maior parte delas possui familiares com histórico de alergia ou asma. Pela análise fatorial aplicada, foi possível constatar que três primeiros fatores explicam 80,71% da variabilidade encontrada na amostra. Estatisticamente, as seguintes variáveis foram correlacionadas a tais fatores: sexo masculino, presença de animais de estimação, diagnóstico de rinite e/ou eczema e amamentação e sua duração. Conclusões: Foi possível concluir que a descrição do conjunto dos achados deste estudo encontra respaldo na literatura pertinente. Variáveis como sexo masculino e presença de animais de estimação, mesmo na amostra de conveniência, corroboraram com achados de outros estudos. Já para a variável amamentação e sua duração, os resultados contradizem algumas literaturas, reforçando que os achados são conflitantes neste aspecto. Apesar da existência de muitos estudos que relatam um efeito benéfico da amamentação sobre a prevenção de asma, a presença dessa variável esteve fortemente associada ao grupo em estudo. A utilização da análise multivariada permitiu caracterizar quais variáveis dentro dos fatores de risco para a asma foram as mais pertinentes para este grupo</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-04-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135088</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v50i2p91-101</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 No. 2 (2017): mar./abr.; 91-101</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 50 Núm. 2 (2017): mar./abr.; 91-101</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 50 n. 2 (2017): mar./abr.; 91-101</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/135088/130922</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2022-08-30T21:20:37Z" completeListSize="1467" cursor="1075">7ddf3e8530dc4093c0d2b45f2cbabe31</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
