<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-08-29T21:19:58Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="rmrp">https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/240</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:07:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Relevance and treatment of heart failure’s injuries to skeletal musculature</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Relevância e tratamento das lesões características da insuficiência cardíaca na musculatura esquelética</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bueno Júnior, Carlos R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Insuficiência Cardíaca. Sistema Musculoesquelético. Biologia Molecular. Terapia.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Pacientes com insuficiência cardíaca, a via final das doenças cardiovasculares e a primeira causa de internação em idosos no Brasil, apresentam deterioração do tecido muscular esquelético. Além disso, as lesões na musculatura têm relação direta com a qualidade de vida e a autonomia dos pacientes, por meio do nível de tolerância aos esforços físicos, além de constituírem um preditor independente de mortalidade na síndrome. Ao longo da presente revisão de literatura serão discutidos em relação à insuficiência cardíaca: seu conceito e um breve histórico; a importância da musculatura esquelética; as anormalidades funcionais, estruturais, bioquímicos e moleculares que acometem esse tecido; as potenciais causas dessas alterações (hiperatividade simpática, redução na ingestão alimentar, espécies reativas de oxigênio, citocinas pró-inflamatórias e diminuição do nível de atividade física e do fluxo sanguíneo); e os efeitos da principal terapia direcionada para combater essa disfunção, o treinamento físico aeróbio de intensidade moderada. Reconhecida a importância do tecido muscular esquelético na síndrome, essa é uma área da investigação científica com muitos temas ainda não estudados, como o efeito de terapias farmacológicas utilizadas pelos pacientes, de exercícios físicos aeróbios de maior intensidade e intervalados, de exercícios físicos de força, de intervenções nutricionais e de terapias celulares e gênicas. No futuro, os resultados desses estudos que serão desenvolvidos certamente contribuirão para uma menor degeneração da musculatura esquelética na doença, o que, consequentemente, vai melhorar a&#160; ualidade de vida, a autonomia e o prognóstico dos pacientes.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Heart failure patients, the final pathway of the cardiovascular diseases and the first cause of admission in hospital in Brazil, present skeletal musculature injuries. Furthermore, the damages in this musculature have direct relationship with the quality of life and the autonomy of the patients, by the physical exercise tolerance, and are an independent predictor of mortality in the syndrome. During this review will be discussed about heart failure: its concept and a brief history; the importance of the skeletal musculature; the functional, structural, biochemical and molecular injuries that undergoes this tissue; the main causes of these damages (sympathetic hyperactivity, decreased food intake, reactive oxygen species, inflammatory cytokines and reduced physical activity level and blood flow); and the effects of the principal therapy to prevent this dysfunction, the moderated intensity aerobic physical training. If we agree about the importance of the skeletal muscle tissue in the syndrome, this is an area of scientific investigation with many subjects still not studied, like the effect of: pharmacological therapies used by the patients, high intensity aerobic physical exercises, strength physical exercises, nutritional interventions and cellular and genetic therapies. In the future, the results of these studies that will be developed certainly will contribute to less degeneration of the skeletal musculature in the disease, what, consequently, will improve the quality of life, the autonomy and the prognosis of the patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2009-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/240</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v42i4p437-450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 No. 4 (2009); 437-450</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 Núm. 4 (2009); 437-450</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 42 n. 4 (2009); 437-450</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/240/241</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/241</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:07:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The imminence of death in question: the perspective of psychologists and clinical management of public health</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A iminência de morte em questão: a perspectiva e o manejo clínico de psicólogos da saúde pública</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pfeifer, Paula M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Palma, Cláudia M. S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Psicologia Clínica. Saúde Pública. Morte. Psicologia em Saúde.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Psychology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Clinical . Public Health. Death. Health Psychology.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study design:&#160;It is a qualitative research. Objective: To qualify the practice of the psychologist, that is, how they behave and work facing questions concerning death in the institutional context.&#160;Methods:&#160;Initially, it was carried out a survey on the number of psychologists who work in the health public system in Santa Maria establishing a sample of twelve professionals. Later, semi-structured and individual one-hour long interviews were conducted. The recorded interviews were transcribed and then read individually; highlighting the parts of speech that showed the way the psychologist develops his work and from the recurrence, some categories of analysis were elaborated, trying to articulate a group's view. The theoretical- psychoanalytic focus was used for the data analysis. Results:&#160;The results showed contradictions between the performance and positioning of the psychologist on the verge of death of a patient, with the predominance of individual characteristics in their act. Thus we could realize the danger of adopting a practice anyone can do, in the case of situations where there is not a specific handling, with stress in the dominance of individual characteristics.&#160;Conclusion:&#160;Although training in psychology does not have any specificity with regard to death, which imposes the professional some professional difficulties in situations of imminent death, these difficulties can be minimized since the psychologist has clearly defined - to himself and to the institution in which he works - what is his function, thus without missing his professional dimension. Moreover, it is reinforced the importance of the psychologist having his own personal therapy to be able to deal with those matters which demand his individual characteristics.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: trata-se de uma pesquisa qualitativa.&#160;Objetivo:&#160;qualificar a prática do psicólogo, isto é, como se posiciona e atua frente às questões referentes à morte no contexto institucional.&#160;Metodologia: Inicialmente, foi realizado levantamento sobre o número de psicólogos que atuam na rede pública de Santa Maria, constituindo-se uma amostra de doze profissionais. Posteriormente, realizamos entrevistas semi-estruturadas e individuais, com duração de uma hora. As entrevistas gravadas foram transcritas, e em seguida, lidas individualmente, destacando-se as falas que apontavam para o modo de trabalho do psicólogo elaborando-se, a partir da recorrência, categorias de análise, buscando-se articular uma perspectiva grupal. O enfoque teórico utilizado para a análise de dados foi o psicanalítico.&#160;Resultados:&#160;Os resultados apontaram contradições entre a atuação e o posicionamento referido pelo psicólogo na iminência da morte de um pac iente, sobrepondo-se um fazer invadido pela pessoalidade do profissional. Além disso, constatamos o perigo de adotar-se uma prática que pode ser feita por qualquer um, no caso de situações onde não há um manejo específico da morte, destacando-se o predomínio da pessoalidade.&#160;Conclusão:&#160;apesar da formação em psicologia não conter uma especificidade no que diz respeito à morte, o que impõe ao profissional dificuldades operativas nas situações de morte iminente, essas dificuldades podem ser minimizadas desde que o psicólogo tenha bem definido - para si e para a instituição na qual atua - qual é a sua função, assim, não perdendo a dimensão profissional. Além disso, reforça-se a importância do psicólogo realizar sua terapia pessoal, perante um fazer marcadamente convocador da pessoalidade.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2009-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/241</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v42i4p451-460</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 No. 4 (2009); 451-460</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 Núm. 4 (2009); 451-460</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 42 n. 4 (2009); 451-460</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/241/242</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/242</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:07:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Intracranial pressure changes during pulmonary expansion maneuver in patients with severe traumatic brain injury, monitored at the unity of intensive therapy</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Variações da pressão intracraniana durante manobra de expansão pulmonar em pacientes com trauma cranioencefálico grave, monitorizados em unidade de terapia intensiva</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Silvia Aparecida</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Israel, Vera L.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Aguiar, Luiz R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisioterapia (Especialidade). Serviço Hospitalar de Fisioterapia. Terapia Respiratória. Pressão Intracraniana. Trauma Craniocerebral.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy (Specialty). Respiratory Therapy. Intracranial Pressure. Traumatic Brain Injury. Physical Therapy Department</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hospital.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">In physical therapy, there are specific means available for rehabilitation in the ICU, as well as for patients with severe traumatic brain injury (TBI). Among the available techniques, the pulmonary expansion maneuver, a kinesiotherapy technique aimed at mobilizing lung secretions, preventing and treating atelectasis.Model of the study: The study was classified as field research (experimental), based on assessment of the ICP during and after pulmonary expansion maneuver.&#160;Objective: To verify how the pulmonary expansion therapy affects intracranial pressure (ICP) in patients with severe TBI. Methodology: The study was approved by the Ethics and Research Committee of the PUCPR (opinion 1455). It was carried out at the unity of intensive therapy (ICU) in the Cajuru University Hospital, Curitiba-PR. Fifteen severe TBI patients of both genders participated in the study, their ages ranging between 18 and 50 years. The monitored variables were ICP, mean arterial pressure (MAP) and brain perfusion pressure (BPP). Results:&#160;During the application of the research protocol it was observed that MAP and the BPP remained within or close to normal range with slight changes, while ICP increased approximately 1 mmHg then returning to baseline values. Mean ICP in the 1st, 2nd and 3rd days were 5,42 (±4,69) mmHg, 6,71 (±6,84) mmHg and 5,60 (±4,33) mmHg with statistical significance of p&amp;lt;0,001, p=0,008 and p=0,001 respectively.&#160;Conclusions: The pulmonary expansion maneuver may be performed in severe TBI patients who are hemodynamically stable and have a baseline ICP below 20 mmHg.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A fisioterapia dispõe de recursos específicos para a reabilitação em unidade de terapia intensiva (UTI), assim como nos pacientes com traumatismo cranioencefálico (TCE) grave. Entre essas técnicas, destaca- se a manobra de expansão pulmonar, que é uma técnica cinesioterapêutica, a qual tem função de mobilizar secreção pulmonar, prevenir e tratar atelectasias. Modelo do estudo: O estudo foi classificado como pesquisa de campo (experimental), baseada em avaliação da PIC durante e após a manobra de expansão pulmonar. Objetivo: Verificar a influência da manobra fisioterapêutica de expansão pulmonar nos valores da pressão intracraniana (PIC) em pacientes com TCE grave. Metodologia: A pesquisa foiaprovada pelo Comitê de Ética e Pesquisa da PUCPR, com o parecer 1455.&#160;Foi realizada na unidade de terapia intensiva (UTI) do Hospital Universitário Cajuru, Curitiba-PR. Participaram do estudo 15 pacientes de ambos os sexos, com TCE grave e com faixa etária entre 18 e 50 anos. As variáveis monitorizadas foram a PIC, a pressão arterial média (PAM) e a pressão de perfusão cerebral (PPC).&#160;Resultados: Durante a aplicação do protocolo de pesquisa observou-se que a PAM e a PPC mantiveram-se dentro ou próximos da normalidade com mínimas variações, enquanto que a PIC evolui com variação aproximada de 1 mmHg retornando aos valores iniciais. As médias da PIC no 1º dia, 2º dia e 3º dia foram 5,42 (±4,69) mmHg, 6,71 (±6,84) mmHg e 5,60 (±4,33) mmHg, com significância estatística respectivamente p&amp;lt;0,001, p=0,008 e p=0,001. Conclusões: A manobra de expansão pulmonar pode ser realizada em pacientes com TCE grave, estáveis hemodinamicamente e com PIC abaixo de 20 mmHg.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2009-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/242</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v42i4p466-476</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 No. 4 (2009); 466-476</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 Núm. 4 (2009); 466-476</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 42 n. 4 (2009); 466-476</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/242/243</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/243</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:07:51Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:TEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">50 years of pediatric residency training program of child care and Pediatrics Department of School of Medicine of Ribeirão Preto - University of São Paulo</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">50 anos de residência médica do Departamento de Puericultura e Pediatria da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto da USP</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Del Ciampo, Luiz Antonio Del Ciampo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Residência médica. Educação Médica. Pediatria.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Residency</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical. Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical. Pediatrics.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The article presents the history of fifty years of the Pediatric Residency Training Program of Child Care and Pediatrics Department of School of Medicine of Ribeirão Preto of University of São Paulo, started in 1957, highlighting historical aspects, the number of places offered and the residents who have lawfully pursued activities by the year 2006.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O artigo apresenta a trajetória de cinqüenta anos do Programa de Residência Médica do Departamento de Puericultura e Pediatria da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto da Universidade de São Paulo, que foi iniciado em 1957, destacando seus aspectos históricos, o número de vagas oferecidas e de médicos residentes que nele exerceram atividades, até o ano de 2006.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2009-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/243</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v42i4p477-481</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 No. 4 (2009); 477-481</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 Núm. 4 (2009); 477-481</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 42 n. 4 (2009); 477-481</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/243/244</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/244</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:07:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:PV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Liver Transplantation in Ribeirão Preto. The evolution of a strategic Institutional procedure</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Transplante de fígado em nosso meio. A evolução de um procedimento estratégico institucional</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Orlando Castro e</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Fernanda Fernandes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Teixeira, Andreza Côrrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mente, Ênio David</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sankarankutty, Ajith Kumar</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2009-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/244</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v42i4p482-484</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 No. 4 (2009); 482-484</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 Núm. 4 (2009); 482-484</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 42 n. 4 (2009); 482-484</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/244/245</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/245</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:07:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:NTI</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Resumos de Dissertações de Mestrado e Teses de Doutorado apresentadas na Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto - USP de julho a setembro de 2009</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Editor, O</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2009-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/245</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v42i4p485-522</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 No. 4 (2009); 485-522</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 Núm. 4 (2009); 485-522</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 42 n. 4 (2009); 485-522</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/245/246</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/246</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:07:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:INM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A Morte de José Fernando de Castro Figueiredo</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Troncon, Luiz Ernesto Almeida</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2009-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/246</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v42i4p524-526</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 No. 4 (2009); 524-526</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 Núm. 4 (2009); 524-526</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 42 n. 4 (2009); 524-526</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/246/247</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/247</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Apresentação</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Guimarães, Marco Aurelio</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/247</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i1p1-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 1 (2008); 1-2</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 1 (2008); 1-2</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 1 (2008); 1-2</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/247/248</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/248</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:CAP</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">MEDICO LEGAL CENTRE (CEMEL) OF THE FACULTY OF MEDICINE OF RIBEIRÃO PRETO-USP: REPORT OF SEVEN YEARS OF HUMANITARY PRACTICE WITH UNIDENTIFIED HUMAN CORPSES</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">CENTRO DE MEDICINA LEGAL DA FMRP–USP: RELATO DE SETE ANOS DE PRÁTICA HUMANITÁRIA COM CADÁVERES HUMANOS NÃO-IDENTIFICADOS</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Martin, Carmen Cinira Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silveira, Teresa C. P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guimarães, Marco A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Melki, João A. D.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina Legal. Cadáver. Identificação de vítimas. Indigentes. Família.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Forensic Medicine. Cadaver. Victims identification. Homeless people. Family</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The authors present a report of the seven years experience of the Medico Legal Centre (CEMEL) of the Faculty of Medicine of Ribeirão Preto of the University of São Paulo (FMRPUSP) in receiving and keeping non-identified copses and in the attention to the families that search for missing relatives. In CEMEL, victims of natural, suspicious or violent deaths are examined, whose can be carbonized, putrefied or skeletonized, situations in which identification is difficult and require full attention of professionals involved. CEMEL has as priority the rescue of human dignity in dealing with corpses and their families, because of the repetitive denounces of disrespectful treatment in many mortuaries in Brazil. From December 1999 to December 2006, 166 non-identified bodies were examined, being 112 of recent deaths, 45 skeletonized, 7 in advanced putrefaction and 2 carbonized. The interviews with those allegedly relatives was done in all cases to obtain the life history of the deceased, which allowed the identification of 25 people. Obtaining valid information for identification was proportionally more efficient to the longer time spent with the relatives, the availability in help, the interest in listening to their complaints and the care in keeping the corpses.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Os autores apresentam um relato da experiência de sete anos do Centro de Medicina Legal (CEMEL) da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto da Universidade de São Paulo (FMRP-USP), no recebimento e guarda de cadáveres não-identificados e na atenção às famílias que procuram parentes desaparecidos. No CEMEL, vítimas de morte violenta são examinadas pelos peritos do IML, as quais podem estar carbonizadas, putrefeitas ou esqueletizadas, situações nas quais a identificação é difícil e requer atenção completa dos profissionais envolvidos. O CEMEL tem como um de seus objetivos no trabalho tanatológico, o resgate da dignidade humana no trato com os cadáveres e seus familiares, através da educação continuada de seus funcionários sobre estes princípios. De dezembro de 1999 a dezembro de 2006 foram examinados 166 cadáveres sem identificação, sendo 112 de pessoas recém falecidas, 45 esqueletizados, 7 em estado de putrefação avançada e 02 carbonizados. As entrevistas com as pessoas que se apresentaram como sendo familiares foram realizadas em todos os casos para conhecimento da história de vida do falecido, o que possibilitou a identificação de 25 pessoas. A obtenção de informações válidas para identificação foi proporcionalmente mais eficaz quanto maior o tempo de contato com os familiares, a disponibilidade em atendê-los, o interesse em ouvir suas queixas e o zêlo e trato na guarda do cadáver.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/248</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i1p3-6</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 1 (2008); 3-6</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 1 (2008); 3-6</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 1 (2008); 3-6</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/248/249</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/249</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:CAP</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">LAF 1.0: ESTABLISHMENT OF A COMPUTERIZED SYSTEM FOR LABORATORIES OF FORENSIC ANTHROPOLOGY</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">LAF 1.0: IMPLANTAÇÃO DE UM SISTEMA INFORMATIZADO PARA LABORATÓRIOS DE ANTROPOLOGIA FORENSE</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Crocco, Luís G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brondi, Guilherme O.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Felipe, Joaquim C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Soares, Andjara T.C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Evison, Martin P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guimarães, Marco Aurelio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina Legal. Antropologia Forense. Ossadas. Software.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Forensic Medicine. Forensic Anthropology. Bones. Software.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: A Software development for registration and recovery of information on Forensic Anthropology, based on the protocol developed during the project “UK – Brazil Scientific Cooperation – Forensic Anthropology and Identification of Human Remains”.&#160;Methods: Considering it is a Browser accessed application (software that allows Internet access, as Microsoft Internet Explorer®), it was necessary to choose an adequate programming language to this requirement as the server application. The chosen language was PHP® and the server application was Apache®. For data storage it was chosen the Data Bank Managing System MySQL®.&#160;Results: Tests performed with real data proved the LAF 1.0 efficiency, considering safety, reliability in storing and recovering data, as well as user satisfaction with clean, pleasant interfaces. This version was registered at the National Institute of Intellectual Property (INPI) and it is available for use in all medico-legal services interested in the creation of a Forensic Anthropology laboratory.&#160;Conclusions: The software improoved the generation of anthropological examination reports at Medico Legal Centre (CEMEL) and allowed the creation of a computerized tool for use in similar services, which will permit easiness in personal capacitating in Forensic Anthropology. Nowadays the software is in its updated version designated as LAF 2.0.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Desenvolvimento de um software para cadastro e recuperação de informações em Antropologia Forense baseado no protocolo desenvolvido durante o projeto “UK –Brazil Scientific Cooperation – Forensic Anthropology and Identification of Human Remains”. Metodologia:&#160;Por se tratar de um aplicativo acessado via Browser (software que permite o acesso à Internet, como o Microsoft Internet Explorer®) foi necessária a escolha de uma linguagem de programação que se enquadrasse nesse requisito juntamente com uma aplicação servidora. A linguagem escolhida foi PHP® e a aplicação servidora foi o Apache®. Para o armazenamento dos dados foi escolhido o Sistema Gerenciador de Banco de Dados MySQL®. Resultados: Testes realizados com dados reais comprovaram a eficiência do LAF 1.0 em se tratando de segurança, confiabilidade no armazenamento e recuperação dos dados além de satisfação do usuário, com o visual limpo e agradável das interfaces. Esta versão foi registrada no Instituto Nacional de Propriedade Intelectual (INPI) e encontra-se disponível gratuitamente para uso em todos os serviços médico-legais interessados em implantar um laboratório de Antropologia Forense.&#160;Conclusões:&#160;O software agilizou a geração de laudos de exames antropológicos para o Laboratório de Antropologia Forense do Centro de Medicina Legal (CEMEL) e permitiu a criação de uma ferramenta informatizada gratuita para uso em outros serviços semelhantes, o que permitirá maior facilidade na capacitação de pessoal para o trabalho em Antropologia Forense. O software encontra-se atualmente em sua versão de atualização, denominada LAF 2.0.&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/249</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i1p12-16</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 1 (2008); 12-16</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 1 (2008); 12-16</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 1 (2008); 12-16</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/249/250</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/250</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:CAP</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">ALCOOLEMIA E MORTES DE CAUSAS VIOLENTAS</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">BLOOD ALCOHOL CONCENTRATION AND VIOLENT DEATHS</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Paula, Carolina M.C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ruzzene, Maria A.M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martinis, Bruno S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Alcohol. Violent death. Forensic toxicology. Gas Chromatography.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Álcool. Morte violenta. Toxicologia Forense. Cromatografia em fase gasosa.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Brazilian Legislation requests blood alcohol tests only for fatal victims of traffic accidents. In this work we will discuss the need of doing blood alcohol tests for all victims of violent death since abusive use of alcohol represents an important risk factor for all kinds of violent death. The proposal of this study was to analyze the relationship between blood alcohol concentration and the causes of violent death according to gender and age. Blood samples of fatal victims due to violence, from necroscopic examination performed at the Núcleo de Perícias Médico Legal de Ribeirão Preto (NPML-RP) at the Centro de Medicina Legal da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto da Universidade de São Paulo (CEMEL/FMRP/USP) were analyzed in the period from 2002 to 2004. The ethanol analyses were done by gas chromatography using flame ionization detector and using Headspace technique for samples injection. The results showed that higher blood alcohol positivity was observed for victims of accidents, especially for traffic accidents, following by homicides, suicides and undetermined manner of violent deaths. It was observed also that samples collected from male victims were predominant and more than 50% of them presented blood alcohol above the limit established by the Brazilian traffic law which is 0.6 g/l. Results suggests that alcohol abused is highly correlated with violent deaths, mainly traffic accidents involving young males.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Legislação Brasileira determina a realização do exame de alcoolemia apenas para vítimas fatais de acidentes de trânsito. Neste trabalho é discutida a necessidade da realização do exame toxicológico de álcool no sangue de todas as vítimas fatais de causa externa ou violenta, pois o uso abusivo do álcool pode estar intimamente relacionado com esses tipos de morte. O objetivo deste estudo foi analisar e conhecer a relação entre a concentração de álcool no sangue e as mortes de causa violenta, considerando os parâmetros sexo e faixa etária. Foram analisadas amostras de sangue de vítimas fatais de causa violenta provenientes de necropsia realizadas pelo Núcleo de Perícia Médico Legal de Ribeirão Preto (NPML-RP) no Centro de Medicina Legal da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preta da Universidade de São Paulo, no período de 2002 a 2004. As análises de etanol foram realizadas pela técnica de cromatografia em fase gasosa com detector de ionização por chama e Headspace. Os resultados mostraram que nos acidentes, em especial nos acidentes de trânsito, a maior parte dos indivíduos envolvidos apresentava alcoolemia positiva, seguido dos homicídios e suicídios. Houve predominância das amostras do sexo masculino, sendo que mais que 50% das vítimas apresentavam alcoolemia positiva, com valores acima do permitido pelo Código de Trânsito Brasileiro, que é de 0,6 g/l. Os resultados sugerem que o álcool está altamente correlacionado com as mortes de causas violentas, principalmente nos acidentes de trânsito e envolvendo indivíduos jovens do sexo masculino.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/250</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i1p24-29</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 1 (2008); 24-29</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 1 (2008); 24-29</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 1 (2008); 24-29</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/250/251</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/251</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:CAP</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">CRANIOMETRIC LANDMARKS DEFINITIONS FROM MULTIPLANAR MAGNETIC RESONANCE IMAGES (MRI) REGARDING FORENSIC FACIAL RECONSTRUCTION</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">DEFINIÇÕES DE PONTOS CRANIOMÉTRICOS EM IMAGENS MULTIPLANARES DE RESSONÂNCIA MAGNÉTICA (RM) PARA FINS DE RECONSTRUÇÃO FACIAL FORENSE</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Welson D. F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Diniz, Paula R. B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Antonio C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martin, Carmen C. S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guimarães, Marco A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina Legal. Pontos Craniométricos. Tecidos Moles. Face. Reconstrução Facial.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Forensic Medicine. Craniometric Landmarks. Soft Tissues. Face. Facial Reconstruction.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Facial reconstruction can be a useful tool in the process of medico-legal identification. The method has presented a continuous evolution through the years, becoming more accurate. Its reliability is, in part, due to the facial soft tissues measurements that are applied to reconstruct a face from a skull. The aim of this study was investigating and knowing data about the correct localization and definitions of 22 craniometric landmarks established in the literature from anatomical structures and adapt them to images obtained from digital exams of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), allowing the future measurements of cranio-facial soft tissues thickness of living Brazilians with high precision and reliability. It was evidenced the necessity of changing the localization methods of bone anatomical references and their soft tissues correspondents, especially in three landmarks, where detailed knowledge about dental anatomy is required. The establishment of these definitions will give support to the setting of an anthropomorphic table containing the facial soft tissues thickness of Brazilians regarding their utilization in forensic facial reconstruction, to fill this gap in the Brazilian medico-legal knowledge.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A reconstrução facial pode ser uma ferramenta útil dentro do processo de identifica ção médico-legal. O método tem apresentado uma evolução contínua ao longo dos anos, tornando-se mais acurado. A sua fidelidade deve-se em parte as medidas de tecidos moles que são empregadas para se reconstituir o rosto a partir de um crânio. A proposta deste estudo foi a de investigar e conhecer dados sobre a correta localização e definição de 22 pontos craniométricos estabelecidos na literatura a partir de estruturas anatômicas e adaptá-los para imagens obtidas em exames digitais de ressonância magnética (RM), de forma a permitir a futura mensura ção da espessura dos tecidos moles crânio-faciais de brasileiros vivos com alta precisão e confiabilidade. Ficou evidenciada a necessidade de mudança na forma de localizar as referências anatômicas ósseas e seus correspondentes em tecidos moles, especialmente em três pontos, onde o conhecimento detalhado de anatomia dental é requerido. O estabelecimento dessas definições poderá fundamentar as bases da elaboração de uma tabela antropomórfica contendo as espessuras de tecidos moles da face de brasileiros com vista à aplicação em reconstituição facial forense, para preencher esta lacuna do conhecimento médico-legal no Brasil.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/251</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i1p17-23</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 1 (2008); 17-23</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 1 (2008); 17-23</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 1 (2008); 17-23</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/251/252</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/252</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:CAP</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">EFFECT OF TESTOSTERONE ON THE DEVELOPMENT OF Chrysomya albiceps (Wiedemann) (Diptera: Calliphoridae)</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">EFEITO DA TESTOSTERONA NO DESENVOLVIMENTO DE Chrysomya albiceps (Wiedemann) (Diptera: Calliphoridae)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ferrari, Ana C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Soares, Andjara T. C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guimarães, Marco A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Thyssen, Patrícia Jacqueline</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diptera. Esteróides. Entomologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Forense. Medicina Legal.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Diptera. Steroids. Forensic entomology. Forensic Medicine.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Medico-Legal or Forensic Entomology can be defined as the application of the study of insects and other arthropods which, in association with criminalistic processes, have the the purpose of desovering useful information for an investigation. Nowadays, the insects are a reliable alternative for toxicological analysis, especially when tissues and liquids usually required for this purpose are absent, once insects store some ingested substances which can change their growth rate, being this a relevant fact in the determination of the cause and the time since death. Previous experiments in our laboratory on the testosterone effects on body decomposition suggested that this hormone could interfere in the cadaveric fauna development. With the objective of investigating testosterone influence on the Chrysomya albiceps larval development, a common species in cadaveric fauna, an experimental study was done from eggs of a laboratory maintained colony of this species. The eggs were divided in four groups of 30 and put in glass flasks with 50g of artificial diet in each of them, with testosterone being added in two of them. The larvae were weighted each 12 h during all interval of the larval growing. The studied larvae did not present any difference in the stages of development, but larvae from the experimental group had 5 times the weight of the larvae from the control group and with bigger size. This result shows a significant influence of testosterone in the growth of C. albiceps.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Entomologia Médico-Legal ou Forense pode ser definida como a aplicação do estudo de insetos e outros artrópodes que, em associação com procedimentos criminalísticos, têm o propósito de descobrir informações úteis para uma investigação. Atualmente, os insetos são uma alternativa confiável para análises toxicológicas, especialmente na ausência de tecidos e fluidos normalmente utilizados para esse propósito, pois estes armazenam algumas substâncias ingeridas, o que pode alterar a sua taxa de desenvolvimento, sendo este fato relevante na determinação da causa e do tempo de morte. Experimentos prévios de nosso laboratório sobre efeitos da testosterona na decomposição corporal sugeriram que este hormônio poderia interferir no desenvolvimento da fauna cadavérica. Com o objetivo de se investigar a influência da testosterona no desenvolvimento larval de Chrysomya albiceps, uma espécie comum na fauna cadavérica, um estudo experimental foi realizado a partir de ovos de uma colônia da referida espécie mantida em laboratório. Os ovos foram divididos em quatro grupos de 30 e colocados em potes de vidro com 50g de dieta artificial cada, tendo sido a dieta acrescida de testosterona em dois deles. Pesagens foram realizadas de 12 em 12 horas durante todo o intervalo de crescimento larval. As larvas analisadas não apresentaram diferença nos estadios de desenvolvimento, porém as larvas do grupo experimental estavam com cinco vezes o peso das larvas do grupo controle e com tamanho aumentado. Tal resultado evidencia uma influência significativa da testosterona no crescimento de larvas de C. albiceps.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/252</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i1p30-34</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 1 (2008); 30-34</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 1 (2008); 30-34</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 1 (2008); 30-34</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/252/253</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/253</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:CAP</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">INFLUÊNCIA DOS HORMÔNIOS ESTERÓIODES SEXUAIS NO TEMPO DE ESQUELETIZAÇÃO DE RATOS WISTAR</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">INFLUENCE OF STEROID SEXUAL HORMONES ON SKELETIZATION TIME OF WISTAR RATS</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Guimarães, Marco Aurelio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Abrão, Ricardo M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Soares, Andjara T.C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Cláudia B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, José E.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martin, Carmen C.S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Decomposição corporal. Esqueletização. Esteróides sexuais. Adipocera. Rato.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Body decomposition. Skeletization. Sexual steroids. Adipocere. Rat.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The establishment of the postmortem interval is one of the most complicated and difficult tasks in forensic investigation because of many factors that affect this process (temperature, humidity, aerobic and anaerobic conditions, presence of microorganisms and soil conditions). Body intrinsic factors frequently not are related to de body decomposition. To investigate if the skeletonization process is under interference of sexual steroid hormones an experimental investigation with Wistar rats was done (30 male and 60 females divided in sub-groups at different hormonal phases). The animals were raised until they reach body weight between 350 and 450g, when were killed in a CO2 chamber and buried. Analysis of the environmental (temperature, humidity and rain) and corporal factors (body weight and body fat) showed that variation in these factors did not interfere on the skeletonization process. After the exhumation, only the male control group for testosterone showed complete skeletonization. The castrated males with no testosterone reposition and the castrated males with testosterone reposition showed minimum skeletonization. All female groups showed partial skeletonization. Analysis of the putrefaction residues from the groups with partial and minimum skeletonization showed the presence of the characteristic fatty acids of adipocere composition. Considering that both animal groups (males and females) were buried at the same place, under the same environmental and body conditions, during the same time interval, it is possible to conclude that sexual steroid hormones are responsible for the observed difference in body decomposition, being testosterone the main intervenient factor in this process. Besides, the experimental model also evidenced its potential use for future studies in the process of adipocere formation.&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A estimativa do tempo de morte é um dos problemas mais complicados e difíceis da Medicina Legal devido aos diversos fatores que interferem nesse processo (temperatura,umidade, condições aeróbica e anaeróbica, presença de microrganismos e condições do solo). Fatores intrínsecos ao corpo freqüentemente não são relacionados à decomposição corporal. Para investigar se o processo de esqueletização sofre interferência dos hormônios esteróides sexuais foi realizado um trabalho experimental com ratos Wistar (30 machos e 60 fêmeas divididos em subgrupos em diferentes fases hormonais). Os animais foram cuidados até atingirem o peso entre 350 e 450g, quando foram mortos em câmara de CO2 e sepultados. A análise dos fatores ambientais (temperatura, umidade do ar e chuvas) e corporais (peso e gordura corporal) mostrou que a variação destes não interferiu no processo de esqueletização. Após as exumações, apenas o grupo de machos controles para testosterona apresentou esqueletização completa. Os machos castrados sem reposição de testosterona e os machos castrados com reposição de testosterona apresentaram esqueletização mínima. Todos os grupos das fêmeas apresentaram esqueletização parcial. A análise dos resíduos de putrefação dos grupos com esqueletização mínima e parcial evidenciou a presença de ácidos graxos característicos da composição de adipocera. Considerando-se que os dois grupos de animais (machos e fêmeas) foram sepultados no mesmo local, sob as mesmas condições ambientais e corporais, durante o mesmo intervalo de tempo, é possível concluir que os hormônios esteróides sexuais são responsáveis pela diferença observada na decomposição corpórea, sendo a testosterona o principal interveniente neste processo. Além disso, o modelo experimental também evidenciou o potencial de utilização para ser utilizado futuramente em estudos do processo de formação de adipocera.&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/253</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i1p35-42</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 1 (2008); 35-42</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 1 (2008); 35-42</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 1 (2008); 35-42</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/253/254</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/254</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:CAP</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">EFFECTS OF TESTOSTERONE, ESTRADIOL OR PROGESTERONE ON THE BODY DECOMPOSITION OF CASTRATED RATS</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">EFEITOS DA TESTOSTERONA, ESTRADIOL OU PROGESTERONA NA DECOMPOSIÇÃO CORPORAL DE RATOS CASTRADOS</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Soares, Andjara T.C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferrari, Ana C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guimarães, Marco Aurelio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina Legal. Ratos. Castração. Decomposição corporal. Testosterona.Estradiol. Progesterona.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Forensic Medicine. Rat. Castration. Body decomposition. Testosterone. Estradiol. Progesterone.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Previous results from our laboratory showed that males and females buried in the same place and in the same environmental conditions, conduct the male bodies to reach complete skeletonization before the female ones. So, it was decided to investigate if castrated male rats submitted to different steroid treatments showed different body decomposition patterns. Fifty male Wistar rats were anesthetized at 21 days of age and 40 of them were castrated while 10 were submitted to sham surgeries. The animals were divided into the following groups: Co- Control (sham surgery); Ca- Castreted; T- Testosterone (castrated + testosterone propionate); E- Estradiol (castrated + estradiol cipionate); P- Progesterone (castrated + progesterone). The animals were killed at 81 days of age in a CO2 chamber and were buried in the same grave. Exhumation was done 120 days after burial. The body decomposition was more advanced in the Group T, decreasingly followed by the Groups P, Co and Ca. The Group E was not considered in the analysis because of the significant if differences in body weight in comparison to the other groups in the time of death. The results indicate that steroid sexual hormones can interfere in the process of the body decomposition. This experimental biological model raises an important implication for forensic purposes, once hormonal profiles can induce different aspects of the body decomposition in the same interval of time, opening a precedent to justify investigation of human material to avoid doubts in the determination of the time since death in criminal investigations.&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Resultados prévios do nosso laboratório mostraram que ratos machos e fêmeas, quando sepultados em um mesmo local e sob as mesmas condições ambientais apresentam decomposição corporal diferenciada, com os corpos dos machos atingindo esqueletização completa antes das fêmeas. Então, decidiu-se investigar se ratos machos castrados submetidos a diferentes tratamentos com esteróides sexuais desenvolveriam padrões diferentes de decomposição corporal. Cinqüenta ratos Wistar machos foram anestesiados aos 21 dias de idade e 40 deles foram castrados enquanto 10 foram submetidos à cirurgia sham. Os animais foram divididos nos seguintes grupos: Co- Controle (cirurgia sham); Ca- Castrado; T- Testosterona (castração + propionato de testosterona); E- Estradiol (castração + cipionato de estradiol); P- Progesterona (castração + progesterona). Os animais foram mortos aos 81 dias de idade em câmara de CO2 e foram sepultados no mesmo local. A exumação foi feita 120 dias após o sepultamento. A decomposição corporal estava mais avançada no grupo T, seguindo decrescentemente pelos grupos P, Co e Ca. O grupo E não foi considerado nesta análise devido à diferença significativa no peso corporal no momento da morte em relação aos outros grupos. Os resultados indicaram que os hormônios esteróides sexuais podem interferir no processo de decomposição corporal. Esse modelo biológico experimental apresenta uma importante implicação forense, uma vez que perfis hormonais podem induzir diferentes aspectos na decomposição corporal no mesmo intervalo de tempo, abrindo um precedente para justificar a investigação em material humano para evitar dúvidas na determinação do tempo desde a morte em investigações criminais.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/254</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i1p43-49</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 1 (2008); 43-49</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 1 (2008); 43-49</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 1 (2008); 43-49</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/254/255</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/255</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">MEDICO-LEGAL DATA ON DROWNING IN RIBEIRÃO PRETO REGION (SP, BRAZIL): A STEP FOR PREVENTION</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">DADOS MÉDICO-LEGAIS SOBRE AFOGAMENTOS NA REGIÃO DE RIBEIRÃO PRETO (SP, BRASIL): UM PASSO PARA A PREVENÇÃO</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Araújo, Rodrigo T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martin, Carmen C. S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martinis, Bruno S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Evison, Martin P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guimarães, Marco Aurelio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina Legal. Epidemiologia. Ferimentos e Lesões. Afogamento. Brasil.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Forensic Medicine. Epidemiology. Wounds and Injuries. Drowning. Brazil.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This is a prevalence study with the first specific description of drowning cases in a non-coastal area of Brazil, in the locality of Ribeirão Preto, State of São Paulo—a region with standards of living comparable to those in developed countries—regarding the establishment of preventative measures for this specific kind of injury.&#160;Methodology: An analysis of the forensic documentation of 89 drowning cases occurred between 2001 and 2004. The pattern of drowning fatalities was studied in relation to parameters like age, sex, socio-economic background and evaluation of alcohol consumption.Results&#160;: rate of 2.69 cases per 100,000 habitants per year was observed. The predominant profile among drowning victims was that of the Caucasian male of economically productive age (15 to 59 years), accidentally drowned in rivers and dams in rural areas during the summer and autumn, being impossible the evaluation of alcohol consumption. Conclusion and Relevance&#160;: the observation of the victim profile through the analysis of forensic reports allowed the development of a successful pilot program of drowning prevention that can be expanded to other non-coastal areas in Brazil, regarding the reduction of the number of victims by prevention. The difficulties in alcohol consumption analysis are discussed.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este é um estudo de prevalência com a primeira descrição específica de casos de afogamento em uma área não-costeira do Brasil, em Ribeirão Preto, estado de São Paulo, uma região com padrão de vida comparável ao de países desenvolvidos, com o objetivo de estabelecer medidas preventivas para este tipo específico de trauma.&#160;Metodologia&#160;: Uma análise da documentação médico-legal de 89 casos de afogamento ocorridos entre 2001 e 2004. O padrão de mortes por afogamento foi estudado através de parâmetros como idade, sexo, características sócio-econômicas e avaliação do consumo de álcool. Resultados: um índice de 2,69 casos por 100.000 habitantes foi observado. O perfil predominante entre as vítimas de afogamento foi o do homem caucasiano em idade economicamente produtiva (15-59 anos), afogados acidentalmente em rios e represas na área rural durante o verão e o outono, sendo inviável a avaliação do consumo de álcool.&#160;Conclusão e Relevância&#160;: a observação do perfil da vítima de afogamento através dos relatórios médico-legais permitiu o desenvolvimento de um projeto piloto de sucesso na prevenção de afogamentos que pode ser expandido para outras áreas não-costeiras do Brasil, visando à redução do número de vítimas através da prevenção. As dificuldades de investigar a influência do consumo de álcool são discutidas.&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/255</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i1p50-57</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 1 (2008); 50-57</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 1 (2008); 50-57</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 1 (2008); 50-57</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/255/256</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/256</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">COMPARISON OF NUTRITIONAL STATUS BETWEEN YOUNG AND ELDERLY WOMEN: RELATION WITH LEPTIN AND IGF-I</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">COMPARAÇÃO ENTRE O ESTADO NUTRICIONAL DE MULHERES IDOSAS E MULHERES JOVENS: RELAÇÃO COM A LEPTINA E O IGF-I</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Miyamoto, Marcia V.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Melo, Camila M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro, Sandra M. L.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Envelhecimento. Leptina. Fator de Crescimento Similar à Insulina-I. Estado Nutricional.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aging. Leptin. Insulin-like Growth Factor-I. Nutritional Status.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Aim: to compare nutritional status between old and young women, from anthropometric, dietetic and biochemical variables, looking for relation with leptin and IGF-I concentration.&#160;Methods:&#160;18 voluntary women were distributed in two groups: -more than 60 years old (n=10), named “old” (O); - between 20-30 years (n=8), named “young” (Y). They were evaluated: body mass index (BMI), waist circumference (WC) and body composition by bioelectric impedance (fat mass and fat free mass); diet evaluation by three food diary calculated by energy, macronutrients and cholesterol; plasmatic concentration of lipids, glucose, albumin, leptin and IGF-I.&#160;Methods:&#160;18 voluntary women were distributed in two groups: -more than 60 years old (n=10), named “old” (O); - between 20-30 years (n=8), named “young” (Y). They were evaluated: body mass index (BMI), waist circumference (WC) and body composition by bioelectric impedance (fat mass and fat free mass); diet evaluation by three food diary calculated by energy, macronutrients and cholesterol; plasmatic concentration of lipids, glucose, albumin, leptin and IGF-I. Results:&#160;“O” group presented higher values from BMI, WC, percent body fat, leptin levels and low density lipoproteins. “Y” group presented higher values from IGF-I and percent lean body mass. Leptin correlated positive and significantly with fat mass and WC, when analyzed for all individuals. After adjustment of leptin for body fat, there were not significant differences between groups. After adjustment of IGF-I by body lean mass, “Y” presented higher values.&#160;Conclusions&#160;: leptin levels are higher in old women, proportional to an increase in body fat, specifically visceral fat. It&#160; was possible to identify a relation among leptin, somatotrophic axis and liver lipoprotein metabolism. Energetic balance was negative for all the subjects without any deviation in nutritional status; it should be due to underreporting of food ingestion and overreporting of physical activity.&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivos:comparar, entre mulheres idosas e mulheres jovens, o estado nutricional a partir de variáveis antropométricas, dietéticas e bioquímicas, buscando relação com as concentrações plasmáticas de leptina e IGF-I.&#160;Métodos:&#160;18 mulheres voluntariamente recrutadas foram distribuídas em dois grupos: I= idosas (mais de 60 anos, n=10) e J= jovens (entre 20-30 anos, n=8). Foram avaliados: índice de massa corporal (IMC), circunferência de cintura (CC) e composição corporal (massa gorda e massa livre de gordura) por bioimpedância elétrica; três diários alimentares calculados quantitativamente em energia, macronutrientes e colesterol; concentrações plasmáticas de glicose, lipídeos, albumina, leptina e IGF-I.&#160;Resultados :O grupo I apresentou maiores valores de IMC, CC, percentual de gordura corporal e concentração plasmática de leptina e lipoproteínas de baixa densidade. O grupo J apresentou maiores valores para as concentrações plasmáticas de IGF-I e para o percentual de massa magra. A leptina correlacionou-se positiva e significativamente com a massa gorda e com a CC na análise do grupo todo. Após o ajuste da leptina pela massa gorda, não foram observadas diferenças entre os grupos. Após o ajuste do IGF-I pela massa livre de gordura, o grupo J apresentou maiores valores. As concentrações plasmáticas de albumina e de glicose apresentaram-se dentro da normalidade e sem diferenças entre os grupos.&#160;Conclusões: as concentrações de leptina são mais elevadas em mulheres idosas, proporcionalmente ao aumento da massa gorda, em especial a gordura visceral. Foi possível identificar relação entre leptina, eixo somatotrófico, e metabolismo hepático de lipoproteínas. O balanço energético foi negativo para ambos os grupos, porém não foram identificados desvios no estado nutricional, o que pode indicar subnotificação de relatos alimentares e supernotificação de atividade física.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/256</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i1p58-66</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 1 (2008); 58-66</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 1 (2008); 58-66</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 1 (2008); 58-66</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/256/257</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/257</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">DIETARY REFERENCE INTAKES FOR THE EVALUATION AND PLANNING OF DIETS FOR CHILDREN AGED ONE TO EIGHT YEARS</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">VALORES DE REFERÊNCIA DE INGESTÃO DE NUTRIENTES PARA AVALIAÇÃO E PLANEJAMENTO DE DIETAS DE CRIANÇAS DE UM A OITO ANOS</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Vieira, Marta N. C. M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Japur, Camila C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Resende, Cristina M. M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Monteiro, Jacqueline P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Nutrição Infantil. Necessidades Nutricionais. Recomendações Nutricionais.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child Nutrition. Nutritional Requirements. Nutrition Policy. Reference Values. Energy Intake.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Dietary Reference Intakes (DRIs) have been developed in order to help dietary planning and the assessment of nutrient intake for individuals and populations. These values were proposed in the late nineties to replace the recommended daily allowances (RDAs), innovating and creating new concepts of dietary planning and assessment due to the recently updated information about nutrient requirements, the establishment of maximum intake levels in need to include the concept of risk-reduction of chronic-degenerative diseases, and a subdivision within each age range due to the different nutrient requirements in each stage of life. Considering the food consumption assessment important in full-range attention to the children’s health, and enabling funds to health professionals in nutritional monitoring and diagnosis, the main objective of the current study was to present, in a practice way, the nutritional recommendations and their applications for children aged 1 to 8 years old, based on the DRIs Methodology.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Os valores de referência de ingestão dietética (Dietary Reference Intakes) foram desenvolvidos para auxiliar no planejamento alimentar e avaliação da ingestão de nutrientes de indivíduos e populações. Foram propostos a partir do final da década de 90, em substituição às recomendações estabelecidas em 1989 (RDAs), visando a implementação de inovações como a criação de novos conceitos de avaliação e planejamento de dietas, devido à disponibilidade de informações atualizadas sobre necessidades e ingestão de nutrientes; o estabelecimento dos níveis máximos de ingestão com o surgimento do conceito de redução do risco de doenças crônico-degenerativas e a subdivisão dentro de cada faixa etária, devido às demandas diferenciadas de nutrientes para cada etapa da vida. Considerando a importância da avaliação do consumo alimentar na atenção integral à saúde da criança e a fim de subsidiar os profissionais de saúde no diagnóstico e acompanhamento nutricional, o objetivo deste trabalho foi apresentar de maneira prática as recomendações nutricionais e seu modo de aplicação em crianças de um a oito anos de idade baseando-se na metodologia das DRIs.&#160;&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/257</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i1p67-76</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 1 (2008); 67-76</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 1 (2008); 67-76</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 1 (2008); 67-76</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/257/258</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/258</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:NTI</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">RESUMOS DE DISSERTAÇÕES DE MESTRADO E TESES DE DOUTORADO APRESENTADAS NA FACULDADE DE MEDICINA DE RIBEIRÃO PRETO - USP DE OUTUBRO A DEZEMBRO DE 2007</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Editor, O</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/258</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i1p86-132</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 1 (2008); 86-132</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 1 (2008); 86-132</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 1 (2008); 86-132</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/258/259</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/259</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The real importance of cost management in a teaching hospital: theoretical considerations</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A importância da gestão de custos em hospitais de ensino: considerações teóricas</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dallora, Maria Eulália Lessa do Valle</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Forster, Aldaisa Cassanho</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hospitals, Teaching</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hospital Costs</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hospital Administration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Financial Management, Hospital</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hospitais de Ensino</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Custos Hospitalares</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Administração Hospitalar</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Administração Financeira de Hospitais</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo deste trabalho é discutir as características dos hospitais de ensino e o papel que a gestão de custos assume no contexto dessas instituições de saúde. O aumento dos gastos e custos na saúde é acompanhado com preocupação pelos gestores. O conhecimento dos custos é passo fundamental para a gestão dos hospitais, que estão inseridos em um contexto de custos elevados, recursos escassos, pressão por qualidade e bons serviços. Nos hospitais de ensino, organizações complexas, a gestão dos custos vem assumindo grande importância, pois além da assistência à saúde, têm a importante missão de formação de recursos humanos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The impact of rising Health Care Costs are observed with preoccupation by their managers. The knowledge of the costs is a basic step for the hospital management that are inserted in a context of raised costs, scarce resources, pressure for quality and good services. At teaching Hospitals a complex organization, the management of the costs comes assuming great importance, because besides the attendance to the health, they have the important mission of human resources formation.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/259</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i2p135-142</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 2 (2008); 135-142</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 2 (2008); 135-142</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 2 (2008); 135-142</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/259/260</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/260</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">MORPHOLOGICAL CHARACTERISTICS OF ADULT SKELETAL MUSCULAR TISSUE ESTIMATED BY ANALYZING ITS FUNCTIONAL PERFORMANCE</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">ANÁLISE DO DESEMPENHO FUNCIONAL PARA ESTIMAR CARACTERÍSTICAS MORFOLÓGICAS DO TECIDO MUSCULAR ESQUELÉTICO DE SUJEITOS ADULTOS</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Priscila Cação Benedini</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Back, Cláudio Gregório Nuernberg</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mattiello-Sverzut, Ana Cláudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Morfologia. Músculo Esquelético. Reabilitação. Força Muscular.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Morphology. Skeletal Muscle. Rehabilitation. Muscle Strength.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This short review aims to analyze the capacity of functional analysis, through isokinetic dynamometry, to gather information on muscle fiber contractile characteristics in normal sedentary individuals, athletes, elderly people and in muscular alterations (atrophy and myopathy). The studies, here reported, demonstrated that by kinetic functional analysis, in contrast to the in vitro&#160;one, muscular performance in individuals may be quantified in conditions close to their daily or sportive activities. Thus, it is possible to precisely determine the influence of muscular adaptations in conducting these activities and, in addition, verify how muscular contraction functions in adverse clinical conditions like, lack of use, muscular atrophy, aging and myopathy. Different functional variables (fatigue index, torque, potency and work) are strongly related with different types of fibers, particularly with type 2 fast contraction fiber. Consolidation of the dynamometer as an instrument for measuring and/or diagnostic of various muscular conditions is highly relevant to therapeutic practice and merits emphasizing to health professionals.&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Esta breve revisão aborda a capacidade da análise funcional, através da dinamometria isocinética, em inferir características contráteis das fibras musculares em indivíduos normais sedentários, atletas, idosos e nas alterações musculares (atrofia e miopatia). A análise dos estudos aqui abordados demonstrou que a análise funcional isocinética, em contraste com a realizada in vitro, quantifica o desempenho muscular em condições próximas das atividades de vida diária ou esportiva dos sujeitos. Portanto, é possível determinar mais precisamente a influência das adaptações musculares na realização destas atividades e, além disso, como a função muscular se comporta em condições clínicas adversas como desuso, atrofia muscular, envelhecimento e miopatias. As diferentes variáveis funcionais (índice de fadiga, torque, trabalho e potência) apresentam fortes relações com diferentes tipos de fibras, com destaque para a fibra de contração rápida do tipo 2. A consolidação do dinamômetro como instrumento de medida e/ou diagnóstico das diferentes condições musculares é de grande relevância para a prática terapêutica e merece tornar-se mais evidente para os profissionais da saúde.&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/260</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i2p143-152</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 2 (2008); 143-152</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 2 (2008); 143-152</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 2 (2008); 143-152</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/260/261</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/261</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">PSYCHOSSOCIAL DETERMINANTS OF DOMESTIC CARE BY FAMILIESS MEMBERS OF PERSONS WHO LIVE WITH HIV/AIDS</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">DETERMINANTES PSICOSSOCIAIS DO CUIDADO DOMÉSTICO POR MEMBROS DE FAMÍLIAS DE PESSOAS QUE VIVEM COM HIV/AIDS</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Machado, Cíntia Yuri S. B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Figueiredo, Marco Antonio C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Lícia B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">HIV. Cuidadores. Família.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">HIV. Caregivers. Family.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The investment in training and counselling of laypeople involved in the care in HIV/aids has allowed the creation of parallel resources to the hospital attendance. The family can represent a source of resources to regulate hospitalization flow and to reduce the amount of time spent coping with the disease and its desruptive effects, determined by preconceptions of gender, sexuality, use of drugs and homosexuality. This research aimed at identifying, under the perspective of domestic caregivers, some elements of appropriation of effetive conditions for the maintenance of care of people with HIV/aids in the domestic environment. Half-structuralized interviews were carried with 4 domestic caregivers, their relatives with HIV/aids companions, in the clinic of the Special Unit of Treatment the Infectum-Contagious Illnesses from the Clinics Hospital of the Faculty of Medicine of Ribeirão Preto. The interviews had followed the procedures of evocation, articulation and verification of answers. Later, successive analyses of content, on the transcription of the interviews, had allowed the synthesis in Thematic Categories and Subcategories. The contents related the containing for physical and affective needs, characteristic of the roles incorporated by the woman in the division of work for gender, and the search of a reciprocity related to affection exchange, involving the caregiver and the cared person, were prevalent in the speech of the participants. The results point to the necessity of reintegration of the psychoafective balance of the woman, as domestic caregiver, in a context determined for the feminine vulnerability and the naturalization of the rules of gender.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O investimento em formação e orientação de pessoas leigas envolvidas no cuidado em HIV/aids tem permitido a criação de recursos paralelos ao atendimento hospitalar. A família pode representar uma fonte de recursos para regular o fluxo da hospitalização e amenizar o convívio da pessoa com a doença e seus efeitos desagregadores, determinados por pré-concepções de gênero, sexualidade, uso de drogas e homossexualidade. Esta pesquisa teve como objetivo identificar, sob a perspectiva de cuidadoras domésticas, alguns elementos para a apropria ção de condições efetivas para a manutenção do cuidado de pessoas com HIV/aids no ambiente doméstico. Foram realizadas entrevistas semi-estruturadas com 4 cuidadoras domésticas, acompanhantes de seus familiares com HIV/aids, no ambulatório da Unidade Especial de Tratamento a Doenças Infecto-Contagiosas do Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto - USP. As entrevistas seguiram os procedimentos de evocação, enunciação e verificação de respostas. Posteriormente, sucessivas análises de conteúdo sobre a transcrição das entrevistas, permitiram a síntese em Categorias e Subcategorias Temáticas. Os conteúdosrelacionados à continência para as necessidades físicas e&#160;afetivas, características de papéis incorporados pela mulher na divisão de trabalho por gênero, e a busca de uma reciprocidade quanto à troca de afetos, envolvendo cuidador e pessoa cuidada, foram prevalentes na fala das participantes. Os resultados apontam para a necessidade de reintegração do equilíbrio psicoafetivo da mulher, enquanto cuidadora doméstica, num contexto determinado pela vulnerabilidade feminina e a naturalização dos papéis de gênero. (CNPq).</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i2p153-161</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 2 (2008); 153-161</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 2 (2008); 153-161</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 2 (2008); 153-161</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/261/262</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/262</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">SELF-MEDICATION IN OPHTHALMOLOGY</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">AUTOMEDICAÇÃO EM OFTALMOLOGIA</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Espíndola, Rodrigo França</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schellini, Silvana Artioli</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Padovani, Carlos Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Self Medication</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ophthalmic Solution</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Blindness</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Prevention.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Automedicação. Soluções oftálmicas. Cegueira. Prevenção.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Purpose: To analyze the conditions, consequences and risks of self-medication in patients attended in ophthalmology emergency room at Hospital das Clínicas de Botucatu (UNESP).&#160;Methods: Sixty patients who had used any form of self-medication were studied according: age, sex, professional activity, mainly complain, visual acuity (best-corrected vision), who administrated the self-medication (friends/parents, pharmacy clerk, advertisement, or the person himself), sort of medication or product used (eyedrops/ointments/contact lenses), cost (R$), time expenditure to medical attention, ocular complications, risk of visual loss and final diagnose.&#160;Results: The majority of patients with self-medication were male (72%). The mean age was 40,9 years (7-77 years). Patients usually used eyedrops that they had at home and delayed 3 days to the first medical evaluation. The most frequently kind of topical eyedrop used was vasoconstrictor (17%). However, many patients even knew what kind of medication they had dropped in their eyes (21%). The great majority of the patients (68%) were exposed to the risk of visual loss.According to our results, self-medication may cause visual complications in 12% of patients, in which, 42% was related to the contact lenses fit without ophthalmologic assistance. Conclusion:The majory of the patients used medication that they had in home. The topical vasoconstrictor was the most frequently used drug, however, they did not know which medication were dropping in their eyes (21%).&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Avaliar as características, conseqüências e o risco da prática da automedica ção em pacientes atendidos no Pronto Socorro de oftalmologia do Hospital das Clínicas de Botucatu (UNESP).&#160;Métodos:Foram incluídos no estudo 60 pacientes que haviam se submetido a qualquer forma de automedicação. Os seguintes dados foram coletados no momento do atendimento: idade, sexo, profissão, queixa principal, acuidade visual com melhor correção, como ocorreu a indicação da automedicação (por amigos/parentes, balconista, mídia ou por conta própria), tipo de medicamento (colírio ou pomada) /produto utilizado (lente de contato), custo (R$), tempo gasto para procurar assistência médica especializada, como se deu a orienta ção para procura de um oftalmologista, complicações oculares devido à automedicação, o risco de complicação, diagnóstico final. Resultados:A maioria dos atendidos era do sexo masculino (72%). A idade dos pacientes variou de 7 a 77 anos, sendo a m dia de 40,9 anos. A maioria dos pacientes utilizou medicamentos que já possuía no domicílio e demoravam em média três dias para procurar auxílio especializado. Os vasoconstritores tópicos foram a classe de colírios mais utilizadas pelos analisados (17%), porém muitos não sabiam que droga estavam instilando nos olhos (21%). A grande maioria dos pacientes atendidos (68%) possuía potencial risco de prejuízo visual. Foram encontrados 12% &#160;de complicações devido a pratica da automedicação, sendo que destes, 42% foi devido ao uso de lentes de contato sem a supervisão de um oftalmologista.&#160;Conclusão: A maioria dos pacientes atendidos utilizou medicamentos que já possuía no domicílio. A classe de medicamento mais usada foi a de vasoconstritores tópicos, porém muitos, não sabiam que droga estavam instilando em seus olhos (21%). &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/262</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i2p162-168</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 2 (2008); 162-168</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 2 (2008); 162-168</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 2 (2008); 162-168</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/262/263</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/263</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">VARIATION OF THE TRAINING OVERLOAD IN THE BEHAVIOR OF THE MUSCULAR FORCE AND SUBJECTIVE PERCEPTION OF PAIN IN SEDENTARY FEMALE</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">VARIAÇÃO DA SOBRECARGA DE TREINAMENTO NO COMPORTAMENTO DA FORÇA MUSCULAR E DA PERCEPÇÃO SUBJETIVA DE DOR EM MULHERES SEDENTÁRIAS</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Maior, Alex Souto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Menuci, Thiago</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Soares, Vinícius</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Lucas Rafael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gribov, Márcio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Simão, Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Strength. Physical Exercise. Muscle Pain.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força Muscular. Exercício Físico. Dor Muscular Tardia.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The aim of the study was to analyze and compare gains of strength muscle and to observe the behavior of the subjective perception of pain (SPP) in the period eight weeks in sedentary women through two different programs from resistive exercises. The study was composed of 16 women (27.5 ± 4.8 years; 57 ± 3.9 kg; 162.8 ± 3.3 cm; 21.4 ± 1 kg/m2) healthy and sedentary. They were separate in two different groups: group 1 (G1) - during two initial weeks accomplished two sets of 10 repetitions with load that varied of 40 to 60% of the mass weight. However, 3th and 4th weeks they executed three sets of 10 repetitions to 80% of 1RM. Among 5th and 8th weeks it happened progressive increase of the set number for four maintaining the number of repetitions (10 repetitions) and same overload value; group 2 (G2) - program continuous in the exercise training of three sets of 10 repetitions was accomplished in the first two weeks with a load that varied of 40 to 60% of the corporal weight. Subsequent weeks the training was altered for four sets of 10 repetitions with an equivalent load to 80% of 1RM along the eight weeks of training. For analysis of the strength muscle the test of 1RM was used in the end of 2nd, 4th, 6th and 8th weeks with intention of to verify the behavior of the strength muscle starting from the displacement of loads and to optimize the training load. The exercises used in the training protocol and in the test of 1RM they were: leg press 45°, knee extension, knee flexion, lat pull down, elbow flexion, elbow extension. SPP was presented to each volunteer 48:00h after accomplishment of the test of 1RM. ANOVA Two Way following by the test post hoc of Bonferroni verified that the results intra-groups for G1 presented significant difference for all of the exercises in all the tests. However, G2 the significant difference was observed, in a large part of the exercises, only of the 3° and 4° test in relation to the 1° test. For the analyses inter-groups the test Mann-Whitney for independent samples verified increase significant of strength muscle in the G1 in relation to G2 with exercises leg press 45°, elbow flexion, elbow extension. In relation to SPP a significant fall was observed in the analogical scale of G1 in relation to G2 (p &amp;lt;0.001). The conclusion revealed that the progressive overload imposed G1 promoted increased gains of muscle strength than G2.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo do estudo foi analisar e comparar os ganhos de força e observar o comportamento da percepção subjetiva de dor (PSD) no período de oito semanas em mulheres sedentárias através de dois programas distintos de exercícios resistidos. O estudo foi composto de 16 mulheres (27,5 ± 4,8 anos; 57 ± 3,9 kg; 162,8 ± 3,3 cm; 21,4 ± 1, kg/m2 aparentemente saudáveis e sedentárias. Elas foram separadas aleatoriamente em dois grupos distintos: Grupo 1 (G1) - os indivíduos nas duas primeiras semanas realizaram duas séries em 10 repetições com carga que variava de 40 a 60% do peso corporal. Entre a 3a e a 4 semana treinaram com três séries de 10 repetições a 80% de 1RM (repetição máxima). Entre a 5a e a 8a semana ocorreu aumento progressivo do número de séries para quatro, mantendo o número de repetições (10 repetições) e a mesma sobrecarga; Grupo 2 (G2) - foi realizado um programa de treinamento contínuo de três séries de 10 repetições nas duas primeiras semanas com uma carga que variava de 40 a 60% do peso corporal. Nas semanas subseqüentes o treinamento foi alterado para quatro séries de 10 repetições com uma carga equivalente a 80% de 1RM ao longo das oito semanas de treinamento. Para análise da força muscular foi utilizado o teste de 1RM no final da 2a, 4a, 6a e 8a semanas com intuito de verificar o comportamento da força muscular e otimizar a carga de treinamento. Os exercícios utilizados no protocolo de treinamento e no teste de 1RM foram: leg press 45°, extensão de joelho, flexão de joelho, puxada pela frente, flexão de cotovelo e extensão de cotovelo. A PSD foi apresentada a cada voluntário 48h pós a realização de cada teste de 1RM. A ANOVA Two Way seguida do teste post hoc de Bonferroni verificou que os resultados intra-grupos para G1 apresentaram diferença significativa para todos os exercícios em todos os testes. Contudo, em G2 a diferença significativa foi observada, em grande parte dos exercícios, somente do 3º e 4º teste em relação ao 1º teste. Para as análises inter-grupos o teste Mann-Whitney para amostras independentes verificou ganhos de força significativo do G1 em relação a G2 nos exercícios leg press 45°, rosca tríceps e rosca bíceps. Em relação a PSD foi observada uma queda significativa na escala analógica de G1 em relação a G2 (p&amp;lt;0,001). Em conclusão, a sobrecarga progressiva imposta ao G1 promoveu significativos ganhos de força muscular e menor PSD em relação ao G2.&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i2p168-176</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 2 (2008); 168-176</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 2 (2008); 168-176</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 2 (2008); 168-176</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/263/264</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/264</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:09:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">PREVALENCE OF OVERWEIGHT AND OBESITY AMONG PRESCHOOL CHILDREN OF HIGH LEVEL ECONOMICAL PARTNER OF ARACAJU-SE</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">PREVALÊNCIA DE SOBREPESO E OBESIDADE EM PRÉ-ESCOLARES DE ALTO NÍVEL SÓCIOECONÔMICO DA CIDADE DE ARACAJU-SE</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Diego A. S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Obesidade. Pré-escolar. Estudos Transversais. Classe Social. Saúde da Criança.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Obesity. Preschool. Cross-sectional Study. Social Class. Child Health.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Model of Study: Prevalence Study. Objective: The objective of the present study was to esteem the prevalence of overweight and obesity among preschool children of high level economical partner of Aracaju-Sergipe city, Brazil, measured in a direct way. Methods: 243 children, being 51% of the female sex from 3,5 to 5,5 years old of high level economical partner, in agreement to National Association of Company of Research was appraised with relationship to the weight and the stature, to calculate IMC and to classify them in normal, overweight or obesity in agreement with the criteria of it Cole et al. Results: The prevalence of overweight was 16% and the obesity of 7,9%, and there were not significant differences in the prevalence of overweight and obesity between boys and girls (p &amp;gt; 0,05), as well as there were not differences among the groups of age for each sex (p &amp;gt; 0,05). Conclusion: The overweight and the obesity were made presents in a sample of children from 3,5 to 5,5 years of age of high purchasing power of the Aracaju city.&#160;&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo de Estudo: Estudo de Prevalência. O objetivo do presente estudo foi estimar a prevalência de sobrepeso e obesidade em pré-escolares de alto nível socioeconô-mico da cidade de Aracaju-Sergipe, Brasil, medido de forma direta. Métodos: 243 crianças, sendo 51% do sexo feminino de 3,5 a 5,5 anos de idade de alto nível socioeconômico, segundo critérios da Associação Nacional de Empresa de Pesquisa, foram avaliadas quanto ao peso e a estatura, para se calcular o IMC e classificá-las em normal, sobrepeso ou obesidade de acordo com os critérios de Cole et al. Resultados:&#160;Na amostra estudada a prevalência de sobrepeso foi de 16% e a obesidade de 7,9%, sendo que não houve diferenças significativas na prevalência de sobrepeso e obesidade entre meninos e meninas (p &amp;gt; 0,05). Não houve também diferenças entre os grupos de idade para cada sexo (p &amp;gt; 0,05). Conclusão: O sobrepeso e a obesidade se fizeram presentes em uma amostra de crianças de 3,5 a 5,5 anos de idade de alto poder aquisitivo da cidade de Aracaju-SE.&#160;&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/264</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v41i2p177-181</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 No. 2 (2008); 177-181</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 41 Núm. 2 (2008); 177-181</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 41 n. 2 (2008); 177-181</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/264/265</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2022-08-30T21:19:58Z" completeListSize="1467" cursor="75">8c34e6089db9bc0340de57cc5ef66262</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
