<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-08-29T21:20:15Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="rmrp">https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1193</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Doença de Crohn e gestação</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Crohn’s disease and pregnancy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Marcolin, Alessandra Cristina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Carla Vitola</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dias, Cleusa Cascaes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Troncon, Luiz Ernesto Almeida</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Duarte, Geraldo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Crohn Disease. Pregnancy. Fertility.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doença de Crohn. Gravidez. Fertilidade.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A doença de Crohn é uma enterite granulomatosa, transmural, crônica, de etiologia desconhecida que pode acometer qualquer parte do trato gastrintestinal, atingindo, preferencialmente, o íleo distal, os cólons e a região anorretal. Seu curso é variável, podendo ser de caráter indolente e prolongado, seguindo um padrão de exacerbações e remissões. A incidência da doença de Crohn aumentou nos últimos 30 anos e, na maioria dos casos, as manifestações clínicas iniciam-se na segunda e terceira décadas da vida, acometendo as mulheres em pleno período reprodutivo. O fator mais importante para o prognóstico gestacional, nessas mulheres, é a atividade da doença no início da gravidez. Complicações obstétricas como aborto espontâneo, parto pré-termo, malformações fetais e retardo de crescimento intra-útero, ocorrem com as recidivas da doença no período periconcepcional ou durante o primeiro trimestre gestacional. A evolução da doença de Crohn, durante a gestação, também dependerá da atividade da mesma, no início da gestação. Nesta revisão, os autores avaliaram os principais aspectos etiológicos, clínicos e terapêuticos da doença de Crohn durante a gravidez, discutindo detalhadamente os efeitos da doença sobre a gestação e as conseqüências da gravidez sobre a evolução dessa doença.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Crohn’s disease is a chronic transmural granulomatous enteritis of unknown etiology that may affect any part of the gastrointestinal tract, preferentially involving the distal ileum, the colons and the anorectal region. Its course is variable, of a dormant and prolonged nature, with a pattern of exacerbations and remissions. The incidence of Crohn’s disease has greatly increased in the last 30 years, with the absolute majority of cases starting to show clinical manifestations in the second and third decades of life, and with women being affected during their reproductive years. The disease activity in the beginnig of pregnancy is the most important factor affecting both the prognosis of Crohn’s disease and gestational prognosis. Obstetrical complications as spontaneous abortion, preterm delivery, fetal malformation and intrauterus growth retardation happen when the disease is active in the periconceptional period or during the first trimester of pregnancy. In the present review, the authors evaluate the major etiological, clinical and therapeutic aspects of Crohn’s disease during pregnancy, with a detailed discussion of the effects of the disease on pregnancy and the consequences of gestation for the evolution of the disease.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1193</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i1p64-69</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 1 (2001); 64-69</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 1 (2001); 64-69</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 1 (2001); 64-69</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1193/1212</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1194</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Diagnóstico bacteriológico das infecções do trato urinário: uma revisão técnica</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Bacteriological diagnostic of urinary tract infections: A technical revision</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Camargo, Ilana L. Baratella da C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Maschieto, Andresa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Salvino, Caio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Darini, Ana Lúcia Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Urinary Tract Infections. Diagnosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Laboratory. Bacteriuria.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Infecções Urinárias. Diagnóstico Laboratorial. Bacteriúria.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Urinary tract infection is one of the most common diseases and it can affect more than one site or one single place like urethra (urethritis), prostate (prostatitis), urinary bladder (cystitis) or kidney (pielonephritis). Urine is considered sterile and may suffer bacterial contamination from skin, clothes or external genitals, so it should be collected, kept and transported appropriately, to avoid false results in laboratory analysis. Urethritis and cistitis non gonococcal are commonly caused by members of Enterobacteriacea family but Escherichia coli is the casual agent of approximately 80% of the cases between fertile age women without urinary tract leison. Other microrganisms including Klebsiella sp., Enterobacter sp., Proteus sp., Pseudomonas sp and the Enterococcus sp are frequently found in patients with obstructive leisons or paralytical diseases affecting the renal function. Staphylococcus saprophyticus is an important opportunistic pathogenin human urinary tract infections, especially in young, sexually active females. The patient must be informed about the recommended procedures related to the collect time, way of obyaining and all the necessary asepsis, such as the professional must be up to date about the techniques utilized for the isolation, identification and susceptibility test of the microrganism. Currently, there are chemical and authomatical methods and excelent kits for laboratorial diagnosis of urinary infections, helping and accelerating the process of identification and efficient treatment to the infected patient.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Entre as doenças mais comuns está a infecção do trato urinário, afetando mais de um sítio ou um único local como a uretra (uretrite), próstata (prostatite), bexiga (cistite) ou rins (pielonefrite). A urina é considerada estéril e pode sofrer contaminação de bactérias da pele, da roupa ou da genitália. Por isso, se não colhida, armazenada e transportada adequadamente, pode-se obter falsos resultados em exames bacteriológicos. Bactérias da família Enterobacteriacea estão envolvidas em quase todas as uretrocistites não gonocócicas, sendo a Escherichia coli o agente causal de aproximadamente 80% dos casos entre mulheres na idade fértil, sem lesões do trato urinário. Outros microrganismos, incluindo Klebsiella sp., Enterobacter sp., Proteus sp., Pseudomonas sp. e Enterococcus sp., são freqüentemente encontrados em pacientes com lesões obstrutivas ou doenças paralíticas, afetando a função renal. Staphylococcus saprophyticus é um importante patógeno oportunista na infecção do trato urinário em humanos, especialmente em mulheres jovens, sexualmente ativas. O paciente deve ser informado quanto aos procedimentos recomendados, relacionados com o horário da colheita, modo de obtenção e toda a assepsia necessária, assim como o profissional deve estar bem atualizado quanto às técnicas utilizadas para o isolamento, identificação e antibiograma. Atualmente, existem métodos químicos automatizados e kits excelentes para o diagnóstico presuntivo de infecções urinárias, auxiliando e agilizando os processos de identificação e de tratamento eficaz ao paciente infectado.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1194</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i1p70-78</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 1 (2001); 70-78</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 1 (2001); 70-78</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 1 (2001); 70-78</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1194/1213</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1195</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Tempo de permanência do dispositivo venoso periférico, in situ, relacionado ao cuidado de enfermagem, em pacientes hospitalizados</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Time of permanence of the peripherical venous device in situ related to the nursing care to hospitalized patients</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pereira, Renata Cristina de C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zanetti, Maria Lúcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro, Kátia P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Infusions</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Intravenous</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">complications. Nursing Care.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Infusões Endovenosas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">complicações. Cuidados de Enfermagem.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The technological development of the intravenous therapy imposes to the nurse technical-scientific ability for this practice. This study purposed to relate the permanence time in situ of the peripherical venous devices with the nursing care. The obtained data point that in 50% of the venous stipplers, with time of permanence less than 24 h, the degree of nursing care was unsatisfactory, having 9.4 % of them remained in situ for a period upper than 72 h. The average of the time of permanence in situ of the peripherical venous device was 29,2 h, what demonstrates necessity to intensify the studies on this thematic aiming at qualification of nursing care.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O desenvolvimento tecnológico da terapia intravenosa impõe ao enfermeiro competência técnica e científica. Este estudo descritivo teve como objetivo relacionar o tempo de permanência in situ dos dispositivos venosos, periféricos com o cuidado de enfermagem. Os dados obtidos apontam que, em 50% das punções venosas, com tempo de permanência inferior a 24 h, o grau de cuidado de enfermagem foi insatisfatório, tendo 9,4 % delas permanecido in situ por um período superior a 72 h. O tempo médio de permanência do dispositivo venoso periférico, in situ foi de 29,2 h, o que demonstra necessidade de intensificar estudos visando à qualificação do cuidado de enfermagem.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1195</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i1p79-84</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 1 (2001); 79-84</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 1 (2001); 79-84</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 1 (2001); 79-84</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1195/1214</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1196</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Dados epidemiológicos da litíase renal em hospital de referência em Belo Horizonte - Minas Gerais</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology of renal calculi in a reference hospital in Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais state</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Petroianu, Andy</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira Neto, José Estevão</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alberti, Luiz R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Kidney Calculi. Epidemiology. Sex. Laterality.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cálculos Renais. Epidemiologia. Sexo. Lateralidade.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: A litíase renal é uma afecção muito comum na prática clínica e múltiplos fatores estão relacionados com sua etiopatogenia, embora não tenhamos encontrado estudo algum sobre a epidemiologia da litíase no Brasil. Objetivo: Avaliar a influência da idade, do sexo, da cor da pele e da lateralidade como fatores de risco para cálculo renal. Pacientes e Métodos: Foram estudados 400 prontuários de pacientes com diagnóstico de litíase urinária, nos Serviços de Nefrologia e Urologia do Hospital das Clínicas da Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais, em Belo Horizonte. Todos os diagnósticos foram confirmados pela história clínica associada a métodos de imagem. &amp;nbsp;Resultados: Houve predomínio de pacientes do sexo feminino (54,5 %) sobre o masculino com litíase renal. Os doentes brancos constituíram a maioria (75%), seguidos pelos mulatos (23,3%) e, em uma muito pequena proporção, pelos negros (1,8%). A idade média foi de 39,81, +- 15,61 anos. Não houve diferenças quanto à lateralidade dos cálculos, mas os homens tiveram mais cálculos bilaterais do que as mulheres. Conclusão: Na população estudada no presente trabalho, o cálculo renal foi mais freqüente em adultos jovens, brancos&amp;nbsp;e do sexo feminino, sem diferenças quanto à lateralidade. Os resultados sugerem uma possível relação entre nefrolitíase e cor da pele.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Introduction: Renal lithiasis is a very common disorder in the clinical practice, and multiple factors are related to its ethiopathogenicity. However, we did not find any study aboutthe epidemiology of lithiasis in Brazil. Objective: To acess the influence of age, sex, skin color and laterality of stones as risk factors for renal calculi. Methods: 400 charts of patients with diagnosis of nephrolithiasis were studied in the Nephrology and Urology Unit of the Hospital das Clínicas of Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais, in Belo Horizonte. All diagnoses were confirmed by clinical history associated to imaging studies. Results: The presence of this disease was higher in women (54,5%) than men. The proportion of white patients (75%) with nephrolithiasis was significantly higher than colored (23,3%), and black patients (1,8%). The mean age was 39,81±15,61 years. The side of calculi was not different in both sexes, but men presented more bilateral stones than women. Conclusion: In the population studied in the present paper, nephrolithiasis was more frequent in white young adults, mainly in women, without prevalence of side. These results suggest possible relation between kidney stones and skin color.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1196</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i1p85-88</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 1 (2001); 85-88</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 1 (2001); 85-88</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 1 (2001); 85-88</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1196/1215</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1197</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da maturação do processo de raciocínio diagnóstico de estudantes de medicina</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">An appraisal of the maturation of medical students’ diagnostic ability</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sobral, Dejano T.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Diagnosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Clinical. Students</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical. Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical. Attitude. Diagnostic Thinking Inventory.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diagnóstico Clínico. Estudantes de Medicina. Educação Médica. Atitude. Inventário de Raciocínio Diagnóstico.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The purpose of this study was to assess the utility of the Diagnostic Thinking Inventory (DTI) for appraisal of diagnostic ability development in relation to medical students’ learning perceptions. The inventory was administered to 88 medical students of both sexes, before and after regular clinical studies, five-month apart. Different measures of students’ learning perceptions (self-confidence as a learner, meaningfulness of learning experience and reflection in learning) and academic achievement were also obtained. The results showed significant albeit small differences between the two DTI measures as well as positive significant correlation of measures of learning perceptions with DTI scores. There was a significant relationship between the effect size of the intervention and the perception of self-determination in the diagnostic process. The data reinforce the idea that the DTI scores reflect, in addition to knowledge and skills, the learners’ perceptions of personal efficacy in the diagnostic process. Such perceptions can be influenced by many factors of the learning context as well as the learners’ attitudes to learning. In conclusion, the findings indicate the discrimination sensibility of the instrument and suggest its usefulness in monitoring the maturation of the clinical diagnostic process.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O propósito do estudo foi averiguar a utilidade do Inventário de Raciocínio Diagnóstico (IRD) na avaliação da maturação do processo de diagnóstico clínico, em conexão com percepções sobre o aprendizado na formação médica. O inventário foi aplicado entre 88 estudantes de Medicina, de ambos os sexos, em dois semestres consecutivos na fase de iniciação clínica. Foram, também, obtidos dados de percepções do aprendizado (valorização do aprendizado, autoconfiança do aprendiz e reflexão na aprendizagem) e de rendimento acadêmico. Os resultados revelaram diferenças significantes, porém pequenas, entre as duas medidas dos escores do IRD e correlações&amp;nbsp;positivas e significantes desses escores com pontuações das três medidas de percepção do aprendizado. Observou-se uma relação significativa entre o tamanho do efeito e a percepção de autodeterminação do processo diagnóstico. Os dados indicam que o IRD reflete, além de conhecimento e habilidades específicas, a percepção de eficácia pessoal no processo de diagnóstico, que pode ser influenciada por diferentes fatores do contexto do aprendizado e de atitudes do aprendiz. Em conclusão, os achados apontam a sensibilidade discriminativa do instrumento e sugerem sua utilidade no acompanhamento da maturação do processo de diagnóstico clínico.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1197</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i1p89-99</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 1 (2001); 89-99</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 1 (2001); 89-99</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 1 (2001); 89-99</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1197/1216</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1198</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:EDT</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Agradecimentos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Maria de Lourdes Veronese</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1198</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p117-117</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 117-117</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 117-117</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 117-117</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1198/1217</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1199</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:39Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:EDT</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Primeiro Transplante de Fígado em Ribeirão Preto</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva Junior, Orlando Castro</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1199</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p119-120</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 119-120</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 119-120</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 119-120</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1199/1218</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1200</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3A+Med.+Int.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Apresentação</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Basile-Filho, Anibal</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1200</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p121-122</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 121-122</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 121-122</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 121-122</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1200/1219</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1201</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:37Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3A+Med.+Int.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The pregnant patient in intensive care unit</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A paciente gestante na unidade de terapia intensiva</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nogueira, Antonio A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reis, Francisco J.C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reis, Patrícia A.S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pregnancy. Intensive Care Units. Maternal Mortality.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Gravidez. Unidades de Terapia Intensiva. Mortalidade Materna.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Intensive Care Unit (ICU) admission of pregnant patient is rare, however, the ortality rate of obstetric patients admitted to the ICU is high. The objective of this paper is to present some aspects of the physiologic changes in pregnancy and the most important points of the fetal well-being in order to provide the best management for the critically ill pregnant patient. Several topics were presented such as preeclapsia, amniotic fluid embolism, tocolitic-induced pulmonary edema, obstetric hemorrhage, obstetric infections and trauma in pregnancy. The knowledge of the pregnant patient and fetal physiology as well as the obstetric complications are very important in order to avoid maternal mortality due suboptimal standard of care.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A internação de pacientes gestantes, em unidades de terapia intensiva (UTI), é rara, contudo, dentre tais pacientes, apresenta-se elevada mortalidade. O objetivo deste artigo é discutir alguns aspectos da fisiologia normal da gestante, assim como os principais aspectos do bem-estar fetal, de forma a tornar possível uma melhor abordagem das pacientes: gestantes gravemente enfermas. São discutidas ainda algumas situações como a pré-eclampsia, a embolia por líquido amniótico, o edema pulmonar induzido por tocolíticos, as hemorragias de causa obstétrica, as infecções de causa obstétrica e o trauma na gestação. O conhecimento das particularidades da gestação e do bem-estar fetal, assim como o de algumas situações específicas da gestação, é fundamental no sentido de se reduzir a mortalidade das pacientes gestantes internadas em UTI.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1201</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p123-132</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 123-132</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 123-132</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 123-132</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1201/1220</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1230</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3A+Med.+Int.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Modos de assistência ventilatória</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Modes of mechanical ventilation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pádua, Adriana Ignácio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martinez, José Antônio Baddini</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Respiration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Artificial. Ventilators</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Mechanical. Respiratory Insufficiency.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Respiração Artificial. Respiradores Mecânicos. Insuficiência Respiratória.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">There are several mechanical ventilation modalities available nowadays. The choice of the most apropriate ventilatory approach in a specific clinical situation depends on the features of the patient, type of ventilator available, and the experience of the medical and paramedical teams in handling the machine. This article gives a general view about the most important ventilatory modalities, the principles involved in their design, indications, and use in the daily clinical setting, aiming to help the reader to become familiarized with handling mechanical ventilators, essential tools to keep alive patients with respiratory failure.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Diversas são as modalidades de ventilação mecânica por pressão positiva atualmente disponíveis. A escolha do modo mais adequado para uma determinada situação está na dependência das características clínicas do paciente, do tipo de respirador disponível, e da experiência da equipe médica e paramédica com o seu manuseio. O presente artigo fornece uma visão geral dos princípios envolvidos com a aplicação dos principais modos de assistência ventilatória, suas indicações e aplicações na prática diária, visando a que o leitor possa familiarizar-se com o manuseio dos respiradores mecânicos, elementos essenciais para a manutenção da vida em quadros de insuficiência respiratória.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1230</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p133-142</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 133-142</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 133-142</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 133-142</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1230/1250</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1313</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3A+Med.+Int.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Transporte do paciente crítico</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Transport of critically ill patients</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pereira Júnior, Gerson Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nunes, Taciana Leonel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Basile-Filho, Aníbal</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Transportation of Patients. Critical Care. Critical Illness.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transporte de Pacientes. Cuidados Críticos. Pacientes Críticos.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Intrahospital transport of critically ill patients is often necessary for optimal patient care. The increasing sophistication of nonportable diagnostic tests that aid physicians in diagnosing complex problems require the transport of critically ill patients outside the protective environment of the intensive care unit for prolonged periods. However, transport of intensive care unit patients within the hospital has been associated with a high rate of potentially detrimental complications. Interfacility patient transfers should occur when the benefits to the patient exceed the risks of the transfer. When a patient needs services that exceed the available resources of a facility, the patient should be transferred to a facility with the required resources. The decision to transfer a patient is the responsibility of the attending physician at the referring hospital. In this article, we discussed the role of intrahospital and interhospital transport of the critically ill patient.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O transporte intra-hospitalar do paciente crítico faz-se necessário para seu encaminhamento da sala de admissão ao Centro Cirúrgico ou à Unidade de Terapia Intensiva e para a realização de testes diagnósticos não portáteis, partindo da sala de admissão ou da unidade de terapia intensiva. A duração do transporte pode ser prolongada, ficando o paciente fora do ambiente “protegido” de um área de cuidados intensivos, sendo um período de potenciais complicações. O transporte inter-hospitalar deve ocorrer, quando os benefícios esperados para o paciente crítico excedem os riscos inerentes ao transporte e, também, quando o paciente necessita de cuidados que não existam no hospital onde está. A decisão e a efetuação do transporte são responsabilidade do médico que o assiste. Tal transporte envolve a presença de um veículo adaptado com todos os equipamentos necessários para a monitorização e suporte avançado de vida. Neste artigo, os autores discutem o papel do transporte intra e inter-hospitalar do paciente crítico.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1313</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p143-153</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 143-153</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 143-153</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 143-153</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1313/1338</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1421</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O ciclo da vesícula sináptica: panorama molecular</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The synaptic vesicle cycle: a molecular overview</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Arisi, Gabriel M. Arisi M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Neder, Luciano</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moreira, Jorge E.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Synaptic Vesicle. Synaptic Proteins. Synapse. Neurotransmitters.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Vesículas Sinápticas. Proteínas Sinápticas. Sinapse. Neurotransmissores.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A presente revisão aborda um ponto específico dentro da sinapse, provavelmente o mais crucial: as interações moleculares entre proteínas da membrana das vesículas sinápticas e da membrana plasmática pré-sináptica. Uma linguagem molecular muito precisa permite a fusão entre as membranas da vesícula sináptica e a plasmática, fusão que libera o neurotransmissor contido na vesícula para a fenda sináptica. A vesícula sináptica foi alvo, nos últimos anos, de uma verdadeira dissecção molecular. É a organela celular com a mais completa descrição estrutural e cinética de seus componentes protéicos. A descoberta de famílias de proteínas homólogas, presentes em todos os tipos celulares eucariotos, como a Rab e a SNARE (SNAP receptors), demonstrou que o ciclo da vesícula sináptica é uma interação entre sistemas protéicos, universais e específicos, de regulação do tráfego vesicular e de fusão de membranas lipídicas. O endereçamento e o controle do fluxo das estruturas precursoras das vesículas sinápticas até o terminal sináptico são realizados pela família Rab de pequenas GTPases. As proteínas da superfamília das kinesinas são as responsáveis pela ação mecânica no transporte anterógrado das estruturas precursoras, ao longo dos microtúbulos do citoesqueleto axonal. As proteínas SNARE realizam a fusão das vesículas com a membrana do terminal pré-sináptico. A proteína sinaptotagmina controla a formação do complexo SNARE em um modo dependente de cálcio. Embora já se tenha conhecimento da maior parte das proteínas envolvidas no ciclo da vesícula sináptica, tem-se ainda que elucidar muitas das funções e interrelações entre elas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The present review approaches a specific point in the synapse, probably the main one: the molecular interactions between the synaptic vesicle proteins and the presynaptic membrane proteins. A very precise language is talked between the vesicular and presynaptic membranes that allow the neurotransmitter release to the synaptic cleft. In recent years, the synaptic vesicle has been molecularly dissected, and it is probably the cell organelle with the most complete structural and kinetical description of its protein components. The discovery of families of homologue proteins in all eucariotic cells such as Rabs and SNAREs (SNAP receptors), demonstrated that the synaptic vesicle cycle depends on a refined interaction between a specific and universally distributed system of proteins that regulates the vesicle motion and fusion. The kinesin family is in charge of the mechanics for the anterograde transport of the raw material from the neuronal soma along microtubules in the axonal cytoskeleton. Sorting and flux control of the synaptic vesicle structural precursors is done by the Rab family of small GTPases. SNARE proteins make the fusion of the vesicles with the presynaptic terminal. Synaptotagmin regulates the formation of the SNARE complex in a calcium dependent mode. Although many of these proteins and their functions are well known, there is a large segment of knowledge on structure and interactions yet to be known.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1421</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p154-169</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 154-169</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 154-169</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 154-169</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1421/1453</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1639</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudo histórico: organizacional da comissão de controle de infecção hospitalar de um hospital universitário</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Historical: organizational study about the hospital infection control committee of an university hospital</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Magda Fabbri Isaac</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Branca Maria Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Commissions. Infection Control. Nosocomial Infection. History.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Comissões. Controle de Infecções. Infecção Hospitalar. História</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este trabalho caracteriza-se como um estudo histórico-organizacional da trajetória da Comissão de Controle de Infecção Hospitalar do Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto da Universidade de São Paulo, desde a sua constituição (1973) até o momento atual (1997), com base em atas e processos organizados cronologicamente. Para esta abordagem foi utilizada a metodologia de estudo de caso, que se caracterizou pelo exame detalhado da documentação, com vistas à determinação de categorias e subcategorias temáticas que representassem o complexo das atividades desenvolvidas pela referida comissão. As atividades desenvolvidas estiveram basicamente, centradas nas de vigilância epidemiológica das infecções, ensino e educação continuada, assessoria em projetos relacionados à planta física e segurança do trabalho. O estudo poderá contribuir como fonte de informações de fácil acesso para a própria comissão, para a constituição de novas comissões e, até mesmo, para o desenvolvimento de futuras pesquisas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This work is characterized by a historical - organizational study about the Hospital Infection Control Committee trajectory at Hospital das Clínicas from Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto da Universidade de São Paulo, since its constitution (1973) until this moment (1997), based on registers and processes organized chronologically. The methodology used for this approach was the case study, characterized by detailed examination of documents, with the purpose of determining categories and sub - categories that had been representative of activities complex developed by the Committee. The activities developed by the Committee were centered basically on infection epidemiological vigilance, continued teaching and education, project advising in relation to physical plans and work safety. This work can also contribute as an easy to reach source of information for the Committee itself, for constitution of other Committees and even though to future researches.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1639</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p170-176</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 170-176</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 170-176</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 170-176</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1639/1684</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1658</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Curcumina e norbixina: ação no metabolismo lipídico de aves domésticas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Curcumim and norbixin: action of lipidic metabolism in poultry</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Rosimar Regina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Tania Toledo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nagem, Tanus Jorge</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pinto, Aloísio Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Albino, Luiz Fernando Teixeira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ameida, Márcia Rogéria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leão, Maria Aparecida</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Curcumin. Norbixin. Cholesterol. Poultry.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Curcumina.Norbixina.Colesterol.Aves Domésticas</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudos em animais experimentais têm mostrado que corantes naturais previnem o desenvolvimento de doenças cardiovasculares. O objetivo deste trabalho é avaliar o efeito de curcuma e norbixina na redução dos lipídios sanguíneos em pintos hipercolesterolêmicos. Os resultados mostraram que curcuma e norbixina provocaram reduções significativas nos níveis de colesterol total, colesterol-LDL, colesterol-VLDL e triacilglicerol, não se apresentando reduções nos níveis de colesterol-HDL.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Studies in experimental animals have been suggesting that natural colorants they protect against the development of cardiovascular diseases. The objective went evaluate the curcumin effect and norbixin in the reduction of the blood lipids in poultry hypercholesterolemics. The results showed that curcumin and norbixin presented significant reductions in the levels of total cholesterol, cholesterol-LDL, cholesterol-VLDL and triacylglicerol, not presenting reductions in the levels of cholesterol-HDL.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1658</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p177-182</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 177-182</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 177-182</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 177-182</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1658/1703</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/1726</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação de indicadores do controle da contaminação ambiental da sala de operação: um estudo piloto</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">AN EVALUATION OF CONTROL INDICATORS OF ENVIRONMENTAL CONTAMINATION IN THE OPERATING ROOM: A PILOT STUDY</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nobre, Luciane F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Galvão, Cristina M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Graziano, Kazuko U.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Corniani, Fabiana</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Environmental Monitoring. Cross Infection. Operating Rooms</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Monitoramento Ambiental. Infecção Hospitalar. Salas de Cirurgia.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O controle da contaminação ambiental, na sala de operação, é uma das medidas de prevenção da infecção do sítio cirúrgico. Assim, o presente estudo teve como objetivo identificar se os padrões mínimos para o controle da contaminação ambiental estão sendo considerados pelos profissionais de saúde que atuam na unidade de Centro Cirúrgico. A investigação foi desenvolvida em um hospital geral, público; a coleta de dados realizou-se através de observação das cirurgias, utilizando instrumentos previamente elaborados, na especialidade de ginecologia e obstetrícia, no mês de janeiro de 2000, perfazendo um total de 23 procedimentos anestésicocirúrgicos observados. Realizamos uma análise descritiva e matemático-estatística, utilizando freqüência absoluta e porcentagem. Ao analisarmos o conjunto de itens do Padrão 1, que retrata a limpeza e montagem da sala de operação, e do Padrão 2, relativo aos princípios de assepsia cirúrgica, constatamos que a maioria dos procedimentos foi realizada pelos profissionais que atuavam na unidade, da forma preconizada pela literatura, entretanto, alguns itens avaliados evidenciaram a necessidade de reavaliação das práticas desenvolvidas pela equipe de saúde em relação ao controle da contaminação ambiental, bem como a atualização sobre os avanços técnico-científicos para o controle da infecção do sítio cirúrgico.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The control of environmental contamination in the operating room is an important measure to control infection in surgical sites. Therefore, this study aimed at identifying if minimum control patterns of environmental contamination are being considered by health professionals who perform their activities in operating rooms. The research was developed in a public general hospital and data were collected in the month of January, 2000, through the observation of gynecological and obstetrical operations using previously elaborated instruments, totaling 23 anaesthetic-surgical procedures observed. Subsequently, the authors carried out a descriptive and mathematical-statistical analysis using the absolute frequency and percentage. When analyzing the set of items for Pattern 1, which refers to the cleaning and preparation of the operating room, and those for Pattern 2, which are related to the principles of surgical asepsis, we found that most of the procedures were carried out by the professionals performing in the unit according to the patterns preconized by literature. However, some of the evaluated items showed the need for a re-evaluation of the practices developed by the health team regarding the control of environmental contamination as well as for the professionals’ up-dating on technical and scientific advancements for infection control in surgical sites.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1726</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p183-193</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 183-193</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 183-193</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 183-193</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/1726/1771</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/3105</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Transplante de fígado: relato do primeiro caso realizado no hospital das clínicas da faculdade de medicina de Ribeirão Preto da universidade de São Paulo</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Liver transplantation: case report of the first patient submitted to this procedure at the hospital das clínicas da faculdade de medicina de Ribeirão Preto - USP</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>França, Alex V.C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martinelli, Ana L.C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sankanrankutty, Ajith K.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rizzo, Cláudia C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva Junior, Orlando Castro</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Liver Transplantation. Carcinoma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hepatocellular. Liver Cirrhosis.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transplante de Fígado. Carcinoma Hepatocelular. Cirrose Hepática.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Liver transplantation is the main treatment option for patients with acute or chronic liver diseases when other surgical and clinical options haven´t been effective. In chronic liver diseases, the presence of hepatocellular carcinoma, when small in size, is an indication for liver transplantation. The authors present the first patient submitted to liver transplantation at the Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina – USP. The patient had cirrhosis due to hepatitis C virus, as well as hepatocellular carcinoma. While awaiting the transplant, he was submitted arterial embolization and percutaneous ethanol injection of the tumor, in order to delay it´s progression. There were no surgical complications. The piggy-back technique was used, with a choledoco-choledocal biliary anastomosis, stented with a T-tube. Immunosuppression was established using cyclosporin A and prednisone. Acute cellular rejection, on the ninth postoperative day was successfully treated with methylprednisolone (1g/day, IV, for 3 days). The patient was discharged on the 13th post-operative day. This case demonstrates the importance of early diagnosis and indication of liver transplantation in patients with hepatocellular carcinoma associated with cirrhosis, as well as one of the possible complications. The establishment of this group, specialized in the treatment of liver diseases, along with the technological and scientific developments have made this procedure a reality in the region of Ribeirão Preto, situated in the interior of the state of São Paulo.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O transplante de fígado constitui o principal tratamento para os pacientes portadores de doença hepática crônica ou aguda, em situações em que outras opções terapêuticas clínicas e/ou cirúrgicas não tenham sido eficazes no controle da doença. Dentre as doenças do fígado, o carcinoma hepatocelular, quando de pequeno tamanho, constitui uma das indicações para a realização do transplante. Relatamos o caso do primeiro paciente submetido ao transplante de fígado no Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão - USP. Ele era portador de cirrose hepática pelo vírus da hepatite C, associada à presença de carcinoma hepatocelular; enquanto em lista de espera pelo transplante, foi submetido à embolização arterial e alcoolização tumoral com o intuito de ser impedida a progressão da neoplasia. O transplante de fígado foi realizado sem intercorrências cirúrgicas, utilizando-se a técnica de piggyback com anastomose biliar colédoco-colédoco com permanência de dreno de Kher. O esquema imunossupressor utilizado foi o duplo, associando-se ciclosporina A e prednisona. No nono dia de pós-operatório, ocorreu episódio de rejeição celular, tratado com sucesso com metilprednisolona (1.0 g/dia, IV durante três dias). O paciente recebeu alta hospitalar no 13 o&amp;nbsp;dia de pósoperatório. O caso evidencia a importância do diagnóstico precoce e a indicação do transplante de fígado em portadores de carcinoma hepatocelular, bem como, uma das possíveis complicações no pós-operatório. A concretização de mais um grupo especializado no tratamento das doenças crônicas do fígado e o desenvolvimento científico, tecnológico e de ensino da Região de Ribeirão Preto, no interior do Estado de São Paulo, possibilitaram a realização, com sucesso, do caso aqui relatado. &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/3105</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p194-199</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 194-199</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 194-199</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 194-199</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/3105/3794</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/3206</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:PV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">La incorporación de la medicina de familia en la enseñanza de la medicina en españa</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The inclusion of family medicine in medical education in spain</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="es-ES">La incorporación de la medicina de familia en la enseñanza de la medicina en españa</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Otero, Ángel</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/3206</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p200-201</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 200-201</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 200-201</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 200-201</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>spa</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/3206/3896</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/3752</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:PV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Considerações sobre a formação em medicina de família e atenção primária</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Comments about graduate and undergraduate studies on family medicine and primary health care</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Forster, Aldaisa C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/3752</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p202-203</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 202-203</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 202-203</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 202-203</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/3752/4442</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/3927</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:NTI</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">In Memorian: João Francisco Cêntola Nóbrega (21/04/1937 – 28/05/2001)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bicas, Harley E. A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/3927</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i2p224-225</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 2 (2001); 224-225</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 2 (2001); 224-225</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 2 (2001); 224-225</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/3927/4617</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/3997</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3AHem+e+Tromb.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Apresentação</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Franco, Rendrik F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/3997</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i3/4p225-227</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 3/4 (2001); 225-227</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 3/4 (2001); 225-227</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 3/4 (2001); 225-227</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/3997/4687</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/3998</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3AHem+e+Tromb.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisiologia da coagulação, anticoagulação e fibrinólise</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Overview of coagulation, anticoagulation and fibrinolysis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Franco, Rendrik F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Coagulation. Anticoagulation. Fibrinolysis.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Coagulação. Anticoagulação. Fibrinólise.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O presente artigo revisa aspectos de fisiologia dos sistemas de coagulação, anticoagulação e fibrinólise, que são relevantes para a compreensão de mecanimos etiopatogênicos operantes em doenças hemorrágicas e trombóticas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The present article revises different aspects of the coagulant, anticoagulant and fibrinolytic systems, which are relevant for a better understanding of aetiopathogenetic mechanisms operating in bleeding and thrombotic disorders.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/3998</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i3/4p229-237</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 3/4 (2001); 229-237</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 3/4 (2001); 229-237</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 3/4 (2001); 229-237</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/3998/4689</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/4034</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3AHem+e+Tromb.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Investigação diagnóstica dos distúrbios hemorrágicos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Diagnostic investigation of bleeding disorders</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rizzatti, Edgar Gil</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Franco, Rendrik F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Bleeding Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">diagnosis.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Distúrbios Hemorrágicos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">diagnóstico.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Na presente revisão, discutimos as ferramentas clínicas e laboratoriais, utilizadas na investigação de distúrbios hemorrágicos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">In this review we discuss the importance of several clinical and laboratory tools currently used in the investigation of bleeding disorders.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/4034</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i3/4p237-247</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 3/4 (2001); 237-247</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 3/4 (2001); 237-247</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 3/4 (2001); 237-247</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/4034/4795</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/4065</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3AHem+e+Tromb.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Trombofilias hereditárias</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Inherited thrombophilias</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Franco, Rendrik F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Thrombosis. Gene. Risk Factors.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Trombose. Gene. Fatores de Risco.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">In this review we discuss the contribution of genetic factors to the occurrence of venous thromboembolism.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Na presente revisão, discutimos a contribuição de fatores genéticos para a ocorrência de tromboembolismo venoso.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/4065</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i3/4p248-257</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 3/4 (2001); 248-257</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 3/4 (2001); 248-257</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 3/4 (2001); 248-257</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/4065/4886</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/4110</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3AHem+e+Tromb.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Trombofilias adquiridas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Acquired thrombophilias</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Garcia, Andrea A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Franco, Rendrik F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Thrombosis. Risk Factors.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Trombose. Fatores de Risco.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Na presente revisão, discutimos a contribuição de fatores de risco adquiridos para a ocorrência de tromboembolismo venoso.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">In this review we discuss the contribution of acquired risk factors to the occurrence of venous thromboembolism.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/4110</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i3/4p258-268</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 3/4 (2001); 258-268</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 3/4 (2001); 258-268</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 3/4 (2001); 258-268</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/4110/4975</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/4130</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:15:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3AHem+e+Tromb.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Tratamento do tromboembolismo venoso</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Treatment of venous thromboembolism</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rizzatti, Edgar Gil</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Franco, Rendrik F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Venous Thrombosis. Pulmonary Embolism</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">treatment. Heparin. Anticoagulants.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Trombose Venosa. Embolia Pulmonar</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">tratamento. Heparina. Anticoagulantes.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Deep vein thrombosis (DVT) is defined as an episode of thrombosis involving deep veins, usually of the lower limbs. DVT is frequently accompanied by pulmonary embolism (PE). Venous thromboembolism (VTE) is the generic term commonly used to refer to both clinical conditions indistinctly. In this paper, we present a brief review of current concepts in the treatment of VTE. Use of unfractionated and low molecular weight heparin is approached, and special attention is given to its transition to long term use of oral anticoagulants. In addition, specific therapeutic measures in special clinical conditions and in the supportive management of patients with VTE are also discussed.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A trombose venosa profunda (TVP) é definida como um episódio de trombose, envolvendo as veias profundas dos membros inferiores. A TVP é freqüentemente acompanhada por embolia pulmonar (EP). Tromboembolismo venoso (TEV) é o termo empregado para designar ambas as eventualidades indistintamente. No presente artigo, oferecemos uma breve revis ão dos conceitos atualmente preconizados para o tratamento do TEV. São abordados aspectos relativos à utilização da heparina não fracionada, aos novos esquemas terapêuticos com as heparinas de baixo peso molecular e à transição para o tratamento clássico com anticoagulantes orais a longo prazo. Adicionalmente, são discutidas condutas em situações clínicas especiais, além de medidas terapêuticas que se mostraram eficazes no tratamento de pacientes com TEV.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/4130</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v34i3/4p269-275</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 No. 3/4 (2001); 269-275</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 34 Núm. 3/4 (2001); 269-275</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 34 n. 3/4 (2001); 269-275</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/4130/5033</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2022-08-30T21:20:15Z" completeListSize="1467" cursor="525">ece4b8f8a0af27bc9cd207062e3dd575</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
