<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-08-29T21:20:44Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="rmrp">https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/162945</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-27T16:24:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil epidemiológico de cirurgias em serviço de urgência e emergência</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiological profile of surgery in emergency service</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lyra, Carlos Alberto Miranda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dantas, Lara Rebeca Correia Franca</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Todt, Stella Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Palmeira, Isabella Paiva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Figueiredo, Maria Bernadete Galrão de Almeida</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Sonia Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epidemiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cirurgia Geral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Serviço Hospitalar de Emergência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">General Surgery</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Emergency Service, Hospital</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo de estudo: Estudo observacional, analítico e transversal. Objetivo: Analisar o perfil epidemiológico dos pacientes do serviço de urgência e emergência de um hospital privado que foram submetidos a cirurgias. Metodologia: Estudo realizado em um hospital privado com análise de prontuários médicos de pacientes de ambos os sexos com idade igual ou superior a 16 anos que entraram no Serviço de Urgência e Emergência da instituição e foram encaminhados para cirurgia, no período de junho a agosto de 2017. Resultados: Analisou-se 104 prontuários, destes 53,84% corresponderam ao sexo masculino com média de idade de 46,03 anos. O tempo médio de internação foi 4,22 dias, com desvio padrão 7,01 dias e a mediana de 2 dias. Aqueles que apresentam comorbidades corresponderam a 70,19%. Houve um óbito de paciente de 83 anos após neurocirurgia com 62 dias de internação (0,96%). A maior gama das cirurgias correspondeu à apendicectomia com 25 procedimentos (43,85%), tempo médio de internação de 2,32 dias e a média de idade de 36,36 anos. Conclusão: Não houve diferença estatística entre os sexos (p=0.23) e a idade média foi de 46 anos com tempo médio de internação de 4 dias. As doenças abdominais e do aparelho locomotor se apresentaram como as principais causas de entrada no serviço de urgência, mantendo o padrão previamente estabelecido na literatura. Das cirurgias por doenças inflamatórias do aparelho digestivo, enfatiza-se a apendicectomia devido à apendicite aguda.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study model: Observational, analytical, and cross-sectional study. Objective: To analyze the epidemiological profile of patients from the emergency room of a private hospital who underwent surgery. Methodology: Study conducted in a private hospital with analysis of medical records of patients of both sexes aged 16 years or older who entered the institution's Emergency Department and were referred for surgery, from June to August 2017. Results: It was analyzed 104 medical records, of which 53.84% corresponded to males with a mean age of 46.03 years. The average length of stay was 4.22 days, with standard deviation 7.01 days and median of 2 days. Those with comorbidities corresponded to 70.19%. One patient died 83 years after neurosurgery with 62 days of hospitalization (0.96%). The largest range of surgeries corresponded to appendectomy with 25 procedures (43.85%), mean length of stay of 2.32 days, and mean age of 36.36 years. Conclusion: There was no statistical difference between genders (p = 0.23), and the mean age was 46 years with a mean length of stay of 4 days. Abdominal and locomotor disorders were the main causes of admission to the emergency room, maintaining the pattern previously established in the literature. Surgery for inflammatory diseases of the digestive tract emphasizes appendectomy due to acute appendicitis.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-10-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/162945</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i3p247-251</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 3 (2020); 247-251</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 3 (2020); 247-251</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 3 (2020); 247-251</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/162945/163775</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Carlos Alberto Miranda Lyra, Lara Rebeca Correia Franca Dantas, Stella Costa Todt, Isabella Paiva Palmeira, Maria Bernadete Galrão de Almeida Figueiredo, Sonia Oliveira Lima</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/163128</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-14T18:21:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Relação entre o estresse e a autoestima de gestantes durante o pré-natal</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Relationship between stress and self-esteem of pregnant women during prenatal care</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gomes, Franco Celso da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Aragão, Francisca Bruna Arruda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Serra, Liana Linhares Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chein, Maria Bethânia Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Joelmara Pereira Furtado dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Liane Maria Rodrigues dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reis, Andréa Dias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Fernanda Ferreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pregnant Women</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Psychosocial Impact</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Prenatal Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stress, Psychological</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Social Support</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Gestantes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Impacto Psicossocial</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cuidado Pré-Natal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estresse Psicológico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Apoio Social</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: analisar os componentes do perfil psicossocial de gestantes durante o pré-natal.&amp;nbsp;Métodos: estudo quantitativo, analítico, realizado com 160 gestantes, entre 14 e 47 anos de idade, atendidas num Hospital de referência do Maranhão, em 2017.&amp;nbsp;Resultados: a maioria das gestantes tinha entre 19 a 35 anos de idade (48,75%); realizaram de 0 a 5 consultas de pré-natal (40,65%) e eram nulíparas (43,13%). A análise de regressão linear evidenciou a influência do estresse devido a problemas financeiros e relacionados à família, os itens que mais explicaram o constructo autoestima foram sentir que não é um fracasso e sentir-se satisfeita consigo mesma; A correlação de Pearson do estresse e autoestima foi negativa e com influência significativamente forte. Conclusão: o estresse dentre os fatores psicossociais é o que mais influencia para alterações no pré-natal provavelmente na autoestima, pois quando relacionado com estresse evidenciou relação negativa.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Analyzing the components of the psychosocial profile of pregnant women during prenatal care.&amp;nbsp;Methods: a quantitative and analytical study performed with 160 pregnant women between the ages of 14 and 47 assisted at a reference hospital in Maranhão, in 2017. Results: the majority of pregnant women were between 19 and 35 years of age (48.75%); attended to 0-5 prenatal appointments (40.65%), and were nulliparous (43.13%). The linear regression analysis evidenced the influence of stress due to financial and family-related problems; the items that most explained the construct of self-esteem were feeling that they are not a failure and feeling satisfied with themselves; Pearson's correlation of stress and self-esteem was negative and had a significantly strong influence. Conclusion: the stress among the psychosocial factors is the one that most influences prenatal changes probably in self-esteem because when related to stress it showed a negative relation.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-04-27</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163128</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i1p27-34</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 1 (2020): jan./fev./mar.; 27-34</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 1 (2020): jan./fev./mar.; 27-34</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 1 (2020): jan./fev./mar.; 27-34</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163128/160359</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/163153</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-06T17:32:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeito do contraceptivo hormonal na depressão, ansiedade e qualidade de vida: estudo controlado</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effect of hormonal contraception on depression, anxiety and quality of life: a controlled study</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Flávia Cristina Barros de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Aragão, Francisca Bruna Arruda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brito, Luciane Maria Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reis, Andréa Dias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira Neto, Clariano Pires de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chein, Maria Bethânia da Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Anxiety</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Depression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Contraceptives</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ansiedade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Depressão</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Contraceptivos</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Identificar o efeito do uso de contraceptivos hormonais orais na depressão, ansiedade e qualidade de vida. Métodos: Neste estudo, utiliza-se o método transversal e a amostra foi 113 mulheres em idade reprodutiva. Para avaliação de depressão, ansiedade e qualidade de vida foram utilizados o Inventário de BECK, IDATE Traço-Estado e o SF-36, respectivamente. Para análise estatística utilizou-se o programa STATA 14.0. O nível de significância adotado foi de 5%. Resultados: Mulheres que utilizam contraceptivos tiveram idade 24,02±5,30 anos, menarca 12,23±1,40 anos e peso 58,90±10,20 kg. O não consumo de álcool e tabaco foi de 73 (64,60%) e 111(98,23%), respectivamente. Nas usuárias de contraceptivos hormonais orais combinados e não usuárias de contraceptivos hormonais orais combinados em relação ao tipo de ansiedade e nível de depressão, não houve diferença estatisticamente significante. Prevaleceram as mulheres assintomáticas em relação a depressão (não usuárias de contraceptivos hormonais orais combinados 61/82,43%) e presença de ansiedade/traço e ansiedade/estado, em ambos os grupos. A qualidade de vida não foi prejudicada pelo uso ou não dos contraceptivos hormonais orais combinados. Conclusão: O uso do Contraceptivo não está relacionado á presença de ansiedade, depressão e alteração de qualidade de vida.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Identify the effect of oral hormonal contraceptive use on depression, anxiety, and quality of life. Methods: A cross-sectional study method was used and the sample was 113 women on reproductive age. Depression, anxiety, and QoL were assessed by the BECK Inventory, the State-Trait IDATE, and the SF-36, respectively. For the statistical analysis, the STATA 14.0 program was used. The level of significance was 5%. Results: Women who use oral contraceptives have age 24,02 ± 5,30 years, menarche 12,23±1,40 years, and weight 58.9 kg. Nonconsumption of alcohol and tobacco prevailed, respectively, with 73 (64.60%) and 111 (98.23%). Concerning the use of combined oral hormonal contraceptives and without the use of COHC in relation to the type of anxiety and level of depression, there was no statistically significant difference between them. Asymptomatic women prevailed in relation to depression (without the use of combined oral hormonal contraceptives 61/82.43%) and presence of anxiety/trait and anxiety/status in both groups. QoL was not impaired by the use of combined oral hormonal contraceptives or not. Conclusion: Contraceptive use is not related to the presence of anxiety, depression, and quality of life alteration.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-08-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163153</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i2p127-133</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 2 (2020); 127-133</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 2 (2020); 127-133</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 2 (2020); 127-133</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163153/162584</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/163368</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-27T16:24:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Cannabidiol as adjuvant therapy in a patient with Zellweger syndrome: a case report</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Uso de canabidiol como terapia adjuvante em paciente com síndrome de Zellweger: relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Samilly</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Machado, Elias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fóla, Fabricio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carneiro, Zumira Aparecida</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lourenço, Charles Marques</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Síndrome de Zellweger</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Peroxinas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epilepsia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Canabidiol</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Zellweger Syndrome</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Peroxins</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epilepsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cannabidiol</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Também denominada síndrome cerebrohepatorenal, a síndrome de Zellweger é uma doença autossômica recessiva rara, pertencente ao espectro de erros inatos do metabolismo que afetam os peroxissomos. São causados ​​principalmente por mutações em qualquer um dos 14 genes PEX diferentes que codificam para proteínas envolvidas na montagem do peroxissoma, sendo a mais comum do PEX1. O quadro clínico geralmente é observado no período neonatal e primeira infância, incluindo alterações faciais, hipotonia profunda e ausência de reflexos neonatais, além de disfagia, disfunção hepática e convulsões. O diagnóstico é feito a partir da clínica e testes bioquímicos e confirmados pela visualização da mutação em um dos 14 genes PEX. Como não há tratamento específico, é feito tratamento sintomático. Nosso paciente masculino de 1 ano e 9 meses apresentou a hipotonia congênita como sintoma marcante, além de crises convulsivas recorrentes logo após o nascimento. Evoluiu com necessidade de gastrostomia e estagnação de marcos neuromotores. O diagnóstico foi confirmado aos seis meses, através da dosagem de ácidos graxos de cadeia longa. Crises convulsivas evoluíram de maneira refratária a diversos anticonvulsivantes e com elevada frequência diária, por isso iniciamos canabidiol (CBD-RSHO GOLD) por via enteral que reduziu significantemente as crises. Não há tratamento definitivo para esta enfermidade, sendo importante tratamento sintomático das crises convulsivas e terapias de reabilitação, nesse caso, o uso de (CBD- RSHO GOLD) provocou uma redução de 92% na frequência de crises diárias do paciente. No entanto, não é possível concluir, ainda, melhoras em outros sinais e sintomas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Also referred to as “brain-liver-kidney” syndrome, the Zellweger syndrome is a rare autosomal recessive disorder, belonging to the spectrum of inborn errors of metabolism that affect peroxisomes. They are caused mainly by mutations in any of the 14 different PEX genes that code for proteins involved in the assembly of peroxisome, being the most common of PEX1. The clinic is usually observed in the neonatal and early childhood period, including facial changes, deep hypotonia, and absence of neonatal reflexes in childhood, in addition to dysphagia, hepatic dysfunction, and seizures. The diagnosis is made from clinical and biochemical tests and confirmed by the visualization of the mutation in one of the 14 PEX genes. Since there is no specific treatment, symptomatic treatment is done. Our 1-year and 9-month-old male patient presented congenital hypotonia as a striking symptom in addition to recurrent seizures shortly after birth. It evolved with the need for gastrostomy and stagnation of neuromotor frames. The diagnosis was confirmed at six months by the measurement of long-chain fatty acids. Convulsive seizures evolved in a manner that was refractory to several anticonvulsants and with a high daily frequency, so we initiated cannabidiol (CBD-RSHO GOLD) by an enteral route that significantly reduced the seizures. Since there is no available treatment for seizures, in this case, the use of CBD-RSHO GOLD reduced by 92% the daily seizure frequency. However, it is not possible to conclude further improvements in other signs and symptoms.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-10-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163368</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i3p321-326</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 3 (2020); 321-326</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 3 (2020); 321-326</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 3 (2020); 321-326</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163368/163839</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Samilly Oliveira, Elias Machado, Fabricio Fóla, Zumira Aparecida Carneiro, Charles Marques Lourenço</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/163452</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-08T19:25:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil microbiológico da colonização do sítio de inserção do cateter venoso central considerando dois curativos transparentes</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Microbiological assessment of the colonization of a central venous catheter insertion site considering two transparent dressings</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pereira, Gabriela Levorato</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Margatho, Amanda Salles</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Denissani Aparecida Ferrari dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Bruna Nogueira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reis, Paula Elaine Diniz dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Basile-Filho, Anibal</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silveira, Renata Cristina de Campos Pereira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Central Venous Catheters</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Dressing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Occlusive Dressings</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Microbiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cateteres Venosos Centrais</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Bandagens</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Curativos Oclusivos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Microbiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do Estudo: estudo transversal da fase prospectiva de um ensaio clínico. Objetivo: identificar os microrganismos e a sensibilidade antimicrobiana no sítio de inserção do cateter venoso central coberto pelo curativo gel de clorexidina ou pelo filme transparente de poliuretano. Metodologia: estudo transversal, descritivo, realizado com adultos críticos no período de abril a dezembro de 2014 em um hospital universitário no interior do estado de São Paulo. Imediatamente após a retirada do curativo, foi coletada amostra de swab da pele do sítio de inserção do cateter, semeado em placas de Agar sangue e Agar MacConkey e incubadas em estufas bacteriológicas a 35 °C. Nas amostras que apresentaram crescimento bacteriano após 24 horas de incubação, foram realizados testes de sensibilidade aos antimicrobianos utilizando o equipamento automatizado Vitek II (Biomerieux®). Resultados: 45 pacientes fizeram uso do curativo gel de clorexidina e 47 utilizaram o filme transparente de poliuretano. No grupo com o curativo gel de clorexidina houve crescimento dos microrganismos Acinetobacter baumannii, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Morganella morganii, Enterobacter cloacae, Staphylococcus aureus e Staphylococcus epidermidis em 13 amostras de swabs. O Staphylococcus aureus apresentou resistência a oxacilina. No grupo do filme transparente de poliuretano seis amostras foram positivas com o crescimento de Serratia marcescens, Acinetobacter baumannii, Staphylococcus epidermidis, Staphylococcus haemolyticus e Klebsiella pneumoniae, esta resistente a amicacina (Klebsiella pneumoniae carbapenemase - KPC). Conclusão: os resultados demonstram maior crescimento bacteriano no sítio de inserção do cateter venoso central coberto pelo curativo gel de clorexidina quando comparado ao filme transparente de poliuretano.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study design: a prospective, cross-sectional study. Objectives: identify microbiological growth at the insertion site of the central venous catheter covered by a chlorhexidine impregnated dressing or a transparent polyurethane dressing, and identify antimicrobial sensitivity. Methods: immediately after dressing removal, a skin swab was collected from the catheter insertion site and seeded in blood agar plates and MacConkey agar, then incubated in bacteriological incubators at 35 °C. After 24 hours, the plates were analyzed to verify the presence of microbial growth. In the samples that displayed microbial growth, the identification and the sensitivity test were performed using the automated equipment Vitek II (Biomerieux®). Results: A total of 45 patients were treated with chlorhexidine impregnated dressing and 47 with transparent polyurethane dressing. In the chlorhexidine dressing group, 13 swabs samples presented with microbial growth of the following bacterial populations: Acinetobacter baumannii, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Morganella morganii, Enterobacter cloacae, Staphylococcus aureus, and Staphylococcus epidermidis. Staphylococcus aureus presented resistance to oxacillin. In the transparent polyurethane dressing group, six samples were positive for the growth of Serratia marcescens, Acinetobacter baumannii, Staphylococcus epidermidis, Staphylococcus haemolyticus, and amikacin resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae (Klebsiella pneumoniae carbapenemase - KPC). Conclusion: The results demonstrate higher bacterial growth in the chlorhexidine impregnated dressing compared to the transparent polyurethane dressing.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-08-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163452</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i2p135-145</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 2 (2020); 135-145</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 2 (2020); 135-145</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 2 (2020); 135-145</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163452/162585</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/163476</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:00:42Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Anais</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Anais do I Simpósio sobre Evidência no Manejo da dor (SEMDOR) da FMRP-USP</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Movimento e Dor, Laboratório de Pesquisa sobre</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Resumos de Simpósios</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Manejo da Dor</dc:subject>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2019-10-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163476</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 No. supl.4 (2019): Suplemento 4 - Anais do I Simpósio sobre Evidência no Manejo da dor (SEMDOR) da FMRP-USP; 1-30</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 52 Núm. supl.4 (2019): Suplemento 4 - Anais do I Simpósio sobre Evidência no Manejo da dor (SEMDOR) da FMRP-USP; 1-30</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 52 n. supl.4 (2019): Suplemento 4 - Anais do I Simpósio sobre Evidência no Manejo da dor (SEMDOR) da FMRP-USP; 1-30</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163476/157143</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/163953</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-06T17:34:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Distribuição ultraestrutural de colágeno tipo IV em feridas experimentais após tratamento com papaína</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Ultrastructural distribution of type IV collagen in experimental wounds after treatment with papaine</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Brito Junior, Lacy Cardoso de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Levy, Ian Eliezer</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Wound Healing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Papain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ulcer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology, Experimental</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Collagen Type IV</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cicatrização de Feridas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Papaína</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Úlcera</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epidemiologia Experimental</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Colágeno Tipo IV</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study model: Experimental. Objective: Investigate the distribution of type IV collagen fibers by transmission electron microscopy, in experimental wounds treated with papaine solutions. Methodology: Adult male Wistar rats (n = 18) underwent a surgical procedure to remove a square section of skin from the cervical region, and then separated into two groups: Group I (n = 9), without treatment; and Group II (n = 9), treated with papain solutions of 10% (up to the 7th day), 6% (from the 8th to the 14th day) and 4% (from the 15th to the 21st day). All animals were sacrificed at 7, 14 and 21 days, and the injured areas removed, washed in PBS, and fixed in 2.5% glutaraldehyde, 4% freshly prepared formaldehyde in buffered solution containing 60 mM Pipes, 20 mM Hepes, 10 mM ethyleneglycol-bis- (B-aminoethylether) -N, N, N'-tetraacetic acid, 70 mM KCl, and 5 mM MgCl 2 pH 7.2 for 1h; post-fixed in solution containing 1% osmium tethoxide, 0.8% ferrocyanide, and 5 mM calcium chloride; dehydrated in graduated acetone and soaked in Epon® to make thin sections stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate and examined under a Zeiss LEO EM 906 (TEM) transmission electron microscope. Results: The distribution of type IV collagen fibers from papaine-treated lesions (Group II) at 14 and 21 days was more organized than Group I fibers. Conclusions: Papaine has proven to be an important facilitator for the organization of type IV collagen fibers in experimental wounds.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: Experimental. Objetivo: Investigar a distribuição de fibras colágeno tipo IV, por microscopia eletrônica de transmissão, em feridas experimentais tratadas com soluções de papaína. Metodologia: Ratos Wistar (n=18), machos, adultos, foram submetidos a procedimento cirúrgico para a retirada de seção quadrada de pele da região cervical, e posteriormente separados em dois grupos: Grupo I (n = 9), sem tratamento; e Grupo II (n = 9), tratado com soluções de papaína a 10% (até o 7º dia), 6% (do 8º ao 14º dia) e 4% (do 15º ao 21º dia). Todos os animais foram sacrificados com 7, 14 e 21 dias, e as áreas lesadas retiradas, lavadas em PBS e fixadas em 2,5% de glutaraldeo, 4% de formaldeio recém preparado, em solução tamponada contendo 60 mM Pipes, 20 mM Hepes, 10 mM etilenoglicol-bis- (B-aminoetiléter) - Ácido N, N, N'-tetraacético, KCl 70 mM e MgCl2 5 mM pH 7,2 por 1h; pós-fixadas em solução contendo tetróxido de ósmio a 1%, ferrocianeto a 0,8% e cloreto de cálcio a 5 mM; desidratados em acetona graduada e embebidos em Epon® para confecção de secções finas, coradas com acetato de uranilo e citrato de chumbo, e examinadas em microscópio electrônico de transmissão Zeiss LEO EM 906 (TEM). Resultados: A distribuição das fibras colágeno tipo IV das lesões tratadas com papaína (Grupo II), com 14 e 21 dias, mostraram-se mais organizadas que as fibras do Grupo I. Conclusões: A papaína mostrou-se um importante facilitador para organização de fibras colágeno tipo IV em feridas experimentais.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-08-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163953</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i2p147-151</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 2 (2020); 147-151</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 2 (2020); 147-151</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 2 (2020); 147-151</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163953/162586</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/163969</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-27T16:24:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente vascular encefálico isquêmico devido à síndrome do anticorpo antifosfolípide em paciente lúpica: um relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Ischemic stroke due to antiphospholipid syndrome in a lupus patient: a case report</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Thiago Azevedo de Lucena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santana, Leonardo Fernandes e</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Mateus de Sousa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bezerra, Caroline Diniz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gomes, Orlando Vieira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Duarte, Rita Marina Soares de Castro</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lúpus Eritematoso Sistêmico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Síndrome Antifosfolipídica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Antiphospholipid Syndrome</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Lúpus eritematoso sistêmico é uma doença de origem autoimune que apresenta um amplo espectro de manifestações clínicas causadas pelo estado inflamatório crônico. A associação com a síndrome do anticorpo antifosfolípide ocorre em aproximadamente 36% dos pacientes lúpicos. Nesses pacientes, a doença de base e o uso crônico de corticosteroides contribuem para aterosclerose acelerada, uma complicação que agrega risco cardiovascular. Relatamos um caso de acidente vascular encefálico em paciente de 25 anos portadora de lúpus eritematoso sistêmico e síndrome do anticorpo antifosfolípide.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Systemic lupus erythematosus is an autoimmune disease that presents a wide spectrum of clinical manifestations caused by the chronic inflammatory state. Association with antiphospholipid antibody syndrome occurs in approximately 36% of lupus patients. In these patients, the underlying disease and the chronic use of corticosteroids contribute to accelerated atherosclerosis, a complication that adds increased cardiovascular risk. We report a case of stroke in a 25-year-old patient with systemic lupus erythematosus and antiphospholipid antibody syndrome.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-10-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163969</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i3p327-331</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 3 (2020); 327-331</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 3 (2020); 327-331</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 3 (2020); 327-331</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/163969/163838</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Thiago Azevedo de Lucena Costa, Leonardo Fernandes e Santana, Mateus de Sousa Rodrigues, Caroline Diniz Bezerra, Orlando Vieira Gomes, Rita Marina Soares de Castro Duarte</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/164281</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-06T17:36:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Speech therapy and oral health issues in the perception of the older adults that access the Unified Health System</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Questões fonoaudiológicas e odontológicas na percepção de idosos que acessam serviços do Sistema Único de Saúde</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Farias, Ewelyn de Freitas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bulgarelli, Patricia Tavora</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rech, Rafaela Soares</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marques, Luana Xavier</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Camila Mello dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bulgarelli, Alexandre Favero</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Primary Health Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health of the Elderly</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Speech, Language and Hearing Sciences</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Unified Health System</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Geriatric Dentistry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atenção Primária à Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde do Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fonoaudiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sistema Único de Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Odontogeriatria</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study design: Cross-sectional study with data collected from questionnaires applied to older adults at domiciliary visits regarding access to health services. Objective: Analyzing the perception of independent elderly about speech-language and dental issues in the Primary Health Care Services of the Unified Health System/SUS. Methods: Absolute frequencies of the study variables related to speech-language and dental questions were analyzed using the Chi-square test and Fisher's Exact Test, both with a 0.05% significance level. Results: The elderly interviewed were predominantly women (76.5%), white (73.5%), with at least high school education (64.7%). Of these, 92.6% said they had no difficulty in eating, although 51.5% never had a speech therapist evaluation. There was also a higher proportion indicating that the elderly did not need an appointment with the speech therapist (73.5%). Regarding the use of primary care services, 68.7% used the public system, and of these, 94.1% self-perceived their oral health condition as fair/poor. Conclusion: It is suggested to strengthen the care of the elderly in an interdisciplinary and integral way to cover the needs and specificities of this population. The low perception of the importance of care suggests the need for strengthening speech therapy services for the health of the elderly Brazilian population. &amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo de estudo: Estudo observacional e transversal com dados coletados a partir de questionários aplicados aos idosos em visitas domiciliares, sobre acesso a serviços de saúde. Objetivo: Analisar a percepção de idosos independentes sobre questões fonoaudiológicas e odontológicas nos serviços de Atenção Primária à Saúde do Sistema Único de Saúde. Métodos: Foram analisadas frequências absolutas das variáveis de estudo relacionadas a questões fonoaudiológicas e odontológicas através do teste do Qui-quadrado e Teste Exato-de-Fisher, ambos com nível de 0,05% de significância. Resultados: Os idosos entrevistados foram predominantemente mulheres (76,5%), cor branca (73,5%), com no mínimo ensino médio de escolaridade (64,7%). Destes idosos, 92,6% afirmaram não possuir dificuldades para se alimentar, apesar de 51,5% nunca ter feito uma avaliação fonoaudiológica. Houve maior proporção indicando que os idosos não necessitaram de consulta com fonoaudióloga (73,5%). Quanto à utilização de serviços da atenção primária, 68,7% utilizavam o sistema público e desses, 94,1% autoperceberam sua condição de saúde bucal como regular/ruim. Conclusão: Sugere-se o fortalecimento do cuidado dos idosos de forma interdisciplinar e integral, a fim de abranger as necessidades e especificidades dessa população. A baixa percepção da importância do cuidado sugere a necessidade do fortalecimento dos serviços de fonoaudiologia para a saúde da população idosa brasileira.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-08-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/164281</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i2p153-161</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 2 (2020); 153-161</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 2 (2020); 153-161</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 2 (2020); 153-161</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/164281/162587</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/164365</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-06T17:36:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividade física na prevenção de doenças crônicas não transmissíveis em homens</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Physical activity in the prevention of chronic noncommunicable diseases in men</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Aragão, Francisca Bruna Arruda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Elaynne Silva de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Sérgio Augusto Rosa de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Wellington Roberto Gomes de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bezerra, Sonny Állan Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Denilson de Menezes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reis, Andréa Dias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Salvador, Emanuel Péricles</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Men's Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Primary Health Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Noncommunicable Diseases</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde Masculina</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atenção Primária à Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doenças não Transmissíveis</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: A promoção da atividade física (AF) é uma das prioridades das políticas públicas de atenção básica à saúde, especialmente para o público masculino. Objetivo: Avaliar a associação da prática de atividade física com o estilo de vida e presença doenças crônicas não transmissíveis (DCNTs) em usuários do sexo masculino de Unidade Básica de Saúde (UBS). Métodos: Participaram do estudo 119 homens na faixa etária de 20 a 59 anos. A associação entre a prática de atividade física com variáveis sociodemográficas, etilismo, tabagismo, uso de medicamento, presença de doenças crônicas não transmissíveis e conhecimento da política de saúde do homem foi realizada por Regressão Logística com um α=5%. Resultados: A prevalência de atividade física foi de 58,8%, entretanto 36,7% dos participantes faziam uso de medicações diariamente e 70,6% não conhecem a Política Nacional de Atenção Integral à Saúde do Homem. Além disso, fazer atividade física demonstrou como um fator de proteção contra as doenças crônicas não transmissíveis (OR = 2,97; IC 95% 1,03 – 8,55; p = 0,043). Conclusão: A prática de atividade física em homens, independentemente da idade, tabagismo e etilismo foi associada à prevenção de doenças crônicas não transmissíveis.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Introduction: The promotion of physical activity (PA) is one of the priorities of public policies for primary health care, especially for the male audience. Objective: To evaluate the association between physical activity and lifestyle and presence of chronic noncommunicable diseases (NCDs) in male users of the Basic Health Unit (BHU). Methods: 119 men, aged between 20 and 59 years, participated in the study. The association between the practice of physical activity with sociodemographic variables, alcoholism, smoking, use of medication, presence of chronic noncommunicable diseases and knowledge of men's health policy was carried out by Logistic Regression with an α= 5%. Results: The prevalence of physical activity was 58.8%, however 36.7% of the participants used medications daily and 70.6% did not know the National Policy for Comprehensive Attention to Men's Health. In addition, physical activity proved to be a protective factor against chronic non-communicable diseases (OR= 2,97; IC 95% 1,03 – 8,55; p = 0,043). Conclusion: The practice of physical activity in men, regardless of age, smoking and alcohol consumption was associated with the prevention of chronic noncommunicable diseases.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-08-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/164365</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i2p163-169</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 2 (2020); 163-169</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 2 (2020); 163-169</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 2 (2020); 163-169</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/164365/162588</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/164728</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-12-11T14:16:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Association between sarcopenia and history of fractures in elderly patients with type 2 diabetes</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Associação entre sarcopenia e história de fraturas em pacientes idosos com diabetes tipo 2</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Torres, Maria Roseneide dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Lucian Batista de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Peixoto, Marcelo Italiano</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sarcopenia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diabetes Mellitus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fraturas Ósseas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sarcopenia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Diabetes Mellitus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fractures, Bone</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Avaliar a prevalência de sarcopenia em pacientes idosos portadores de diabetes mellitus (DM), verificando sua associação com histórico de fraturas e quedas. Modelo do estudo: Observacional, transversal e analítico. Metodologia: Estudo realizado em hospital universitário de Campina Grande, Paraíba. Envolveu pacientes idosos (≥60 anos) com DM. Foram excluídos aqueles com diagnóstico de osteoporose. O critério preditor de sarcopenia foi a circunferência da panturrilha (CP): &amp;lt;33 cm para mulheres e &amp;lt;34 cm para homens. Resultados: A amostra válida foi de 44 pacientes, todos com diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2). A prevalência de sarcopenia foi de 20,4%. Houve relação estatisticamente significativa entre sarcopenia e história de fraturas em traumas de baixa energia (p = 0,022). Não houve diferença entre os grupos com e sem sarcopenia em relação à história de quedas no último ano (p = 0,589). Houve associação entre uso de psicotrópicos e ocorrência de quedas (p = 0,001). A maioria dos achados convergiram para aqueles já presentes na literatura. Conclusão: Apesar da CP não ser, de forma isolada, um método estabelecido para o diagnóstico de sarcopenia, a perda muscular apontada por tal medida mostrou-se associada a histórico de fraturas em idosos com DM2, de forma que essa acessível mensuração pode alertar para iniciar intervenções que possam melhorar a qualidade de vida dos idosos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Evaluating the prevalence of sarcopenia in elderly patients with diabetes mellitus (DM), verifying their association with a history of fractures and falls. Study model: Observational, cross-sectional, and analytical. Method: The study was conducted at a university hospital in Campina Grande, Paraíba. It included elderly patients (≥60 years) with DM. Those with a diagnosis of osteoporosis were excluded. The predictor criterion for sarcopenia was calf circumference (CC): &amp;lt;33 cm for women and &amp;lt;34 cm for men. Results: The valid sample was 44 patients, all with type 2 diabetes mellitus (DM2). The prevalence of sarcopenia was 20.4%. There was a statistically significant relationship between sarcopenia and history of fractures in low energy traumas (p=0.022). There was no difference between the groups with and without sarcopenia in relation to the history of falls in the last year (p=0.589). There was an association between the use of psychotropic drugs and the occurrence of falls (p=0.001). Most of the findings converged with those already present in the literature.&#160; Conclusion: Although CC is not an established method for the diagnosis of sarcopenia, muscle loss indicated by this measure has been associated with a history of fractures in the elderly with DM2, so that this accessible measurement can alert to initiate interventions that can improve the quality of life of the elderly.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-12-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/164728</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i4p389-397</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 4 (2020); 389-397</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 4 (2020); 389-397</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 4 (2020); 389-397</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/164728/166388</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Maria Roseneide dos Santos Torres, Lucian Batista de Oliveira, Marcelo Italiano Peixoto</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/164812</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-05T20:17:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Anais</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/164997</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-12-11T14:16:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Dados alarmantes sobre a notificação de sífilis congênita em uma capital do Norte brasileiro: um estudo transversal</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Alarming data on the notification of congenital syphilis in a capital of the North of Brazil: a cross-sectional study</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Guimarães, Manoel Pereira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Mateus de Sousa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santana, Leonardo Fernandes e</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gomes, Orlando Vieira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Karla Layse dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Matos, Jauane Vilela Santos Gonçalves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leal, Elaine Azevedo Soares</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Syphilis, Congenital</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Prenatal Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sexually Transmitted Diseases</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sífilis Congênita</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epidemiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cuidado Pré-Natal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doenças Sexualmente Transmissíveis</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study model: A Prevalence study. Objective: Describing the clinical and epidemiological profile of patients with Congenital Syphilis between January 2010 and June 2016 in a capital city in the North of Brazil. Methodology: A survey was carried based on the reports of infection for congenital syphilis of the Epidemiological Surveillance in Rio Branco-Acre from January 2010 to June 2016. The data were analyzed through the SPSS Program. Results: 189 cases of early congenital syphilis were reported. Only 36.51% (n = 69) were diagnosed with gestational syphilis before delivery. The cases evolved with 74.6% of live births, 15.3% of stillborn infants, 6.3% of abortions, and 2.1% of congenital syphilis deaths. The relationship between the maternal VDRL and the outcome of the cases suggests that children from mothers with titles ≥1:16 represent 82.2% of the associated deleterious evolutions (p = 0.045). Conclusion: Congenital syphilis is a pathology still underdiagnosed during pregnancy and, in this study, was more frequent in children of mothers at the height of menacme, low schooling, and urban dwellers. Despite preventive measures already in place, congenital syphilis continues to be a public health problem in this capital of the Brazilian North and should continue to be the target of studies that generate new prevention strategies.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: Estudo de prevalência. Objetivo do estudo: Descrever o perfil clínico e epidemiológico dos portadores de Sífilis Congênita entre Janeiro de 2010 a Junho de 2016 em uma capital do Norte brasileiro. Metodologia: Foi realizado um levantamento das fichas de notificação para infecção por sífilis congênita da Vigilância Epidemiológica em Rio Branco-Acre no período de Janeiro 2010 a Junho de 2016. Os dados foram analisados por meio do Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS). Resultados: Foram notificados 189 casos de sífilis congênita precoce. Apenas 36,51% (n=69) receberam diagnóstico de sífilis gestacional antes do parto. Os casos evoluíram com 74,6% de nascidos vivos, 15,3% de natimortos, 6,3% de abortos e 2,1% de óbitos por sífilis congênita. A relação entre o Venereal Disease Research Laboratory (VDRL) materno e o desfecho dos casos sugere que filhos provenientes de mães com títulos ≥1:16 representam 82,2% das evoluções deletérias associadas (p=0,045). Conclusão: A sífilis na gestação é uma patologia ainda subdiagnosticada durante a gravidez e, nesse estudo, foi mais frequente em filhos de mães no auge da menacme, de baixa escolaridade e moradoras da zona urbana. Apesar das medidas preventivas já implantadas, a sífilis congênita continua sendo um problema de saúde pública nesta capital do Norte brasileiro e deve continuar como alvo de estudos que gerem novas estratégias de prevenção.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-12-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/164997</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i4p398-404</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 4 (2020); 398-404</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 4 (2020); 398-404</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 4 (2020); 398-404</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/164997/166389</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Manoel Pereira Guimarães, Mateus de Sousa Rodrigues, Leonardo Fernandes e Santana, Orlando Vieira Gomes, Karla Layse dos Santos Silva, Jauane Vilela Santos Gonçalves Matos, Elaine Azevedo Soares Leal</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/165060</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-12-11T14:16:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Cocaine cardiotoxicity and ventricular disfunction in a young patient</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Cardiotoxicidade por cocaína e disfunção ventricular em paciente jovem</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Kallen de Carvalho e</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Viaro, Ana Lídia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Okusu, Ana Raquel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bastos, Stéphany Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Roballo, Carla Adriane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ronconi, Thiago Luís</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Disfunção Ventricular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Insuficiência Cardíaca</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cardiotoxicidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cocaína</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ventricular Dysfunction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Heart Failure</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cardiotoxicity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cocaine</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The use of psychoactive substances can induce cardiovascular complications. The purpose of this report is to describe the case of a young patient with dilated cardiomyopathy secondary to cocaine use. Patient with dyspnea for six months, with progressive worsening, paroxysmal nocturnal dyspnea, orthopnea, and lower limb edema. Physical examination showed tachycardia (110 bpm), with other vital signs without alterations, presence of crackling rales in the bases and middle fields, moderate volume ascites, and significant lower limb edema. Electrocardiogram showed sinus rhythm with left chamber overload; chest X-ray only marked cardiomegaly. The echocardiogram showed reduced left ventricular (LV) ejection fraction (7%), enlarged left atrium, and right ventricle (RV), with eccentric hypertrophy and severe left ventricular systolic dysfunction, with moderate RV dysfunction and pulmonary hypertension (39 mmHg). Resonance presented mild right atrial dilatation, RV with significant dilatation, significant biventricular systolic dysfunction, with diffuse hypokinesia, and myocardial fibrosis of non-coronary pattern. The reported case shows a diagnosis whose pathophysiological mechanism of dilated cardiomyopathy is not clear. The most coherent association of dilated cardiomyopathy presented by the patient is related to cocaine abuse, due to the long-term recurrent stimulus that excess catecholamines caused in the myocardium. Given the spectrum of cardiomyopathy, infarction, and arrhythmias that may potentially occur associated with cocaine use, the hypothesis of cardiotoxicity should be considered in the evaluation of a patient with a history of cocaine abuse.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O uso de substâncias psicoativas pode induzir complicações cardiovasculares. O objetivo deste relato é descrever o caso de um paciente jovem com cardiomiopatia dilatada secundária ao uso de cocaína. Paciente com dispneia há seis meses, com piora progressiva, dispneia paroxística noturna, ortopneia e edema de membros inferiores. Ao exame físico apresentava taquicardia (110 bpm), com demais sinais vitais sem alterações, presença de estertores crepitantes em bases e campos médios, ascite de moderado volume e edema importante de membros inferiores. No eletrocardiograma, apresentava ritmo sinusal com sobrecarga de câmaras esquerdas; na radiografia de tórax, apenas cardiomegalia acentuada. O ecocardiograma evidenciou fração de ejeção (FE) do ventrículo esquerdo (VE) reduzida (7%), aumento de átrio esquerdo e ventrículo direito (VD), com hipertrofia excêntrica e disfunção sistólica acentuada do VE, com disfunção moderada do VD e hipertensão pulmonar (39 mmHg). Na ressonância, apresentou dilatação discreta do átrio direito, VD com dilatação importante, disfunção sistólica biventricular importante, com hipocinesia difusa (FE 8% de VD), além de fibrose miocárdica de padrão não coronariano inferosseptal. O caso relatado evidencia um diagnóstico cujo mecanismo fisiopatológico da cardiomiopatia dilatada não está claro. A associação mais coerente da cardiomiopatia dilatada apresentada pelo paciente está relacionada ao uso abusivo de cocaína, devido ao estímulo recorrente e de longa duração que o excesso de catecolaminas provocou no miocárdio. Tendo em vista o espectro de cardiomiopatia, infarto e arritmias que potencialmente podem ocorrer associados ao uso de cocaína, deve-se considerar a hipótese de cardiotoxicidade na avaliação de paciente com história de abuso de cocaína. &#160; &#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-12-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/165060</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i4p464-467</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 4 (2020); 464-467</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 4 (2020); 464-467</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 4 (2020); 464-467</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/165060/166397</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Kallen de Carvalho e Souza, Ana Lídia Viaro, Ana Raquel Okusu, Stéphany Oliveira Bastos, Carla Adriane Roballo, Thiago Luís Ronconi</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/165165</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-27T16:24:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiological analysis of tuberculosis in São Luís – MA</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Análise epidemiológica da tuberculose em São Luís - MA</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Aragão, Francisca Bruna Arruda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Arcêncio, Ricardo Alexandre</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carneiro, Tânia Gomes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cândido, Fernanda Carla de Assis</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cunha, José Henrique da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reis, Andréa Dias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fiorati, Regina Célia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tuberculose</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epidemiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Determinantes Sociais</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação em Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevalência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Tuberculosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Social Determinants</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Prevalence</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Analyzing the occurrence of Tuberculosis registered in São Luís. Method: This is a descriptive epidemiological study, with data obtained from the Notifiable Diseases Information System (SINAN/Tuberculosis) from 2014 to 2016. Descriptive statistics with the calculation of absolute and relative frequency was applied for categorical variables and position and dispersion measures for metric variables. Results: 2,306 cases were found in 378 residential neighborhoods. In 2014, the most affected District was the Vila Cidade Olímpica with 50 cases; in 2015, it had 39 cases, and in 2016 it had 25 cases. Conclusion: The study broadens the knowledge since it presents the epidemiological profile of Tuberculosis cases in São Luís. It was observed that the majority of cases were male, with economically active age, brown ethnic group, and complete secondary education.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Analisar as ocorrências de Tuberculose registradas em São Luís. Método: Trata-se de um estudo epidemiológico descritivo, com dados obtidos do Sistema de Informação de Agravos de Notificação (SINAN/Tuberculose) de 2014 a 2016. Aplicou-se estatística descritiva com cálculo de frequência absoluta e relativa para variáveis categóricas e medidas de posição e de dispersão para variáveis métricas. Resultados: Foram encontrados 2.306 casos em 378 bairros residenciais. Em 2014, o Distrito mais afetado foi a Vila Cidade Olímpica com 50 casos; em 2015, houve 39 casos e em 2016 ficou com 25 casos. Conclusão: O estudo avança no conhecimento na medida em que apresenta o perfil epidemiológico dos casos de tuberculose em São Luís. Observou-se que a maioria era do sexo masculino, em idade economicamente ativa, da raça/cor parda e com ensino médio completo.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-10-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/165165</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i3p252-259</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 3 (2020); 252-259</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 3 (2020); 252-259</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 3 (2020); 252-259</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/165165/163776</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Francisca Bruna Arruda Aragão, Ricardo Alexandre Arcêncio, Tânia Gomes Carneiro, Fernanda Carla de Assis Cândido, José Henrique da Silva Cunha, Andréa Dias Reis, Regina Célia Fiorati</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/165408</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-27T16:24:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil das internações por encefalite viral no Brasil em 2018 por unidade da federação, sexo e faixa etária</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Profile of hospitalizations for viral encephalitis in Brazil in 2018 per state, sex, and age group</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silveira, Elena Caires</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Encefalite Viral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hospitalização</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde Pública</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Encephalitis, Viral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hospitalization</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Public Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Introduction: Viral encephalitis is a condition with high morbidity and mortality rates, and a better understanding of its epidemiology may contribute to the construction of prevention and control strategies. For this reason, this study aimed to draw an epidemiological profile for viral encephalitis in Brazil in 2018 from data on hospitalizations in the Unified Health System (SUS). Methods: Ecological study of spatial analysis. The data studied were hospitalizations for viral encephalitis in SUS in 2018, stratified by federation unit (FU), gender, and age group. The geographical distribution was approached in an exploratory way, whereas gender and age variables were analytically addressed. Results: There were 2075 hospitalizations, with a rate of 0.99/105 inhabitants. The rates for each FU were represented in a colorimetric map, whereas the rates for each sex and age group were exemplified in a univariate comparative table. Discussion: There was a wide numerical variation in hospitalization rates among the FUs, with Pernambuco being the state with the highest incidence (4.13/105 inhabitants) and Paraíba with the lowest (0.29/105 inhabitants). A significant association was found with the risk of hospitalization for viral encephalitis for males and the ages from 1 to 4 years (RR: 3.28) and under one year (RR: 6.02). Conclusion: FU, gender, and age group were important determinants of the hospitalization rate due to viral encephalitis. However, current studies are needed in Brazil and worldwide to better characterize the epidemiology of viral encephalitis.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: A encefalite viral é uma condição com altas taxas de morbimortalidade, e um melhor entendimento de sua epidemiologia pode colaborar para a construção de estratégias de prevenção e controle. Diante disso, este estudo se propôs a traçar um perfil epidemiológico para a encefalite viral no Brasil no ano de 2018 a partir de dados de internações hospitalares no Sistema Único de Saúde (SUS). Métodos: Estudo ecológico de análise espacial. Os dados estudados foram relativos às internações hospitalares por encefalite viral no SUS em 2018, estratificadas por unidade da federação (UF), sexo e faixa etária. A distribuição geográfica foi abordada exploratoriamente, já as variáveis sexo e faixa etária foram abordadas analiticamente. Resultados: Foram registradas 2075 internações, com taxa de 0,99/105 habitantes. As taxas para cada UF foram representadas a partir de um mapa colorimétrico, enquanto as taxas para cada sexo e faixa etária foram representadas em uma tabela comparativa univariada. Discussão: Observou-se ampla variação numérica das taxas de internação dentre as UF, sendo Pernambuco o estado com maior incidência (4,13/105 habitantes) e Paraíba o estado com menor (0,29/105 habitantes). Foi constatada associação significativa com risco de internação hospitalar por encefalite viral para o sexo masculino e para as faixas etárias de 1 a 4 anos (RR: 3,28) e menores de 1 ano (RR: 6,02). Conclusão: UF, gênero e faixa etária foram determinantes importantes da taxa de internação hospitalar por encefalite viral. Todavia, carecem de estudos atuais no Brasil e no mundo para a melhor caracterização da epidemiologia da encefalite viral.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-10-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/165408</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i3p268-274</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 3 (2020); 268-274</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 3 (2020); 268-274</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 3 (2020); 268-274</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/165408/163811</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Elena Caires Silveira</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/165864</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-27T16:24:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Factors associated with immediate transfusion reactions in a university blood center: an analytical, retrospective study</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores associados a reações transfusionais imediatas em um hemocentro universitário: estudo analítico retrospectivo</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Vilar, Vanessa Marques</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Natany da Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nakasato, Gislaine Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lupinacci, Fernando Luiz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Juliana de Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Camila Takao</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores de Risco</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reação Transfusional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transfusão de Sangue</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Risk Factors</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Transfusion Reaction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Blood Transfusion</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">An analytical, cross-sectional, retrospective study. Objectives: Investigating the relationship among immediate transfusion reactions, demographic and clinical characteristics of patients, and transfusion-related characteristics in a university blood center. Methodology: The study was performed with data regarding blood transfusions of the blood center at Universidade Federal de São Paulo in 2016. Patient’s demographic and clinical characteristics and the characteristics of the immediate transfusion reactions were collected. Possible associations were evaluated using Fishers, Mann-Whitney, Chi-square, and Student’s t-test. Statistically significant associations with p≤0.05 were considered. Results: Data from 320 patient records were analyzed, totaling 938 blood transfusions. Of the blood products transfused, 90.3% were red blood cells concentrate administered by nursing assistants in 43.8% of the situations. Immediate transfusion reactions occurred in 4.3% of the situations (n=40). The most common transfusion reaction was fever (47.5%), followed by pruritus (22.5%). The transfusion reactions were more frequent in older patients (p=0.0037) who received two blood transfusions compared to one (p&amp;lt;0.0001), consequently more transfusion bags (p=0.0002), greater total transfused volume (p &amp;lt;0.0001), and longer length of administration (p=0.0017). Patients with aplastic anemia, acute myeloid leukemia, and solid organ neoplasms had immediate transfusion reactions more frequently than patients with other diagnoses (p &amp;lt;0.05). Conclusion: The occurrence of immediate transfusion reactions was related to age, medical diagnosis, number of blood transfusions, number of transfused bags, total transfused volume, and transfusion time. Knowledge of these factors may support specific training for immediate transfusion reactions surveillance.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudo analítico, transversal, retrospectivo. Objetivos: Verificar a relação entre reações transfusionais imediatas, características demográficas e clínicas dos pacientes e características das hemotransfusões em um hemocentro universitário. Metodologia: O estudo foi realizado com dados de transfusões realizadas em 2016 no hemocentro da Universidade Federal de São Paulo. Foram coletados dados demográficos dos pacientes, características das hemotransfusões e ocorrência de reações transfusionais imediatas. Possíveis associações foram avaliadas usando os Testes de Fisher, Mann-Whitney, Qui-quadrado e t de Student. Associações com valores de p&amp;lt;0,05 foram consideradas significativas. Resultados: Foram analisados dados de 320 fichas de pacientes, totalizando 938 transfusões. Dos produtos sanguíneos transfundidos, 90,3% eram concentrados de hemácias, administrados por auxiliares de enfermagem em 43,8% das situações. As reações transfusionais ocorreram em 4,3% das situações (n=40). O sinal de reações mais frequente foi a febre (47,5%), seguido de prurido (22,5%). As reações foram mais prevalentes em pacientes com maior idade média (p= 0,0037), que receberam duas transfusões sanguíneas em comparação a uma (p&amp;lt;0,0001), consequentemente mais bolsas de transfusões (p=0,0002), maior volume total transfundido (p&amp;lt;0,0001) e maior tempo de administração (p=0,0017). Pacientes com anemia aplásica, leucemia mieloide aguda e neoplasias de órgãos sólidos tiveram reações transfusionais imediatas mais frequentemente do que pacientes com outros diagnósticos (p≤0,05). Conclusões: A ocorrência de reações transfusionais imediatas teve relação com a idade, diagnóstico médico, número de hemotransfusões, número de bolsas transfundidas, volume total transfundido e tempo de transfusão. O conhecimento desses fatores pode subsidiar treinamentos específicos voltados para a vigilância quanto às reações transfusionais imediatas.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-10-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/165864</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i3p275--282</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 3 (2020); 275-282</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 3 (2020); 275-282</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 3 (2020); 275-282</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/165864/163812</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Vanessa Marques Vilar, Natany da Costa Ferreira, Gislaine Rodrigues Nakasato, Fernando Luiz Lupinacci, Juliana de Lima Lopes, Camila Takao Lopes</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/165929</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-27T16:24:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevalência e fatores associados à depressão em idosos: um estudo transversal</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Prevalence and factors associated with depression in the elderly: a cross-sectional study</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Leite, Tainara da Silva Mattos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fett, Carlos Alexandre</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stoppiglia, Luiz Fabrizio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Neves, Thiago</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Figueiredo, Karla Régia Ferreira Viana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Rosilene Andrade Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fett, Waléria Christiane Rezende</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Morbidades</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Envelhecimento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Morbidity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aging</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of life</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: Depressão é uma doença psiquiátrica e provoca prejuízos no aspecto biopsicossocial dos indivíduos acometidos. Sua prevalência na população idosa é expressiva, a identificação dos fatores relacionados a este desfecho permitem que medidas preventivas e de tratamento sejam aplicadas precocemente. Objetivo: Avaliar a associação entre depressão, os fatores sociodemográficos e os riscos para a saúde em idosos. Métodos: Estudo transversal com 388 idosos de ambos os sexos com idade igual ou superior a 65 anos, residentes do município de Cuiabá, estado de Mato Grosso (MT), Brasil. Foram usados questionários sociodemográficos, instrumentos de autorrelato de doenças crônicas, de estilo de vida, ocorrência de quedas e de capacidade funcional, escala de depressão geriátrica, avaliação do estado mental e testes de antropometria. Na análise estatística utilizou-se teste do qui-quadrado, odds ratio (OR) e regressão logística múltipla com intervalo de confiança de 95% e p&amp;lt;5%. Resultados: Encontrou-se predominância de mulheres (64%), sendo mulata/cabocla/parda (43%) e casadas (45%). A depressão foi significativamente associada com: o tercil mais baixo de educação &amp;lt;8 anos (OR=2,15; p=0,012); com dependência parcial ou total de atividades instrumentais da vida diária (OR=1,85; p=0,003); ter cinco ou mais doenças crônicas (OR=2,93; p=0,002), ocorrência de quedas nos últimos doze meses (OR=1,90; p=0,021); dificuldades de sono (OR=2,39; p&amp;lt;0,001) e visual (OR=2,28; p&amp;lt;0,001). Conclusão: A depressão estava associada a fatores modificáveis e que podem ser prevenidos. Desta forma, o diagnóstico precoce destes fatores de risco, a inclusão de atividades socias, físicas e cognitivas devem ser consideradas para sua prevenção.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Introduction: Depression is a psychiatric disease that causes losses in the biopsychosocial aspect of the affected individuals. The prevalence in the elderly population is significant, and identify the factors related to this outcome allows preventive measures and treatment can be early applied. Objective: Assessing the association between depression and sociodemographic and health risk factors in the elderly. Methods: This is a cross-sectional study involving 388 elderly of both genders, aged 65 years and older, urban residents of the city of Cuiabá, state of Mato Grosso (MT), Brazil. A sociodemographic questionnaire, as well as a self-report of chronic diseases and lifestyle, a self-report questionnaire of functional capacity, occurrence of falls, Geriatric Depression Scale, mental state assessment, and anthropometry tests were used. The chi-square test, odds ratio (OR), and multiple logistic regression with 95% confidence interval and p&amp;lt;5% were used in the statistical analysis. Results: There was a predominance of women (64%) who were mulatto/caboclo/brown skin (43%) and married (45%). Depression was significantly associated with: the lowest level of education, &amp;lt;8 years (OR=2.15; p=0.012), partial or total dependence of instrumental activities of daily living (OR=1.85; p=0.003), having five or more diseases (OR=2.93, p=0.002), falls in the last twelve months (OR=1.90; p=0.021), and sleep (OR=2.39; p&amp;lt;0.001) and visual difficulties (OR=2.28; p&amp;lt;0.001). Conclusion:&amp;nbsp; Depression in this group of elderly was associated with modifiable and preventable factors in the health of these people. Thus, the early diagnosis of risk factors associated with depression, the inclusion of social, physical and cognitive activities must be considered for their prevention.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-10-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/165929</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i3p205-214</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 3 (2020); 205-214</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 3 (2020); 205-214</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 3 (2020); 205-214</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/165929/163769</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Tainara da Silva Mattos Leite, Carlos Alexandre Fett, Luiz Fabrizio Stoppiglia, Thiago Neves, Karla Régia Ferreira Viana Figueiredo, Rosilene Andrade Silva Rodrigues, Waléria Christiane Rezende Fett</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/166251</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-06T17:37:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores associados à presença de Candida spp. em amostras de fluído vaginal de mulheres residentes em comunidades quilombolas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Factors associated with the presence of Candida spp. in vaginal fluid samples from women living in quilombola communities</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Batista, José Eduardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Anderson Pereira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Aragão, Francisca Bruna Arruda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Gerusinete Rodrigues Bastos dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lobão, Walder Jansen de Mello</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cunha, Caio da Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Thiago de Sousa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sousa, Clice Pimentel Cunha de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Vandilson Pinheiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Candida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Candida albicans</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Vulvovaginal candidiasis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Social Vulnerability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Candida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Candida albicans</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Candidíase vulvovaginal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Vulnerabilidade Social</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Investigate the frequency and factors associated with the detection of Candida spp. in vaginal fluid from women living in a quilombola settlement. Materials and Method: A cross-sectional study was conducted with 177 women living in a quilombola settlement in Northeast, Brazil. Socio-demographic data, living habits, general health, and reproductive health were collected. The material collected in the region of the cervix was submitted to cytopathological examination. Vaginal fluid samples were collected for microbiological analysis. Chi-square test, exact Fisher’s test, and logistic regression models were used for the statistical analysis. Results: Candida spp. was detected in 28.9% of the samples. The most frequent species in positive cases were Candida albicans (49%), followed by Candida krusei (39.2%). After adjustment, it was observed that women aged over 50 years had a higher chance of detecting Candida spp. in vaginal fluid (OR adjusted = 3.46; 95% CI= 1.68-7.12), while women complaining of vaginal discharge had a lower chance of detecting Candida spp. (OR adjusted = 0.29; 95% 95% CI= 0.11-0.78). Conclusion: The findings suggest a high detection of Candida spp. in vaginal fluid among women living in quilombola settlements, which indicates the need for planning measures for prevention and track the cases of vulvovaginal candidiasis in this population group. Besides, the presence of Candida spp. was higher in women from the fifth decade of life, lower in women with complaints of vaginal discharge.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Investigar a frequência e fatores associados à detecção de Candida spp. em fluido vaginal de mulheres residentes em uma comunidade quilombola. Materiais e Método: Um estudo transversal foi conduzido com 177 mulheres residentes em uma comunidade quilombola no Nordeste do Brasil. Foram coletados dados sociodemográficos, hábitos de vida, saúde geral e saúde reprodutiva. O material coletado na região do colo do útero foi submetido a exame citopatológico. Amostras de fluido vaginal foram coletadas para a análise microbiológica. Os testes Qui-quadrado, exato de Fisher e modelos de Regressão Logística foram utilizados na análise estatística. Resultados: Foi detectado Candida spp. em 28,9% das amostras. A espécie mais frequente nos casos positivos foi a Candida albicans (49%), seguida da Candida krusei (39,2%). Após o ajustamento, observou-se que mulheres com idade igual ou maior que 50 anos apresentaram maior chance da detecção de Candida spp. no fluido vaginal (OR ajustada = 3,46; IC95% = 1,68-7,12), enquanto as mulheres com queixa de corrimento vaginal apresentaram uma chance menor de detecção de Candida spp. (OR ajustada = 0,29; IC95% = 0,11-0,78). Conclusão: Os achados sugerem uma elevada detecção de Candida spp. no fluido vaginal entre mulheres residentes em comunidades quilombolas, o que sinaliza a necessidade do planejamento de medidas para prevenção e rastreamento de caso de candidíase vulvovaginal neste grupo populacional. Além disso, a presença de Candida spp. foi mais elevada em mulheres a partir da quinta década de vida, menor nas mulheres com queixas de corrimento vaginal.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-08-07</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/166251</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i2p171-181</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 2 (2020); 171-181</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 2 (2020); 171-181</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 2 (2020); 171-181</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/166251/162589</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/166259</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-12-11T14:16:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Austrian Syndrome: a report of an exceptionally rare and deadly syndrome</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Síndrome de Austrian: descrição de uma entidade excepcionalmente rara e mortal</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jesus, Gustavo Nobre de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Tânia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Caldeira, Alexandre</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fernandes, Susana M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Streptococcus pneumoniae</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Meningitis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pneumonia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Endocarditis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Streptococcus pneumoniae</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Meningite</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pneumonia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Encocardite</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Austrian Syndrome is the rare combination of a triad of endocarditis, meningitis, and pneumonia in the context of pneumococcal infection. Due to the involvement of several anatomical sites, the Austrian syndrome has a high mortality. Importantly, endocarditis is usually not considered during pneumococcal infection. We present a case of Austrian syndrome in a previously healthy 67-year-old woman. She featured with mental state alteration, respiratory failure, and shock, and was diagnosed with ceftriaxone-sensitive pneumococcal bacteremia, meningitis, and pneumonia. A transesophageal echocardiogram revealed vegetation of the mitral valve. Despite an improvement in her medical condition, she remained in a coma and died due to neurological complications. Even though the major cause of mortality in Austrian syndrome is cardiac involvement, meningitis is also linked with high morbidity and eventually death. We emphasize the relevance of an early diagnosis of the triad in order to decrease the very high mortality associated with this syndrome.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A síndrome de Austrian é uma entidade extremamente rara, pautada por meningite, endocardite e pneumonia secundárias a doença pneumocócica invasiva. Devido à expressão multissistêmica, a mortalidade associada é elevada. Particularmente, a manifestação como endocardite é muitas vezes clinicamente insuspeita, carecendo de elevado índice de suspeita. Apresenta-se um caso de síndrome de Austrian numa doente do sexo feminino, 67 anos, previamente saudável. Clinicamente, apresentava coma, insuficiência respiratória e choque, tendo sido diagnosticada pneumonia e meningite, e com bacteremia a Streptococcus pneumoniae. Ecocardiograma transesofágico evidenciou uma vegetação na válvula mitral. Apesar da regressão do quadro respiratório, persistiu um quadro de coma, acabando a doente por morrer. Apesar da principal causa de morte descrita na síndrome de Austrian estar relacionada com complicações de endocardite, apresenta-se um caso único de apresentação e morte por meningite. Com poucos casos descritos mundialmente, sublinha-se a necessidade de um diagnóstico precoce desta tríade, motivo pelo qual relatamos o caso descrito.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-12-11</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/166259</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i4p468-471</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 4 (2020); 468-471</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 4 (2020); 468-471</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 4 (2020); 468-471</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/166259/166398</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Gustavo Nobre de Jesus, Tânia Carvalho, Alexandre Caldeira, Susana M Fernandes</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/166390</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-15T18:40:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Hipoventilação relacionada ao sono de origem central secundária à deficiência de biotinidase: relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Sleep-related hypoventilation due to partial biotinidase deficiency: a case report</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Andressa Fernandes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moraes, Carolina Vicentim de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pelissari, Guilherme Andrade</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carneiro, Zumira Aparecida</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Marcela Almeida</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Borsatto, Taciane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schwartz, Ida Vanessa Doederlein</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lourenço, Charles Marques</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Deficiência de Biotinidase</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Suspensão da Respiração</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hipoventilação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Biotinidase Deficiency</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Breath Holding</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hypoventilation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A hipoventilação relacionada ao sono de origem central resulta em hipercapnia relacionada ao sono na vigência de condições normais do sistema respiratório e excluindo-se outros fatores. Os pacientes portadores dessa patologia podem se apresentar assintomáticos ou com queixas de cefaleia matinal, déficit cognitivo e fadiga, além de eventos como a observação de respiração superficial. No presente relato, descreve-se o caso de uma paciente de 3 anos, com exame físico geral e neurológico normais, desenvolvimento neuropsicomotor adequado, apresentando irregularidades respiratórias e bradicardia durante o sono. Encaminhada para investigação de distúrbios respiratórios do sono, sendo diagnosticada com hipoventilação relacionada ao sono. Através do estudo genético, evidenciou-se a deficiência de biotinidade como a possível ãcausa da sintomatologia, comprovada por dosagens enzimáticas e teste genético molecular. O tratamento medicamentoso foi iniciado precocemente, determinando resolução dos sintomas descritos. A importância do presente relato se encontra na apresentação da deficiência da biotinidase com quadro cardiorrespiratório isolado em criança neurologicamente normal, ademais trata-se de um caso em que a etiologia de Breath-Holding Speels foi a deficiência dessa enzima. Correspondência sugerida pela resolução da hipoventilação central após a introdução da biotina. Além disso, nesse caso, os sintomas ALTE, que aterrorizam o observador e até o profissional, foram solucionados com tratamento simples, a ingesta oral de biotina. Esse relato de caso corrobora com a expansão das possibilidades de manifestações fenotípicas das formas tardias de deficiência de biotinidase, como o fenótipo da SHC.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Idiopathic sleep-related hypoventilation occurs in individuals with hypercapnia during sleep in normal conditions of the respiratory system in the absence of other disorders. Patients with this condition may be asymptomatic or have complaints of morning headache, cognitive deficit and fatigue, and observation of shallow breathing. This report describes the case of a 3-year-old patient with normal physical and neurological exam, appropriate neuropsychomotor development, presenting breathing irregularities, and bradycardia during sleep. The patient was referred to an investigation for sleep respiratory disturbs and was diagnosed with hypoventilation related to sleep. The genetic study, done by enzymatic dosages and molecular genetic tests, showed the deficiency of biotinidase as a possible cause of symptomatology. The drug treatment was initiated early with the resolution of the symptoms. The present clinical report highlights the biotinidase deficiency with an isolated cardiorespiratory condition in a neurologically normal child, which also led to Breath-Holding Spells. This relation was suggested after central hypoventilation resolution following biotin introduction. Besides, Apparent Life-Threatening Events symptoms, which terrify the observer and even professionals, disappeared after the oral intake of biotin. Finally, this case report corroborates the expansion of possibilities for the phenotypic manifestations of late cases from biotinidase deficiency, as the SHC phenotype.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-07-16</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/166390</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2021.166390</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 No. 1 (2021); e166390</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 Núm. 1 (2021); e166390</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 54 n. 1 (2021); e166390</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/166390/174073</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Andressa Fernandes Silva, Carolina Vicentim de Moraes, Guilherme Andrade Pelissari, Marcela Almeida Lopes, Taciane Borsatto, Ida Vanessa Doederlein Schwartz, Charles Marques Lourenço</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/166597</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-15T18:40:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da ação germicida da luz ultravioleta de cabine de segurança biológica frente às espécies bacterianas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of the germicidal action of ultraviolet light in biosafety cabinet concerning bacterial species</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Barbosa, Adriana Sierra Assencio Almeida</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Camargo, Mariana Priscila</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moreira, Julie Anne Corrêa de Magalhães Tavares</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Diman, Rafael Balan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silveira, Mônica da</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Biosafety Cabinet</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Staphylococcus aureus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Klebsiella pneumoniae</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">UV Light</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cabine de Segurança Biológica.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Staphylococcus aureus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Klebsiella pneumoniae</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Luz Ultravioleta</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Introduction: The biological safety cabinet (BSC) is a collective protective device used to hold aerosols produced in laboratory procedures. The BSC protects workers, material handling, and the environment. It relies on ultraviolet light (UV) lamps that have germicidal action, altering the nucleic acids of microorganisms. Objective: The objective of the present study was to evaluate the germicidal action of BSC class II type A2 UV light against the culture of two bacterial species with different conditions of exposure to UV light. Methods: &#160;For the research, the bacteria Staphylococcus aureus ATCC 25923 and Klebsiella pneumoniae ATCC 10031 were used, at a concentration of 1.5x108 Colony Forming Units/ml (CFU/ml), which were seeded in Petri biplates. Use UV light under different conditions and times. Results: The bacterial species showed the same growth or inhibition profile when subjected to different exposure conditions. Petri dishes with the cover open and protected or not with sterilization packaging showed bacterial inhibition at 15 and 20 minutes. The microorganisms in the biplates protected by the aluminum foil and in the biplates with the cover on, regardless of the time and condition, showed bacterial growth. Conclusion: With the results obtained, it is suggested that the germicidal action of UV light was effective, ensuring adequate decontamination and ensuring quality in laboratory biosafety.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: A cabine de segurança biológica (CBS) é um equipamento de proteção coletiva, utilizado para efetuar a contenção de aerossóis produzidos nos procedimentos laboratoriais. A CBS protege tanto os trabalhadores, quanto o material manipulado e o meio ambiente. Dispõe de lâmpadas de luz ultravioleta (UV) que possui ação germicida, alterando os ácidos nucleicos dos micro-organismos. Objetivo: O objetivo do presente estudo foi avaliar a ação germicida da luz UV da CBS classe II, tipo A2, frente à cultura de duas espécies de bactérias com diferentes condições de exposição a luz UV. Material e Métodos: Para o desenvolvimento da pesquisa foram utilizadas as bactérias Staphylococcus aureus ATCC 25923 e Klebsiella pneumoniae ATCC 10031, na concentração de 1,5x108 Unidades Formadoras de Colônias/ml (UFC/ml), que após a semeadura em biplacas de Petri foram expostas à luz UV em diferentes condições e tempos. Resultados: Os resultados obtidos revelaram que as espécies de bactérias apresentaram igual perfil de crescimento ou inibição quando submetidas às diferentes condições de exposição. As biplacas de Petri com as tampas abertas e protegidas ou não com embalagem de esterilização apresentaram, nos tempos 15 e 20 minutos, inibição bacteriana. Nas biplacas protegidas pelo papel alumínio e nas biplacas com a tampa fechada, independentemente do tempo e da condição, os micro-organismos apresentaram crescimento bacteriano. Conclusão: Com os resultados obtidos, sugere-se que a ação germicida da luz UV foi eficaz, garantindo a descontaminação adequada e assegurando a qualidade na biossegurança laboratorial.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-08-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/166597</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2021.166597</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 No. 1 (2021); e166597</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 Núm. 1 (2021); e166597</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 54 n. 1 (2021); e166597</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/166597/174727</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Adriana Sierra Assencio Almeida Barbosa, Mariana Priscila Camargo, Julie Anne Corrêa de Magalhães Tavares Moreira, Rafael Balan Diman, Mônica da Silveira</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/166597</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-12T11:35:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/166641</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-04T15:11:37Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:EDT</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Agenesia de artéria pulmonar</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Agenesis of pulmonary artery</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Marcel Koenigkam</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Agenesia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Agenesis</dc:subject>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-04-27</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/166641</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v53i1p1-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 No. 1 (2020): jan./fev./mar.; 1-2</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 53 Núm. 1 (2020): jan./fev./mar.; 1-2</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 53 n. 1 (2020): jan./fev./mar.; 1-2</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/166641/160353</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Marcel Koenigkam Santos</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/166719</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-01T15:14:39Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RC</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O Carcinoma endometrial é uma causa rara de metástases cutâneas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Endometrial carcinoma metastatic to the scalp</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Aidos, Joana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Sónia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Teresa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martins, Nuno Nogueira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martins, Francisco Nogueira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Scalp metastatis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cutaneous metastasis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Endometrial carcinoma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Metástase do escalpe</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Metástase cutânea</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Carcinoma endometrial</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Endometrial carcinoma is a very rare cause of cutaneous metastasis.&#160;The most frequent presentations of cutaneous metastasis are fast developing nodules or tumors, which are evidence of widespread dissemination in such patients.&#160;We report a case of scalp metastasis from an endometrial adenocarcinoma with a fatal prognosis. &#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O carcinoma endometrial é uma causa rara de metástases cutâneas. A apresentação mais frequente de metástases cutâneas são nódulos ou tumores de rápido desenvolvimento, que evidenciam uma disseminação generalizada nesses pacientes. Relatamos um caso de metástase no couro cabeludo de um adenocarcinoma endometrial com prognóstico fatal.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-10-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/166719</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.rmrp.2021.166719</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 No. 2 (2021); e-166719</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 54 Núm. 2 (2021); e-166719</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 54 n. 2 (2021); e-166719</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/166719/176137</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Joana Aidos, Sónia Gonçalves, Teresa Carvalho, Nuno Nogueira Martins, Francisco Nogueira Martins</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2022-08-30T21:20:44Z" completeListSize="1467" cursor="1250">5cc8d92c98d31c375cedb14f62cbef55</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
