<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-08-29T21:20:06Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="rmrp">https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/465</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:11:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">OCCUPATIONAL ACTIVITY AND SENILE CATARACT – OPINIONS OF PATIENTS OF A UNIVERSITY HOSPITAL</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">ATIVIDADE OCUPACIONAL E CATARATA SENIL – OPINIÃO DE PACIENTES DE HOSPITAL UNIVERSITÁRIO</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Marback, Roberta F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Temporini, Edméa R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Maia Junior, Otacílio O.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schaefer, Tânia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kara-José Junior, Newton</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kara-José, Newton</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Oftalmologia. Saúde Ocupacional. Catarata.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ophthalmology. Ocupational Health. Cataract.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Purpose: To identify perceptions about relationship between the occupational activity and origin of the disease in persons with senile cataract. Methods:&#160;A descriptive observational transversal study was developed by a structured questionnaire which was applied during interviews elaborated from an exploratory study . The sample was accessible with patients with cataract in an ophthalmogical clinic of an university hospital.&#160;Results:&#160;One hundred and ten persons of boths genders (34,5% males and 65,5% females aged between 43 and 89 years old were submitted to the study. The great proportion of persons was not developing payed activities (87,3%). Among the most frequent opinions about the causes of cataract were advanced age (69,1%), excessive use of the vision (57,3%) and influence of hot temperatures against the eyes (40,9%). Regarding the opinions about the relation between professional activities and development of cataract, 56,4% did not believe that the activity shown had influence in the origin of disease, while 43,6% believed in a relation between the occupational activity and the development of the disease. Visual strain (37,5%), excessive hot temperatures (12,5%) and use of chemical substances (10,3%) were the attributable causes of cataract related to professional activities.&#160;Conclusions:&#160;We observed a great predominance of aged with low schooling and not developing payed activities persons and retired from the work market suggesting low socio-economic levels and low acquisitive power. Situations indicated by the examined persons as excessive use of the vision and hot temperatures suffered by the eyes during occupational activities suggest an erroneous knowledge about disease.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">&#160;Objetivo: Identificar a situação ocupacional e percepções de portadores de catarata senil sobre a relação entre a atividade ocupacional exercida e o surgimento da doença. Métodos:&#160;Desenvolveu-se estudo observacional transversal descritivo, por meio de questionário estruturado, aplicado por entrevista, elaborado a partir de estudo exploratório. A amostra, prontamente acessível, foi formada por pacientes atendidos pelo setor de catarata da clínica oftalmológica de um hospital universitário.&#160;Resultados:&#160;A amostra foi constituída por 110 sujeitos de ambos os sexos (34,5% homens; 65,5% mulheres), com idade entre 43 e 89 anos, ± 10,3 anos. A maior proporção dos entrevistados não exercia atividade remunerada (87,3%). Dentre as opiniões acerca das causas da catarata, destacaram-se a velhice (69,1%), o uso excessivo dos olhos (57,3%) e a exposição ao calor nos olhos (40,9%). Quanto à opinião sobre relação entre atividades profissionais exercidas e catarata, 56,4% não acreditavam que o trabalho tivesse influído, enquanto 43,6% atribuíram às atividades ocupacionais a essa afecção ocular. Foram atribuídos às atividades profissionais: o cansaço visual (37,5%), contato com calor excessivo (12,5%) e uso de produto químico (10,3%).&#160;Conclusões:&#160;Evidenciou-se predominância acentuada de idosos de baixa escolaridade, não mais exercendo atividade ocupacional e inativos no mercado de trabalho. Entre os que exerciam, prevaleceram as ocupações manuais especializadas, o que sugere reduzido nível socioeconômico e baixo poder aquisitivo. Atribuíram como causas do comprometimento visual situações decorrentes de atividades ocupacionais, como o uso excessivo dos olhos e a exposição ao calor, evidenciando-se conhecimentos errôneos.&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/465</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v38i3/4p301-309</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 38 No. 3/4 (2005); 301-309</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 38 Núm. 3/4 (2005); 301-309</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 38 n. 3/4 (2005); 301-309</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/465/465</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/466</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:11:39Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:NTIS</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">RESUMOS DE DISSERTAÇÕES DE MESTRADO E TESES DE DOUTORADO APRESENTADAS NA FACULDADE DE MEDICINA DE RIBEIRÃO PRETO - USP DE JULHO/DEZEMBRO 2005</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Editor, O</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/466</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v38i3/4p310-385</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 38 No. 3/4 (2005); 310-385</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 38 Núm. 3/4 (2005); 310-385</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 38 n. 3/4 (2005); 310-385</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/466/466</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/467</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:11:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:AGR</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">AGRADECIMENTOS</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Editor, O</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/467</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v38i3/4p386-386</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 38 No. 3/4 (2005); 386-386</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 38 Núm. 3/4 (2005); 386-386</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 38 n. 3/4 (2005); 386-386</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/467/467</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/469</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Food fortification with iron and vitamin A</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fortificação de alimentos com ferro e vitamina A</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zancul, Mariana Senzi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fortification. Iron. Vitamin A. Nutrition. Public Health.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fortificação. Ferro. Vitamina A. Nutrição. Saúde Pública.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A deficiência de vitaminas, como a vitamina A e minerais, como ferro e iodo, é um grave problema de nutrição/saúde pública em todo o Mundo e principalmente nos países em desenvolvimento, como o Brasil, atingindo especialmente crianças em idade pré-escolar, adolescentes, gestantes e mulheres em idade fértil. Para uma vida saudável e produtiva, as pessoas necessitam ingerir quantidades adequadas de alimentos, incluindo aqueles ricos em vitaminas e minerais. A fortificação de alimentos, ou seja, a adição de vitaminas e minerais a alimentos de uso massivo, visando garantir a ingestão diária recomendada, é um procedimento eficaz na prevenção da deficiência de vários micronutrientes, como as do ferro e as da vitamina A. A fortificação é um processo relativamente simples, mas é importante a seleção correta do tipo de composto a ser utilizado e do alimento usado como veículo de transporte. O alimento pode interferir na absorção do composto, diminuindo sua biodisponibilidade. Muitas vitaminas e minerais são utilizados na fortificação de alimentos. O uso da fortificação industrial de alimentos tem sido um dos melhores processos para o controle das carências nutricionais de microelementos da população, em todo o Mundo. Neste trabalho, são abordados aspectos específicos e recentes da fortificação de alimentos com ferro e vitamina A, porque as deficiências desses micronutrientes são os problemas nutricionais mais importantes do Brasil e do Mundo.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Micronutrients deficiencies such as vitamin A and iron and iodine, are the greatest nutrition and public health problems all over the world in developing countries, including Brazil. This deficiency affects infants, preschool children, teenagers, pregnant and women in fertile age. Food fortification, addition of vitamins and minerals to food of massive use, to guarantee desirable intake of these nutrients is an efficient way to prevent micronutrient deficiency, such as iron and vitamin A. Food fortification is a relatively simple process, but it requires the best choice of the food to be used as vehicle as well as the appropriated selection of the compound to be added. There are several vitamins and minerals used in food fortification. The use of industrial fortification of foods has been one of the best choices to control micronutrients deficiency all over the world. In this work aspects of food fortification with iron and vitamin A are reported and discussed. These deficiencies affect the largest number of persons in the developing world, including Brazil.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/469</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p45-50</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 45-50</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 45-50</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 45-50</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/469/468</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/470</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Ritmos hormonais do pâncreas endócrino: dos fundamentos cronobiológicos às implicações clínicas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Hormone rhythms of the endocrine pancreas: from the chronobiological fundamentals to the clinical implications</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Delattre, Edson</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Chronobiology. Endocrine Rhythms. Circadian Rhythm. Ultradian rhythm. Pulsatile release. Beta Cell. Insulin</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">secretion.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cronobiologia. Ritmos Endócrinos. Ritmo Circadiano. Ritmo ultradiano. Secreção pulsátil. Célula Beta. Insulina</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">secreção.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Initially the theoretical basis for the knowledge of the endocrine rhythms are presented, by taking into consideration that all hormonal secretions display stressed oscillations that denotes a high degree of temporal organization in the endocrine system. Next, the work reviews the rhythm of the endocrine pancreas, by pointing out the circadian and ultradian rhythms of insulin, due to its importance for the physiology and physiopathology of that organ. Both the results secured in vitro and those noticed clinically are presented. The biological reasons for the pulsatile hormones secretion in general are discussed as well as changes of that rhythm, in endocrine pancreas pathologies.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Inicialmente, são apresentadas as bases teóricas para o conhecimento dos ritmos endócrinos, considerando-se que, virtualmente, todas as secreções hormonais apresentam acentuadas oscilações, o que demonstra um alto grau de organização temporal do sistema endócrino. A seguir, o trabalho revisa a ritmicidade do pâncreas endócrino, ressaltando os ritmos circadianos e ultradianos da insulina, em razão de sua importância para a fisiologia e fisiopatologia desse órgão. São apresentados tanto os resultados obtidos in vitro, quanto aqueles verificados clinicamente. Discutem-se as razões biológicas para a secreção pulsátil dos hormônios em geral, bem como as alterações desse ritmo em patologias do pâncreas endócrino.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/470</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p51-64</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 51-64</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 51-64</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 51-64</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/470/738</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/473</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">constipation in children</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Constipação intestinal na criança</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bigélli, Rosa H. M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fernandes, Maria I. M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Galvão, Lívia C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Constipation. Children. Gastrointestinal Motility.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Constipação. Criança. Motilidade Gastrointestinal.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">&amp;nbsp; Objective: To present an update review of intestinal constipation in children, analysing the principal clinic characteristics and its diagnostic and therapeutic approachs.&amp;nbsp;Methods:&amp;nbsp;Recent articles on the topic were reviewed, supplemented by the clinical experience of the Gastroenterology Unit, of the Pediatric Departament- HCRP- USP.&amp;nbsp;Results:&amp;nbsp;The intestinal constipation is a commun problem in the pediatric clinics. Its definition is based on the elimination of painful, difficulted and dry feces. Infants usually present crying during the evacuations. In some children it can be observed important facael retention with or without soiling. The diagnosis is based on a deitailed clinical history and physical examination of the children. The diagnosis in the most of the cases may be done with a carefully clinical history and phisical examination. The treatment must be done according to the basal cause and in the most of the cases dietetic and comportamental changes are necessary.&amp;nbsp;Conclusões:&amp;nbsp;The diagnosis of the intestinal constipation must be done earlier because it is important for the therapeutic sucess, that depends on a adequate diet and a behavioral program to regulate bowel habits.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Apresentar uma revisão sobre a constipação intestinal na criança, analisando as principais características clínicas bem como sua abordagem diagnóstica e terapêutica.&amp;nbsp;Métodos:&amp;nbsp;Revisão bibliográfica atualizada e experiência da Unidade de Gastroenterologia do Departamento de Pediatria- HCRP- USP.&amp;nbsp;Resultados:&amp;nbsp;A constipação intestinal constitui um problema comum na prática pediátrica. Sua definição está baseada na eliminação de fezes ressecadas, com esforço e dor. É comum as crianças pequenas apresentarem choro durante as evacuações. Em algumas crianças, pode ser observada retenção fecal importante, com ou sem escape fecal. O diagnóstico, na maioria dos casos, pode ser feito através de dados de história clínica e exame físico cuidadoso dos pacientes. O tratamento deve ser direcionado à causa básica, necessitando, na maioria dos casos, mudanças dietéticas e comportamentais.&amp;nbsp;Conclusões:&amp;nbsp;O diagnóstico da constipação intestinal deve ser precoce, pois interfere no sucesso terapêutico, que depende de uma adequada alimentação e do recondicionamento esfincteriano. &amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/473</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p65-75</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 65-75</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 65-75</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 65-75</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/473/472</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/476</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O psicólogo interconsultor, na enfermaria de pneumologia, de um hospital escola: caracterização das solicitações de atendimento psicológico</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The psychologist as an interconsultant on the pneumology ward of teaching hospital: characterization of the requests for psychological care</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Osório, Flávia L.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical Psychology. General Hospital. Consultation.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Psicologia Médica. Hospital Geral. Interconsulta.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetiva-se caracterizar as solicitações de atendimento psicológico feitas a um Serviço de Psicologia em Interconsulta, numa Enfermaria de Pneumologia de um Hospital-Escola, por meio da análise dos formulários de solicitação de interconsulta (PI). Analisaram-se os PIs enviados no período de três semestres, caracterizando-se o número total de pacientes, distribuição quanto ao sexo, idade, motivo de solicitação e encaminhamento dado ao caso. Quanto aos resultados obtidos, detectou-se que, para 11,3% dos pacientes internados na enfermaria, no citado período, foi solicitada interconsulta psicológica. Desses pacientes, predominaram os de sexo masculino, na faixa etária dos 50-69 anos. Quanto aos motivos de solicitação, predominaram referências às seguintes categorias: doença neoplásica pulmonar, sintomatologia depressiva, falta de colaboração no tratamento, sintomatologia ansiosa, quadros de somatização, dificuldade de adaptação hospitalar e presença de doença crônica prévia. Quanto ao encaminhamento dos casos, predominou a indicação de atendimento psicoterápico de apoio, seguido de orientação familiar. Percebe-se que a demanda para atendimento psicológico, na Enfermaria de Pneumologia, é adequadamente percebida pela equipe médica, principalmente frente a doenças em que o componente emocional é relevante, tanto no aparecimento como no enfrentamento, e em situações em que sintomas de maior fragilidade psíquica, como a depressão, já se fazem presentes. Conclui-se que, em tal contexto hospitalar, o psicólogo tem um campo de atuação configurado: melhorar a qualidade da assistência ao paciente, provendo cuidados aos aspectos psicossociais, envolvidos na situação de a pessoa estar doente e hospitalizada.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The objective of the present study was to characterize the requests for psychological care presented to an Consultation Psychology Service on a Pneumology ward of a Teaching Hospital, by analyzing the forms for interconsultation requests (PI). The PIs submitted during a period of 3 semesters were analyzed in terms of total number of patients, sex and age distribution, reason for the request, and referral of the case. The results showed that psychological consultation was requested for 11.3% of the patients admitted to the ward during the study period. Male gender and age range from 50 to 69 years predominated among these patients. Among the reasons for the requests there was a predominance of reference to the following categories: neoplastic pulmonary disease, depressive symptoms, lack of compliance with treatment, anxiety symptoms, somatic disorders, difficulty in adapting to the hospital, and presence of a previous chronic disease. With respect to referral, there was a predominance of indication of support psychotherapy, followed by family orientation. A demand for psychological care was observed on the Pneumology ward and was adequately perceived by the medical team, especially in the presence of diseases in which the emotional component is relevant both at the onset of the disease and in terms of coping with it, and in situations in which symptoms of greater psychic fragility, such as depression, are already present. We conclude that, within this hospital context, the field of activity of the psychologist is clearly defined: to improve the quality of patient care by devoting attention to the psychosocial aspects involved in the situation of being ill and hospitalized.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/476</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p76-83</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 76-83</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 76-83</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 76-83</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/476/475</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/480</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:42Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O que eles fazem depois da aula ? as atividades extracurriculares dos alunos de ciências médicas da FMRP-USP</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">What do they do after class? extra curriculum activities of medical students of ribeirão preto-University of São Paulo</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Vieira, Elisabeth Meloni</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barbieri, Carolina Luisa Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vilela, Daniel Bacco</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ianhez Júnior, Edgar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tomé, Fernanda Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Woida, Francesca Maia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martinez, Guilherme Luna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vicente, Luciana Morais</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gava, Nelson Fabrício</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lira, Priscilla Genari</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brandão, Tetzi Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mendonça, Thaís Nociti</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical. Students</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação Médica. Estudantes de Medicina.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Em 1999, o Programa Especial de Treinamento da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto, da Universidade de São Paulo realizou um estudo com 326 alunos, do primeiro ao quarto ano, com o objetivo de identificar e descrever as atividades extracurriculares desses alunos. Em 2002, o estudo foi repetido, utilizando-se o mesmo instrumento, aplicado em 360 alunos. Trata-se, portanto, de estudo transversal, cujas variáveis estudadas são: idade, sexo, ano do curso, atividades extracurriculares ligadas à FMRP-USP, motivo da pratica de tais atividades, horas despendidas com elas, grau de satisfação e motivo de satisfação e insatisfação. Do total de entrevistados, 64% são homens e 36% são mulheres. A média da idade é 20,7 anos e apenas 8% (29) não estavam engajados em nenhuma atividade extracurricular na época da entrevista. Das atividades mais freqüentadas estão as ligas (73%), os treinos esportivos (53%), os estágios em laboratório de iniciação científica (31,5%) e os plantões voluntários (31%). Das atividades não relacionadas à Faculdade, 36% referiram-se ao estudo de uma língua estrangeira e 24,5%, à música ou ao teatro. A maioria gasta, pelo menos, cinco horas semanais com essas atividades. Maior número de atividades foi encontrado, associado ao maior o tempo de permanência do aluno no curso médico (p=0,002), embora a carga horária da grade curricular também aumente com o passar do tempo. Embora não tenham sido encontradas grandes diferenças, ao compararmos os alunos entrevistados em 1999 e 2002, houve aumento significativo de participação em ligas, já que novas foram criadas no período.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">In 1999 the Special Training Programme of the Medical School of Ribeirão Preto conducted a study with 326 undergraduate students from the first to the fourth grade aiming to identify and describe their extra curriculum activities. In 2002 the study was repeated administering the same questionnaire among 360 students. It is, therefore, a cross-seccional study in which the variables are age, sex, grade of course, extra curriculum activities linked to the school, reasons for these activities, weekly hours spent with them, satisfaction levels and reasons for satisfaction or dissatisfaction. From the total of interviewees 64% are male and 36% female, the median age found was 20,7 years old and only 8% (29) of students are not enrolled in any extra curriculum activity at the time of the interview. Belonging to a study group named “leagues” (73%), practicing some sport (53%), developing research (31,5%) or voluntary medical night calls (31%) are amongst the most popular actitivies. Among the activities not linked to the school most students reported to study a foreign language (36%), music or theatre (24,5%). Most of them reported spending at least five hours per week with some of these activivies. Greater number of activities were found associated to higher grade at medical school (p=0,002) despite the increase of time in class. Although there were not found great differences among the students interviewed in 1999 and 2002, there was a significant increase of participation in “leagues” since new of them were created during this time.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/480</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p84-90</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 84-90</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 84-90</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 84-90</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/480/479</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/482</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Análise da prescrição informatizada, em duas clínicas de um hospital universitário</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Analysis of the computerized prescription in two clinics of a teaching hospital</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Freire, Claudia Câmara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gimenes, Fernanda Raphael Escobar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cassiani, Silvia Helena Bortoli</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Prescriptions</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Drug. Medication Errors. Medical Informatics.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Prescrição de Medicamentos. Erros na Medicação. Informática Médica.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: identificar e analisar a redação da prescrição eletrônica, num Hospital Universitário, do Interior do Estado de São Paulo, e propor sugestões para melhorar o sistema.&amp;nbsp;Modelo do estudo:&amp;nbsp;Estudo avaliatório.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Local do estudo : O estudo foi desenvolvido em duas clínicas do Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto - USP, utilizando-se, como objeto de análise, as prescrições na forma eletrônica.&amp;nbsp;População e amostra- Foram analisadas 390 prescrições da Clínica de Ortopedia e 535 prescrições da Clínica Médica, que corresponderam a todas as prescrições avaliadas em 30 dias, não consecutivos.&amp;nbsp;Resultados: Do total de 925 prescrições avaliadas nas duas clínicas, 112 (12,1%) apresentaram rasuras, 129 (13,9%) apresentavam medicamentos suspensos, manualmente ou digitalmente, 261 (28,2%) apresentavam informações que deixavam dúvidas nos profissionais, dentre outros.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To identify and analyze the writing of electronic orders in a universityhospital in São Paulo State and propose suggestions to improve the system.&amp;nbsp;Study model: Evaluative study.&amp;nbsp;Study site: The study was conducted in two clinics at the University Hospital of the Faculty of Medicine of Ribeirão Preto – University of São Paulo - and its object of analysis consisted of electronic orders.&amp;nbsp;Population and sample:&amp;nbsp;390 orders were analyzed in the orthopedics clinic and 535 orders were evaluated in the medical clinic, which corresponded to all orders evaluated in 30 nonconsecutive days.&amp;nbsp;Results:&amp;nbsp;Of the total number of 925 orders evaluated in the two clinics, 112 (12.1%) presented erasures, 129 (13.9%) showed medication suspensions introduced either manually or in typing, 261 (28.2%) presented information that made professionals doubtful, among others. Conclusions:&amp;nbsp;Electronic orders represent a great advancement in the strategies used to minimize errors resulting from badly formulated orders. However, it does not eradicate the possibility of occurrence of medication errors; which indicates that modifications in the system are necessary.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/482</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p91-96</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 91-96</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 91-96</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 91-96</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/482/481</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/483</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Mortalidade por causas externas no município de são josé do rio preto, no período de 1996-1998</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Injury death in são josé do rio preto-1996-1998</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>D’ Avila, Antonio M. M. Pires</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Augusto B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Goldbaum, Moisés</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Information Systems. Population Surveillance. Epidemiologic Surveillance. Preventive Medicine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">statistic &amp; numerical data. Accident Prevention. Mortality Rate.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sistemas de Informação. Vigilância da População. Vigilância Epidemiológica. Medicina Preventiva</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">estatística &amp; dados numéricos. Prevenção de Acidentes. Coeficiente de Mortalidade.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução: Um estudo epidemiológico sobre causas externas, utilizando taxas de mortalidade, foi realizado no Município de São José do Rio Preto, Estado de São Paulo, Brasil. O período considerado foi o triênio 1996-1998. Objetivos: Descrever as taxas de mortalidade por causas externas no Município de São José do Rio Preto, no período de 1996-1998. Metodologia: O estudo foi baseado em dados oficiais do Sistema de Informação de Mortalidade do Ministério da Saúde, e de investigação baseada nas informações dos médicos legistas (IML).A análise dos dados foi feita através dos softwares Epinfo 6.0 e Tabwin. Resultados: Os resultados foram comparados com os valores, obtidos na literatura, de algumas cidades e estados do Brasil. No caso de São José do Rio Preto, observou-se, no peírodo, diminuição no número dos óbitos por causas externas, particularmente nas mortes devidas a acidentes de trânsito, que são mais altas em relação aos valores observados no Brasil e no Estado de São Paulo. O estudo também detectou aumento no número absoluto de homicídios, principalmente nas faixas etárias de 15 a 39 anos de idade. Conclusão: Os resultados demonstram a necessidade de iniciar programas de prevenção à mortalidade pelas citadas causas externas e monitorizar, em nível local, suas ocorrências .</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Introduction: An epidemiological study of the mortality rates by injuries in São José do Rio Preto, State of São Paulo, Brazil, has been carried out. The period considered is 1996-1998. Objectives: To show injuries mortality rates in São José do Rio Preto-SP in 1996-98. Methods: The study was based on official data from the Mortality Information Service of the Brazilian Ministry of Health, and in a survey based on data from medical forensic examiners (IML).Software Epinfo6.0 and Tabwin was utilized for data analises. Results:The results were compared to values obtained in the literature for the other cities of São Paulo and Brazil. In the case of São José do Rio Preto, was observed a decrease in the number of deaths associated with external causes in the period, but particularly in deaths due to traffic accidents with motor vehicles an increase in cases of pedestrians killed by hit-and-run drivers, that is much larger than the corresponding values for Brazil and for the State of São Paulo. The study showed increase in rates of homicides, mainly in the 15 to 39 years age group . Conclusion: This result suggests that is important to start programs to reduce the number of deaths by injuries, as well as the necessity of monitoring locally all these data.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/483</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p97-105</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 97-105</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 97-105</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 97-105</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/483/482</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/484</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Aids, drogas e “ser mulher”: relatos de mulheres soropositivas para o HIV</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Aids, drugs and “to be a woman”: some HIV seropositive women’s reports</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Franco, Fabiana Gaspar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Figueiredo, Marco Antonio Castro</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome. Gender Identity. Substance-Related Disorders.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Síndrome de Imunodeficiência Adquirida. Identidade de Gênero. Transtornos Relacionados ao Uso de Substâncias.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Tendo em vista o status subprivilegiado e a vulnerabilidade social da mulher, foram entrevistadas dez usuárias de drogas injetáveis, portadoras do HIV/Aids, atendidas na Unidade Especial de Tratamento de Doenças Infecciosas (U.E.T.D.I.), do Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto, Universidade de São Paulo. As entrevistas, semi-estruturadas, enfocaram categorias temáticas a priori, complementadas por relatos sobre histórias de vida. Uma análise de conteúdos permitiu o levantamento de algumas representações sobre os temas enfocados: a) para ser mulher, foram identificados conteúdos relacionados à vulnerabilidade ao contágio por HIV, naturalização do papel feminino e resistência à subordinação; b) com respeito ao convívio com o HIV/Aids, conteúdos sobre banalização do contágio, estigma, perdas sociais/materiais, reconstruções e sentimentos adversos; c) relacionado a&amp;nbsp;ser usuária de drogas injetáveis, representações sobre fuga à realidade, dependência e valorações negativas a respeito do desamparo. Tais resultados são discutidos com a perspectiva de subsidiar a orientação de futuros programas de orientação e suporte, considerando a vulnerabilidade feminina, principalmente quanto ao uso de drogas ilícitas e ao contágio por HIV/Aids.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Face to the subprivileged status and the social vulnerability of the women, were interviewed ten women who are carrier of HIV/aids and user of injected drugs, and were attended at Infectious Diseases Treatment Special Unit at the Clinical Hospital of the Medicine Faculty of Ribeirão Preto, University of São Paulo. Semi-structured interviews focused “a priori” thematic categories and were complemented by reports about stories of life. A content analysis allowed the raising of some representations about the themes wich were focused: a) for being a woman, were identified contents related to the feminine vulnerability to HIV, the naturalization of the woman’s role and the resistance to subordination; b) for to live with HIV/aids, appeared contents related to the banalization of contagion, stigma, social/material losses, reconstructions and adverse feelings; c) related to being an injected drugs user, appeared representations about the reality escape, dependency and negative valorizations related to helplessness. Such results are discussed aiming the perspective of subsidize the orientation of future orientative and supportive programmes, considerating the feminine vulnerability, mainly to the use of illegal drugs and HIV/aids contagious..</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/484</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p106-116</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 106-116</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 106-116</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 106-116</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/484/483</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/485</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:37Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:PV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Exame clínico: um ensaio a partir de Foucault</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Clinical examination: an essay from Foucault</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Manço, José Carlos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical. Signs and Symptoms. Pathology.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação Médica. Sintomas e Sinais. Patologia.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">No pensamento de Foucault, a história do conhecimento é descontínua e as mudanças do que ele denomina a épistemê (episteme) não se sucedem de maneira contínua, mas por rupturas. Em duas de suas obras, Foucault oferece material de grande interesse para uma análise não convencional das mudanças do conhecimento humano e do modo de pensar que influenciaram o modelo de clínica médica e do exame clínico, que, de certa forma, chegou aos nossos dias. Os dois textos são: As palavras e as coisas - uma arqueologia das ciências humanas e O nascimento da clínica. Na análise do tema “exame clínico”, decidimos seguir o pensamento de Foucault, para acompanhar as transformações ocorridas no pensamento científico, a partir da Renascença, e o desenvolvimento do método clínico nos séculos XVIII e XIX. Para finalizar, são tecidas considerações críticas acerca das influências que o modelo de exame clínico, descrito pelo filósofo francês causaram na prática da clínica médica nos dias atuais.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">According to Foucault’s thought, history of knowledge is not continuous, and the changes in what he names épistemê do not happen in a continuous manner, but rather through gaps. In two of his works, Foucault offers material of great interest for a non-conventional analysis concerning changes in human knowledge and the pattern of thought that have had influence on the standards of medical practice and clinical examination, which, in a way, have reached our days. These two texts are: The Order of the Things: An Archaelogy of Human Sciences and Birth of the Clinic: An Archaelogy of Medical Perception. During the analysis of the subject “clinical examination”, we have decided to observe Foucault’s thought in order to follow the transformations occurred in scientific thought from Renaissance, as well as the development of clinical methodology during the XVIII and XIX centuries. As a conclusion of this work, we have discussed the influence that the standards of clinical examination described by this French philosopher have brought to the way we practice Medicine at the present time.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/485</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p117-134</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 117-134</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 117-134</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 117-134</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/485/484</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/486</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:NTIS</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Resumos de dissertações de mestrado (m) e teses de doutorado (d) apresentadas na faculdade de medicina de Ribeirão Preto - USP de Janeiro a Junho de 2004</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Editor, O</dc:creator>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/486</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p135-181</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 135-181</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 135-181</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 135-181</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/486/485</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/487</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:INM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">In Memorian: Prof. Luiz Marino Bechelli</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pagnano, Paulo Múcio Guimarães</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/487</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p182-183</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 182-183</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 182-183</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 182-183</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/487/486</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/488</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:VWORK</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Apresentação</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, João S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/488</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p1-1</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 1-1</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 1-1</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 1-1</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/488/487</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/489</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:VWORK</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Comissão organizadora</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>[S.N.], [S.N.]</dc:creator>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/489</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p2-2</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 2-2</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 2-2</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 2-2</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/489/488</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/490</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:VWORK</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Conferências</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>[S.N.], [S.N.]</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/490</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p3-13</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 3-13</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 3-13</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 3-13</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/490/489</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/491</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:VWORK</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Resumos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>[S.N.], [S.N.]</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i1/2p14-44</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 1/2 (2004); 14-44</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 1/2 (2004); 14-44</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 1/2 (2004); 14-44</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/491/490</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/494</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:EDT</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Sobre a importância do delineamento adequado de trabalhos científicos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Maria de Lourdes Veronese</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/494</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i3/4p185-185</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 3/4 (2004); 185-185</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 3/4 (2004); 185-185</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 3/4 (2004); 185-185</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/494/493</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/495</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:SIMSEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Apresentação</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Terra Filho, João</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/495</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i3/4p187-188</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 3/4 (2004); 187-188</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 3/4 (2004); 187-188</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 3/4 (2004); 187-188</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/495/494</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/496</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:SIMSEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Mecanismos de formação de edemas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Mechanisms of edema formation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Coelho, Eduardo Barbosa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Edema</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">physiopathology. Fibrosis. Nephritis. Syndrome. Nephrotic Syndrome. Heart Failure.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Edema</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">fisiopatologia. Fibrose. Nefrite. Síndrome. Síndrome Nefrótica. Insuficiência Cardíaca.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Edema is defined as liquid accumulation in the interstitial space. In this review, the mechanisms of localized and generalized edema formation were discussed as well as semiologic aspects used in approach to its differential diagnosis. The pathophysiologic mechanisms of the cardiac, cirrhotic and renal (nephritic and nephrotic syndromes) edemas were detailed highlighting the alterations of the mechanisms of control of the effective arterial volume.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Edema é definido como acúmulo de fluido no espaço intersticial. Nesta revisão, discutem-se os mecanismos formadores de edemas localizados e dos grandes edemas (generalizados), assim como aspectos semiológicos, empregados em seu diagnóstico diferencial. São detalhados os mecanismos patofisiológicos dos edemas cardíaco, cirrótico e renal (síndromes nefrítica e nefrótica) com destaque para as alterações dos mecanismos de controle do volume arterial efetivo.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/496</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i3/4p189-198</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 3/4 (2004); 189-198</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 3/4 (2004); 189-198</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 3/4 (2004); 189-198</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/496/495</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/497</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:SIMSEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Dispnéia</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Dyspnea</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Martinez, José Antônio Baddini</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Padua, Adriana Inacio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Terra Filho, João</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Dyspnea. Symptoms. Respiration. Physiopathology.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dispnéia. Respiração. Sintomas. Fisiopatologia.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Dispnéia é o termo usado para designar a sensação de dificuldade respiratória, experimentada por pacientes acometidos por diversas moléstias, e indivíduos sadios, em condições de exercício extremo. Ela é um sintoma muito comum na prática médica, sendo particularmente referida por indivíduos com moléstias dos aparelhos respiratório e cardiovascular. Esse sintoma é o principal fator limitante da qualidade de vida relacionada à saúde de pacientes pneumopatas crônicos. Apesar de sua importância, os mecanismos envolvidos com seu surgimento ainda não são completamente conhecidos. Neste artigo, os autores fazem uma pequena revisão de aspectos clínicos e fisiopatológicos desse sintoma.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Dyspnea is a word used to define a sensation of breathing difficulty experimented by patients with different diseases, and healthy individuals during extreme exercise. It is a very common symptom in medical practice, and a particularly frequent complain among subjects with respiratory and cardiac conditions. Dyspnea is the most important symptom affecting health related quality of life of patients with chronic respiratory disorders. The mechanisms responsible for the development of dyspnea are still greatly unknown, despite of its importance. In the present article the authors do a brief review of clinical and physiopathological aspects related to the symptom.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/497</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i3/4p199-207</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 3/4 (2004); 199-207</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 3/4 (2004); 199-207</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 3/4 (2004); 199-207</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/497/496</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/499</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:SIMSEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Ausculta cardíaca: bases fisiológicas - fisiopatológicas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Cardiac auscultation: physiological and physiopathological mechanisms</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pazin-Filho, Antônio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schmidt, André</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Maciel, Benedito Carlos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Heart Auscultation. Heart Sounds.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Auscultação Cardíaca. Ruídos Cardíacos.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">São revistos os mecanismos básicos, determinantes dos sons cardíacos, normais e anormais, com ênfase nas suas implicações para a ausculta cardíaca à beira do leito.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The physiologic and physiopathological mechanisms of normal and abnormal heart sounds are reviewed, including their implications for bedside cardiac auscultation.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/499</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i3/4p208-226</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 3/4 (2004); 208-226</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 3/4 (2004); 208-226</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 3/4 (2004); 208-226</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/499/498</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/500</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:SIMSEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Semiologia cardiovascular: inspeção, palpação e percussão</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Cardiovascular examination: inspection, palpation and percussion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pazin-Filho, Antônio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schmidt, André</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Maciel, Benedito Carlos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cardiovascular System. Semiology. Pulse.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sistema Cardiovascular. Semiologia. Pulso Arterial.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A importância da avaliação da inspeção e da palpação do sistema cardiovascular é ressaltada. Procurou-se demonstrar a importância da interpretação dos dados obtidos na análise do ictus cordis, da perfusão periférica e dos pulsos arteriais e venosos para as diversas cardiopatias, sempre com o objetivo de sistematização.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The inspection and palpation of the physical examination of the cardiovascular system is emphatizated. The value of the analysis of the periferic perfusion and arterial and venous pulses for the systematic evaluation of the several cardiopathies is reinforced. &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/500</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i3/4p227-239</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 3/4 (2004); 227-239</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 3/4 (2004); 227-239</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 3/4 (2004); 227-239</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/500/499</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/501</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:12:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:SIMSEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Medida indireta da pressão arterial sistêmica</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Blood pressure measurement</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schmidt, André</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pazin Filho, Antônio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Maciel, Benedito Carlos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Blood Pressure</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">measurement. Semiology.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pressão Arterial</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">medição. Semiologia.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This article reviews the basis of indirect blood pressure measurement. The technical aspects, confounding factors and special situations, and the normal values supported by literature consensus are reviewed.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este artigo revisa a medição da pressão arterial através do método indireto. São discutidos a técnica de medida e fatores que interferem no método, situações especiais e os valores de referência com base nos consensos recentemente publicados.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/501</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v37i3/4p240-245</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 No. 3/4 (2004); 240-245</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 37 Núm. 3/4 (2004); 240-245</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 37 n. 3/4 (2004); 240-245</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/501/500</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2022-08-30T21:20:06Z" completeListSize="1467" cursor="275">e0e84e96b0f78589b66bc876dd6cffc3</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
