<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-08-29T21:20:23Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="rmrp">https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12699</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp%3A+Tra.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Índices de trauma</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Trauma severity indices</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pereira Júnior, Gerson Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Scarpelini, Sandro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Basile-Filho, Aníbal</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Andrade, José Ivan de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Trauma Severity Indices. Injury Severity Score. Abbreviated Injury Scale. Glasgow Coma Scale. Mortality.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Índices de Gravidade do Trauma. Escala de Gravidade do Ferimento. Escala Resumida de Ferimentos. Escala de Coma de Glasgow. Mortalidade.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A caracterização e documentação dos vários graus de lesões traumáticas são os requisitos básicos para a avaliação do sistema de atendimento ao trauma e para o desenvolvimento de iniciativas para o seu controle. Os índices de trauma são valores matemáticos ou estatísticos, quantificados por escores numéricos, que variam de acordo com a intensidade e os tipos de lesões decorrentes do traumatismo, medidos através de parâmetros anatômicos e fisiológicos. Tais índices representam uma importante e essencial ferramenta para estudos clínicos em trauma. Este artigo descreve vários dos índices de trauma mais comumente utilizados e suas aplicações.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Characterization and documentation of injury severity are requirements for the evaluation of trauma systems and development of iniciatives in injury control. Many indices employing measures of physiologic or anatomic derangement have been developed to quantify injury severity. Trauma scores represent na important and essential tool for clinical studies in trauma besides their use in the characterization of preventable deaths. This article describes several of the more commonly used indices and their applications.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12699</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i3p237-250</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 3 (1999); 237-250</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 3 (1999); 237-250</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 3 (1999); 237-250</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12699/14477</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12700</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp%3A+Tra.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O papel do anestesiologista no atendimento do trauma</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Anesthesiologists role in trauma management</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Slullitel, Alexandre</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sousa, Angela Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fraga, Adilson de Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Heart. Resuscitation. Traumatology. Fluid Therapy. Anesthesia.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Coração. Ressuscitação. Traumatologia. Hidratação. Anestesia.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The role for the anesthetist in multiprofessional trauma team has increased in the last few years. This paper reviews the role of the specialist concerning the pre-hospital and hospital management extended to the rehabilitation period. Methods of airway management, fluid therapy, monitoring and anesthetic drugs use are discussed. Postoperative analgesia as a way to reduce postoperative morbidity and mortality and reduce hospital stays costs is shown .</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O papel do anestesiologista, dentro da equipe de atendimento multiprofissional no trauma, tem aumentado progressivamente nos últimos anos. Esta revisão aborda o papel do especialista tanto em relação ao atendimento pré quanto intra-hospitalar até a fase de reabilitação do trauma. Métodos de controle da via aérea, reposição volêmica, monitorização e uso de drogas anestésicas no traumatizado são discutidos. A analgesia pós-operatória é apresentada como método de redução da morbimortalidade pós-operatória com diminuição dos custos de internação hospitalar .</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12700</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i3p251-261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 3 (1999); 251-261</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 3 (1999); 251-261</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 3 (1999); 251-261</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12700/14478</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12701</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp%3A+Tra.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Pediatric trauma patient</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Trauma no paciente pediátrico</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pereira Junior, Gerson Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Andreghetto, Ana Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Basile-Filho, Aníbal</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Andrade, José Ivan de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lesões. Pediatria. Traumatologia.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pediatrics. Injuries. Traumatology.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The purpose of this chapter is to present those principles of care that impact the integrity of the airway, breathing, and circulation or influence the priorities of advanced trauma life support for the pediatric trauma patient. Assessment and treatment decisions must be made quickly to prevent progression and deterioration to respiratory failure and cardiopulmonary arrest. Definitive evaluation and initial treatment of most other injuries can be safely undertaken after ventilation, oxygenation, and perfusion have been restored. Such definitive care is provided upon completion of the secondary survey, a detailed head-to-toe examination for detection of specific injuries.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este artigo revê os princípios do atendimento inicial ao traumatizado pediátrico, após uma revisão das características específicas da anatomia e fisiologia na infância. Aborda as diferentes situações através das quais o traumatizado pediátrico pode se apresentar e discute as opções que existem em cada fase do atendimento primário, bem como delineia os cuidados definitivos em lesões de alguns sistemas específicos.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12701</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i3p262-281</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 3 (1999); 262-281</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 3 (1999); 262-281</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 3 (1999); 262-281</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12701/14479</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 1999 Gerson Alves Pereira Junior, Ana Claudia Andreghetto, Aníbal Basile-Filho, José Ivan de Andrade</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12702</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp%3A+Tra.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Atendimento à gestante traumatizada</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Trauma in pregnancy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pereira Júnior, Gerson Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Haikel Júnior, Luiz Fernando</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Atique, João Marcos Camillo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nakamura, Ernani Jodi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Basile-Filho, Aníbal</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Andrade, José Ivan de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Injuries. Pregnancy. Cesarean Section. Fetal Death. Abdominal Injuries. Domestic Violence.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lesões. Gravidez. Cesárea. Morte Fetal. Traumatismos Abdominais. Violência Doméstica.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The priorities for management of the pregnant patient are no different than those of the nonpregnancy patient. It is important to follow a methodic evaluation that ensures complete assessment and stabilization of the mother. The mother should be stabilized before the stabilization of the fetus. The physiologic and anatomic changes during the pregnancy can influence outcome. Continuous fetal and maternal monitoring may be necessary. This article discuss about blunt and penetrating abdominal trauma, peritoneal lavage and indications of exploratory laparotomy. Cardiopulmonary resuscitation in pregnancy and perimortem cesarean delivery is considered. Indicators may suggest the presence of domestic violence and should serve to initiate further investigation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este artigo faz uma revisão das alterações anatômicas e fisiológicas que ocorrem durante a gestação e estabelece os princípios da abordagem à gestante traumatizada, delineando os aspectos da monitorização materna e fetal e as patologias próprias da gestação. Diferenciam-se os traumas contusos e penetrantes, discutindo-se o papel do lavado peritoneal diagnóstico e da laparotomia exploradora. Discutem-se a abordagem da gestante em parada cardiorrespiratória e as indicações de cesárea perimorte, bem como os indícios de violência doméstica.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12702</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i3p282-289</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 3 (1999); 282-289</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 3 (1999); 282-289</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 3 (1999); 282-289</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12702/14480</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12703</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Sangria terapêutica</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Therapeutic phlebotomy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Angulo, Ivan L.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Papa, Fábio V.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cardoso, Fernanda G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Phlebotomy. Polycythemia. Hemochromatosis. Therapeutics. Bloodletting.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Flebotomia. Policitemia. Hemocromatose. Terapêutica. Sangria.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A sangria terapêutica é método paliativo de controle de sintomas, simples e antigo, que se mostra eficaz também a longo prazo, melhorando a expectativa e a qualidade de vida. Suas indicações ampliaram-se atualmente e pode ser combinada com outras modalidades terapêuticas. Pode ser utilizada no controle da hiperviscosidade sangüínea nas eritrocitoses, e para a remoção de produto metabólico ou de depósito, tóxicos ao organismo. No Hemocentro, em Ribeirão Preto, as retiradas por eritrocitose representam a grande maioria, sendo 42% póstransplante renal, 30% por doenças cardíacas e pulmonares e 15% por Policitemia Vera. As retiradas por produtos metabólicos e/ou tóxicos acumulados foram 9% na hemocromatose e 4% nas porfirias. Não foram notados efeitos colaterais e os valores alvo do hematócrito foram considerados adequados nas eritrocitoses. As retiradas periódicas levaram a bom controle sintomático dos pacientes. São feitas sugestões de estratégias de condutas, consideradas adequadas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Therapeutic phlebotomy is an old and simple way to relieve sintoms but can raize life spectancy and bring better quality of life. It is incrisingly indicated nowadays, alone or in combination with others therapeutic tools. It can be used to control high blood viscosity in polycythemias or washout of toxic metabolic products or iron in parenquimal cells. At Hemocentro, in Ribeirão Preto, polycythemias were the most common indication for bloodletting, 42% after kidney transplants, 30% by lung and heart diseases, and 15% by polycythemia vera. Toxic metabolic products motivated bloodletting in 9% by iron overload and 4% by porphyria. No adverse efects were noted, target hematocrits were considered adequate in polycythemias and periodic bloodletting exerced an effective control of symptoms. Sugestions were made for better medical practices.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12703</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i3p290-293</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 3 (1999); 290-293</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 3 (1999); 290-293</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 3 (1999); 290-293</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12703/14481</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12704</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Um estudo diferencial sobre crenças de portadores do vírus da imunodeficiência humana (HIV), relacionadas ao enfrentamento psicológico das condições de contágio</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">A differential study about beliefs of persons infected by the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), related to the psychological coping with the conditions of the contagion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Figueiredo, Marco Antonio de Castro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Terenzi, Natalia Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Machado, Alcyone Artioli</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Internal-External Control. Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome. HIV.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Controle Interno-Externo. Síndrome de Imunodeficiência Adquirida. HIV.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo:&amp;nbsp;estudo diferencial.&amp;nbsp;Objetivo: o impacto da Síndrome de Imunodeficiência Adquirida (aids) sobre a integridade afetiva de portadores e pacientes sintomáticos exacerba, na pessoa atendida, sentimentos de insegurança e de perda do domínio sobre a situação em que o atendimento se efetua. Este fato se reflete na resposta do paciente ao tratamento, incidindo de forma negativa sobre sua aderência aos procedimentos prescritos: assim, o conhecimento prévio sobre a maneira com que o paciente avalia as causas da doença e os recursos de que ele próprio dispõe para enfrentá-la constituem um referencial de grande importância para a concepção de estratégias de atendimento. Neste sentido, este estudo foi delineado com o objetivo de verificar as diferentes formas com que o enfrentamento psicológico das condições do contágio pelo HIV se manifesta em pessoas com aids.&amp;nbsp;Metodologia: este trabalho foi delineado, compreendendo dois estudos: a) trinta (30) portadores do HIV, sintomáticos ou não, com idades variando entre dezenove (19) e cinqüenta e nove (59) anos, foram avaliados através da Escala de Locus de Controle de Levenson, permitindo classificá-los em três categorias: internos,&amp;nbsp;teleológicos, cujo controle emana de um poder superior ou vontade divina; b) posteriormente, quarenta (40) pacientes sintomáticos, atendidos em clínicas públicas e particulares, foram avaliados através de uma adaptação da escala de Levenson, contextualizada para a aids. Resultados:&amp;nbsp;para ambos os estudos, considerando os sujeitos definidos pelas variáveis idade e religião, não foram identificados subgrupos diferenciais&amp;nbsp;(p&amp;gt;.05). No primeiro estudo, prevaleceram respostas da externalidade conjugadas à teleologia, nas mulheres,&amp;nbsp;(.59+.17&amp;gt;.17+.08; p&amp;lt;.001); no segundo, foi verificada uma menor propensão à teleologia&amp;nbsp;entre os usuários de serviços particulares, quando comparados aos de serviços públicos&amp;nbsp;(-.32&amp;lt;+.12; p&amp;lt;.001),&amp;nbsp;além de uma maior internalidade nestes últimos.&amp;nbsp;(+.44&amp;gt;+.26; p=.02). Conclusões: tais resultados apontam algumas características distintivas entre os sujeitos quanto à auto-responsabilização e às crenças de razão necessária sobre problemas relacionados à aids. Considerando estas diferenças, foram discutidas algumas características que poderiam nortear&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;futuras estratégias de orientação, subsidiárias ao tratamento clínico da aids. &amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study Model: these results indicate some distinctive characteristics among subjects in terms of self-responsibility and beliefs of a necessary reason about problems related to aids. Considering these differences, some characteristics are discussed which may guide future subsidiary orientation strategies for the clinical treatment of aids.: a differential study.&amp;nbsp;Objective:&amp;nbsp;the impact of Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome (aids) on the affective integrity of carriers and symptomatic patients exacerbates patient feelings of insecurity and of loss of control over the situation during which care is provided. This fact reflects on patient response to treatment, with a negative influence on his compliance with prescribed procedures: thus, previous knowledge about the way the patient evaluates the causes of the disease and his own resources to cope with it represents a reference framework of great importance for the conception of care strategies. In this respect, the present study was designed in order to determine the different forms of psychological coping with HIV contagion by persons with aids.&amp;nbsp;Methodology:&amp;nbsp;the present investigation consisted of two studies: A) 30 patients with HIV, symptomatic or not, ranging in age from 19 to 59 years were evaluated by the Control Locus Scale of Levenson which permitted their classification into three categories: internal (whose control is attributed to the person itself), external (whose control is exerted by stronger others or by the context), and teleologic (whose control emanates from a superior power or divine will). B) In a second study, 40 symptomatic patients seen at public and private clinics were evaluated by an adaptation of the Levenson scale contextualized for aids.&amp;nbsp;Results:&amp;nbsp;differential subgroups were identified (p&amp;gt;.05). In the first study there was a prevalence of externality responses conjugated with teleology among women (.59+,17&amp;gt;+.08; p&amp;lt;.001); in the second there was less propensity to teleology among users of private services compared to users of public services (-.32&amp;lt;+.12; p&amp;lt;.001), as well as a greater internality among the latter (+.44&amp;gt;+.26; p=.02).&amp;nbsp;Conclusions&amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12704</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i3p294-302</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 3 (1999); 294-302</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 3 (1999); 294-302</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 3 (1999); 294-302</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12704/14482</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12705</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Contribuição ao estudo das afecções pulmonares nas autópsias pediátricas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Contribution to the study of pulmonary pediatric pathology in autopsies</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Peres, Luiz C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moraes, Fábio A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yukita, César M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pediatrics. Lung Diseases.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pneumopatias. Pediatria.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo: estudo retrospectivo. Objetivos: determinar a freqüência de algumas das principais afecções pulmonares, pediátricas, com base na casuística de autópsias do Serviço de Patologia do HCFMRP-USP, comparando-a com a literatura, a fim de produzir um texto com informações atualizadas, que possa servir de orientação ao estudo dos problemas, principalmente para alunos de graduação. Metodologia: foram analisados os seguintes dados de quinhentas e cinco (505) autópsias pediátricas, realizadas no Serviço de Patologia do HCFMRP-USP, entre junho de 1993 e junho de 1996: sexo, idade gestacional, idade no momento da morte, peso corporal, causa da morte, peso e alterações pulmonares (petéquias, hemorragias, defeitos de lobação, hipoplasia, pneumonia, pneumotórax, hemotórax, derrame pleural, enfisema intersticial, doença da membrana hialina, displasia broncopulmonar e atelectasia). O programa Epi-Info, versão 6, foi usado para a tabulação dos dados e análise estatística, e os resultados, comparados com a literatura. Resultados: o sexo masculino predominou (53,7%) sobre o feminino (45,9%) e indeterminado(0,4%). A maior parte do óbitos ocorreu no período neonatal precoce (47%), intra-uterino (19%) e neonatal tardio (7%), somando 73% de todos os casos. A idade gestacional variou de dezesseis (16) a quarenta e três) 43 semanas. Prematuridade foi a causa de morte mais freqüente (29,7%), seguida pelas anomalias congênitas (10,9%), anoxia intra-uterina (8,3%), infecções (8,1%), causas perinatais (2,4%), isoimunização (1,8%), neoplasias (0,4%) e outras (38,4%). As afecções pulmonares mais comuns foram: petéquias (49,1%), hemorragia maciça (34,5%), derrame pleural (29,5%), doença da membrana hialina (25,6%), atelectasia (24,6%), pneumonia (16,8%), pneumotórax (10,8%), lobação anormal (8,6%), enfisema intersticial (5%), hipoplasia (4,4%) e displasia broncopulmonar (2,4%). Conclusões: as afecções pulmonares são muito freqüentes nas autópsias pediátricas, representando, muitas vezes, a causa da morte e estão, de uma forma geral, de acordo com as freqüências encontradas na literatura, havendo, no entanto, algumas variações que, possivelmente, refletem diferenças na atenção pré e perinatal, nos diferentes países. As alterações pulmonares identificadas estão, em sua maioria, relacionadas à prematuridade e anomalias congênitas, que representam um terço de todos os óbitos, constituindo-se nos grupos cuja redução traria os maiores benefícios médicos e sócio-econômicos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study model: retrospective study. Objectives: The aim of the present study was to determine the frequency of some of the main pediatric pulmonary diseases among the autopsiesperformed at the Serviço de Patologia do HCFMRP-USP, compared to the pertinent literature in order to compose an updated text which could help mainly undergraduate students in understanding such problems. Methodology: The following data retrieved from the files of 505 pediatric autopsies performed between June 1993 and June 1996 were analyzed: sex, gestational age, age at death, body weight, cause of death, weight and pulmonary problems (petechiae, hemorrhage, lobation defects, hypoplasia, pneumonia, pneumothorax, hemothorax, pleural effusion, interstitial emphysema, hyaline membrane disease, bronchopulmonary dysplasia and atelectasia). The Epi-Info-6 program was used to tabulate and analyze the data. Results: Males predominated over female and indeterminate sex (53.7%; 45.9% and 0.4%, respectively). Most of the deaths were observed in the early neonatal (47%), intra-uterine (19%) and late neonatal (7%), periods, performing 73% of all cases and gestational age ranged from 16 to 43 weeks. Prematurity was the most frequent cause of death (29.7%), followed by congenital anomalies (10.9%), intrauterine anoxia (8.3%), infections (8.1%), perinatal causes (2.4%), isoimmunization (1.8%), neoplasia (0.4%) and other causes (38.4%). The pulmonary problems found were petechiae (49.1%), massive hemorrhage (34.5%), pleural effusion (29.5%), hyaline membrane disease (25.6%), atelectasia (24.6%), pneumonia (16.8%), pneumothorax (10.8%), lobation defects (8.6%), interstitial emphysema (5%), hypoplasia (4.4%) and bronchopulmonary dysplasia (2.4%). Conclusions: Pulmonary problems are very common in pediatric autopsies and frequently represent the cause of death. Their frequency is similar to that reported in the pertinent literature and the variations possibly reflect the differences in pre and perinatal care in the different countries. Most of the pulmonary alterations found are linked to prematurity and congenital anomalies, corresponding to a third of the cases. Reduction of the frequency of these groups would have an important medical and socio-economic impact.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12705</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i3p303-315</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 3 (1999); 303-315</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 3 (1999); 303-315</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 3 (1999); 303-315</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12705/14486</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12710</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:DMT</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da assistência médica prestada no ambulatório da liga de combate às DST/AIDS - centro de saúde, S.P., 1994-1997</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of the care provided by the outpatient clinic of the league of combat against STD/AIDS, health center, S.P., 1994-1997</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ramos, Deborah M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Turco, Fábio de P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moraes, Daniela A. de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cavalli, Ricardo C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Xavier, Naiara F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Forster, Aldaisa C.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Outcome and Process Assessment (Health Care). Medical Care. Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação de Processos e Resultados (Cuidados de Saúde). Assistência Médica. Educação Médica.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este trabalho analisou a assistência médica prestada pelos alunos da Liga de Combate a DST/AIDS, da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto - USP, no curso de três anos emeio, junto ao Programa de Prevenção e Controle de Aids do Centro de Saúde Escola. Foi utilizada a metodologia de avaliação em saúde (processo e resultados), que contemplou o estudo da assistência médica em um período contínuo de seguimento, sendo analisados os diagnósticos formulados, os exames laboratoriais e complementares prescritos, as medidas curativas e de promoção da saúde e prevenção de doenças. Foram estudados sessenta e seis (66) indivíduos, sendo 48,5% comunicantes de portadores do Vírus da Imunodeficiência Humana ou de doentes de aids, 27,3% portadores do HIV e 24,2% de doentes de aids. Houve maioria de pacientes masculinos, embora a relação homem:mulher cresça de 1:1, 2:1 e 3,5:1 no sentido comunicantes, portadores e doentes, com uma frequência modal de 40,9% na faixa etária de trinta (30) e trinta e nove (39) anos, o grau de escolaridade e as ocupações foram característicos de nível socioeconômico baixo. Formularam-se diagnósticos de deficiência da imunidade celular, exposição a doenças transmissíveis (aids, tuberculose e outras doenças infecciosas), infecções respiratórias agudas, doenças sexualmente transmissíveis, parasitoses, entre as principais. Em média, a clientela permaneceu 3,2 meses em seguimento, recebeu 2,4 consultas e 47,7% dela abandonouo atendimento. Os alunos participaram ativamente da pesquisa; a metodologia e as informações quantitativas contribuíram para a avaliação da qualidade da assistência médica, tendo o serviço de saúde correspondido como alternativa institucional para formação e assistência mais próxima da comunidade.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The medical care provided by the students of the League of Combat against STD/AIDS belonging to the Faculty of Medicine of Ribeirão Preto - USP over a period of three and a half years was evaluated. We used the method of health evaluation based on the study of medical care during a continuous period of monitoring. The aim was to assess the quality of the care provided, analyzed in terms of the diagnoses formulated, of laboratory and complementary tests, of curative measures and of health promotion and disease prevention. A total of 66 individuals were studied, 48.5% of them being communicants of patients with HIV and AIDS, 27.3% HIVinfected patients, and 24.2% patients with AIDS. Most patients were males, although the man:woman ratio has been growing from 1:1, 2:1 and 3.5:1 in the following order: communicants, infected subjects and patients, with a modal frequency of 40.9% in the 30 to 39 year age range. Educational level and occupation were characteristic of a low socioeconomic level. The followingdiagnoses were made: cell immune deficiency; contacts with patients with aids, tuberculosis and other infectious diseases; infectious respiratory disease; sexually transmitted diseases; and parasitosis. The clients were followed up on average for a period of 3.2 months and received 2.4 visits, and 47.7% of them abandoned treatment. The students participated actively in the research, the methodology and the quantitative information obtained permitted the assessment of the quality of care, with the health service corresponding to the expectations for an institutional alternative for training and for providing care closer to the community.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12710</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i3p326-334</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 3 (1999); 326-334</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 3 (1999); 326-334</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 3 (1999); 326-334</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12710/14491</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12714</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:TEM</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Ensino clínico na comunidade</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Clinical teaching in community health services</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Troncon, Luiz de Ernesto Almeida</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Students</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical. Schools</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical. Community Network. Community Health Services. Education</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudantes de Medicina. Escolas Médicas. Redes Comunitárias. Serviços de Saúde Comunitária. Educação Médica.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">No curso de graduação em Medicina a mudança do eixo do ensino clínico do hospital universitário para a rede de serviços de saúde na comunidade, constitui, atualmente, uma forte tendência no campo da Educação Médica. Busca-se, com isto, a construção de um novo paradigma de atuação médica, mais adequado às necessidades do público. Esta proposição apresenta justificativas conceituais válidas, tanto do ponto de vista médico como do educacional, e oferece vantagens potenciais para o aprendizado dos estudantes. A proposta de mudança sofre, porém, no interior das escolas médicas, resistências de ordem variada, sobretudo de ordem cultural; a sua implementação encontra, ainda, inúmeras dificuldades práticas. A superação destes obstáculos constitui uma difícil tarefa, que deve envolver não só a escola médica, mas, também, o governo e as entidades médicas. Medidas efetivas de apoio ao ensino clínico na comunidade devem contemplar o fortalecimento do sistema nacional de saúde e a valorização do trabalho dos médicos junto à comunidade.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Moving undergraduate clinical teaching from university hospitals to communitybased services is currently accepted as a strong trend in Medical Education. The main purpose of this change is to build a new model of medical action, which is though to be more suitable to public needs. Community-oriented clinical teaching is justifiable not only as the basis of this new model, but also on educational grounds, since it is thought to have many potencial advantages regarding student learning. There are, however, several cultural factors opposing the acceptance of community-oriented clinical teaching within medical schools. Also, the implementation of the relevant student activities is made difficult by a number of practical reasons. Breaking barriers and overcoming difficulties is a complex task, which should involve medical schools as well as the government and medical councils and associations. Effective actions in support of communitybased clinical teaching must include the strenghtening of the national health system and the valorization of physician’s work in community services.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12714</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i3p335-344</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 3 (1999); 335-344</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 3 (1999); 335-344</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 3 (1999); 335-344</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12714/14495</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12715</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:RESH</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Evocando a XIII semana de debates científicos - Ribeirão Preto, 1959: subsídios para a história do centro acadêmico "Rocha Lima"</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evoking the 13th week of scientific debates - Ribeirão Preto, 1959: subsidies for the history of the academic center "Rocha Lima"</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, José Alberto Mello de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Academic Medical Centers. Congress. Students</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical. Schools</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">history.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Centro Médicos Acadêmicos. Congressos. Estudantes de Medicina. Escolas Médicas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">história.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">During the fifties the “Semanas Brasileiras de Debates Científicos” were important events that assembled undergraduate students in Medicine coming together from all around Brazil to report and discuss the results of their scientific initiation research work done out of the curricular graduate studies. This paper evokes the congress organized in Ribeirão Preto (São Paulo State, Brazil) during 1959 by the Centro Acadêmico ‘Rocha Lima’, the local representative association of students in Medicine and where participate some of the current days more prominents brazilian scientists.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Durante a década de cinqüenta, as Semanas Brasileiras de Debates Científicos representaram um importante evento, que reunia estudantes de medicina de todo o Brasil, paraapresentar e discutir trabalhos de pesquisa realizados como atividade extra-curricular de iniciação científica. Este texto recorda o congresso organizado pelo Centro Acadêmico Rocha Lima,em Ribeirão Preto, no ano de 1959, do qual participaram alguns estudantes que estão hoje entre pesquisadores brasileiros de nomeada.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12715</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i3p345-350</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 3 (1999); 345-350</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 3 (1999); 345-350</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 3 (1999); 345-350</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12715/14496</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12716</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Complicações locais pós-injeções intramusculares em adultos: revisão bibliográfica</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Site adverse reactions after intramuscular injections in adults: review of literature</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cassiani, Silvia H. de B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rangel, Silvia M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Injections</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Intramuscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">complications.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Injeções Intramusculares</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">complicações.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Trata-se de um “survey” descritivo, com o objetivo de verificar os estudos das áreas médica e de enfermagem, que tratam da temática: complicações pós-injeções intramusculares, publicados no período de janeiro de 1970 a agosto de 1997. Foi realizado levantamento bibliográfico, através dos bancos de dados MEDLINE E LILACS. Os artigos foram catalogados em fichas individuais e analisados de acordo com complicações relatadas, causas apontadas, número de casos e tipo de medicação utilizada. Foram encontrados dezoito artigos abordando a temática. A reação adversa mais relatada foi a dor, embora dos seiscentos e setenta (670) casos de pacientes investigados, 61 (sessenta e um) apresentaram os tipos mais diversos de complicações, tais como manchas avermelhadas no local, hipertemia, edema e outros. Na amostra investigada, não houve artigos descrevendo complicações na região ventroglútea, o que permite sugerir que isso deve ser a região prioritária de aplicação de injeções intramusculares. A técnica de aplicação das injeções é importante e exige atenção e cuidados de todos os profissionais, não devendo ser utilizada por pessoas sem orientação técnica e científica.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This study was a descriptive survey. The objetive was to verify the medical and nursing literature published between January, 1970 and August, 1997 about adverse reactions afterintramuscular injections. The MEDLINE and LILACS databases were used. The articles were classified into individual bases and analyzed following the complications cited, causes, number of cases and the medication used. It was found eighteen articles. The adverse reaction more cited was pain, although others reactions were cited as dermatitis, fever and others. In the investigated sample there were not articles describing adverse reactions in the ventro-glútea site. This confirms that it isthe best site of intramuscular injections. The technique of the intramuscular injections is very important and it is necessary attention, responsibility, scientific and technical knowledge of the professionals.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12716</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i4p444-450</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 4 (1999); 444-450</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 4 (1999); 444-450</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 4 (1999); 444-450</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12716/14497</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12717</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Fluid, electrolyte and acid-base disorders: a practical review</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Distúrbios do equilíbrio hidroeletrolítico e do equilíbrio acidobásico: uma revisão prática</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Évora, Paulo Roberto B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reis, Celso Luís dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferez, Marcus A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Conte, Denise A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Garcia, Luís Vicente</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fluid. Water. Electrolytes. Acidosis. Alkalosis. Acid-base Equilibrium. Water-Eletrolyte Balance.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Água. Eletrólitos. Acidose. Alcalose. Equilíbrio acidobásico. Equilibrio hidroeletrolítico.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O equilíbrio hidroeletrolítico e o equilíbrio acidobásico são assuntos de importância para todas as especialidades. Porém, seu entendimento prático é, por vezes, revestido de variados graus de dificuldades. No presente texto apresenta-se o assunto apenas como uma visão prática, adquirida emmais de vinte (20) anos de ensino para estudantes, médicos residentes e médicos pósgraduandos. O texto tem apenas a pretensão didática, sem nenhuma preocupação acadêmica.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Fluid, electrolyte and acid-base disorders are very important subjects for all medical specialties . But their practical learning is, sometimes, very difficult. This text intends to discuss this subject based on more than 20 years of didatic experience teaching medical students, medical residents and post-doctoral students. The text has only didatic pretensions without any academic purpose.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12717</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i4p451-469</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 4 (1999); 451-469</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 4 (1999); 451-469</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 4 (1999); 451-469</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12717/14498</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12718</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Transfusão de granulócitos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Granulocyte transfusion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Santis, Gil Cunha De</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Granulocytes. Neutropenia.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Granulócitos. Neutropenia.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Neutropenic patients are susceptible to severe bacterial and fungal infections. Besides the antibiotic therapy it is possible to transfuse granulocyte to these patients to control septicemia. The granulocytes are colected from normal donors submitted to corticosteroids and/ or citokines (G-CSF) administration in order to increase the number of the granulocytes in peripheral blood. The minimal recommended dose is 1 x 1010 granulocytes per transfusion.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Pacientes neutropênicos são susceptíveis a infecção bacteriana e fúngica. Além da antibioticoterapia, pode-se transfundir granulócitos a esses pacientes. A coleta de granulócitos é feita de doadores normais aos quais foram administrados corticosteróides e/ou fatores de crescimento (G-CSF) para induzir neutrofilia em sangue periférico e aumentar o rendimento da coleta por aférese. A dose transfusional recomendada é de, pelo menos, 1 x 1010/ dia, até o controle da infecção.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12718</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i4p470-477</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 4 (1999); 470-477</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 4 (1999); 470-477</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 4 (1999); 470-477</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12718/14499</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12719</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The importance of the use of filters during the infusion of parenteral nutrition containing lipid emulsions</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A importância do uso de filtros, durante a infusão de nutrições parenterais adicionadas de emulsões lipídicas</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sakamoto, Luiz M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alcântara, Sírlei T. de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Passos, Nilva M. R. R. S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hotta, Júlia K. S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marchini, Júlio S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Filtration. Parenteral Nutrition. Emulsions.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Filtração. Nutrição Parenteral. Emulsões.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Nutrições parenterais com adicionamento de emulsões lipídicas podem apresentar alterações físico-químicas, caracterizadas pela formação de precipitados amorfos ou cristalinos, bem como pelo aumento do tamanho das gotículas de gordura que se agregam. A verificação macroscópica dessas alterações nem sempre é possível, tendo em vista o aspecto opaco das emulsões. Utilizando-se estudo in vitro, este trabalho teve como objetivo evidenciar a presença de precipitados de fosfato de cálcio, de gotículas de gordura da emulsão lipídica com diâmetros superiores aos de hemácias, em nutrições parenterais, e a importância do uso de filtros na retenção dos mesmos. Esses eventos foram demonstrados por meio de inspeção macroscópica e microscópica, em nutrições parenterais contendo fosfato dibásico de potássio e de gluconato de cálcio, como fonte de fósforo e de cálcio, respectivamente, adicionados à mistura de soluções de aminoácidos a 10% p/v, com glicose a 50% p/v, emulsão lipídica a 20% p/v e minerais em diferentes proporções. Os resultados mostraram presença de precipitado de cálcio e de gotículas de gordura aumentadas e/ou agregadas antes da filtração, e ausência dos mesmos imediatamente após. Conclusão: o uso de filtros com poros de 1,2 mm foi capaz de reter precipitados e de impedir a passagem das gotículas de gordura com dimensões tais que pudessem causar embolias microvasculares em pacientes submetidos à nutrição parenteral.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Parenteral nutrition preparations supplemented with lipid emulsions may present physicochemical alterations characterized by the formation of amorphous or crystalline precipitates and by an increased size of fat droplets, which aggregate. A macroscopic verification of these changes is not always possible because of the opaque aspect of the emulsions. The objective of the present in vitro study was to determine the presence of calcium phosphate precipitates, of fat droplets of the lipid emulsion with wider diameters than red blood cells in parenteral nutrition preparations and the importance of the use of filters for the retention of suchprecipitates. These events were demonstrated by macroscopic and microscopic inspection of parenteral nutrition preparations containing potassium dibasic phosphate and calcium gluconate as a source of phosphorus and calcium, respectively, added to the mixture of amino acid solutions at the proportion of 10% (w/v), with 50% glucose (w/v), a 20% lipid emulsion (w/v) and minerals at different proportions. The results showed the presence of a calcium precipitate and of enlarged and/or aggregated fat droplets before filtration, and their absence immediately after filtration. Conclusion:the use of filters with 1.2 mm pores was sufficient to retain the precipitates and to prevent the passage of fat droplets with dimensions that might cause microvascular embolism in patients submitted to parenteral nutrition.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12719</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i4p478-485</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 4 (1999); 478-485</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 4 (1999); 478-485</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 4 (1999); 478-485</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12719/14500</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12720</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Protocolos para tratamento da cefaléia aguda, em unidade de emergência</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Procedures for acute headache treatment in an emergency room</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bigal, Marcelo E.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bordini, Carlos A.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Speciali, José G.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Headache. Emergency Service Hospital. Clinical Protocols.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cefaléia. Serviço Hospitalar de Emergência. Protocolos Clínicos.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Importância do problema: cefaléia é dos sintomas mais comuns na prática clínica, responsável por cerca de 9% dos atendimentos em unidades primárias de saúde e por 1% a 3% dos atendimentos em unidades de emergência, acarretando, portanto, considerável impacto econômico sobre o serviço público de saúde.Comentários: a maioria das unidades de emergência, em nosso meio, não dispõem de drogas utilizadas em outros países para tratamento agudo da cefaléia, como os compostos ergotamínicosou triptanos. Os autores revisam aspectos diagnósticos e terapêuticos das cefaléias primárias agudas, propondo protocolos para seu tratamento em uma unidade de emergência.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Headache is one of the most common symptoms in the clinical practice and it is responsible for about 9% of the appointments in primary care units and for 1% to 3% in the emergency rooms, leading to a considerable economic impact in the public health care system. Most of the emergency rooms in Brazil does not have drugs, like ergotics compounds and tryptans, used in other countries for the acute treatment of headache. The authors make a review of the diagnostic and therapeutic aspects of the acute primary headaches, suggesting protocols for its treatment in an emergency unit.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12720</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i4p486-491</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 4 (1999); 486-491</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 4 (1999); 486-491</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 4 (1999); 486-491</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12720/14501</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12721</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:PV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Reflections about cross infections in the transition to the third millenium</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Reflexões acerca das infecções hospitalares às portas do terceiro milênio</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Andrade, Denise de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Angerami, Emília L. S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cross Infection. Asepsis. Infection Control.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Infecção Hospitalar. Assepsia. Controle de Infecções.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O presente estudo tem como meta primordial desencadear reflexões ou sensibilizar os profissionais de saúde no que tange às infecções hospitalares. As autoras apresentamuma síntese de fatos relevantes, associados à temática, bem como das disposições normativas de prevenção e de controle das infecções hospitalares no Brasil. Em seguida, mostrame analisam as perspectivas para o futuro. Alertam para a necessidade de uma pluralidade de ações, estruturada em recursos humanos e materiais, e reforçam a necessidade de se redimensionar a problemática das referidas infecções ao âmbito mais amplo da organização do sistema de saúde. Também, reforçam alguns cuidados: o uso indiscriminado de antimicrobianos, internações desnecessárias e por tempo prolongado. Sem dúvida, que a conscientização e a mudança de comportamento são condutas essenciais, frente a esse importante problema médico, social e econômico.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The present study has the main purpose of stimulating reflections of health professionals about cross infections. The authors present a synthesis of the relevant facts associated to the theme as well as of the regulations regarding the prevention and control of cross infections in Brazil. Following, they show and analyze the perspectives for the future. They point out the need for actions emphasizing human resources and materials as well as of understanding the problem in the broader context of the organization of the health system. They also give emphasis to some concerns: the indiscriminate use of antimicrobial products, unnecessary and long hospitalizations. Also, the awareness and change of behaviors are essential conducts in order to solve this important medical, social and economic problem.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12721</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i4p492-497</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 4 (1999); 492-497</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 4 (1999); 492-497</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 4 (1999); 492-497</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12721/14502</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/12723</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:NTI</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Homenagem: Prof.Dr. José Alberto Mello De Oliveira</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Roberto Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bueno, Regina Mara C. Faria</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12723</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i4p500-500</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 4 (1999); 500-500</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 4 (1999); 500-500</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 4 (1999); 500-500</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/12723/14503</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/13258</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:17:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevenção da aids: uso de preservativo e percepções de estudantes universitários</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Aids prevention: condom use and perceptions among college students</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Temporini, Edméa Rita</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bandeira, Antonio Carlos Albuquerque</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Medeiros, Maria do Carmo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">prevention. Condoms. Perception.Students.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Síndrome de Imunodeficiência Adquirida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">prevenção. Preservativos. Percepção.Estudantes.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Study design:&amp;nbsp;Analytical survey.&amp;nbsp;1) To get knowledge on college students’ perceptions and behavior concerning condom use for AIDS prevention; 2) to provide subsides for planning educational interventions.&amp;nbsp;Methods:&amp;nbsp;An exploratory study preceded the elaboration of the self-administered questionnaire employed for data collection. College students from three different cities of the State of São Paulo, Brazil integrated a convenient sample.&amp;nbsp;Results:&amp;nbsp;Seven hundred and eleven college students compounded the sample presenting the following characteristics: 43.0% were male students and 57.0%, female ones with ages varying from 17 to 32 years; 65.4% of the males and 43.9% of the females stated having had previous sexual intercourse. Research data disclosed the majority of them as having a reduced or regular risk perception level of getting AIDS/HIV; students of both genders declared their distrust regarding the efficacy of preventive measures. They reported having a low level of confidency condom use and a high level of confidence in a well-known sexual partner as a means for avoiding HIV/AIDS.&amp;nbsp;An increment in the number of researches on social and cultural components associated to risk behaviors regarding AIDS/HIV infection is mandatory in order to guide the planning for further educational interventions aimed to control AIDS/HIV epidemic.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo do estudo:&amp;nbsp;Pesquisa analítica. Objetivos: 1) Conhecer percepções e conduta de estudantes universitários, relacionadas ao uso de preservativo para evitar a AIDS; 2) subsidiar o planejamento de intervenções educativas. Métodos:&amp;nbsp;Elaborou-se questionário auto-aplicável, com base em estudo exploratório. A amostra foi composta por estudantes de facudades de três cidades do Estado de São Paulo, Brasil, e obtida por critério de conveniência. Resultados:&amp;nbsp;Integraram a amostra setecentos e onze (711) estudantes que apresentaram as seguintes características: 43,0% do sexo masculino e 57,0% do sexo feminino, idades entre 17 e 32 anos, 65,4% dos homens e 43,9% das mulheres declararam terem tido relação sexual. A maioria revelou grau reduzido ou médio de percepção do risco de contrair AIDS; estudantes de ambos os sexos manifestaram desconfiança em relação à eficácia de medidas preventivas. Relataram baixa credibilidade no uso de preservativo e alto grau de confiança em parceiro sexual conhecido, para evitar a AIDS. Conclusão:&amp;nbsp;Considera-se necessário incrementar a realização de pesquisas de componentes sociais e culturais associados à conduta de risco, a fim de direcionar o planejamento de intervenções educativas com vistas ao controle da epidemia de AIDS.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1999-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/13258</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v32i3p316-325</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 No. 3 (1999); 316-325</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 32 Núm. 3 (1999); 316-325</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 32 n. 3 (1999); 316-325</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/13258/15076</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/16140</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-11T12:15:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:REV</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Peso ao nascer e crescimento físico do lactente</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Birthweight and infant growth</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Barros Filho, Antonio de Azevedo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barbieri, Marco Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gutierrez, Manoel Romeu Pereira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bettiol, Heloisa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ricco, Rubens Garcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Birth Weight</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Infant Growth</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Height Weight</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Peso ao Nascer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Crescimento-Lactante</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Peso-Estatura</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This review is aimed at discussing the birthweight on subsequent growth of the infant. The authors discuss some factors related to birthweight, growth of the infant, and the catch-up growth of the low-birthweight ones, described in the international literature, and then they describe some Brazilian researchs. They call the attention for some controvertial points found in the literature and for the lack of researchs on this issue in Brazil.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Esta revisão objetiva discutir a influência do peso ao nascer sobre o crescimento do lactente. Os autores analisam e discutem alguns fatores relacionados com o peso, ao nascer, ao crescimento, à recuperação do crescimento dos recém-nascidos de baixo peso, descritos na literatura internacional, e descrevem alguns estudos brasileiros. Chamam a atenção para alguns pontos controvertidos na literatura, bem como para o pequeno números de pesquisas desenvolvidos no Brasil.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1996-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16140</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v29i2/3p258-268</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 29 No. 2/3 (1996); 258-268</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 29 Núm. 2/3 (1996); 258-268</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 29 n. 2/3 (1996); 258-268</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16140/17754</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/16170</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:19:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ARTO</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perdas fetais e natimortalidade no município de Ribeirão Preto-sp, Brasil, 1991 e 1992</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Fetal mortality in Ribeirão Preto city, Brazil, 1991 and 1992</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sardas, Renato</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Manço, Amábile Rodrigues Xavier</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fetal Death. Fetal Mortality.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Morte Fetal. Mortalidade Fetal.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">No Município de Ribeirão Preto ocorreram 299 perdas fetais nos anos de 1991/92, sendo 165, em 1991, e 134, em 92, dos quais 148 eram masculinos, 134 femininos, 21 de sexo ignorado e 15 não declarados. Os óbitos fetais provenientes de outros municípios perfizeram 39,8% deste total. Em 103 Declarações de Óbito, o peso ao nascer não foi declarado. Com relação à duração de gestação, 142 casos (47,5%) tinham 28 ou + semanas, 52 (17,4%) situavam-se entre 20 e 27 semanas, em 105 casos (35,3%) a informação estava em branco ou assinalada como ignorada. A gestação única foi apontada em 46,8% dos casos e não declarada em 46,5%. A hipoxia intra-uterina foi apontada como causa básica de morte, em 41,8% dos casos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">A total of 299 fetal death occured in the Municipality of Ribeirão Preto in 1991/92, 165 in 1991 and 134 in 1992, 148 of which were boys and 134 were girls, 21 of unknown sex, and 15 not declared. The fetal death from other municipalities correspondend to 39,8% of this total. Birth weight was not declared on 103 Declarations. The durantion of gestation was 28 or more weeks in 142 cases (47,5%), 20 to 27 weeks in 52 (17,4%), and this information had not been filled or was marked as unknown in 105 cases (35,3%). A single gestation was pointed out in 46,8% of cases and was not declared in 46,5%. Intrauterine hypoxia was indicated as underying causa in 41,8% of cases.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1997-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16170</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v30i4p508-513</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 30 No. 4 (1997); 508-513</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 30 Núm. 4 (1997); 508-513</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 30 n. 4 (1997); 508-513</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16170/17841</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/16171</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:19:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3A+Cef.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Introdução</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Speciali, José Geraldo</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1997-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16171</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v30i4p419-420</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 30 No. 4 (1997); 419-420</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 30 Núm. 4 (1997); 419-420</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 30 n. 4 (1997); 419-420</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16171/17842</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/16173</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-06-25T16:07:46Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:ART</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação aliação microbiológica das mãos e fossas nasais de manipuladores de alimentos da unidade de alimentação e nutrição de um hospital universitário</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Microbiological evaluation of food manipulator's hands and nasal cavity in a food unit of a university hospital</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Machado, Juliana R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marson, Jorge M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Ana C. S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Paulo R.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Terra, Ana P. S.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Contaminação. Mãos/microbiologia. Manipulação de Alimentos. Staphylococcus aureus. Escherichia coli.</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Contamination. Hand/microbiology. Food Handling. Staphylococcus aureus. Escherichia coli.</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este trabalho teve como objetivo identificar os microorganismos presentes nas mãos e fossas nasais de manipuladores de alimentos da cozinha de um hospital universitário. Foram realizadas coletas de amostras de 24 manipuladores de alimentos, usando swab embebido em solução salina. As amostras foram semeadas em meio de cultivo específico para isolamento e identificação dos microorganismos presentes. Dos 24 manipuladores analisados, todos albergavam Staphylococcus aureus , sendo que 41,67% albergavam esta bactéria nas fossas nasais, 41,67% apenas na palma das mãos, e 16,67% albergavam tanto nas mãos quanto nas fossas nasais.Escherichia coli&#160; esteve presente em 29,17% dos manipuladores, sendo 28,57% nas fossas nasais e 71,43% nas mãos dos manipuladores. Em 12,5% dos manipuladores foram encontradas ambas as bactérias, S. aureus e E. coli , nas mãos. Ademonstração de S. aureus e E. coli nas amostras isoladas dos manipuladores de alimento apontam para a possibilidade da contaminação de alimentos, a partir da colonização das mãos e fossas nasais de manipuladores. A prevenção desta contaminação pode ser feita pelo meio de medidas educativas e disponibilização de produtos que facilitem a higienização adequada das mãos no ambiente de trabalho.&#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This work had as objectives identify microorganisms present in the hands and nasal cavity of food handlers that work in a kitchen of&#160;a University Hospital. It was collected samples of 24 individuals usingswab&#160;Staphylococcus aureus , with 41.67% harbouring this bacterium in nasal cavity, 41.67% in the palm of the hand, and 16.67% in both hands and nasal cavity. Another microorganism detected was Escherichia coli , present in 29.17% of handlers, being 28.57% in nasal cavity and 71.43% in the hands of manipulators. In 12.5% of food handlers were found both S. aureus and E. coli in their hands. The demonstrations of S. aureus e E. coli&#160;in the food handlers´ isolated samples indicate food contamination; arise from contaminated hands and nasal cavity of them. The prevention for this contamination can be applied adopting an orientation procedure and available of products that facilitate the right sanitation of the hands in the work environment. s soaked in saline solution. These samples were sown in culture medium for isolation and identification of the microorganisms. All 24 food handlers presented&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2009-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliado pelos pares</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16173</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v42i4p461-465</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 No. 4 (2009); 461-465</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 42 Núm. 4 (2009); 461-465</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 42 n. 4 (2009); 461-465</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16173/17844</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/16544</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-11T12:09:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3ASem.+Esp.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Semiologia otorrinolaringológica</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Otorhinolaryngologic semiology</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Wilma Terezinha Anselmo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, José Antonio Aparecido</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Otorhinolaryngology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Diagnosis, Otorhinolaryngologic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Otorrinolaringologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diagnóstico Otorrinolaringológico</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Nesta revisão dirigida ao graduando em Medicina e ao médico não especialista, apresentou-se os principais elementos semiológicos das fossas nasais, seios paranasais, laringe, faringe e ouvidos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">In this review directed at medical students and non specialist physicians, the major semiologic elements of the nasal fossae, paranasal sinuses, larynx, pharynx and ear are presented.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1996-03-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16544</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v29i1p61-66</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 29 No. 1 (1996); 61-66</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 29 Núm. 1 (1996); 61-66</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 29 n. 1 (1996); 61-66</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16544/18257</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/16545</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-11T12:15:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3A+Hip.+Art.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Hipertensão arterial secundária</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Secondary hypertension</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, José Gastão Rocha de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hypertension</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hypertension, Secondary</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hormones</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hipertensão</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hipertensão secundária</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hormônios</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Apesar do importante avanço em técnicas diagnósticas, as causas de hipertensão arterial secundária podem ser suspeitadas através de história e exame físico cuidadosos, com o auxílio de estudos laboratoriais simples e acessíveis. Pacientes hipertensos nos quais o diagnóstico etiológico de hipertensão arterial secundária não é definido, na avaliação inicial, podem ser submetidos à investigação adicional, durante o seu seguimento clínico. Incluem-se entre estas situações, resposta terapêutica inadequada, elevação de níveis pressóricos após controle inicial, formas mais graves de hipertensão arterial, alterações eletrolíticas ou de função renal e qualidade de vida prejudicada, entre outras indicações. Este artigo aborda as considerações mais relevantes em relação à abordagem clínica e laboratorial das causas mais freqüentes de hipertensão arterial secundária.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">In spite of advances in diagnostic tests, most types of secondary hypertension can be suspected after a careful history and physical examination and simple, inexpensive laboratory studies. After their initial evaluation, patients who are not suspected of having a specific cause for their hypertension may be selected for additional investigation during careful follow-up because of a poor therapeutic control, increased blood pressures levels during appropriate treatment, more severe forms of hypertensive disease, poor quality of life during treatment, electrolyte and renal function abormalities, among other situations. This article will serve to review some diagnostic approaches to the most frequent causes of secondary hypertension.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1996-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16545</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v29i2/3p220-231</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 29 No. 2/3 (1996); 220-231</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 29 Núm. 2/3 (1996); 220-231</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 29 n. 2/3 (1996); 220-231</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16545/18258</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/16582</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-09-11T12:18:37Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmrp:Simp.%3A+Ens.+Med.+Gr.</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Ensino médico de graduação: em busca de maior qualidade</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Teaching medical students: in search of increased quality</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Troncon, Luiz Ernesto de Almeida</dc:creator>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">NULO</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Os trabalhos que compõem este simpósio constituem, em seu conjunto, uma coletânea de muito interesse para os leitores da revista e para todos os que têm envolvimento profissional com a área da Educação Médica.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Universidade de São Paulo. Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1996-12-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2176-7262.v29i4p365-371</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="en-US">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 29 No. 4 (1996); 365-371</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="es-ES">Medicina (Ribeirao Preto); Vol. 29 Núm. 4 (1996); 365-371</dc:source>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina (Ribeirão Preto); v. 29 n. 4 (1996); 365-371</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2176-7262</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0076-6046</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/rmrp/article/view/16582/18295</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2022-08-30T21:20:23Z" completeListSize="1467" cursor="725">1ab1f4bf2ca1e62da5ac8450f00be5fc</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
