<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-08-07T14:49:16Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="actafisiatrica">https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103640</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T18:24:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of postural balance under single and double task conditions in sedentary and non-sedentary elderly females</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação do equilíbrio postural sob condição de tarefa única e tarefa dupla em idosas sedentárias e não sedentárias</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carmelo, Verena de Vassimon Barroso</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Garcia, Patrícia Azevedo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Postural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividade Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Elderly</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Postural Balance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective:To evaluate and compare the dynamic balance under the single and double task conditions both of elderly females who practice physical exercises regularly and of sedentary elderly females. Methods: The sample was composed of 28 elderly, with 14 non-sedentary (67.20±4.21 years), and 14 sedentary (68.78±5.26 years). To evaluate their balance and mobility, the Timed Get up and Go test was used and correlated with the motor task and to the cognitive task. The Student t-test was applied for independent samples and the paired Student t-test, considering the significance level of α=0,05. Results: The non-sedentary elderly women performed the simple test in a significantly less time than the sedentary ones (9.40 vs 11.21 seconds; p=0.016), and the test correlated with a motor task (9.41 vs 11.81 seconds; p=0.007). There was no statistically significant difference between the averages in the time to perform the cognitive task between the two groups (p=0.169). For the non-sedentary group, the time to perform the cognitive task was significantly longer than in the simple test and in the motor task (p=0.021 and p=0.014, respectively), as well as for the sedentary group (p=0.000 and p=0.002, respectively). In both groups, positive moderate to highly significant correlations were observed between the performances of the simple and cognitive double, simple and motor double, and the motor double and cognitive double tests. Conclusion: The study demonstrated the positive influence of regular physical activity on functionality and the negative impact of adding a cognitive task to balance and mobility of elderly females.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Avaliar e comparar o equilíbrio dinâmico sob a condição de tarefa única e de dupla-tarefa de idosas praticantes de exercício físico regular e idosas sedentárias. Métodos:&#160; Amostra composta por 28 idosas, 14 idosas não-sedentárias (67,20±4,21 anos) e 14 idosas sedentárias (68,78±5,26 anos). Para avaliação do equilíbrio e mobilidade foi utilizado o teste Timed Get up and Go simples e associado à tarefa motora (carregar uma bandeja com dois copos plásticos vazios) e à tarefa cognitiva (contar regressivamente a partir de cem). Foram aplicados os testes t-student para amostras independentes e t-student pareado, considerando o nível de&#160; significância de α=0,05. Resultados: Idosas não sedentárias realizaram em tempo significativamente menor que as idosas sedentárias o teste simples (9,40 vs 11,21 segundos; p=0,016) e o teste associado a tarefa motora (9,41 vs 11,81 segundos; p=0,007). Não houve diferença estatisticamente significativa entre as médias do tempo de realização da tarefa cognitiva entre os dois grupos de idosas (p=0,169). No grupo não sedentárias, o tempo para realização da tarefa cognitiva foi significativamente maior do que no teste simples e na tarefa motora (p=0,021 e p=0,014, respectivamente) assim como no grupo sedentárias (p= 0,000 e p=0,002, respectivamente). Nos dois grupos foram observadas correlações significativas positivas moderada a alta entre os desempenhos nos testes simples e duplo cognitivo, simples e duplo motor, duplo motor e duplo cognitivo. Conclusão: Demonstrou a influência positiva da prática de atividade física regular na funcionalidade e o impacto negativo da adição da tarefa cognitiva no equilíbrio e mobilidade de idosas.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103640</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v18i3a103640</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 3 (2011); 136-140</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103640/102103</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103641</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T18:30:42Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Characteristics of motorcycle accident victims treated at a leading rehabilitation center in the south of Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Características das vítimas de acidentes motociclisticos atendidas em um centro de reabilitação de referência estadual do sul do Brasil</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schoeller, Soraia Dornelles</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bonetti, Albertina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Gelson Aguiar da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rocha, André</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gelbcke, Francine Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Khan, Patricia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Traffic Accidents</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motorcycles</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Population Characteristics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation Centers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidentes de Trânsito</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Motocicletas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Características da População</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Centros de Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This study outlines the characteristics of motorcycle accident victims treated at a leading rehabilitation center in the south of Brazil. It is a descriptive and quantitative study, which uses results found from research focused on spinal cord injury - SCI. A total of 207 medical records, containing the following information: origin, age, sex, date and cause of injury, were analyzed. The study revealed that victims of motorcycle accidents were most commonly young males (81.09%), 10% of whom were younger than 18 years old. Half of the victims had extremely serious or very serious injuries - SCI, brain injury, or lower limb amputation. The motorcycle accident death rate in in the state of Santa Catarina and in Brazil rose 250% from 2000 to 2009, while the population growth was only 16%. Motorcycle accidents constitute a serious public health problem due to the increase in the number of people injured and the severity of the injuries. Public policies - education, public health and safety, need to be established in order to reverse this trend.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Esta investigação caracteriza os usuários vítimas de acidentes de moto atendidos em um centro de reabilitação de referência estadual do sul do Brasil. É parte de pesquisa voltada ao trauma raquimedular - TRM. Estudo descritivo e quantitativo. Foram investigadas em 207 prontuários: procedência, idade, sexo, data e causa da lesão. Constatou-se que as vítimas de acidentes motociclísticos são homens (81.09%) jovens, dos quais, 10% menores de 18 anos. Metade dos usuários tiveram lesões extremamente ou muito graves – TRM, traumatismo crânio encefálico e amputação de membros inferiores. O coeficiente de mortalidade por acidentes motociclísticos no Brasil e em Santa Catarina cresceu 250% no período de 2000 a 2009, enquanto o crescimento populacional foi de 16%. Os acidentes motociclísticos constituem-se grave problema de saúde pública pelo número cada vez maior de pessoas atingidas e gravidade das lesões. Urge estabelecer políticas públicas – educação, segurança pública e saúde, objetivando inverter esta tendência.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103641</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v18i3a103641</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 3 (2011); 141-145</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103641/102104</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103642</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T18:39:09Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Relação entre cadência da subida e descida de escada, recuperação motora e equilíbrio em indivíduos com hemiparesia</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Relationship between stair-climbing rate, balance and motor recovery in individuals with hemiparesis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Amaral-Natalio, Mavie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nunes, Guilherme da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Herber, Vanessa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Michaelsen, Stella Maris</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Paresis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Postural Balance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Cerebral Vascular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paresia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividade Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Postural</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Verificar a relação entre a cadência de subida e descida de escada, e os graus de recuperação motora de membros inferiores e de equilíbrio dinâmico de indivíduos com hemiparesia. Método: Participaram do estudo 16 indivíduos com hemiparesia devido AVE, sendo 13 homens, com idade média de 56,6±12,6 anos. A cadência de subida e descida de escada foi mensurada através do tempo decorrido (degraus/minuto), separadamente, para subir e descer uma escada de 4 degraus (altura: 17 cm), em velocidade confortável. Resultados: A média da cadência de subida de escada foi 60,4±22,6 degraus/minuto e a de descida de escada foi 58,7±23,6 degraus/minuto. O grau de recuperação motora de membros inferiores foi de 24,8±5,2 pontos na Escala Fugl-Meyer, e a média no TUG foi de 19,8±23,1 segundos. Foi verificada correlação moderada entre a medida de cadência de subida de escada e os graus de recuperação motora (r=0,60, p=0,01) e de equilíbrio dinâmico (r= -0,61, p=0,01). Da mesma forma, a medida de cadência de descida de escada apresentou correlação moderada com o grau de recuperação motora (r=0,58, p=0,02), e com o grau de equilíbrio dinâmico (r= -0,64, p=0,007). Verificou-se que o grau de recuperação motora compartilha 36% de variância com a medida da cadência de subida de escada e 33% com a cadência de descida. Conclusões: A habilidade de subir e descer escada apresenta relação com a recuperação motora de membros inferiores, sendo que o equilíbrio dinâmico apresenta maior associação com a cadência de descida de escada em indivíduos com hemiparesia.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To study the relationship between the cadence when climbing up and down stairs, and the levels of motor recovery of the lower limbs and dynamic balance of individuals with hemiparesis. Method: The study included 16 individuals with hemiparesis due to stroke, of which 13 were men with a mean age 56.6±12.6 years. The stair-climbing cadence was measured by elapsed time (steps/minute), separately, for climbing up and down four steps (height: 17 cm) at a comfortable speed.&#160; Results: The average cadence when climbing up the stairs was 60.4±22.6 steps/ minute and when climbing down was 58.7±23.6 steps/minute. The level of motor recovery of the lower limbs was 24.8±5.2 points on the Fugl-Meyer Scale, and the TUG average was 19.8±23.1 seconds. Moderate correlation was found between the measurement of the cadence when climbing up the stairs and the levels of motor recovery (r= 0.60, p= 0.01) and dynamic balance (r= -0.61, p= 0.01). Likewise, the measurement of the cadence when climbing down the stairs presented a moderate correlation with the level of motor recovery (r= 0.58, p= 0.02), and with the degree of dynamic balance (r= -0.64, p= 0.007).&#160; Conclusions: The ability to climb up and down stairs is correlated to motor recovery of the lower limbs, and the dynamic balance is more closely correlated to the cadence of climbing down stairs in individuals with hemiparesis.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103642</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v18i3a103642</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 3 (2011); 146-150</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103642/102106</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103643</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T18:44:39Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Hand therapy contributions in cerebral palsy: a systematic review</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Contribuições da terapia da mão na paralisia cerebral: uma revisão sistemática</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Alyne Kalyane Câmara de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Mariana Seabra da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>De Grande, Alaine Aparecida Benetti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferrigno, Iracema Serrat Vergotti</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos da Mão/reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia Ocupacional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Literatura de Revisão como Assunto</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hand Injuries/rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Occupational Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Review Literature as Topic</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este trabalho teve como objetivo identificar contribuições da área da terapia da mão para pessoas com paralisia cerebral, disponível na literatura bibliográfica nacional e internacional on-line, analisando a produção existente e verificando a existência de trabalhos estruturados. Configurou-se como sendo um estudo descritivo, retrospectivo, através critérios de revisão sistemática da literatura para coleta, seleção e análise dos dados. A busca foi realizada no período de fevereiro de 2010 a janeiro de 2011, nas bases de dados LILACS, MEDLINE, BIREME, SCOPUS e CINAHL, publicados em português e inglês, no período de 2003 a 2010. Onze artigos foram incluídos na revisão e utilizou-se um formulário elaborado pelas pesquisadoras para avaliá-los conforme a caracterização e qualidade das informações contidas. Os resultados evidenciaram que os assuntos com maior enfoque na amostra foram sobre intervenção ortótica, estimulação elétrica neuromuscular, toxina botulínica e função manual. Apesar de contribuírem com o conhecimento sobre intervenções na paralisia cerebral, os estudos não citam claramente os achados como contribuições da especialidade terapia da mão sobre o tema, e limitações metodológicas foram encontradas, inferindo-se a necessidade de maior rigor metodológico e qualidade das informações nos trabalhos científicos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This study sought to identify the contributions of the hand therapy field to people with cerebral palsy, available in the domestic and international literature online, analyzing the existing works and verifying the existence of structured studies. It was configured as a descriptive, retrospective study, through the criteria of systematic review of the literature for the collection, selection, and analysis of data. The search was done from February of 2010 to January of 2011, on the LILACS, MEDLINE, BIREME, SCOPUS, and CINAHL databases, on works published in Portuguese and English, between 2003 and 2010. Eleven articles were included in the review and a form prepared by the researchers was used to evaluate these articles according to the characterization and quality of the information contained. The results demonstrated that the most discussed subjects in the sample were orthotic intervention, neuromuscular electrical stimulation, botulinum toxin, and manual function. Despite contributing to knowledge on cerebral palsy interventions, the studies did not clearly mention the findings as contributions from the hand therapy specialty on the theme, and methodological limitations were found, implying the need for more methodological rigor and quality of information from the scientific studies.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103643</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v18i3a103643</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 3 (2011); 151-156</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103643/102107</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103644</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T18:47:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação virtual através do videogame: relato de caso no tratamento de um paciente com lesão alta dos nervos mediano e ulnar</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Virtual rehabilitation using video games: a case report of the treatment of a patient with high median and high ulnar nerve lesions</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>De Grande, Alaine Aparecida Benetti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Galvão, Fábio Ricardo de Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gondim, Luiz Carlos Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia Ocupacional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Nervos Periféricos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Jogos de Vídeo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Occupational Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Peripheral Nerves</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Video Games</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este estudo teve como objetivo verificar o uso da reabilitação virtual, como recurso terapêutico ocupacional, em um paciente com lesão alta dos nervos mediano e ulnar, bem como descrever e comparar os graus da amplitude de movimento das articulações do membro lesado. Trata- se de uma pesquisa do tipo longitudinal com um paciente de 09 anos de idade, sexo masculino, diagnosticado com lesão nervosa, na Clínica Escola de Terapia Ocupacional da Universidade Potiguar, no período de maio a setembro de 2010. Nos 13 encontros, foram utilizados televisão, o videogame Nintendo® Wii e quatro jogos e um goniômetro como instrumentos de intervenção e coleta de dados. Na reavaliação, observou-se a movimentação ativa e o aumento da amplitude de movimento em todas as articulações medidas: cotovelo em flexão e extensão; antebraço em pronação e supinação; punho em flexão, extensão, desvio ulnar e desvio radial; polegar em flexão de metacarpofalangiana, flexão interfalangiana, abdução e estágio III de oponência (Kapangji); II, III, IV e V quirodátilos. Os metacarpos apresentaram ganhos em flexão e extensão. Os resultados desse estudo evidenciaram a eficácia do videogame, comprovado através da avaliação goniométrica. O indivíduo estudado voltou a realizar as atividades de vida diária de forma independente e retornou as suas atividades esportivas de forma competitiva.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The intent of this study was to verify the application of virtual rehabilitation as a resource for occupational therapy for a patient with high median and high ulnar nerve injuries, and to describe and compare the levels of range of motion of the injured limb joints. This was a longitudinal survey with a 9 years old patient, male, diagnosed with nerve damage at the Potiguar University School of Occupational Therapy Clinic. The survey was carried out from May to September of 2010. Throughout the 13 sessions, a television and a Nintendo ® Wii video game (with four games) were used as intervention tools, and a goniometer was used for collecting data. During reassessment, active movement and increased range of motion in all joints assessed were observed: elbow flexion and extension; forearm pronation and supination; wrist flexion, extension, radio and ulnar deviation; thumb metacarpophalangeal flexion, interphalangeal flexion, abduction and opponency at stage III (Kapandji); II, III, IV and V fingers. The metacarpals presented improvements in flexion and extension. The results showed the effectiveness of video games as evidenced by goniometric evaluation. The patient studied regained the ability to perform activities of daily living independently and to play sports competitively.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103644</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v18i3a103644</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 3 (2011); 157-162</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103644/102108</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103658</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T15:09:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudo retrospectivo do estado funcional de pacientes com fratura do rádio distal submetidos à osteossíntese com placa LCP</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">A retrospective study of functionality of patients with distal radius fracture after osteosynthesis with an LCP volar plate</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Clé, Paula Guaraldo Villa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tasso, Luiz Eduardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barbosa, Rafael Inácio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fonseca, Marisa de Cássia Registro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Elui, Valéria Meirelles Carril</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Roncaglia, Frederico Balbão</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mazzer, Nilton</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barbieri, Cláudio Henrique</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fixadores Internos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fraturas do Rádio</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Internal Fixators</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Radius Fractures</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">As fraturas do rádio distal estão entre as mais comuns do esqueleto humano, correspondendo a um sexto de todas as fraturas. Para seu tratamento, existem diversas técnicas cirúrgicas e materiais de síntese que podem ser utilizados, no entanto, o uso de placa volar tem se mostrado eficiente e apresentado poucas complicações. Objetivo: Realizar uma análise retrospectiva do estado funcional de pacientes com fratura do radio distal submetidos à osteossíntese com placa volar LCP que passaram por um programa de reabilitação. Método: A amostra foi composta por 14 pacientes com fratura unilateral de rádio distal submetidosàosteossíntese com placa volar LCP 2,4 mm ou 3,5 mm. Os indivíduos foram divididos em dois grupos: grupo acometido (n = 14), composto pelos punhos fraturados; grupo controle (n = 14) composto pelos punhos contralaterais. Foram realizadas medidas de amplitude de movimento (ADM) ativa e passiva do punho, força de preensão e pinças e aplicado um questionário de disfunção do membro superior (DASH). Para a análise dos dados, foi realizada comparação entre os grupos, acometido e controle, por meio de testes de significância de duas amostras independentes para médias. Resultados: A média encontrada para o questionário DASH foi de 10,63 pontos (± 12,23). Em relação às medidas de força de preensão e pinças, e de ADM de punho, não houve diferenças significantes na comparação entre os grupos (p &amp;gt; 0,05). Conclusão: Na amostra analisada, pode-se concluir que, após um ano de pós-operatório, os pacientes apresentam resultados semelhantes na comparação, o que evidencia uma recuperação satisfatória do estado funcional.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Distal radius fractures are the most common fractures of the human skeleton, accounting for one sixth of all fractures. For his treatment, there are several surgical techniques and synthesizing materials that can be used, however, the use of a volar plate has been proven effective and haspresented few complications. Objective: Here was to make a retrospective study of thefunctionality of patients with distal radius fracture after internal fixation with an LCP volar plate that went through a rehabilitation program. Method: The sample consisted of 14 patients with unilateral distal radius fracture who underwent internal fixation with a 2.4 mm or 3.5 mm LCP volar plate who completed 1 year after surgery in 2010. The subjects were divided into two groups: affected group (n = 14), composed of fractured wrists; control group (n = 14) composed of the contralateral wrists. Measurements were made of active and passive range of motion (ROM) of the wrist, grip strength, pinch grip strength, and a questionnaire of disabilities of the arm, shoulder, and hand (DASH). The data was analyzed to compare the affected and controlgroups, through tests of significance of two independent samples for means. Results: The average for the DASH questionnaire was 10.63 points (± 12.23). For measures of grip strength, pinch grip strength, and ROM, there were no significant differences in comparison groups (p &amp;gt; 0.05). Conclusion: We concluded that after one year post-surgery, patients showed similar results when comparing the wrists, which shows a satisfactory recovery of functional status.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103658</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v18i4a103658</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 4 (2011); 163-168</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103658/102110</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103658/102111</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103659</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T15:25:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Estado cognitivo dos usuários com AVE na atenção primária à saúde em João Pessoa - PB</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Cognitive condition of patients with CVA in primary health care in João Pessoa - PB</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mendes, Luciana Moura</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Neves, Robson da Fonseca</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro, Kátia Suely Queiroz Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brito, Geraldo Eduardo Guedes de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lucena, Eleazar Marinho de Freitas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Batista, Hermínio Rafael Lopes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Morais, Jairo Domingos de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atenção Primária à Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cognição</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores Socioeconômicos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Testes Neuropsicológicos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Primary Health Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cognition</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Socioeconomic Factors</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neuropsychological Tests</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Cerebrovascular Accident orStroke (CVA) has a high prevalence worldwide causing neurological disability in adults. Cognitive deficit is one of the most important consequences, since its recognition is difficult and thus may interfere with the rehabilitation process and lead to impacts on the life quality of affected people. Objective: The goal was to estimate the prevalence of cognitive impairment in stroke among those with Primary Health Care (PHC), as well as to describe the clinical and sociodemographic characteristics, and the cognitive dimensions affected. Method: This was a cross-sectional study carried out in the city of João Pessoa - PB with 140 people enrolled in the Family Health Program that had been affected by stroke within the previous five years. Results: Over half of the people studied had manifestations suggesting cognitive impairment (54.9%) in the following dimensions: memory recall (70%), attention and calculation (60%), and read and apply (60%). In addition, the majority was elderly (73.1%) and, regarding the clinical characteristics of stroke, had declared that in the previous five years had had only one episode (64.2%) triggered in the last 13 months or more (76.1%). Also, half of the participants (50.7%) were unable to tell us the type of stroke they had suffered. Conclusion: The cognitive dimensions affected by stroke require further investigation in order to provide more funding to improve the assistance provided under the PHC.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O Acidente Vascular Encefálico (AVE) apresenta alta prevalência em todo o mundo, desencadeando incapacidades neurológicas em adultos. O déficit cognitivo é uma das sequelas mais importantes, sendo difícil o seu reconhecimento, podendo interferir no processo de reabilitação e acarretar impactos na qualidade de vida dos usuários acometidos. Objetivo: Estimar a prevalência de déficit cognitivo em usuários com AVE na Atenção Primária à Saúde (APS), bem como descrever as características sociodemográficas, clínicas e dimensões cognitivas afetadas. Método: Estudo de corte transversal desenvolvido no Município de João Pessoa-PB com 140 indivíduos adscritos no Programa Saúde da Família que foram acometidos por AVE nos últimos cinco anos. Resultados: Mais da metade dos indivíduos analisados apresenta quadro sugestivo de comprometimento cognitivo (54,9%), nas seguintes dimensões: memória de evocação (70%), atenção e cálculo (60%) e ler e executar (60%); além disso, a maioria era de idosos (73,1%);no que se refere às características clínicas do AVE declaram que nos últimos cinco anos tiveram apenas um episódio (64,2%) desencadeado nos últimos 13 meses ou mais (76,1%). A metade dos participantes não soube informar o tipo de AVE (50,7%). Conclusão: As dimensões cognitivas afetadas pelo AVE precisam de maiores investigações, afim de fornecer mais subsídios para melhorar a assistência prestada no âmbito da APS.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103659</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20110002</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 4 (2011); 169-174</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103659/102112</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103659/102113</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103661</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T21:41:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Down Syndrome health care protocol - IMREA/HCFMUSP</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Protocolo de cuidado à saúde da pessoa com Síndrome de Down - IMREA/HCFMUSP</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tempski, Patricia Zen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Miyahara, Kátia Lina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Munique Dias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Ricardo Bocatto de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oyakawa, Aline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Down Syndrome</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Patient Care Team</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation Centers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Síndrome de Down</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equipe Interdisciplinar de Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Centros de Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Síndrome de Down (SD) ou trissomia do cromossomo 21 é a cromossomopatia mais comum no ser humano, acontece independente de sexo, etnia ou classe social. No Brasil, nasce aproximadamente uma criança com SD para cada 700 nascimentos. Sabe-se que as pessoas com síndrome de Down, quando bem atendidas e estimuladas, têm potencial para plena inclusão social. Este protocolo foi elaborado pela equipe multiprofissional de Cuidado à Saúde da Pessoa com síndrome de Down do Instituto de Medicina Física e Reabilitação do Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo. Objetivo: Oferecer orientações para o cuidado à saúde da pessoa com Síndrome de Down, nos diferentes níveis de atenção a saúde, em todo o seu ciclo vital. Método: A elaboração do protocolo de cuidado integral à saúde da pessoa com síndrome de Down baseou-se em buscas no sistema PubMed, SciELO e no Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews utilizando como palavras chaves: “Down Syndrome” e “Síndrome de Down”; “Trisomy 21”, “Trisomíadel Cromosoma 21” e “Trissomia do Cromossomo 21” e “Growth”, “Desarollo” e “Crescimento”. Resultados: Os artigos revistos foram publicados no período de 1972 a 2011 e limitados às línguas: inglesa, espanhola e portuguesa. Priorizamos revisões sistemáticas e metanálises. Foram incluídos também registros prévios a 1972 considerados históricos. Conclusão: Os dados foram analisados por um grupo de especialistas que discutiu os resultados e elaborou este protocolo.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The Down syndrome (DS) or chromosome 21 trisomy is the most common chromosomopathy in human beings, it occurs regardless of gender, ethnicity, or social class. In Brazil, there is approximately one child born with DS for every 700 births. It is known that people with Down syndrome well cared-for and stimulated have potential for full social inclusion. This protocol was prepared by the Down Syndrome Personal Health Care multiprofessional team at the IMREA/HCFMUSP. Objective: Is to offer orientation in the health care of a person with Down Syndrome, in the different levels of attention to health, throughout his/her life. Method: The preparation of the total care protocol for the health of a person with Down syndrome was based on searches in the PubMed and SciELO systems and on the Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews using the keywords: Down syndrome and Syndrome of Down, Trisomy 21, "Trisomía del Cromosoma 21", Chromosome 21 trisomy, Growth, "Desarollo", and "Crescimento". Results: The articles reviewed were published from 1972 to 2011 and limited to the languages: English, Spanish, and Portuguese. Records previous to 1972 were also included for being considered historical. Conclusion: The data was analyzed by a group of specialists that discussed the results and prepared this protocol.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103661</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20110003</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 4 (2011); 175-186</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103661/102114</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103661/102115</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103663</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T16:44:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação do comportamento lúdico da criança com paralisia cerebral e da percepção de seus cuidadores</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of ludic behavior in children with cerebral palsy and of their caretakers’ perception</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zaguini, Camila Gomes Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bianchin, Maysa Alahmar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lucato Junior, Rui Vicente</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chueire, Regina Helena Morganti Fornari</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cuidadores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ludoterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Caregivers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Play Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">For children, playing helps develop their abilities and in acquiring action and adaptation strategies. Depending on the diagnosis, on the associated or non-associated disturbances, the child with Cerebral Palsy may have difficulties in acquiring general abilities during his or her development, including playing. Objective: We sought to evaluate the ludic behavior of the child with Cerebral Palsy and to verify their caretakers’ perceptions towards the ludic action of the child, so as to offer them occupational treatment later on. Method: The research was quantitative, qualitative, and transversal. For collecting data, the authors used: Initial Interview with parents and the child’s ludic behavior Evaluation. Results: Through the interview we noticed that 90% of them became interested by the presence of other children, that the majority of the materials used by them during playing were those with audible stimuli (90%), and according to their styles of expression, the majority (31.5%) expressed themselves by gestures according to their need –25% by facial expressions. Following their interests, 42.5% of the children expressed themselves with words and 55% always showed attitudes towards playing. When evaluating the subject, we noticed that 69.1% showed an attitude in playing and only 64% presented some ability for playfulness. Conclusion: The study showed that the Initial Interview with Parents was fundamental in helping evaluate the Ludic Behavior. With this evaluation we could observe that their ludic ability is unlimited, but that it does not interfere in the interest or in the ludic attitude of the child. In that manner, playing is essential as a resource in Occupational Therapy for the rehabilitation of children with Cerebral Palsy.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O brincar, para a criança, ajuda no desenvolvimento de suas habilidades e na aquisição de estratégias de ação e adaptação. A criança com Paralisia Cerebral, dependendo do seu diagnóstico, dos distúrbios associados ou não, pode apresentar dificuldades no processo de aquisição de habilidades gerais do seu desenvolvimento, inclusive no brincar. Objetivo: Avaliar o comportamento lúdico da criança com paralisia cerebral e verificar a percepção de seus cuidadores em relação à ação lúdica da criança, para, posteriormente, oferecer tratamento terapêutico ocupacional. Método: Pesquisa transversal qualitativa e quantitativa. Para a coleta de dados foram utilizados: Entrevista Inicial com os pais e a Avaliação do Comportamento Lúdico com a criança. Resultados: Por meio da entrevista, pode-se perceber que 90% se interessam pela presença de outras crianças, que os materiais mais utilizados nas brincadeiras são os estímulos sonoros (90%), em suas formas de expressão, que a maioria, com 31,5%, se expressa por gestos em suas necessidades, em seus sentimentos 25% o fazem por expressão do rosto. De acordo com seus interesses, 42,5% se expressam por palavras e 55% das crianças sempre apresentam atitudes para no brincar. Na avaliação com o sujeito, vimos que 69,1% têm atitude no brincar e apenas 46,64% têm capacidade para o lúdico. Conclusão: O estudo mostrou que a Entrevista Inicial com os Pais foi fundamental para auxiliar na Avaliação do Comportamento Lúdico. Com essa avaliação, pode-se observar que a capacidade lúdica é limitada, mas não interfere no interesse e na atitude lúdica da criança. Assim, o brincar é indispensável como recurso da Terapia Ocupacional na reabilitação das crianças com Paralisia Cerebral.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103663</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20110004</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 4 (2011); 187-191</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103663/102116</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103663/102117</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103664</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T16:49:14Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevalência da síndrome do Túnel do Carpo em usuários de cadeira de rodas devido à lesão medular</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Prevalence of Carpal Tunnel syndrome in wheel-chair users due to medullary lesion</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nunes, Lucas Martins de Exel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Raimundo, Verônica Magalhães</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cordeiro, Quirino</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guerrini, Karen Fraga Moreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ramos, Arquimedes de Moura</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chung, Tae Mo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Wheelchairs</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neurophysiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spinal Cord Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cadeiras de Rodas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neurofisiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Síndrome do Túnel Carpal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos da Medula Espinal</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Medullary lesions create numerous functional limitations directly related to the loss of nervous functions. However, the mechanics associated with the use of a wheelchair impose a load on the upper limbs that seems to be linked to secondary lesions in the tendinous and nervous structures. Objective: This study seeks to evaluate the appearance of signs of electromyographic impairments of the median nerve around the carpal tunnel in individuals who use wheelchairs due to medullary lesion. Method: Following a transversal design, all the individuals with medullary lesion in the rehabilitation program at the HC-FMUSP Institute of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation in the year 2010 were submitted to a study of nervous conduction and electromyography. Those findings were correlated with biodemographic and clinical variables, as well as to characteristics of the use of wheelchairs. Results: Twenty-eight (28) individuals were evaluated, with an average age of 41.4 years (60.7% males). Most patients moved the wheelchair for less than four hours and would move it less than 500 meters a day. An absence of painful symptoms was found in 67.9%, while only 7.1% presenting positive Phalen and/or Tinel test. Half of the sample presented the neurophysiological diagnostic of carpal tunnel syndrome (CTS), which had a statistically significant association with age (p = 0.024), but not with the time and distance moving the wheelchair daily, the use of protection or adaptation of the wheelchair, of pain in upper limbs, or the presence of positive signs of CTS in the physical exam. Conclusion: We concluded that the electromyographic signs of CTS are very prevalent in these individuals, which suggests more situations of risk for the integrity of their upper limbs and demands the development of a more efficient biomechanical strategy for prevention.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A lesão medular acarreta inúmeras limitações funcionais diretamente relacionadas à perda das funções nervosas. Todavia, a mecânica associada ao uso de cadeiras de rodas impõe uma sobrecarga aos membros superiores que parece estar associada ao aparecimento de lesões secundárias em estruturas tendíneas e nervosas. Objetivo: Avaliar o surgimento de sinais eletromiográficos de comprometimento do nervo mediano na altura do túnel do carpo em indivíduos usuários de cadeiras de rodas devido à lesão medular. Método: Seguindo um desenho transversal, todos os indivíduos com lesão medular sob programa de reabilitação no Instituto de Medicina Física e Reabilitação do HC-FMUSP no ano 2010 foram submetidos a estudo de condução nervosa e eletromiografia. Esses achados foram correlacionados com variáveis biodemográficas e clínicas, bem como características do uso de cadeiras de rodas. Resultados: Foram avaliados 28 indivíduos, com média de idade de 41,4 anos (60,7% homens). A maioria dos pacientes tocava a cadeira de rodas por um tempo inferior a quatro horas e percorria uma distância tocando a cadeira de rodas inferior a 500 metros por dia. A ausência de sintomas dolorosos ocorreu em 67,9%, enquanto apenas 7,1% apresentavam o teste de Phalen e/ou Tinel positivos. Metade da amostra apresentava o diagnóstico neurofisiológico de síndrome do túnel do carpo (STC), que apresentou associação estatisticamente significante com a idade (p = 0,024), mas não com tempo e distância percorrida tocando a cadeira de rodas diariamente, uso de proteção ou adaptação na cadeira de rodas, sintomatologia dolorosa em membros superiores ou presença de sinais positivos para STC ao exame físico. Conclusão: Os sinais eletromiográficos de STC são muito prevalentes nesses indivíduos, o que sugere maiores situações de risco para a integridade dos membros superiores e exige o desenvolvimento de estratégias biomecanicamente mais eficazes para a prevenção.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20110005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 4 (2011); 192-195</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103664/102118</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103664/102119</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103665</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T16:52:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A mesoterapia melhora a amplitude articular em pacientes com tendinite do manguito rotador</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Mesotherapy improves range of motion in patients with rotator cuff tendinitis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sposito, Maria Matilde de Melo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rivera, Daniele</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Metsavaht, Leonardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Infiltration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rotator Cuff</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Mesotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Shoulder</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Tendinopathy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Infiltração</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Manguito Rotador</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Mesoterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ombro</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tendinopatia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Há evidências publicadas sobre o efeito da mesoterapia para as doenças inflamatórias do ombro. Objetivo: Avaliar o ganho de amplitude de movimento (ADM) em pacientes com tendinopatia do manguito rotador tratados com mesoterapia. Uma série retrospectiva de casos conduzida a partir de prontuários médicos. Um serviço ambulatorial de reabilitação e ortopedia. População: 145 pacientes com diagnóstico clínico de tendinopatia do manguito rotador, com limitação da amplitude de movimento ativa. Método: Os sujeitos do estudo foram tratados com mesoterapia entre 1995 e 2008, as mesclas foram selecionadas de acordo com o perfil do paciente e sua tolerância. O efeito sobre a ADM foi qualificado como “sem melhora” ou “com melhora”. A melhora da sintomatologia foi correlacionada com a idade, duração dos sintomas e drogas usadas na mesoterapia. A realização concomitante de fisioterapia também foi correlacionada com o desfecho. Os efeitos adversos foram avaliados sistematicamente. Resultados: 117 pacientes (80,7%) apresentaram melhor objetiva da ADM ou a dor. O resultado não foi influenciado pela idade, duração dos sintomas ou pela realização concomitante de fisioterapia. Apenas efeitos adversos menores foram observados. Conclusão: Este estudo sugere que a mesoterapia pode ser eficaz no tratamento da tendinopatia do manguito rotador, seja pela melhora da dor, ADM ou função global do membro superior. O impacto clínico deste estudo é que a mesoterapia pode ser associada ao tratamento fisioterapêutico padrão para melhorar ADM e dor na tendinopatia do manguito rotador.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">There is published evidence on the effect of mesotherapy for inflammatory shoulder diseases. Objective: Evaluate the gain in range of motion (ROM) in patients with rotator cuff tendinopathy treated with mesotherapy. A retrospective series of cases conducted from medical records. Location: an outpatient rehabilitation and orthopedic service. 145 patients with clinical diagnosis of rotator cuff tendinopathy, with limited active range of motion. Method: The study subjects were treated with mesotherapy between 1995 and 2008, the blends were selected according to the patient’s profile and tolerance. The effect on the ROM was qualified as “not improved” or “improved”. The improvement in symptomatology was correlated to age, duration of symptoms, and drugs used in the mesotherapy. The concomitant application of physical therapy was also correlated with the result. The adverse effects were evaluated systematically. Results: 117 patients (80.7%) presented objective improvement of ROM or of pain. The result was not influenced by age, duration of symptoms, or by the concomitant application of physical therapy. Only smaller adverse effects were observed. Conclusion: This study suggests that mesotherapy can be efficient in the treatment of rotator cuff tendinopathy, for the improvement of pain, ROM, or global functioning of the upper limb. The clinical impact of this study is that mesotherapy can be associated with the standard physical therapy treatment to improve ROM and pain in rotator cuff tendinopathy.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103665</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20110006</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 4 (2011); 196-199</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103665/102120</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103665/102121</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103666</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T16:57:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Performance of insured workers in the rehabilitation service at the National Institute for Social Security</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Desempenho dos segurados no serviço de reabilitação do Instituto Nacional de Seguridade Social</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Vacaro, Jerri Estevan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pedroso, Fleming Salvador</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Trabalhadores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação Profissional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Seguridade Social</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Workers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation, Vocational</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Social Welfare</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo principal deste trabalho é verificar o desempenho dos segurados que participaram do programa de reabilitação profissional junto ao Instituto Nacional de Seguridade Social (INSS) de Porto Alegre/RS. Método: Foram estudados todos os segurados participantes do processo de reabilitação profissional ao longo do ano de 2008 no INSS de Porto Alegre/RS. Por meio do Sistema de Administração de Benefício por Incapacidade e do Cadastro Nacional de Informações Sociais, foram coletadas todas as informações referentes aos seus benefícios e ao programa de reabilitação profissional. Os dados foram tabulados no programa SPSS for Windows 17.0, a partir do qual foram feitas todas as análises. Resultados: Os dados mostraram que 553 (69%) dos segurados eram homens e 249 (31%), mulheres. Quanto à idade, variou entre 18 e 60 anos, com média de 38,9 anos. Inicialmente, 645 (80,4%) estavam empregados e 157 (19,6%), desempregados. Após um ano do término do programa de reabilitação, 29,4% dos segurados estavam trabalhando. Os segurados empregados tiveram um retorno de 40,6% e 76,7% dos desempregados não retornaram ao trabalho. Segurados em benefício por acidente de trabalho retornaram em 58,7 % dos casos e 29,6% dos segurados em auxílio-doença. Os segurados que permaneceram até um ano em benefício tiveram sucesso de 72,4% e com mais de cinco anos, 24,7%. Conclusão: Os segurados empregados, em benefício espécie acidente de trabalho, durante tempo menor em benefício e que foram reabilitados dentro da própria empresa, alcançaram índice maior de retorno ao trabalho se comparados ao índice dos desempregados, com longos benefícios e aqueles cuja empresa não ofereceu outra função.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The main objective of this study was to evaluate the performance of insured workers who participated in the vocational rehabilitation program from the INSS (National Institute of Social Security) in Porto Alegre/RS. Method: We selected all of the insured workers participating in the vocational rehabilitation process during the year of 2008 in Porto Alegre/RS at INSS. Through the Administration System for Disability Benefits and the National Register of Social Information, all information was collected regarding the benefits and vocational rehabilitation program. The data was tabulated using SPSS 17.0 for Windows in which all tests were made. Results: The results showed that 553 (69%) of the insured were men and 249 (31%) were women. Their ages ranged from 18 to 60 years with an average of 38.9 years. Initially, 645 (80.4%) were employed and 157 (19.6%), unemployed. One year after the end of the rehabilitation program, 29.4% of the insured were working. While 40.6% of those employed had returned to work, 76.7% of the unemployed had not. Those on leave for accidents at work returned 58.7% of the time, and also 29.6% of those on sick leave. Those who remained on leave for one year had a success rate of 72.4%, and those with more than five years 24.7%. Conclusion: Those who remained employed, went on sick leave for a shorter time, and were rehabilitated within the company enjoyed a higher rate of return to work than those who became unemployed, were off work for a longer time, and whose company did not offer them another job.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103666</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20110007</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 4 (2011); 200-205</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103666/102122</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103666/102123</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103668</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T17:12:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Composição corporal de esportistas com lesão medular e com poliomielite</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Body composition of active persons with spinal cord injury and with poliomyelitis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro, Sandra Maria Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kehayias, Joseph</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Regina Célia da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tirapegui, Julio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Nutrition Assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Body Composition</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Paraplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Poliomyelitis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividade Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação Nutricional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Composição Corporal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paraplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Poliomielite</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This study sought to evaluate the body composition of subjects with active spinal cord injuries and polio. Method: Two groups of males and females, active, free-living, of similar ages and body mass index (BMI), were distributed according to the source of deficiency: SCI – low spinal cord injury (T5-T12) and P – survivors of poliomyelitis infection. Body composition was analyzed by DEXA (fat and lean mass); bioelectrical impedance by vector analysis (BIVA analysis; resistance and reactance). Participants of the same gender were compared according to the source of deficiency, and both groups had their values compared to a reference population, when available. Results: Mean vectors were assessed with Hotelling’s T2 test and compared by Mahalanobis distance (D). DEXA analysis pointed out the men of P group with higher absolute amount of lean mass, and consequently the higher body lean mass index; both groups presented lower values than a reference study. With regard to BIVA analysis, P men presented higher resistance than SCI men and, consequently, a lower phase angle. Conclusion: Considering body composition as an indirect indicator of nutritional status, the present study suggests that, even with both groups presenting lower values than a reference population, there is a possibility of an increased nutritional risk for polio individuals than SCI, and this risk seems to be higher in men than in women. Further investigation, adopting biochemical and dietetic markers, and a higher sample size, certainly could better explore and understand our results.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O presente estudo teve por objetivos avaliar a composição corporal de esportistas com lesão medular traumática e poliomielite. Método: Dois grupos de homens e mulheres, esportistas, com idades e índice de massa corporal (IMC) similares, foram distribuídos em dois grupos, de acordo com a origem da deficiência: LM- lesão medular traumática baixa (T5-T12) e P - sequelas de poliomielite em apenas um dos membros inferiores. Composição corporal analisada por DEXA (gordura e massa magra corporais); bioimpedância elétrica por análise vetorial- BIVA (resistência, reactância e ângulo de fase). Os participantes do mesmo gênero foram comparados de acordo com a origem da deficiência; os grupos foram comparados à população de referência, quando esses dados eram disponíveis. Resultados: Os vetores gerados na análise por bioimpedância foram avaliados pelo teste Hotelling’s T2 e suas distâncias comparadas (Mahalanobis distance, D) entre si e com uma população de referência. Na análise por DEXA, os homens com LM apresentam maior quantidade absoluta de massa magra e, consequentemente, o maior índice de massa magra do que os P. Ambos apontaram valores inferiores à população de referência. Na análise por bioimpedância, os homens do grupo P apresentaram maior resistência que os LM e, como consequência, os menores ângulos de fase. O grupo LM foi o que mais se aproximou da população de referência. Conclusão: Considerando a composição corporal como indicador indireto do estado nutricional, o presente estudo aponta que, embora ambas as origens de deficiência apresentem valores de massa magra inferiores e valores de resistência superiores aos estudos de referência, as pessoas com poliomielite podem estar em risco nutricional aumentado em relação às pessoas com lesão medular. Esse risco parece ser maior nos homens do que nas mulheres. Dados adicionais de avaliação nutricional, como o uso de marcadores bioquímicos e dietéticos, e com um maior número de avaliados, certamente poderão explorar e elucidar melhor esses achados.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103668</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20110008</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 4 (2011); 206-210</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103668/102124</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103668/102125</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103669</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T17:20:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Is the use of computerized electrical stimulation associated with cycloergometrics in individuals with medullary lesion beneficial for the muscular parameters?</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O uso da estimulação elétrica computadorizada associada à cicloergometria em indivíduos com lesão medular é benéfico para os parâmetros musculares?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Naki, Igor Kaoru</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moreira, Maria Cecília dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electric Stimulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Paraplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quadriplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spinal Cord Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estimulação Elétrica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício Físico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paraplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Quadriplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos da Medula Espinal</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The aim of this study was to determine whether the use of FES produces muscular benefits for individuals with spinal cord injuries. Method: A review of the literature was done in the electronic database MEDLINE, PubMed, LILACS and SciELO, without limitation of time or language. The PICO strategy has been used for this research. Results: 554 articles were found. From these, 432 were excluded by title, resulting in 122 articles left. Out of these articles the duplicates were excluded resulting in 73 articles; 36 were then excluded after reading the abstract and 33 more after reading the full text. Four studies were selected. Two articles included males and females in their studies and two only included males. Three studies included quadriplegics and paraplegics in the same study; one included only quadriplegics. One of the studies used a more frequent training routine, seven times a week; three trained only three times a week. The duration of the studies was varied considerably, from six weeks to one year. The resulting measurements for strength and resistance evaluation were performed in different manners, by muscle transverse section area measurement, limb circumference, and muscle biopsy; however, all studies presented at least one of the measurements provided by the equipment, power output or work output. Improvement of the power output and work output has been shown in all studies. Despite the heterogeneity encountered in these studies, the outcomes evaluated by them indicate a significant increase in the power output and work output after training periods, with gains starting from six weeks of training at least three times a week. Conclusion: Future studies are needed to assess different responses in different groups of subjects, paraplegics or quadriplegics, under different frequencies and periods of training, and thereby provide the elaboration of more directed training protocols.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este artigo tem como objetivo revisar a literatura sobre o uso do Computerized Functional Electrical Stimulation (CFES) com desfechos musculares para os indivíduos com lesão medular. Método: Foi realizada revisão bibliográfica sistemática nas bases eletrônicas de dados MEDLINE, PubMed, LILACS e Portal SciELO, sem delimitação de tempo ou idioma. Utilizou-se da estratégia PICO para pesquisa, as palavras-chave foram selecionadas a partir dos descritores em ciências de saúde e relacionaram-se com lesão medular, estimulação elétrica e parâmetros musculares. Resultados: Foram encontrados 554 artigos. Desses, 432 foram excluídos pelo título, resultando em 122 artigos. Destes, foram excluídas as duplicidades, resultando num total de 73 artigos; 36 foram excluídos pelo resumo e 33 após a leitura do estudo. Quatro estudos foram selecionados. Dois artigos incluíram homens e mulheres em seus estudos, dois apenas homens. Três estudos incluíram tetraplégicos e paraplégicos no mesmo estudo, um incluiu apenas tetraplégicos. Um dos estudos utilizou frequência de treinamento maior, sete vezes por semana, três fizeram uso de uma frequência de treinamento de três vezes por semana. A duração dos estudos teve grande variação, de seis semanas até um ano. As medidas de resultado para a avaliação de força e resistência foram realizadas de diversas maneiras, por medida de área de secção transversal dos músculos, circunferência do membro e a biópsia muscular; contudo, todos os estudos apresentavam ao menos uma das medidas fornecidas pelo equipamento, a avaliação de potência gerada (power output) ou do trabalho realizado (work output). Em todos os estudos, houve melhora da potência gerada ou do trabalho realizado. Apesar da heterogeneidade encontrada nestes estudos, os desfechos dos estudos avaliados indicam aumento significativo de potência gerada e trabalho realizado após os períodos de treinamentos, com ganhos a partir de seis semanas e treinamentos a partir de três vezes por semana. Conclusão: Estudos futuros são necessários para avaliar as respostas em diferentes grupos de sujeitos, paraplégicos e tetraplégicos, em diferentes frequências de treinamento e em diferentes períodos de treinamento, proporcionando, assim, a elaboração de protocolos de treinamento cada vez mais direcionados.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103669</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20110009</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 4 (2011); 211-216</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103669/102126</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103669/102127</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103670</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T17:27:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Uso de um ambiente de realidade virtual para reabilitação de acidente vascular encefálico</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Use of interactive video game for stroke rehabilitation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Lucas Barbosa de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Paim, Chennyfer da Rosa Paino</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imamura, Marta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alfieri, Fabio Marcon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Interface Usuário-Computador</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">User-Computer Interface</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O acidente vascular encefálico (AVE) é uma condição clínica isquêmica ou hemorrágica que compromete o sistema nervoso central e pode desencadear déficits motores e cognitivos. Muitas pesquisas são feitas para buscar formas de amenizar os sintomas e recuperar o máximo de funções dos indivíduos. Atualmente, as últimas tendências da reabilitação são explorar o avanço tecnológico e aparelhos de realidade virtual, como o Nintendo Wii®. Objetivo: Identificar os resultados funcionais obtidos na reabilitação de indivíduos com AVE utilizando a interface de jogos do Nintendo Wii®. Método: Para esta revisão da literatura foram selecionados artigos dos bancos de dados MEDLINE, PubMed e biblioteca Cochrane pela estratégia PICO. Os descritores usados foram: User-Computer Interface AND Stroke AND Rehabilitation. Resultados: De 229 artigos encontrados, apenas três foram utilizados nessa revisão, pois apresentavam relação direta ente Wii e AVE. Todos os trabalhos apresentaram benefícios motores, como melhora da coordenação e da agilidade de membros superiores com o uso do Wii associado a terapias convencionais, como a fisioterapia e terapia ocupacional. Conclusão: Novos estudos devem ser realizados com o Wii e as novas tecnologias de realidade virtual que surgem a cada dia a fim de melhorar o nível de evidência científica quanto ao uso destes recursos na reabilitação de indivíduos portadores de sequela de AVE.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Stroke is an ischemic or hemorrhagic clinical condition that affects the central nervous system and engenders cognitive and motor deficits. Many studies are made each year to find better ways to alleviate the symptoms and recover as many of the functions lost as possible. Nowadays, the latest trends in rehabilitation are exploiting advances in technology and virtual reality devices, such as the Nintendo Wii®. Objective: To identify the functional results obtained in the rehabilitation of individuals with stroke using the interface of the Nintendo Wii games. Method: For this systematic review, articles were selected from MEDLINE, PubMed and the Cochrane Library through the PICO strategy. The keywords used were: User-Computer Interface; Stroke; and Rehabilitation. Results: We found 229 articles, of which only 3 were used in this review, because they showed a direct relationship between Wii and stroke. All studies showed benefits such as improved motor coordination and agility of upper limbs using the Wii associated with conventional therapies such as physiotherapy and occupational therapy. Conclusion: Further studies should be performed with Nintendo Wii® and the new Virtual Reality Technologies that appear every day in order to improve the level of scientific evidence regarding the use of these resources in the rehabilitation of stroke patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2011-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103670</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20110010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 18 n. 4 (2011); 217-221</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103670/102128</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103670/102129</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2011 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103672</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-27T12:51:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Ground reaction forces analyses during the gait of healthy individuals with and without the use of a calcaneus insole</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Análise das forças de reação do solo durante a marcha de indivíduos sadios com e sem uso de calcanheiras corretivas</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kleiner, Ana Francisca Rozin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carmo, Aline Araujo do</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kletecke, Regina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Burgos, Danielle</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Marcio Ferreira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barros, Ricardo Machado Leite de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Postura</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pronação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Supinação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">pé</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Posture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pronation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Supination</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Foot</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The foot forms the base of propulsion and balance during the gait. It is well known that excessive or prolonged pronation and supination changes the gait’s mechanical movement. Hence, the use of corrective insoles is recommended when calcaneus alterations (valgus and varun) are present. Objetive: The main purpose of this article was to analyze the effects of a calcaneus insole on normal individuals on the Ground Reaction Force variables. Method: The experiment used ten adults (31.9 ± 6,7 years, 65.9 ± 15.4 kg and 1.7 ± 0.1 m) and registered no apparent changes in gait or pathologies that have an effect on the locomotor system. The following gait conditions were analyzed and compared: barefoot, using a sport shoe, and using the sport shoe with insole. The variables analyzed were vertical, medial lateral, and anterior-posterior dynamic ground reaction forces. An ANOVA one-way was used in order to compare the three different conditions. Statistically significant differences were revealed between the conditions of barefoot and sport shoe with insole for the vertical GRF during initial contact Fz1 (F2,59 = 3.4; p &amp;lt; 0.0406) and for the GRF anterior-posterior in the terminal stance phase Fy2 (F2,59 = 3.63; p &amp;lt; 0.0332). Results: These results indicated that the use of an insole increased the vertical impact on the locomotor system during the response to load phase, probably because of its greater stiffness compared to the barefoot or sport shoe trials. The insole also changed the GRF anterior-posterior during the terminal stance that corresponded with the acceleration/propulsion gait phase. Conclusion: Just based on the analysis of the dynamic variables, it was concluded that the use of insoles did not induce any significant increase in lateral forces that would indicate the reduction of excessive pronation or supination during the response load phase. The use of an insole produced a significant dynamic effect on the pronation/supination only in the propulsive gait phase.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O pé constitui a base de apoio e propulsão para a marcha. É conhecido que a supinação e a pronação excessiva ou prolongada podem alterar a mecânica da marcha. Assim, o uso de calcanheiras corretivas para o desvio do calcâneo (valgo/varo) tem sido recomendado. Objetivo: Deste estudo foi analisar a influência do uso de calcanheiras na marcha de indivíduos normais através da Força de Reação do Solo (FRS). Método: Participaram do estudo dez adultos (31,9 ± 6,7 anos, 65,9 ± 15,4 kg e 1,7 ± 0,1 m) sem alterações aparentes de marcha ou patologias com reflexo sobre o aparelho locomotor. Foram comparadas as seguintes condições de marcha: descalça, tênis e tênis com calcanheira. As variáveis dependentes foram as componentes vertical, médio-lateral e ântero-posterior da FRS. Para a análise estatística a ANOVA one-way com medidas repetidas no fator condição (descalço, tênis e calcanheira) foi empregada (α &amp;lt; 0,05). Foram reveladas diferenças estatisticamente significativas entre as condições descalço e calçado com tênis e calcanheira para a componente vertical da FRS na fase de contato inicial Fz1 (F2,59 = 3,4; p &amp;lt; 0,0406) e na fase de apoio terminal para a componente antero-posterior Fy2 (F2,59 = 3,63; p &amp;lt; 0,0332). Resultados: Esses indicam que o uso de calcanheiras aumenta o impacto vertical sobre o aparelho locomotor na fase de resposta à carga, provavelmente devido a sua maior rigidez comparada ao pé descalço ou calçado com tênis. A calcanheira alterou também o padrão de resposta da componente antero-posterior da FRS na fase de terminal do apoio, que corresponde à fase de aceleração/propulsão na marcha. Conclusão: Baseado apenas na análise das variáveis dinâmicas foi possível concluir que o uso de calcanheira não induziu aumento significativo de forças laterais que poderiam indicar redução da pronação ou supinação excessiva durante a fase de resposta à carga. O uso da calcanheira produziu efeito dinâmico significativo sobre a pronação/supinação apenas na fase propulsiva da marcha.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103672</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20120001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 19 n. 1 (2012); 1-5</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103672/102130</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103672/102131</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2012 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103673</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-27T12:55:42Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeito da dominância lateral no desempenho da destreza manual em pessoas com síndrome de Down</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effect of lateral dominance on manual dexterity in people with Down syndrome</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Guimarães, Renata</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Blascovi-Assis, Silvana Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Macedo, Elizeu Coutinho de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Destreza Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Mãos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Síndrome de Down</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Skills</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hand</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Down Syndrome</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivos: Avaliar o efeito da dominância lateral na destreza manual em um grupo de crianças e adolescentes com Síndrome de Down (SD) e comparar o resultado de participantes com SD com pessoas sem a síndrome. Métodos: Participaram do estudo 100 crianças e adolescentes de ambos os sexos e idade variando de 7 a 9 anos e de 14 e 15 anos. 50 pessoas tinham diagnóstico de SD (GSD) e 50 sem a síndrome (GC). O Teste Caixa e Blocos (TCB) foi usado por possibilitar avaliação da atividade motora a partir da contagem do número de blocos transferidos entre duas divisões de uma caixa padronizada. O TCB é simples e sua aplicação não demanda habilidades cognitivas complexas. Resultados: O número de blocos transferidos por minuto foi menor nos participantes do GSD do que os do GC, com evidente desvantagem na destreza manual para ambas as mãos. Não foi observado efeito de dominância no GSD, mas no GC este efeito foi observado com melhor desempenho no lado dominante. Conclusões: O TCB foi útil para a quantificação da destreza manual em pessoas com SD já que é de fácil aplicação e compreensão por pessoas com déficit cognitivo.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To evaluate the effect of lateral dominance on manual dexterity in a group of children and adolescents with Down syndrome (DS) and to compare the results from participants with DS with people without the syndrome. Method: The study included 100 children and adolescents of both sexes with ages ranging from 7 to 9 years and 14 to 15 years. 50 people were diagnosed with DS (GDS) and 50 without the syndrome (GC). The Box and Blocks Test (BBT) was used because it allows assessment of motor activity by counting the number of blocks transferred between two divisions of a standard box. The BBT implementation is simple and does not require complex cognitive skills. Results: The number of blocks transferred per minute was lower in participants of GDS than the GC, with a clear disadvantage for manual dexterity in both hands. There was no effect of dominance in the GDS, but the GC showed better performance on the dominant side. Conclusion: The BBT was useful for the quantification of manual dexterity in people with DS as it is easy to apply and understand by people with cognitive impairment.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20120002</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 19 n. 1 (2012); 6-10</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103673/102132</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103673/102133</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2012 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103674</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-27T13:05:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effects of geotherapy and phytotherapy associated with kinesiotherapy in the knee osteoarthritis: randomized double blind study</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeitos da geoterapia e fitoterapia associadas à cinesioterapia na osteoartrite de joelho: estudo randomizado duplo cego</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Arthur, Katleen</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nascimento, Ligia Carla do</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Figueiredo, Delize Alves da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Lucas Barbosa de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alfieri, Fábio Marcon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Clay</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Phytotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Osteoarthritis, Knee</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Argila</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fitoterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Osteoartrite do Joelho</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia por Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Geotherapy is the therapeutic use of clay materials which are defined as natural earths that have different minerals in their composition. Objective: This work aimed to compare the pain, mobility, weight-bearing, and functional impairment in individuals with Knee Osteoarthritis who had undergone two types of physiotherapy treatments: the first group associated Geotherapy with Kinesiotherapy (GGK) and second group associated Geotherapy and Phytotherapy with Kinesiotherapy (GGFK). Method: This study was a randomized double-blind clinical trial, which was attended by 25 individuals of both sexes aged over 43 years; they underwent 10 sessions lasting 45 minutes each. The individuals performed the assessments to check for pain by using a visual analogue scale (VAS); to assess functional mobility, the test Timed Up and Go (TUG) test; to assess disability and symptoms, the Lequesne Algo functional questionnaire; and finally the Nintendo Wii Fit®, to measure weight-bearing between members. Results: The results showed that only the GGFK had improved functional mobility. Both groups improved the intensity of pain and symptoms after the intervention and that improvement in GGFK was superior for symptoms in relation to GGK. Both groups showed a reduction in the intensity of pain and symptoms after the intervention, and the GGFK improvement was greater than the GGK for symptoms of Osteoarthritis (OA). Neither group showed any improvement in weight-bearing. Conclusion: It was concluded that geotherapy and phytotherapy associated with kinesiotherapy can be beneficial in reducing the pain and functional impairment associated with knee OA.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A geoterapia é o uso terapêutico de argilas, que são definidas como materiais naturais terrosos que possuem em sua composição diferentes tipos de minerais. Objetivo: Este trabalho teve como objetivo comparar a dor, mobilidade, descarga de peso e prejuízos funcionais em indivíduos com osteoartrite de joelho, submetidos a dois tipos de tratamentos fisioterapêutico: grupo de geoterapia associada a cinesioterapia (GGC) e grupo de geoterapia associada a fitoterapia e cinesioterapia (GGFC). Método: O estudo foi um ensaio clínico randomizado duplo-cego no qual participaram 25 indivíduos de ambos os sexos com idade acima de 43 anos. Ambos submetidos a 10 sessões com duração de 45 minutos. Os indivíduos realizaram as avaliações para verificação da dor pela Escala visual analógica (EVA), para avaliar a mobilidade funcional o teste Timed Up and Go (TUG), para avaliar a incapacidade e sintomas o Questionário Algo funcional de Lequesne, e para medir a descarga de peso entre os membros o Nintendo Wii Fit®. Resultados: Mostraram que apenas o GGFC obteve melhora da mobilidade funcional. Ambos os grupos melhoraram a intensidade da dor e sintomas após a intervenção sendo que a melhora do GGFC foi superior ao GGC em relação aos sintomas da OA. Ambos os grupos não mostraram melhoras quanto à descarga de peso. Conclusão: A geoterapia e fitoterapia associada à cinesioterapia podem ser benéficas quanto à redução da dor e prejuízos funcionais associados à OA de joelho.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103674</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20120003</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 19 n. 1 (2012); 11-15</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103674/102134</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103674/102135</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2012 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103676</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-27T13:18:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeitos da imersão nos parâmetros ventilatórios de pacientes com distrofia muscular de Duchenne</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effects of immersion on the breathing parameters of patients with Duchenne muscular dystrophy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Camila de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Raphael Augusto Fernandes de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Spalvieri, Daiane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Braga, Douglas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Misao, Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscular Dystrophy, Duchenne</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hydrotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Immersion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pulmonary Ventilation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Distrofia Muscular de Duchenne</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hidroterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Imersão</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ventilação Pulmonar</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Em muitos centros de reabilitação, a fisioterapia aquática é utilizada para o tratamento de pacientes com distrofia muscular de Duchenne (DMD). Entretanto, são escassas as evidências científicas sobre os efeitos da imersão nos parâmetros ventilatórios desses pacientes. Objetivo: Avaliar os efeitos da imersão no nível da sétima vértebra cervical (C7) com relação aos parâmetros ventilatórios de pacientes com DMD. Método: Participaram do estudo quinze meninos com diagnóstico de DMD e média de idade de 12 anos. Coletados dados gerais e história clínica, os pacientes foram avaliados em solo e em imersão sob seguintes parâmetros: Saturação parcial de oxigênio (SpO2), frequência cardíaca (FC), pressões inspiratórias (PI Máx.) e expiratórias (PE Máx.) máximas, Volume Minuto (VM), Frequência Respiratória (FR), Volume Corrente (VC), Capacidade Vital Forçada (CVF) e Pico de Fluxo Expiratório (PFE). A SpO2 sofreu uma redução após a avaliação no meio líquido quando comparada aos valores anteriores à avaliação no mesmo meio (p = 0,01). Resultados: A FR foi maior em meio líquido que em solo (p = 0,02). As PI Máx. e as PE Máx. não se modificaram em meio líquido. Dentre os volumes analisados, a CVF e o PFE apresentaram valores menores em meio líquido quando comparada aos valores mensurados em solo (p = 0,004). VM e VC não sofreram alteração. Ao se relacionar os valores de CVF em solo e em meio líquido, assim como, os valores de PFE, observa-se que há correlação positiva entre os dados coletados em solo e em meio líquido (CVF: r = 0,692, p = 0,006; PFE: r = 0,913, p = 0,0001). A imersão no nível de C7 foi capaz de reduzir a CVF e o PFE de pacientes com DMD, bem como provocar aumento da FR dos mesmos. Conclusão: Com os dados de correlação entre valores em solo e em meio líquido da CVF e do PFE, há possibilidade de se sugerir um valor para estas variáveis em meio líquido a partir de valores mensurados em solo. Estes dados podem fornecer um melhor embasamento para avaliar a indicação de atividades em meio líquido para pacientes com DMD, em diferentes estágios de evolução da doença.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">In many rehabilitation centers, Aquatic Physiotherapy is commonly used as an optional treatment for Duchenne Muscular dystrophy (DMD) patients. However, there is so little scientific evidence about the immersion effects on the breathing parameters of these patients. Objective: Our goal was to evaluate the immersion effects to the depth of the seventh cervical vertebra (C7), related to the breathing parameters in DMD patients. Method: Fifteen boys with DMD participated of the study, averaging 12 years in age. Clinical history and general information were investigated, and the following parameters were evaluated on the ground and inside the pool: Partial Oxygen Saturation (SpO2), heart rate (HR), maximal inspiratory (PI Max.) and expiratory (PE Max.) pressures, minute volume (MV), respiratory rate (RR), tidal volume (TV), Forced Vital Capacity (FVC) and peak expiratory flow (PEF). The SpO2 diminished after the aquatic evaluation when compared to values beforehand (p = 0.01). RR was higher inside the pool than outside (p = 0.02). PI Max. and PE Max. did not change inside the pool. Results: Analyzing the results for volumes, FVC and EPF were reduced inside the pool when compared to evaluation on solid ground (p = 0.004). MV and TV did not change. A positive correlation between ground and pool values of FVC and PEF was seen (FVC: r = 0.692, p = 0.006; EPF: r = 0.913, p = 0.0001). C7 immersion was able to reduce SpO2, FVC, and PEF, while increasing the RR of DMD patients. Conclusion: With the correlation between ground and pool values of FVC and PEF encountered in this study, there is a possibility of predicting pool values for these parameters using only the ground data. These findings could lead to a scientific base for a better Aquatic Physiotherapy prescription for DMD patients, at different pathology stages.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103676</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20120005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 19 n. 1 (2012); 21-25</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103676/102136</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103676/102137</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2012 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103677</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-27T13:36:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Imagem corporal em pessoas com esclerose múltipla ativas e sedentárias</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Body Image in active and sedentary people with multiple sclerosis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tavares, Maria da Consolação Gomes Cunha Fernandes Tavares</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Campana, Angela Nogueira Neves Betanho</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Multiple Sclerosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Body Image</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Esclerose Múltipla</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Imagem Corporal</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: The aim of this research was to evaluate perceptive and attitudinal aspects of body image among people with multiple sclerosis, and the differences between these variables among active and sedentary people. Method: This study was descriptive, exploratory, and cross-sectional. The sample was composed of 26 volunteers, with Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) up to 6. Software for Perceptual Assessment, Adaptive Probit Estimation, Appreciation Scale of Own Body, Symptom scale, and a demographic questionnaire were the scales used to collect data. Nominal data were submitted to a descriptive analysis and interval data were submitted to inferential analysis. Results: The main results indicate accuracy in body perception, with high sensitivity to body change - the active people being the more sensitive. Also, 73% were dissatisfied with their appearance and tingling pain was the most frequent complaint. There was no association between dissatisfaction with body parts and painful body parts, and the reasons for their being dissatisfied were mostly esthetic. Conclusion: We concluded that regular physical activity seems to contribute to enhancing body perception, but not body satisfaction. In its turn, pain was established as a real fact - however, apart from physical appearance, indicating for health professionals who work with this clinical group that appearance and body function are distinct elements of body identity, and both have an impact on the subject relationship with its body.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Desta pesquisa foi verificar aspectos perceptivos e atitudinais da imagem corporal pessoas com Esclerose Múltipla e as diferenças destas variáveis entre praticantes e não praticantes de atividade física. Método: Esta foi uma pesquisa descritiva e exploratória, de corte transversal. A amostra foi composta por 26 voluntários, com Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) até 6. Os instrumentos utilizados foram: o Software de Avaliação Perceptiva (SAP), o Adaptive Probit Estimation, Escala de Apreciação do Próprio Corpo, Escala de Sintomas e um questionário demográfico. Os dados nominais foram submetidos a uma análise descritiva e os intervalares à análises inferenciais. Resultados: Principais indicam acurácia na percepção do corpo, com alta sensibilidade a mudanças corporais, sendo os praticantes de atividade física os mais sensíveis. Ainda, que 73% estão insatisfeitos com sua aparência e que o tipo de dor em formigamento é a queixa mais frequente. Não houve uma associação entre insatisfação com partes do corpo e áreas dolorosas, e os motivos para a insatisfação aglutinam-se em razões estéticas. Conclusão: A prática regular de atividade física parece contribuir para aumentar a percepção corporal, mas não a satisfação com o corpo. A dor estabeleceu-se como um fato real, porém independente da aparência física, indicando aos profissionais de saúde que trabalham com estas pessoas que a aparência e a função do corpo são elementos distintos da identidade corporal, e tanto um quanto o outro provoca impacto na relação do sujeito com seu corpo.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103677</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20120006</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 19 n. 1 (2012); 26-31</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103677/102138</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103677/102139</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2012 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103678</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-27T13:44:05Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Funcionalidade após a cirurgia de quadril: correlação entre equilíbrio, idade, independência e depressão em idosos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Functionality after hip surgery: correlation between balance, age, independence, and depression among the elderly</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Couto, Marcela de Abreu Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reiff, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Castro, Alessandra Paiva de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Postural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fraturas do Fêmur</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fraturas do Quadril</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidentes por Quedas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Accidental Falls</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Postural Balance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Femoral Fractures</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hip Fractures</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To determine correlations between age and balance, independence, and depression among the elderly who suffered hip fractures following a fall. Method: The consecutive sample included elderly who had suffered hip fractures within the past 24 months. We evaluated 14 elderly patients (12 women and two men); with an average age of 78 ± 6.9 years old. A questionnaire was applied to obtain general data, Timed Up and Go (TUG test), Berg Balance Scale (BBS), Geriatric Depression Scale - Short form (GDS-S), Barthel Index (BI), and Waist-hip ratio (WHR). We used the one-way ANOVA, t-test, and Pearson correlation tests with a significance levels of 5%. Results: Mean tests: BBS (35.38 ± 33.06), the TUG test (28.40 ± 10.59), the pre-fall GDS-S 6.33 ± 1.52, the post-fall GDS-S 7.66 ± 1.52, and the WHR 1.05 ± 0.35 for men and 0.92 ± 0.12 for women. The Barthel Index pre-fall was 16.20 ± 5.4 and the Barthel Index post-fall was 15.12 ± 6.78. The greater the age, the longer the stay, but there was no correlation between age and function. There was a negative correlation between age and balance, but age was not related to the level of depression. Conclusion: A positive correlation was found between age and length of stay and a negative correlation was found between age and balance. There was a decrease in the BBS, and an increase in the length of the TUG test and WHR.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Verificar correlações entre a idade e o equilíbrio, a independência, tempo de internação, e a depressão em idosos que sofreram fratura do quadril após quedas. Método: Amostra consecutiva incluiu idosos que sofreram fratura de quadril há até 24 meses. Foram avaliados 14 idosos (12 mulheres e dois homens), com idade média de 78 anos ± 6,9. Foi aplicado um questionário para obtenção de dados gerais, Time Up and Go (TUG test), Escala de Equilíbrio Berg (EEB), Escala de Depressão Geriátrica Abreviada (EDGA), Índice de Barthel e Razão cintura-quadril (RCQ). Foi aplicado ANOVA one-way, teste t e teste de correlação de Pearson com um nível de significância de 5%. Resultados: As médias dos testes: EEB (35,38 ± 33,06), o TUG test (28,40 ± 10,59); a EDGA pré-queda 6,33 ± 1,52; a EDGA pós-queda 7,66 ± 1,52; o RCQ 1,05 ± 0,35 para homens e 0,92 ± 0,12 para mulheres. O Índice de Barthel pré-queda 16, 20 ± 5,4 e o Índice de Barthel pós-queda 15,12 ± 6,78. Quanto maior a idade, maior é o tempo de internação e que não há correlação entre idade e função (IC: 0,643; valor p ≤ 0,013). Houve correlação negativa entre idade e equilíbrio, mas a idade não está relacionada ao nível de depressão (IC: -0,556; valor p ≤ 0,048). Conclusão: Foi verificada correlação positiva entre idade e tempo de internação e correlação negativa entre idade e equilíbrio. Houve a diminuição da pontuação de EEB, aumento do tempo do TUG Test e aumento da RQC.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103678</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20120007</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 19 n. 1 (2012); 32-36</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103678/102140</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103678/102141</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2012 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103679</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-27T13:51:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A influência da terapia por exercício com espelho nas limitações funcionais dos pacientes hemiparéticos: uma revisão sistemática</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The influence of mirror therapy on functional limitations of hemiparetic patients: a systematic review</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Conceição, Lívia Portugal da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Priscila de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cardoso, Leyne de Andrade</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Skills</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Destreza Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia por Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo do estudo foi verificar a influência da terapia por exercício com espelho (TEE) nos déficits sensoriais e motores dos pacientes hemiparéticos acometidos por Acidente Cerebrovascular (ACV), através de revisão sistemática. Método: Foi realizada a revisão nas bases de dados LILACS, MEDLINE, SciELO e PubMed, referente aos últimos 12 anos. A qualificação dos artigos foi feita através da plataforma PEDro. Resultados: Foram incluídos no trabalho cinco artigos em que todos eram ensaios clínicos, randomizado e controlado, que utilizaram a TEE no tratamento de pacientes hemiparéticos. A pontuação dos estudos variou de 4 a 7 pela escala PEDro, com uma nota média de 6,2. Discussão: Alguns estudos mostraram que a TEE é benéfica para aumentar a destreza, amplitude e velocidade do movimento, e outros evidenciaram que há uma maior função e recuperação motora nos pacientes tratados com a TEE.&#160; Conclusão: A TEE é benéfica para a recuperação motora, função sensório-motora e para a diminuição da dor. Indivíduos acometidos por ACV necessitam de fisioterapia e, claro, a quantidade de terapia pode influenciar no aprendizado motor, bem como a plasticidade neural. Sabemos a importância da estimulação de forma intensiva para aumentar a capacidade adaptativa do Sistema Nervoso Central em resposta a experiências, adaptações e condições diversas a estímulos repetidos. Dessa forma, se faz necessária a realização de novos protocolos de atendimento com diferentes frequências para evidenciar futuros resultados com a realidade em centros de reabilitação.&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The purpose of this study was to assess the influence of mirror therapy (MT) on sensory and motor deficits of hemiparetic patients affected by stroke, through systematic review. Method: A review was performed in the LILACS, MEDLINE, PubMed and SciELO databases, covering the last 12 years. The classification of articles was made through the PEDro platform. Results: This study included all five articles, clinical trials, and randomized controlled trial, which used MT in the treatment of hemiparetic patients. The scores of studies ranged from 4 to 7 by the PEDro scale, with an average grade of 6.2. Discussion: Some studies have shown that MT is beneficial to increase the accuracy, range, and speed of movement and other studies have indicated that there is a greater recovery and motor function in patients treated with MT. One study analyzed hemiparetic patients with acute stroke and with complex regional pain syndrome type 1 (CRPSt1), concluding that MT improves motor and sensory function. Conclusion: MT is beneficial for motor recovery, sensorymotor function, and decreased pain. Individuals affected by stroke require physical therapy and the amount of therapy can influence the motor learning and neural plasticity. We know the importance of intensive stimulation to increase the adaptive capacity of the central nervous system in response to experiences, and adaptations to repeated stimuli under various conditions. Thus, it is necessary to carry out new clinical protocols with different frequencies to show future results with reality in rehabilitation centers.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103679</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20120008</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 19 n. 1 (2012); 37-41</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103679/102142</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103679/102143</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2012 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103682</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-27T14:01:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The impact of aquatic therapy on the agility of a non-ambulatory patient with Duchenne muscular dystrophy</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Interferência da fisioterapia aquática na agilidade de paciente com distrofia muscular de Duchenne não deambulador</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Kaitiana Martins da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Braga, Douglas Martins</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hengles, Ricardo Cristian</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Beas, Allan Rogers Venditi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rocco, Fernanda Moraes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Distrofia Muscular de Duchenne</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hidroterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscular Dystrophy, Duchenne</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hydrotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Distrofia Muscular de Duchenne (DMD) é uma doença progressiva. A incapacidade de andar em geral acontece no início da adolescência, posteriormente ocorre à restrição na cadeira de rodas (CR), nesta fase da doença a cadeira de rodas é a única forma de locomoção. A agilidade na CR é um fator fundamental para a independência funcional desses indivíduos. Objetivo: O objetivo deste trabalho é verificar a interferência da fisioterapia aquática na agilidade de uma criança com DMD não deambuladora. Método: Este estudo é de caráter clínico prospectivo intervencional. O paciente foi submetido a dez sessões de fisioterapia aquática como forma de intervenção, utilizando como instrumentos de avaliação: Escala EgenKlassifikationteste de agilidade em ziguezague, saturação de oxigênio (SatO2), frequência respiratória (FR), capacidade vital forçada (CVF), volume corrente (VC), volume minuto (VM), pico de fluxo de tosse (PFT), pressão inspiratória (PImáx) e pressão expiratória máxima (PEmáx). O protocolo de intervenção da fisioterapia aquática foi definido com enfoque na agilidade com deslocamento com CR. Resultados: Foi possível observar melhora da agilidade no deslocamento com cadeira de rodas, manutenção do escore da escala EK, diminuição do VC, VM e PFT. Conclusão: Os resultados demonstraram que para este paciente a fisioterapia aquática pode interferir de forma positiva na agilidade no deslocamento com a cadeira de rodas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy (DMD) is a progressive disease. The inability to walk is common in early adolescence, and with the restriction to a wheelchair at this stage of the disease, the wheelchair becomes the patient’s only form of locomotion. Their agility in the wheelchair is a key factor for the functional independence of these individuals. Objective: The objective of this study was to verify the impact of aquatic therapy on non-ambulatory children with DMD. Method: This study has a prospective, interventional, clinical character. The patient underwent ten sessions of aquatic therapy as an intervention, using the following assessment tools: EgenKlassifikation scale, zigzag agility test, oxygen saturation (SatO2), respiratory rate (RR), forced vital capacity (FVC), tidal volume (TV), minute volume (MV), peak cough flow (PCF), and maximal inspiratory (PImax) and maximal expiratory (PEmax) pressures. The intervention protocol of aquatic therapy was defined focusing on the agility in maneuvering the wheelchair. Results: Improvement in agility was observed in moving wheelchair, maintenance of the EK scale score, and a decrease in TV, MV, and PCF. Conclusion: The results showed that for this patient, aquatic therapy may intervene positively in his mobile agility in the wheelchair.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103682</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20120009</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 19 n. 1 (2012); 42-45</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103682/102144</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103682/102145</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2012 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103684</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-27T14:05:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Estimulação elétrica funcional otimizada em pacientes com hemiparesia por doença cerebrovascular</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Functional electrical stimulation optimized in patients with hemiparesis due to cerebrovascular disease</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oshiro, Simone Hitomi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Carolina Lemes de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bim, Amanda Carolina da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Gisele Saraiva Reis de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estimulação Elétrica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiparesia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral/reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke/rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electric Stimulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Paresis</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Functional Electrical Stimulation (FES) is one of the techniques used on patients with motor sequelae such as hemiparesis after a stroke (CVA). Recent studies show positive results for the use of FES in the increase of isometric muscular strength for wrist extensors and reduction of tonus for patients with active extension of upper wrist at 20° before the intervention. Objective: As for the amplitude of movement and reduction of tonus in patients with 10° and 20° of active extension of the wrist, no significant gains were observed. Method: This study evaluated the efficiency of optimized functional electrical stimulation (O-FES) for two weeks on the manual dexterity and range of movement (ROM) of three individuals showing hemiparesis due to a stroke. Results: All the patients improved in one or more items of the evaluation (manual dexterity and ROM). Conclusion: We can conclude that the application of stimulation according to this new parameter showed benefits with a short time of stimulation on those patients with only a hint of finger movement.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Estimulação Elétrica Funcional (FES) é uma das técnicas utilizadas em pacientes com sequelas motoras como a hemiparesia após acidente vascular cerebral (AVC). Estudos recentes mostram resultados positivos para o uso de FES no aumento da força muscular isométrica de extensores de punho e redução do tônus para pacientes com extensão ativa de punho superior a 20° antes da intervenção. Objetivo: Com relação à amplitude de movimento e redução do tônus para pacientes com 10° e 20° de extensão ativa de punho, não se observaram ganhos significativos. Método: Este estudo avaliou a eficácia da estimulação elétrica funcional otimizada (FES-O) por duas semanas sobre a destreza manual e a amplitude de movimento (ADM) em três indivíduos apresentando hemiparesia decorrente de AVC. Resultados: Todos os pacientes apresentaram melhora em um ou mais itens da avaliação (destreza manual e ADM).Conclusão: Podemos concluir que a aplicação de estimulação de acordo com este novo parâmetro mostrou-se benéfica,em pouco tempo de estimulação naquelespacientes com apenas esboço de movimento de dedos.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-03-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103684</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20120010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 19 n. 1 (2012); 46-49</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103684/102146</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103684/102147</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2012 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103686</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T14:43:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Chronic cerebral vascular accident: rehabilitation</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente vascular cerebral crônico: reabilitação</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Terranova, Thaís Tavares</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Albieri, Fabiola Olea</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Munique Dias de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ayres, Denise Vianna Machado</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cruz, Sissi Farrardo da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Milazzotto, Mariana Vita</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tsukimoto, Denise Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imamura, Marta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Guias de Prática Clínica como Assunto</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Practice Guidelines as Topic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This study revised articles from the MEDLINE (PubMed) databases and other research sources, with no time limit. To do so, the search strategy adopted was based on (P.I.C.O.) structured questions (from the initials "Patient"; "Intervention"; "Control" and "Outcome". As keywords were used: (stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders OR intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism and thrombosis) AND exercise therapy AND upper extremity; (stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders OR intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism and thrombosis) AND restraint induced therapy; stroke AND exercise therapy AND upper extremity; (intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism and thrombosis OR stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders) AND electric stimulation therapy AND upper extremity; (intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism and thrombosis OR stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders) AND (orthotic devices OR splints) AND upper extremity;knowledge of Results OR biofeedback OR electromyography AND stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders OR intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism and thrombosis AND rehabilitation; stroke AND upper extremity AND functional laterality; stroke AND upper extremity AND robotics AND physical therapy modalities; stroke AND body weight supports treadmill training AND floor walking; stroke AND gait disorders AND (treadmill exercises OR floor walking); stroke AND postural balance AND physical therapy modalities; stroke AND postural balance AND feedback, sensory; (stroke OR hemiplegia) AND gait disorders, neurologic AND orthotic devices; (stroke OR hemiplegia) AND gait disorders, neurologic AND (feedback, sensory OR proprioception). stroke AND (TENS OR transcutaneous electric stimulation); (stroke OR hemiplegic) AND electric stimulation therapy AND muscle spasticity; hemiplegic AND electric stimulation therapy AND spasticity; stroke AND (virtual reality OR wii game); (stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders OR intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism OR thrombosis) AND resistance training AND recovery function; stroke AND biofeedback, psychology AND Electromyography AND gait; (stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders OR intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism and thrombosis) AND biofeedback, psychology AND (gait OR gait disorders, neurologic).</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este estudo revisou artigos nas bases de dados do MEDLINE (Pub-Med) e demais fontes de pesquisa, sem limite de tempo. Para tanto, adotou-se a estratégia de busca baseada em perguntas estruturadas na forma (P.I.C.O.) das iniciais: "Paciente"; "Intervençao"; "Controle" e "Outcome". Como descritores utilizaram-se: (stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders OR intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism and thrombosis) AND exercise therapy AND upper extremity; (stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders OR intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism and thrombosis) AND restraint induced therapy; stroke AND exercise therapy AND upper extremity; (intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism and thrombosis OR stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders) AND electric stimulation therapy AND upper extremity; (intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism and thrombosis OR stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders) AND (orthotic devices OR splints) AND upper extremity;knowledge of Results OR biofeedback OR electromyography AND stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders OR intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism and thrombosis AND rehabilitation; stroke AND upper extremity AND functional laterality; stroke AND upper extremity AND robotics AND physical therapy modalities; stroke AND body weight supports treadmill training AND floor walking; stroke AND gait disorders AND (treadmill exercises OR floor walking); stroke AND postural balance AND physical therapy modalities; stroke AND postural balance AND feedback, sensory; (stroke OR hemiplegia) AND gait disorders, neurologic AND orthotic devices; (stroke OR hemiplegia) AND gait disorders, neurologic AND (feedback, sensory OR proprioception). stroke AND (TENS OR transcutaneous electric stimulation); (stroke OR hemiplegic) AND electric stimulation therapy AND muscle spasticity; hemiplegic AND electric stimulation therapy AND spasticity; stroke AND (virtual reality OR wii game); (stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders OR intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism OR thrombosis) AND resistance training AND recovery function; stroke AND biofeedback, psychology AND Electromyography AND gait; (stroke OR cerebrovascular disorders OR intracranial arteriosclerosis OR intracranial embolism and thrombosis) AND biofeedback, psychology AND (gait OR gait disorders, neurologic).</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2012-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103686</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20120011</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 19 n. 2 (2012); 50-59</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103686/102148</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103686/102149</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2012 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2023-08-08T14:49:16Z" completeListSize="935" cursor="400">3ce3e68bda9042f15e4ae6adba4bf1c0</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
