<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-08-07T14:49:03Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="actafisiatrica">https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102493</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-01-14T22:50:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O efeito da terapia de biofeedback por eletromiografia de superfície na flexão de joelho da marcha hemiparética</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The effects of biofeedback therapy by surface electromyography on knee flexion in hemiparetic gait</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Priscila Garcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vasconcelos, Jeane Cintra Peixoto de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ramos, Arquimedes de Moura</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moreira, Maria Cecília Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, José Augusto Fernandes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kavamoto, Cristianne Akie</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Biofeedback</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Biofeedback</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The main objective of this paper was to evaluate the effects of biofeedback therapy by surface electromyography (EMG) on knee flexion in hemiparetic gait. A 58 years old male patient was selected for this study, 11 months after a stroke resulting in left side hemiparesis. Initially, he was subjected to a physical examination and observational gait analysis. Before treatment, the patient was also referred to the movement laboratory of the institution (DMR HC FMUSP). The patient underwent a treatment plan comprising twelve sessions of biofeedback therapy by surface EMG during seven weeks. Right after the end of the therapy the evaluation was repeated. The results showed that gait asymmetry was diminished. Left hip circumduction during swing was decreased. Pelvic obliquity during the whole gait cycle was lower than that of the initial evaluation. Lower values for right hip abduction during initial contact and mid swing were also measured. Left ankle dorsiflexion during the swing phase of gait was increased. Although biofeedback therapy was focused on knee flexion, the gait pattern of the patient showed global improvements. For example, left ankle dorsiflexion during the swing phase was increased while hip circumduction was less apparent. This can probably be explained by the fact that therapy was delivered while the patient was performing a functional activity, gait. These results show that biofeedback therapy by surface EMG seems to be a promising technique in the management of stroke patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo deste trabalho foi avaliar o efeito da terapia de biofeedback por eletromiografia (EMG) de superfície na flexão de joelho na marcha hemiparética. Foi avaliado um paciente do sexo masculino, 58 anos com hemiparesia esquerda, após acidente vascular encefálico (AVE) e 11 meses de lesão. Foi realizada avaliação física e análise observacional da marcha, seguida da avaliação tridimensional da marcha no Laboratório de Análise do Movimento da Divisão de Medicina de Reabilitação do Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo (DMR HC FMUSP), pré e pós intervenção terapêutica. Foram realizadas 12 sessões de biofeedback por EMG de superfície durante sete semanas. Os resultados mostraram melhora na simetria da marcha, com diminuição da circundução do quadril esquerdo, redução da obliqüidade pélvica durante todo o ciclo da marcha, diminuição da abdução do quadril no contato inicial e balanço médio à direita e aumento da dorsiflexão esquerda durante a fase de balanço. Embora o enfoque inicial tenha sido o movimento de flexão de joelho, os resultados demonstraram melhoras globais na marcha, como o aumento da dorsiflexão e a diminuição da circundução do quadril no membro inferior parético. Isso pode ser explicado pelo fato do treinamento ter sido realizado dentro de uma atividade funcional, a marcha. A terapia de biofeedback por EMG de superfície parece ser uma técnica promissora no tratamento de pacientes com alterações da marcha após AVE.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102493</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v11i3a102493</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 11 n. 3 (2004); 125-131</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102493/100807</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2004 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102495</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:21:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Toxina botulínica tipo A: propriedades farmacológicas e uso clínico</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Botulinum toxin type A: pharmacological properties and clinical use</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sposito, Maria Matilde de Mello</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Toxina Botulínica Tipo A</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Botulinum Toxins, Type A</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">All information contained in this review refers to the botulinum toxin type A (BTX-A) produced by Allergan Inc. represented in Brazil by Allergan Produtos Farmacêuticos and which name is BOTOX®. Botulinum toxin type-A (BTX-A) is a biologic agent that is obtained in laboratory; it is a stable crystalline substance, lyophilized in human albumin, and supplied in sterile vacuum-sealed vial (in the case of BOTOX®) to be diluted in saline solution. BTX-A is naturally produced by Clostridium botulinum, an anaerobic bacterium that produces eight serologic types of toxin, out of which type A is the most potent, and therefore, it is clinically used.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Todas as informações contidas neste trabalho de revisão são referentes a toxina botulínica do tipo A (TBA) produzida por Allergan Inc, representada no Brasil por Allergan Produtos Farmacêuticos, cujo nome comercial é BOTOX®. A toxina botulínica do tipo-A é um agente biológico obtido laboratorialmente, sendo uma substância cristalina estável, liofilizada em albumina humana e apresentada em frasco a vácuo estéril, para ser diluída em solução salina. A TBA é produzida naturalmente pelo Clostridium botulinum, uma bactéria anaeróbia, que produz oito tipos sorológicos de toxina, sendo a do tipo-A a mais potente e por isto utilizada clinicamente.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2004-12-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102495</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v11iSupl.1a102495</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 11 n. Supl.1 (2004): Toxina Botulínica Tipo A; S7-S44</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102495/100810</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2004 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102497</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:23:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Edit</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A Acta Fisiátrica agora é digital</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Acta Fisiátrica is now digital</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Revistas Eletrônicas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electronic Journals</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Através do novo portal eletrônico será possível o encaminhamento de artigos originais, revisões bibliográficas, relatos de casos, opinioes e cartas com custo reduzido e menor tempo de postagem, facilitando a tarefa de autores para direcionamento das suas pesquisas para ao seu objetivo final - a publicação. O novo website também permite maior velocidade e agilidade no contato dos autores com a edição, por exemplo quando sao solicitadas alterações ou complementações dos textos originais por parte dos revisores. Se o objetivo da pesquisa é o desenvolvimento de conhecimento e o objetivo da revista é a divulgação, entao a inclusão de resultados das pesquisas em um veículo com acesso mais amplo só significará maior divulgação da produtividade acadêmica, tornando o conhecimento mais acessível ao leitor.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102497</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 1 (2005); 6-6</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102497/100811</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102498</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:24:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação de um manual de exercícios domiciliares para pacientes externos de um ambulatório de bloqueio neuromuscular</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of a manual of home exercises for outpatients from a neuromuscular block program</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Figueiredo, Márcia de Menezes Paranhos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barbosa, Márcia Cristina Catarino</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moreira, Maria Cecília Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Espasticidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercícios Fisioterapêuticos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação em Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Toxina Botulínica Tipo A</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemiplegy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spasticity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapeutic Exercises</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Education in Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Type A Botulinum Toxin</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O Acidente Vascular Encefálico (AVE) constitui um grande desafio ao processo de reabilitação por ocasionar, dentre os sintomas secundários, a hemiplegia espástica com hipertonia, redução de força e flexibilidade muscular e alterações osteoarticulares que dificultam a funcionalidade dos pacientes acometidos. Neste contexto, a intervenção fisioterapêutica deve ser freqüente e contínua para minimizar as complicações inerentes a esta enfermidade. O enfoque deste trabalho visou em analisar a aplicabilidade de um programa de exercícios domiciliares para pacientes externos do Ambulatório de Bloqueio Neuromuscular Periférico da Divisão de Medicina Física e Reabilitação do Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo (DMR) baseando-se na capacidade dos pacientes e cuidadores em assimilar e compreender a necessidade de executar os exercícios prescritos após a infiltração de toxina botulínica tipo A (TBA). Participaram deste estudo 30 pacientes que não realizavam tratamento na DMR, portadores de hemiplegia espástica após AVE isquêmico ou hemorrágico que foram submetidos à infiltração de TBA nos membros inferiores. O manual proposto continha 13 exercícios e o fisioterapeuta assinalava quais deveriam ser realizados, de acordo com a musculatura infiltrada, com intervalo de tempo especificado a serem executados diariamente. Os exercícios foram demonstrados para esclarecimento de dúvidas pré-existentes. Após 1 mês, os pacientes retornaram ao ambulatório e respondiam um questionário composto por 10 questões que coletavam dados sobre a aplicabilidade do manual de exercícios domiciliares como recurso terapêutico. A partir dos resultados obtidos, constatou-se que o programa foi efetivo pela didática do manual ser compreensível, possibilitando que a maioria dos pacientes realizasse os exercícios ativamente, favorecendo no processo educacional dos pacientes e cuidadores em relação aos cuidados à saúde. No entanto, verificou-se que alguns sujeitos apresentaram dificuldade em executar os exercícios que solicitavam a utilização do membro superior comprometido, sendo sugerido por eles, a inclusão de exercícios complementares que favoreçam a prática da cinesioterapia com a autonomia de execução. Conclui-se que para que o manual seja mais eficiente, é necessária a inserção de diferentes métodos de execução a fim de contemplar todos os pacientes com AVE respeitando o padrão motor apresentado e seus respectivos déficits funcionais.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Stroke is a great challenge to rehabilitation causing, among secondary symptoms, spastic and hypertonic hemiplegia, reduction of strength, flexibility and joint deformity, leading to desability THUS. So, to reduce the complications related to this condition, physical therapeutic measures must be frequent and continuous. Our work is aimed at evaluating the feasibility of a home exercises program manual for Peripheral Neuromuscular Blockade Ambulatory at the Division of Rehabilitation Medicine (DMR) outpatients, considering the patients and caregivers' ability to understand the need of practicing the prescribed exercises after type A botulinum toxin (TBA) treatment. Thirty new outpatients with spastic hemiplegia caused by ischemic or hemorrhagic stroke and treated with lower limb TBA injection were enrolled on it. The program had 13 exercises and a physical therapist would select which of them should be done every day, according to the injected muscles. Exercises were performed with the patients in order to clarify any doubts. After 1 month, patients answered 10 questions about the home exercises manual feasibility as a therapeutic resource. Results showed the efficacy of the program, because manual was clear and most of patients had practiced the exercises actively, favoring the heath-related education between them and the caregivers. Otherwise, some subjects had difficulty to realize the exercises that demanded the diseased upper limb action. These subjects suggested the inclusion of complimentary exercises, favoring kinesiotherapy practice allied to execution autonomy. In conclusion, it is necessary to increase the manual efficiency, the inclusion of different execution methods to attend all the stroke patients with their respective motor pattern and disabilities.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v12i1a102498</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 1 (2005); 7-10</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102498/100812</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102500</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:24:11Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da dor e função de pacientes com lombalgia tratados com um programa de Escola de Coluna</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of pain level and function on low back pain patients treated with Back School program</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Caraviello, Eliana Zeraib</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wasserstein, Sílvia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chamlian, Therezinha Rosane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Masiero, Danilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Back Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Back School</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lombalgia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Escola de Coluna</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Incapacidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The incidence of lumbar pain affects approximately 80% of the population at some point in their life, being, therefore, a major public health problem. The differential diagnosis of the spinal diseases is very broad, but it is known that a substantial number of occurrences are related to posture and inadequate body movements. Therefore, the Back School developed a treatment option for these patients. This work focused on the evaluation of pain level and the lack of functional capacity of the patients before and after attending the Back School. The Roland-Morris survey and the analogical visual scale of pain were used for such purpose. A total of 30 patients were evaluated from May 2004 to November 2004. The sample consisted of predominantly middle-aged (median of 48.1 years), overweight (70%), females (86.7%) from low education levels. The majority of patients demonstrated improvement of the pain (56,7%) and the function ( 60%) by the end of the rehabilitation program.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">As dores lombares incidem em cerca de 80% da população em algum momento de sua vida, sendo, portanto, um grande problema de saúde pública. O diagnóstico diferencial das doenças da coluna vertebral é bastante amplo, mas sabe-se que boa parte das afecções está relacionada a posturas e movimentos corporais inadequados. Criou-se, portanto, a Escola de Coluna como opção de tratamento a estes pacientes. Neste trabalho avaliamos a dor e a incapacidade funcional dos pacientes, antes e após freqüentarem a Escola de Coluna, através do questionário de Roland-Morris e da Escala Visual Analógica de Dor. Estudamos 30 pacientes no período de maio a novembro de 2004, sendo 86,7% do sexo feminino, com idade média de 48,1 anos, de baixa escolaridade e com excesso de peso (70%). A maioria dos pacientes apresentou melhora da dor (56,7%) e da função (60%) após o término do programa de reabilitação.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102500</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20050002</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 1 (2005); 11-14</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102500/100813</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102501</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:24:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Constraint-induced therapy as an approach to the improvement of upper limb in stroke patients</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A terapia de restrição como forma de aprimoramento da função do membro superior em pacientes com hemiplegia</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Monroy, Heloisa Moreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kaihami, Harumi Nemoto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Otsubo, Priscilla Pereira dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">CI-Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Functional Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disabilities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neuroplasticity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia de Restrição</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação Funcional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Incapacidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neuroplasticidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A terapia de restrição consiste na imobilização do membro superior não comprometido de pacientes hemiplégicos em decorrência de acidente vascular cerebral (AVC) como forma de estímulo ao uso do membro superior que teve a sua força reduzida. Experimentos realizados em algumas amostras específicas de pacientes mostram resultados promissores com essa abordagem. Este estudo teve o objetivo verificar seu efeito numa amostra de pacientes hemiplégicos em processo de reabilitação. Foram selecionados pacientes com AVC há mais de 6 meses que se encontravam em processo de reabilitação e possuíssem força para extensão da mão e dedos de pelo menos 10º de forma voluntária. A aplicação da restrição foi associada a 6 horas de terapia multidisciplinar diariamente em dias de semana e orientada a manutenção das atividades nos finais de semana. Para avaliação dos resultados foram usados os seguintes instrumentos: medida de independência funcional (MIF), teste motor de Wolf (TMW), escala de avaliação das deficiências do AVC (EADAVC) e dinamometria de preensão. Observou-se ganho estatisticamente significante na MIF (108,5 ± 6,4 versus 113 ± 7,3, p = 0,02) e TMW (10,5 ± 6,4s versus 6,5 ± 3,7s, p = 0,006), mas não na EADAVC (56,7 ± 4,4 versus 59,4 ± 8,4, p = 0,16) ou Dinamometria de pressão (16,2 ± 4,5 kgf versus 16,3 ± 5,4 kgf, p = 0,98). A conclusão deste estudo é que a aplicação da técnica de restrição do membro superior em pacientes hemiplégicos pode resultar em ganhos agudamente, indicando um caminho alternativo na abordagem das suas incapacidades.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Constraint induced therapy (CI-therapy) consists in the restriction of movements by the preserved upper limb of stroke patients as a means of stimulation of the use of the weakened limb. Experiments performed in selected samples have shown some promising results. This study aimed at verifying the effect of such approach in a sample of stroke patients under rehabilitation. Patients were selected once their cerebral vascular injury had happened at least 6 months previously, and they could perform a 10 degree extension of the wrist and finger voluntarily. Beyond the restriction, 6 daily hours of therapy were performed and there was orientation to keep up with the therapeutic activities at home in the weekends. Evaluating instruments were: Functional Independence Measure (FIMTM), Wolf motor function test (WMFT), stroke impairment scale (SIAS) and hand grip dynamometry. A statistically significant improvement could be observed in FIM (108,5 ± 6,4 versus 113 ± 7,3, p = 0,02) and WMFT (10,5 ± 6,4s versus 6,5 ± 3,7s, p = 0,006), but not in SIAS (56,7 ± 4,4 versus 59,4 ± 8,4, p = 0,16) or grip dynamometry (16,2 ± 4,5 kgf versus 16,3 ± 5,4 kgf, p = 0,98). We concluded that the use of CI-therapy in stroke patients may acutely produce functional improvement, indicating an alternative pathway in the approach to their disabilities.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102501</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20050001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 1 (2005); 15-19</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102501/100814</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102507</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:24:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Use of body weight support over ground in gait training of the spinal cord injuried patient</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Utilização do suporte de peso corporal em solo no treino de marcha do lesado medular</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Faria, Caroline Del Vecchio de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moreira, Maria Cecília dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barbosa, Márcia Cristina Catarino</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sabbag, Lívia Maria Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Suporte de Peso Corporal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Treino de Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismo da Medula Espinhal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Body Weight Support</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait Training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spinal Cord Injury</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O presente trabalho consiste na utilização do suspensor de peso corporal (SPC) como recurso a ser empregado quando o paciente lesado medular alcança a fase de preparação para a marcha, pois permite o treino com a descarga gradativa de peso sobre o solo, proporcionando a adaptação do paciente à atividade, com menor gasto energético. Objetivo: Demonstrar a utilização do suporte de peso corporal como recurso auxiliar no treino de marcha inicial do lesado medular e apontar o ganho funcional, representado pela distância/tempo percorrida, associado ao gasto energético e à freqüência cardíaca. Sujeito: Paciente vítima de acidente automobilístico em 2003, com diagnostico de lesão medular completa, nível T7 hipotônica. Procedimento: O treinamento de marcha com o suspensor de peso corporal constou de 21 sessões com duração de 30 minutos, 2 vezes por semana. Um teste ergoespirométrico foi realizado antes e após o treinamento. Resultados: O paciente apresentou redução da pressão arterial de 150/100 mmHg para 120/80 mmHg, aumento da distância percorrida de 30 m para 70 m, considerável redução do tempo de duração de cada volta e redução da FC de repouso e das FC de pico. Considerando os coeficientes físicos relacionados, freqüência cardíaca média por volta e tempo total de realização do teste, houve expressiva melhora no desempenho físico do paciente.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The present research consists in the use of body weight support (BWS) as a resource when the spinal cord injured patient reaches the phase of preparation for gait, because it allows to the trainings with the gradual discharge of weight on the ground, providing the adaptation of the patient to the activity, with lower energy expense. Objective: To demonstrate the use of body weight support as an auxiliary resource in the initial gait training in an individual with spinal cord injury and to show the functional gain, represented by the distance/ time covered, associate to the energy expenditure and the cardiac rate. Subject: Patient victim of automobile accident in 2003, with diagnostic of spinal cord injury, hypotonic T7 level. Procedure: The gait training with body weight support consisted of 21 sessions with duration of 30 minutes, 2 times per week. An ergoespirometric test was carried through before and after the training. Results: The patient presented reduction of the blood pressure of 150/100 mmHg for 120/80 mmHg, increase covered distance of 30 m for 70 m, considerable reduction of duration time of each lap and reduction the cardiac frequency of rest and the cardiac frequency of peak. Considering the related physical coefficients, average cardiac frequency for lap and total time of accomplishment of the test, he had expressive improves in the physical performance of the patient.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102507</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v12i1a102507</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 1 (2005); 21-25</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102507/100815</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102510</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:24:25Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Tend.+Refle.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina e arte: observações para um diálogo interdisciplinar</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Art and science: notes to an interdisciplinary dialogue</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cherem, Alfredo Jorge</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Art</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physiatry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Anatomy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">History of Medicine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Arte</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisiatria</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Anatomia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">História da Medicina</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Begining from other non-invasive methods, some medical specialists find themselves involved with the question of the diagnostic and the evaluation of the incapacity provoked by WRMD. It is expected that each one may develop the knowledge specific to his specialty, but in dialogue with other areas, owing to the fact that specialists sustaining their profession from exclusively technical knowledge do not always recognize that medicine is a science that was for a long time also an art. On that way attempt to this link may result in a larger interdisciplinary horizon. Connecting Medicine and Art, this text aims to enrich the specialist's understanding through the history of "signs" and "symptoms" that occur in the body. Such knowledges, coming since the Renaissance as through Leonardo Da Vinci, Michelangelo, and Vesálio allow us establish - even though by a seemingly distant and indirect route - with an approach by which we may become more attentive and discerning in the observation of details. From the patient's history to his physical examination until the correct diagnosis, the physician could reduce the indication of complementary exams and the recommendation of invasive methods.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Partindo de métodos não invasivos, algumas especialidades médicas encontram-se envolvidas com a questão do diagnóstico e avaliação da incapacidade provocada pelos distúrbios osteomusculares relacionados ao trabalho. O que se espera das mesmas é que desenvolvam conhecimentos próprios e singulares, mas em interlocução com outras áreas, devendo-se salientar o fato de que, a partir de concepções exclusivamente técnicas, os especialistas nem sempre reconhecem que a medicina é uma ciência que durante um longo período foi também uma arte. Daí que atentar para esse elo pode resultar num alargamento do próprio horizonte interdisciplinar. Relacionando medicina e arte, o presente texto pretende contribuir para que o entendimento do especialista seja enriquecido através da história dos sinais e sintomas que insidem sobre o corpo. Tais conhecimentos, vindos desde o renascimento e legados pelos artistas como Leonardo Da Vinci, Miguelangelo e Vesálio permitem reconhecer, ainda que por via aparentemente distante e indireta, um meio para que nos tornemos mais atentos e criteriosos na observação de detalhes. Transitando do histórico para o exame físico do paciente, até chegar a uma diagnóstico preciso, o médico poderá reduzir ao mínimo necessário a solicitação de exames complementares e a recomendação de práticas invasivas.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102510</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v12i1a102510</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 1 (2005); 26-32</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102510/100816</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102523</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:26:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Comparação do ganho de flexibilidade isquiotibial com diferentes técnicas de alongamento passivo</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Comparison of hamstring flexibility gain with different techniques of static stretching</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bonvicine, Cristiane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Claus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Batigália, Fernando</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Range of Motion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stretching</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physiotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Amplitude de Movimento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Alongamento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia por Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Embora vários estudos tenham investigado os efeitos dos exercícios na amplitude de movimento e rigidez articular, a duração ideal do alongamento ainda não foi determinada. Este estudo objetivou comparar os efeitos de duas diferentes técnicas de alongamento muscular isquiotibial repetitivo passivo quanto ao ganho de amplitude de movimento, durante quatro semanas. Foram estudadas 30 mulheres, voluntárias, de mesma faixa etária, divididas em dois grupos de quinze. Foi realizada a goniometria da flexão de quadril de ambos os membros inferiores das 30 voluntárias. O grupo estudado recebeu uma sessão de alongamento sustentado por 60 segundos no membro inferior direito e 2 sessões de alongamento de 20 segundos, com intervalo de 10 segundos, no membro inferior esquerdo. As outras 15 participantes constituíram o grupo controle e não receberam nenhuma intervenção. A comparação do ganho de alongamento entre os grupos foi realizada pelo teste t de Student (amostras de distribuição normal), teste t para amostras variáveis (amostras de distribuição não normal), e teste t pareado (para a comparação entre as duas sessões de alongamento). O ganho de alongamento no membro inferior direito no grupo tratado foi significativo(p&amp;lt;0.001), assim como o ganho de alongamento no membro inferior esquerdo (p&amp;lt;0.001). A variação da amplitude de movimento no grupo controle não foi significante (p=0,80). O ganho de amplitude de movimento foi maior no membro inferior direito (p=0,001). O ganho de amplitude de movimento para a musculatura isquiotibial mostrou ser maior em sessões de alongamento passivo de uma série de 60 segundos cada.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Although several studies have investigated the effects of exercise in range of motion and joint rigidity, the right amount of stretching has not been determined. The purpose of this study was to compare the effects on the hamstring muscles after two different techniques of repetitive static stretching during four weeks in order to compare the gain of range of motion. Thirty women of similar age were divided into two groups of 15 for the study. Measurement of range of motion for hip flexion in both legs was performed in all women. The studied group (n=15) received a session of sustained stretching during 60 seconds in the right limb and two sessions of stretching during 20 seconds with interval of 10 seconds in the left limb. The control group did not receive any intervention. Student’s t test was used to compare the gain of stretching between both groups; paired t test was used to compare abnormal distribution, and the comparison between two sessions of stretching was performed by the matched t test. The gain of stretching in the right leg of the treated group was significant (p&amp;lt;0.001). The gain of stretching in the left leg of the treated group was also significant (p&amp;lt;0.001). The variation of range of motion in the control group was not significant. The gain of range of motion was greater in the right leg (p&amp;lt;0.001). The gain of range of motion in relation to hamstring muscles showed to be greater in the static stretching sessions of 60 seconds each.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102523</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20050005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 2 (2005); 43-47</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102523/100818</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102525</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:26:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação dos sintomas de disfunção miccional em crianças e adolescentes com paralisia cerebral</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of voiding dysfunction symptoms in children and adolescents with cerebral palsy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Amaral, Cássia Maria Carvalho Abrantes do</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalhaes, João Tomás de Abreu</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Trato Urinário</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Crianças e Adolescentes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Bexiga Neurogênica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Urinary Tract</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Children and Adolescents</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neurogenic Bladder</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">To evaluate voiding dysfunction symptoms in subjects with cerebral palsy (CP) and their relationship with variables such as: neurologic diagnosis, age, sex, the fact of having received or not prenatal care, birth weight, walking, speech, cognitive involvement, constipation and previous urinary tract infection (UTI), besides verifying, among the studied cases, the presence of neurogenic bladder. Methods: It was a cross-sectional study, whitch evaluated one hundred patients aged between 2-18 years diagnosed with CP who attended pediatric appointments in the outpatient clinic of Pediatrics of the Associação de Assistência à Criança Deficiente – AACD (Association of Assistence to the Handicapped Child), without severe mental deficiency. All these patients were submitted to IQ Tests, Pediatric Interview besides Urodynamic Study. Results: After recruiting and examining one hundred subjects with CP aged 2-18 years, the present study found 30 cases with urinary symptoms. Eleven of these cases were diagnosed as neurogenic bladder. Among the variables analysed, only the mean age (9,35 years) has shown statistically significant relation with urinary tract dysfunction. Conclusions: Children and adolescents with CP presented voiding dysfunction symptoms irrespective of the variables presented, except for the age, which might be related to the lower degree of their dementia and motor function diagnoses. Among the patients with urinary symptoms, 11 presented urodynamic studies compatible with neurogenic bladder (36,67%). The early urinary tract dysfunctional diagnosis is intended to avoid possible alteration of the Upper Urinary Tract. Also, it represents a preventive treatment for such patients, allowing them a better quality of life, hence contributing to their rehabilitation and integration into society.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliar as disfunções do trato urinário inferior (DTUI) em pacientes com paralisia cerebral (PC) e sua relação com variáveis como: diagnóstico neurológico, idade, sexo, realização ou não de pré-natal durante o período gestacional, peso ao nascimento, deambulação, fala, cognitivo, constipação intestinal e história de infecção do trato urinário (ITU), além de verificar, entre os casos estudados, a presença de bexiga neurogênica. Métodos: Estudo transversal que avaliou 100 pacientes com idade entre 2 e 18 anos completos com diagnóstico de PC que compareceram em consulta pediátrica no ambulatório de pediatria da Associação de Assistência à Criança Deficiente (AACD), sem deficiência mental (DM) grave através de avaliação psicológica de QI, entrevista pediátrica e estudo urodinâmico. Resultados: Após a avaliação de 100 casos de PC entre crianças e adolescentes de 2 a 18 anos, foram verificados 30 casos de pacientes com sintomas urinários, 11 destes com quadros urológicos de bexiga neurogênica. Entre as variáveis analisadas, apenas a média de idade (9,35 anos) apresentou relação estatisticamente significativa com a presença de sintomas urinários. Conclusão: As crianças e adolescentes com PC apresentaram sintomas de disfunções do trato urinário independente das variáveis analisadas, exceto pela idade, o que pode estar relacionado talvez à menor gravidade de seus quadros de DM e deficiência motora. Entre os pacientes com sintomas urinários, 11 apresentaram estudos urodinâmicos compatíveis com bexiga neurogênica (36,67%). O diagnóstico dos sintomas de disfunção do trato urinário precoce tem como objetivo evitar possíveis alterações do trato urinário superior, além de significar um tratamento preventivo para estes pacientes, proporcionando uma melhora de qualidade de vida e ajudando no processo de sua reabilitação e incorporação à sociedade.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102525</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v12i2a102525</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 2 (2005); 48-53</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102525/100819</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102526</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:26:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Impacto da hospitalização na independência funcional do idoso em tratamento clínico</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The impact of hospitalization on functional independence of elderly in clinical units</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Kawasaki, Kozue</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Diogo, Maria José D’Elboux</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hospitalização</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medida de Independência Funcional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividades de Vida Diária</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hospitalization</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Functional Independece Measure</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Activities of Daily Living</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Elderly</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo geral deste trabalho foi avaliar a independência funcional de idosos hospitalizados em unidades de clínica médica. O estudo foi realizado em um hospital universitário do município de Campinas, SP, com 28 idosos de ambos os sexos, internados para tratamento clínico, com idade média de 68 anos. Foi utilizado o instrumento de Medida da Independência Funcional (MIF) no momento da internaçao, durante o período de hospitalizaçao, no momento da alta e um mês após a alta hospitalar. Foi possível observar uma diminuiçao nos valores da MIF total e seus domínios durante a hospitalizaçao, quando comparado a admissao (média: 109,2±14,0), a alta (média: 97,8±19,4) e um mês após o retorno ao domicílio (média: 114,4±14,1), com diferença significativa (p&amp;lt;0,05)nos valores da MIF da alta hospitalar ao domicílio, e da admissao a alta hospitalar, na MIF total e nos seus domínios. Durante a internaçao, houve declínio dos escores das tarefas da MIF de autocuidado, de controle da urina, de transferência, de locomoçao e de resoluçao de problemas. Conclusão: os resultados mostraram a ocorrência de declínio da independência funcional durante o período de hospitalizaçao e recuperaçao funcional após retorno ao domicílio.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The general objective of this study was to evaluate functional independence inpatient of elderly patients in clinical wards of medical services. The study was conducted at the University Hospital in Campinas, SP with 28 geriatric inpatient admitted to the clinical wards. The Functional Independence Measure (FIMTM) instrument was used to assess patients at three moments: hospital admission, hospital discharge, and one month after discharge. Results: There was a decline of total FIMTM scores and their domains, motor and cognitive, during the period of hospitalization. At hospital admission the mean was 109.2±14.0, at hospital discharge the mean score was 97.8 ±19.4 and one month after the discharge the mean was 114.4±14.1, with significant difference (p&amp;lt;0.05) from admission to discharge, as well as from discharge to one month after discharge either in total FIMTM scores or in its domains. The items of self-care, bladder continence, transfer, locomotion and problems resolving decreased during the hospitalization. Conclusion: There was a functional decreased between hospitalized elderly and a recovered after return home.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102526</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20050003</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 2 (2005); 55-60</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102526/100820</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102527</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:26:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Funcitional Independence of spinal cord injured patients</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Independência funcional de pacientes com lesão medular</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pinto, Paulo Potiguara Novazzi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sakamoto, Hatsue</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lesão medular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Independência Funcional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medida de Independência Funcional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividades de Vida Diária</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spinal Cord Injury</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Functional Independency</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Activities of Daily Living</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">To know the clinical presentation of spinal cord injured patients in terms of functional independence allows rehabilitation services to organize themselves in order to respond to the needs of these people in a most efficient way. On aiming to describe such standards of functioning, 150 medical charts of spinal cord injured patients discharged from two rehabilitation centers from 2000 to 2003 were reviewed for clinical, demographic and functional data. Male participation was 72% of the sample; mean age was (33.8 ± 14.2 years), being 21.3% of the cases due to non-traumatic injuries. Among traumatic injuries, 30.5% were cervical, 52.5% thoracic and 17.0% lumbar. Mean period between injury and the star of rehabilitation was 22.6 ± 46.7 months. At the begging of the rehabilitation, Stairs (11.9%) and Dressing lower body (24%) presented as the activities in which less patients were independent, while Feeding (68.4%) and Grooming (51.6%) showed more independence. The period from onset of injury was directly associated with motor FIM, confirming the clinical impression that spinal cord injured patients develop some degree of independence even without therapeutic support owing to the demands of daily life. Rehabilitation approach must be as early as possible in order to enable the acquisition of best performance, in the shortest time and the most appropriate way because the independence achieved without professional support may mean a compromise in security and higher energetic costs.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Conhecer a apresentação dos pacientes com lesão medular em termos de independência funcional permite aos serviços de reabilitação estruturarem-se para atenderem às demandas dessa população de forma mais eficiente. Com o objetivo de descrever tal padrão de funcionalidade, 150 relatórios de alta de pacientes com lesão medular de dois centros de reabilitação no período de 2000 a 2003 foram consultados para obtenção de dados clínicos, demográficos e da medida de independência funcional. Homens corresponderam a 72% da amostra, com média de idade de 33,8 ± 14,2 anos, sendo 21,3% dos casos devido a lesões não-traumáticas. Entre as lesões traumáticas, 30,5% em nível cervical, 52,5% torácicas e 17% lombares. O período médio de lesão foi de 22,6 ± 46,7 meses. No início do programa de reabilitação, Escadas (11,2%) e Vestir a metade inferior do corpo (24%) foram as tarefas nas quais menos pacientes apresentavam independência funcional, enquanto Alimentação (68,4%) e Higiene pessoal (51,6%) apresentaram maior independência. O período decorrido desde a instalação da lesão esteve diretamente associado a ao valor da MIF motora no início da reabilitação, confirmando a impressão clinica de que mesmo sem a orientação profissional os pacientes com lesão medular desenvolvem algum grau de independência funcional em virtude das necessidades enfrentadas no dia-a-dia. O atendimento de reabilitação ao paciente com lesão medular deve ser o mais precoce possível a fim de propiciar a aquisição de melhor desempenho em menor tempo e de formas mais apropriadas, pois por vezes a independência atingida faz-se às custas de comprometimento de segurança ou maior custo energético.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102527</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20050004</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 2 (2005); 61-66</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102527/100821</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102528</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:26:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Influência da transferência reto-femoral na excursão dos joelhos em pacientes com paralisia cerebral</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The influence of rectus femoris transfer on knee range of motion of cerebral palsy patients</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Binha, Anny Michelly Paquier</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cristante, Adriana Rosa Lovisotto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alonso, Gláucia Somensi de Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Morais Filho, Mauro César</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Juliano, Yara</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Análise de Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Articulação do Joelho</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Amplitude Articular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transferência Reto-Femoral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait Analysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Knee Joint</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Range of Motion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rectus Femoris Transfer</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A marcha com o joelho rígido é um padrão comum na paralisia cerebral e a etiologia, em muitos casos, é a espasticidade do músculo reto-femoral. A transferência deste músculo para flexor de joelho tem sido usada como tratamento, porém com resultados variados. Para avaliar a efetividade deste procedimento, vinte e oito pacientes com paralisia cerebral tipo diparesia espástica, submetidos à transferência do reto-femoral, foram estudados retrospectivamente. No subgrupo A (n=16), os pacientes não usavam órteses ou auxiliares para marcha e enquanto que no subgrupo B (n=12) sim. Foi considerado como critério de inclusão a realização da análise computadorizada da marcha antes e após cirurgia. O objetivo foi avaliar o efeito do tratamento no arco de movimento dos joelhos (cinemática) e na qualidade de vida dos pacientes (questionário). Resultados mostraram aumento do arco de movimento dos joelhos para os dois subgrupos (p=0,006 para o A e p=0,045 para B). A avaliação subjetiva (questionário) demonstrou alto nível de satisfação após tratamento apesar dos familiares responderem que quase não houve mudanças nas atividades de vida diária. Os resultados sugerem ser necessário uma investigação adicional para identificar outros fatores que poderiam alterar os resultados e que, um instrumento mais objetivo, como o GMFM é uma opção melhor para avaliação funcional.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Stiff knee gait is a common walking pattern in cerebral palsy and rectus femoris spasticity is the etiology in many cases. Rectus femoris transfer has been used in the treatment of this condition, but surgery outcomes are variable. In order to evaluate the effectiveness of this procedure, twenty-eight patients with diparetic spastic cerebral palsy, that had undergone rectus femoris transfer, were reviewed in retrospective study. In the subgroup A (n=16), patients did not use orthosis or walking aids, but in the subgroup B(n=12) they did. A complete tridimensional gait analysis before and after surgery was considered an inclusion criterion. The objective was to evaluate the effect of treatment at knee range of motion (kinematic) and patient quality of life (questionnaire). Results show increase of knee range of motion in both subgroups (p = 0,006 in the subgroup A and p = 0,045 in the subgroup B). The subjective evaluation (questionnaire) demonstrated high level of satisfaction despite the fact that there was no change in the activities of dairy life after surgery. The results suggest that further investigation is necessary to identify which factors could influence rectus transfer results and a more objective instrument, like Gross Motor Function Measure, is a better option to evaluate function level.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102528</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v12i2a102528</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 2 (2005); 67-71</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102528/100822</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102529</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:26:44Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Tend.+Refle.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Identidade, é possível esquecê-la?</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Identity, is it possible to forget it?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Schewinsky, Sandra Regina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Memória</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Identidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Teoria Sócio-Histórica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Memory</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Identity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Socio-Historic Theory</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O presente trabalho tem como objetivo uma reflexão sobre as dificuldades e sofrimentos impingidos à pessoa que apresenta prejuízos de memória, principalmente no tocante a sua identidade, em função de um acometimento mórbido cerebral que acarretou déficits cognitivos, além da instalação da Hemiplegia. Para adentrar este percurso utilizarei o referencial teórico da Psicologia Sócio-Histórica, pois o indivíduo desenvolve-se com suas peculiaridades e singularidades em um processo dialético na interação com o meio e com o outro. Será discutido porque os déficits de memória podem ser tão dramáticos, interferindo na consciência, na atividade, afetividade e identidade da pessoa. Finalmente como o atendimento de reabilitação pode facultar o processo de metamorfose da identidade do paciente.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This work aims to make some considerations about the difficulties and suffering impinged to the person who presents memory deficiency, mainly in terms of identity, due to a morbid event in the brain, which has also led to hemiparesis. In order to develop these observations, the socio-historic theory will be the reference, because the individual grows in his own peculiarities in a dialectic process of interaction with the environment and the others. It will be discussed the reason memory deficits can be so dramatic, interfering with conscience, activity and identity of the patient. Finally, it is discussed the way the approach in rehabilitation can allow a transformation in the individual’s identity.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102529</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v12i2a102529</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 2 (2005); 72-76</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102529/100823</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102530</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:29:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da neuropatia periférica: correlação entre a sensibilidade cutânea dos pés, achados clínicos e eletroneuromiográficos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of diabetic neuropathy: correlation between cutaneous sensibility in the feet, clinical and eletroneuromyographic findings</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Ary</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nery, Caio Augusto de Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marciano, Lúcia Helena Soares Camargo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Garbino, José Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diabetes Mellitus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neuropatia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevenção</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Eletroneuromiografia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação Clínica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Diabetes Mellitus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neuropathy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Prevention</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electroneuromyography</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Clinical Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Avaliar a eficácia dos monofilamentos de Semmes-Weinstein no diagnóstico e prognóstico do pé com neuropatia diabética. Método: Estudo prospectivo em 35 pacientes diabéticos tipo II. Os pacientes foram submetidos a um protocolo contendo anamnese, levantamento das queixas, exames clínicos, estudo neurofisiológico e pesquisa da sensibilidade cutânea nos pés. Resultado: Pôde-se constatar bom grau de concordância entre os monofilamentos de Semmes-Weinstein e o estudo neurofisiológico. Os monofilamentos de Semmes-Weinstein se revelaram sensíveis para detectar pacientes com algum tipo de alteração. Discussão: constatou-se bom grau de coincidência entre os monofilamentos de Semmes-Weinstein e o estudo neurofisiológico expresso pelo coeficiente de correlação de Spearman (r= 0,677). Os monofilamentos de Semmes-Weinstein demonstraram ser eficazes na detecção de alterações da sensibilidade cutânea, observando-se que 91% dos pacientes apresentaram variações entre os graus 2 e 5. O estudo neurofisiológico detectou 69% dos pacientes na faixa de 2 a 5 graus. A maior diferença entre os dois métodos ficou evidenciada nos pacientes sem comprometimento (grau 1), demonstrando uma sensibilidade mais elevada dos monofilamentos de Semmes-Weinstein. O estudo também mostrou uma boa correlação entre o comprometimento clínico dos pacientes com os déficits neurológicos medidos pelos monofilamentos de Semmes-Weinstein. Conclusão: os monofilamentos de Semmes-Weinstein são confiáveis para diagnosticar a neuropatia diabética dos pés. Há correlação entre os achados neurofisiológicos e os critérios clínicos obtidos com os monofilamentos. Os monofilamentos de Semmes-Weinstein ajudam na avaliação do prognóstico e evolução do pé diabético e podem ser utilizados com segurança na avaliação dos pés com neuropatia periférica.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To evaluate the efficacy of the Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments for diagnosis and prognosis of feet with diabetic neuropathy. Methods: a prospective study with 35 type II diabetic patients. Patients took part of a protocol including anamnesis, complaints, physical examination, electrophysiological study and determination of cutaneous sensitivity of the feet. Results: Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments and electrophysiological study coincided highly. The Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments were sensitive to detect patients with some degree of change. Discussion: A good degree of agreement was observed between the Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments and electrophysiological study methods, as expressed by the correlation coefficient of Spearman (r= 0.677). The Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments were more sensitive to detect patients with some type of change, because we observed 91% of patients between grade 2 and grade 5. The electrophysiological study detected 69% of patients in the same range. Major difference was observed in patients without involvement (grade 1) showing elevated sensitivity of the Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments. The study also showed good correlation between clinical involvement of patients with neurological deficits measured with the Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments. Conclusion: the Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments are reliable to diagnose neurophatic diabetes of the feet. There is correlation between neurological findings and clinical criteria obtained with the monofilaments. The Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments are helpful in the evaluation of prognosis and evolution of the diabetic foot and they may be safely utilized in the evaluation of the feet with peripheral neuropathy.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102530</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v12i3a102530</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 3 (2005); 87-93</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102530/100824</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102531</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:29:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effects of aerobic training on quality of life and functional capacity of chronic stroke survivors</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeitos do treinamento aeróbio na qualidade de vida e na capacidade funcional de indivíduos hemiparéticos crônicos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Moura, Regina Márcia Faria de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Renata Cristina Magalhães</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lage, Diana Cunha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Amaral, Emiliana Alcântara Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aerobic Conditioning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Condicionamento Aeróbio</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Indivíduos com seqüela do acidente vascular cerebral (AVC) apresentam, na maioria das vezes, um alto custo energético durante a realização das atividades e apesar das evidências dessa alteração após o AVC, poucos são os autores que têm investigado os efeitos do treinamento aeróbio. Objetivo: Avaliar os efeitos de um treinamento aeróbio na capacidade funcional e na qualidade de vida (QDV) de indivíduos com seqüelas decorrentes do AVC na fase crônica. Casuística e Método: Foram avaliados dois participantes, um do sexo masculino e um do feminino, que foram recrutados na Clínica Escola do Centro Universitário Newton Paiva, em Belo Horizonte/MG. A capacidade funcional foi avaliada pelo Teste de Caminhada de 6 minutos e a percepção da QV pelo instrumento Perfil de Saúde de Nottingham (PSN), aplicados antes da intervenção, na 10ª, 20ª, 30ª e 40ª sessões. Resultados e Discussão: A redução tanto da distância quanto da velocidade de caminhada estão geralmente associadas a alterações de equilíbrio, fraqueza muscular e descondicionamento físico. Neste estudo houve aumento da distância caminhada dos dois participantes sugerindo melhora da capacidade funcional. Também houve redução no escore do PSN que também sugere uma melhor QV após o protocolo de reabilitação. Conclusão: Os participantes do estudo apresentaram melhora da capacidade funcional e alteraram positivamente a percepção da QV após programa de treinamento aeróbio. Para generalização dos resultados para a população com seqüelas decorrentes do AVC na fase crônica são necessários estudos com casuística maior.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Stroke victims presentwith a high energetic consumption during the motor activities most of the times and, despite the evidences of this post stroke deficiency, few authors have investigated the effects of aerobic training. Objective: To assess the effects of an aerobic training in functional capability and quality of life (QOL) in people with chronic impairment following stroke. Methods: Two participants were assessed, one man and one woman, recruited from Newton Paiva University clinic school, in Belo Horizonte/MG. The functional capability was assessed by the Six Minutes Walk Test and the perception of QOL by the Nottingham Health Profile instrument (NHP). Evaluations were performed before the intervention and repeated within the 10th, 20th, 30th and 40th sessions. Results and Discussion: The reduction both in the distance and in the walk velocity are in general associated with changes in balance, muscle weakness and physical deconditioning. In the present study the distance walked by both participants has increased, suggesting improvement in the functional capability. A reduction in the score of the NHP has also been noticed, which suggests a better quality of life after the rehabilitation protocol. Conclusion: The participants of the study increased their functional capability and altered in a positive way their perception of QOL after the aerobic training program. To generalize these results to people with sequels of a stroke in a chronic phase studies with a bigger sample are necessary.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102531</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v12i3a102531</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 3 (2005); 94-99</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102531/100825</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102532</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:29:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Multiple sclerosis and exercise</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Esclerose múltipla e exercício físico</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Furtado, Otávio Luis Piva da Cunha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tavares, Maria da Consolação Gomes Cunha Fernandes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Multiple Sclerosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Esclerose Múltipla</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício Físico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividade Física</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Multiple sclerosis is a chronic neurological disease with unknown etiology, characterized by axon damage and demyelinated areas of the central nervous system. The physical disability and the associated symptoms are usually related to the functional systems impairment and disuse. Immunomodulatory and immunosuppressive agents are commonly used for the treatment, however they can delay but not interrupt the disease progress. In the last two decades muscle strength, aerobic, aquatic and yoga programs have been developed for groups with multiple sclerosis showing its efficiency and safety. From a literature review we will discuss the impact of these programs in relevant aspects of the disease like strength alterations, fatigue, spasticity, depression and abnormal heat reaction.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A esclerose múltipla é uma doença neurológica crônica de origem desconhecida, caracterizada por lesões axonais e áreas de desmielinização do sistema nervoso central. Nessa doença, a incapacidade física e uma série de sintomas estão relacionados ao comprometimento de sistemas funcionais e ao desuso. O tratamento geralmente inclui o uso de imunomoduladores e imunossupressores, que são capazes de retardar, mas não interromper sua progressão. Nas duas últimas décadas, programas incluindo exercícios de fortalecimento muscular, exercícios aeróbios, atividades em meio aquático e ioga têm se mostrado seguros e eficazes para pessoas com esclerose múltipla. A partir de revisão bibliográfica, discutiremos essas pesquisas e seu impacto em aspectos relevantes da doença como as alterações da força muscular, fadiga, espasticidade, depressão e a reação anormal ao calor.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102532</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v12i3a102532</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 3 (2005); 100-106</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102532/100826</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102533</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:29:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The influence of unilateral negligence in the performance of activities of daily living: report of 3 cases</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A influência da negligência unilateral no desempenho de atividades de vida cotidiana: relato de 3 casos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tsukimoto, Denise Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Valester, Gabriela Antunes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Activities of Daily Living</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Perceptual Motor Performance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemispatial Neglect</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Task Performance and Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ecological Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Occupational Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Encefálico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividades de Vida Diária</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Negligência Hemi-Espacial</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação e Desempenho de Tarefas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Desempenho Psicomotor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação Ecológica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia Ocupacional</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A negligência unilateral é descrita como uma limitação na habilidade de direcionar, responder ou orientar-se frente a estímulos apresentados no lado oposto ao da lesão cerebral, freqüentemente se manifestando através de sistemas sensoriais variados, incluindo os sistemas visual, somatosensorial e auditivo e é diagnosticada quando esta habilidade diminuída não pode ser atribuída a déficits motores ou sensitivos. O objetivo deste estudo é analisar e discutir as implicações deste acometimento influenciando o desempenho das atividades de vida cotidiana, através da realização de três relatos de caso e análise da atividade de alimentação, resultando no desenvolvimento de uma versão inicial de um protocolo para análise de atividade específica para quadros de negligência unilateral.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Unilateral neglect is described as a impaired ability to attend, respond, or orient to stimuli presented to the side opposite a brain lesion, frequently occurring across various sensory systems, including the visual, somatosensory, and auditory systems and it is diagnosed when this impaired ability cannot be attributed to sensory or motor deficits. The aim of this study is to analyze and discuss the important implications of this condition affecting the performance of activities of daily living, through three case reports and analysis of the activity of feeding, resulting in the development of an initial version of a protocol for activity analysis specific for patients with unilateral neglect.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102533</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v12i3a102533</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 3 (2005); 108-114</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102533/100827</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102534</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:29:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação objetiva da síndrome dolorosa miofascial: uso da termografia antes e após tratamento associando mesoterapia a bloqueio anestésico</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Myofascial syndrome objective evaluation: thermography before and after treatment with mesotherapy and trigger-point injections</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Balbinot, Luciane Fachin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vieira, Luiz Rosa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Síndrome Dolorosa Miofascial</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Termografia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da Dor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Mesoterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Infiltração Anestésica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Myofascial Pain Syndrome</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Thermography</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pain Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Mesotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Analgesic Injection</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Síndrome miofascial é um diagnóstico comum em pacientes com dor segmentar. As queixas costumam ser inespecíficas; o uso da técnica de Fischer associando algometria de pressão e técnicas especiais de palpação auxiliam a identificar os pontos gatilhos ativos. A mesoterapia (intradermoterapia) mostra-se muitas vezes mais eficaz quando associada às técnicas de bloqueio paraespinal e bloqueio de pontos gatilhos com lidocaína. O resultado deste tratamento pode ser documentado através da termografia, além dos meios clínicos já citados. O padrão de cores (vermelho a verde, no caso da imagem colorida ou tons de cinza na imagem em preto e branco) indica gradiente de temperatura. Neste estudo, descrevemos o caso clinico de uma paciente feminina, de 54 anos de idade, com queixa de dor severa em região cervical, referida ao membro superior direito. A mesma foi tratada com mesoterapia associada a bloqueio paraespinal e bloqueio de pontos-gatilho ativos e o resultado deste tratamento foi avaliado clinicamente e pela termografia 25 minutos após e 03 dias após o tratamento. Os autores concluíram que a termografia é um método promissor na avaliação da dor miofascial. Mais estudos são necessários para usar a termografia como método auxiliar na triagem de casos de LER/DORT, visto que, em nossa experiência, é freqüente a associação desta síndrome, como fator agravante.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Myofascial pain syndrome is a very common diagnose in patients with segmental pain and complains are very unspecific; the use of Fischer’s technique, with algometry and special palpation method helps identifying active trigger points (TP). Mesotherapy seems to have better and faster results if associated with Dr Fisher’s technique of paraspinal block (PSB) and TP injections. It can be documented (qualitatively and quantitatively) by infrared thermography beside algometry. The different colors (red to green) or scale of gray in a black&amp;amp;white image indicate more than 1 grade centigrade change. In this paper we described a case of a 54 years old woman with neck pains referred to her right arm. She was treated with Mesotherapy, PSB and TP injections. The results were evaluated by visual analogue scale, algometry, palpation techniques and thermography. The authors concluded that thermography is a promissory method for pain evaluation. More studies are necessary about thermography as an auxiliary method for myofascial pain syndrome diagnose, particularly when associated with repetitives injuries which are usual in our experience.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2005-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102534</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v12i3a102534</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 12 n. 3 (2005); 115-117</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102534/100828</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2005 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102535</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:33:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Discussão crítica sobre o uso da água como facilitação, resistência ou suporte na hidrocinesioterapia</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Discussing about the use of water as facilitation, resistence or support in hydrotherapy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Candeloro, Juliana Monteiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Caromano, Fátima Aparecida</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hidrocinesioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício Físico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hydrotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The hydrotherapy is a physiotherapeutic resource based in the hydrodynamic that includes the flotation and the viscosity analysis. It provides that the motors activities in warm pool can be facilitated resisted or offer support to the body or its segment. In this revision it is discussed motor activities in these three situations focusing the correct posture to be used for a certain therapeutic objective besides as the aquatic equipment that can offer progression to motor activities.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A hidrocinesioterapia é um recurso fisioterapêutico que utiliza os efeitos fisiológicos decorrentes da imersão em água aquecida, dentre eles a flutuação e a viscosidade que fazem com que as atividades motoras possam ser facilitadas, resistidas ou ofereçam suporte ao corpo ou seus segmento. Nesta revisão discute-se a prática de atividades motoras nestas três situações, enfocando o decúbito correto a ser utilizado para um determinado objetivo terapêutico e como os equipamentos aquáticos podem oferecer progressão no grau de dificuldade para diferentes atividades motoras.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102535</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i1a102535</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 1 (2006); 7-11</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102535/100829</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102535/157770</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102563</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:33:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Tratamento fisioterapêutico do ombro doloroso de pacientes hemiplégicos por acidente vascular encefálico: revisão da literatura</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Physiotherapy treatment in hemiplegic shoulder pain in stroke patients: literature review</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Klotz, Tatiana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Borges, Heloise Cazangi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Monteiro, Vanessa Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chamlian, Therezinha Rosane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Masiero, Danilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Shoulder Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physiotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Cerebrovascular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ombro Doloroso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The objective of this study was to review on literature the effect of the physiotherapeutic treatment for hemiplegic shoulder pain. In order to review the literature, articles published from 1997 to 2004 and indexed in: Medline, Lilacs, Pubmed and Cochrane were used. Trials were considered if they included patients of any age with a clinical diagnosis of stroke with hemiplegic shoulder pain in acute or chronic phase, without previous stroke. Sixty-six articles were identified, but only 12 studies met the inclusion criteria. According to the literature reviewed, its possible to suggest that the electric stimulation is the most studied modality and that offers a promising future for the treatment of hemiplegic shoulder pain, however more research with better methodology must be performed.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo deste estudo foi revisar na literatura estudos sobre os efeitos dos métodos fisioterapêuticos utilizados para tratar ombro doloroso no paciente hemiplégico após Acidente Vascular Encefálico (AVE). Para a realização dessa revisão bibliográfica, foram utilizados artigos publicados no período de 1997 a 2004 e indexados nas seguintes bases de dados: Medline, Lilacs, Pubmed e Cochrane. Os artigos selecionados incluíam pacientes de qualquer idade com diagnóstico de AVE em fase aguda ou crônica sem histórico de outra patologia precedente ou AVE prévio com déficits persistentes e quadro clínico de ombro doloroso após episódio de injúria cerebral. Dos 66 artigos selecionados, 12 encontravam-se nos critérios de inclusão. Com base na literatura consultada, foi possível sugerir que a estimulação elétrica constitui-se no recurso fisioterapêutico mais estudado e mais promissor no tratamento do ombro doloroso, porém ainda necessitando de pesquisas com melhor qualidade metodológica.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102563</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i1a102563</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 1 (2006); 12-16</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102563/100846</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102563/157771</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102567</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:33:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Epidemiologia das lesões esportivas em atletas de basquetebol em cadeira de rodas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology of sportive injuries in basketball wheelchair players</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rocco, Fernanda Moraes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Saito, Elizabete Tsubomi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Esporte Adaptado</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos em Atletas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Úlcera de Decúbito</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tendinte</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Adapted Sports</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Athletes Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Decubitus Ulcers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Tendonitis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A atividade esportiva para os portadores de deficiência física (PPD) foi desenvolvida com o objetivo de ser recreativa e reabilitacional, entretanto, para alguns o esporte desperta uma vocação competitiva. Nesta situação, um número excessivo de treinamentos e competições pode levar a aumento no risco de lesões esportivas, que segundo a literatura é semelhante para atletas com ou sem deficiência. Objetivo: Identificar as lesões esportivas mais freqüentes nos atletas de basquetebol em cadeira de rodas. Casuística e método: Foi realizada entrevista dirigida com 26 atletas do sexo masculino de basquetebol em cadeira de rodas, com idade entre 18 a 47anos (média de 27 anos), que participaram de um campeonato de basquetebol em cadeira de rodas em 2003. Foram obtidas informações pessoais dos atletas, etiologia da deficiência física, quanto tempo que pratica o esporte, horas de treino por semana, queixa de dor e quantificação da mesma pela escala verbal analógica, histórico de lesões durante a prática esportiva e tempo de afastamento. Resultados: Dentre as deficiências físicas apresentadas pelos atletas a lesão medular correspondeu a 42%, seqüela de poliomielite a 31% e amputação de membros inferiores a 27%. O tempo em que praticavam o esporte variou de 2 meses a 13 anos, com média de 6.5 anos. A carga horária de treinamento foi em média 21horas de treino por semana. Nestes atletas observou-se queixa de dor em 54%, sendo em sua maioria em membros superiores (79%). De todos os atletas apenas 6 (23%) nunca tinham apresentado lesão durante jogo ou treinamento. Entre os 11 atletas lesados medulares, 3 (27%) apresentaram afastamento devido à úlcera de pressão (região isquiática, sacra e paravertebral). Dentre as lesões esportivas ocorridas temos que 75% delas foram de forma aguda e 25% por esforço repetitivo. Discussão: Na literatura há muitos estudos que evidenciam uma alta prevalência de acometimento muscular em atletas que competem em cadeira de rodas, acompanhado de queixa de dor na extremidade superior do corpo, principalmente no ombro. Contusões e entorses de metacarpos são as lesões agudas e tendinites as lesões por esforço repetitivo mais encontradas na literatura. Quando expressamos o tempo de afastamento das atividades esportivas temos na literatura que em 52% este ocorre por 7 dias ou menos, em 29% por 8 a 21 dias, e em 19% por período maior que 22 dias. Vários autores citaram úlcera de pressão como fator de afastamento das atividades esportivas variando de 14% a 20% entre os atletas com lesão medular. Nosso estudo evidenciou aspectos semelhantes.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Sportive activity for people with disabilities has been developed in order to be recreative and rehabilitative however, for some people, the sport rises a competitive aspiration. In such situations, an excessive number of training sessions and competitions may lead to an increased risk of sport injuries, which, according to the literature, is similar in disabled and able-bodied athletes. Objective: To identify the most frequent sport injuries of basketball wheelchair players. Patients and method: an interview was conducted with 26 male wheelchair basketball athletes, whose age varied from 18 to 47 years (mean: 27 years), and who participated in the state championship in 2003. Biodemographic data, as well as the etiology of the injury, weekly time spent with the sport and training activities, previous injuries during the sport practice and periods without sport practice due to those injuries, pain intensity evaluated by the visual analogue scale. Results: spinal cord injury corresponded to 42% of the patient, poliomielites to 31%, lower limb amputation to 27%. Sport practice varied form 2 months to 13 years, with an average of 6.5 years. Mean training periods was 21 hours weekly. Pain complaint was present in 54%of these athletes , being mostly localized in the upper limbs (79%). Only 6% of the sample had never had an injury during a game or training. Of the 11 spinal cord injured patients, 3 (27%) were not playing because of pressure sores (isquiadic, sacral and paravertebral). Among the musculosqueletal injuries, 75% were installed acutely, and 25% due to chronic repetitive efforts. Discussion: many studies comment about the increased incidence of musculoskeletal affections in wheelchair competitors, followed by pain in the upper extremity, mainly in the shoulder. Sprains and strains of metacarpophalangeal joints are the acute injuries and tendonitis are the repetitive strain injuries mostly described. The period of prevention from training in 52% of patients is less than 7 days, in 29% between 8 and 21 days, and in 19% of the athletes it is more than 22 days. Many authors mention that pressure sores prevent sport activities in spinal cord injured athletes. Our study showed similar results.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102567</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i1a102567</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 1 (2006); 17-20</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102567/100848</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102567/157775</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102569</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:33:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Identification of factors associated to pressure sores in paraplegic individuals and related to leisure activities</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Identificação de fatores associados às úlceras por pressão em indivíduos paraplégicos relacionados às atividades de lazer</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Leite, Valéria Barreto Esteves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Faro, Ana Cristina Mancussi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Paraplegy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pressure Sore</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paraplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Úlcera por Pressão</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The spinal cord injury provokes motor and sensory deficits, vasomotor and autonomic alteration bellow the level of injury. The pressure sore (PS) is frequently observed and serious among paraplegic individuals. The goals of this study are to identify the factors associated to PS among paraplegic individuals which injury was in T6 or bellow and related then to PS prevention and leisure activities. The study was done in a selection place of a rehabilitation center in São Paulo-Brazil. The population was constituted by 35 paraplegic individuals and 90,32% were male; 22,58% had more than 53 years old; 45,16% had paraplegy from 1 to 3 years and 83,87% had trauma as the cause of injury. The use of television and videocassette was cited by 67,74%. In relation to the nature of leisure activities, 70,0% referred as passive activities and 18,18% as active. The PS occurred less frequently among individuals with active leisure actions. The preventive interventions cited more often were skin self-exam and change of positions. The health assistance must be holistic and based on preventive intervention. In the selection the rehabilitation professional’s an opportunity to promote therapeutic approach in order to prevent PS.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">As lesões da medula espinhal trazem como conseqüência o déficit motor e sensitivo, abaixo do nível lesionado além de disfunções vasomotoras e alterações autonômicas, entre outras. A úlcera por pressão (UP) é uma das mais freqüentes e graves conseqüências da lesão medular, ainda observada na maioria dos indivíduos paraplégicos. O objetivo deste estudo foi identificar os fatores associados à úlcera por pressão em indivíduos paraplégicos com lesão nível T6 ou abaixo, relacionados à prevenção de UP e atividades de lazer. A pesquisa foi realizada na triagem de um centro de reabilitação no município de São Paulo, junto a 35 indivíduos paraplégicos. Deste total (35) 90,32% eram do sexo masculino, 22,58% deles com idade maior do que 53 anos, com tempo de paraplegia entre 1 e 3 anos para 45,16 e etiologia traumática da paraplegia para 83,87% dos casos. O uso da televisão e vídeo foi a atividade de lazer mais citada (67,74%). Verificou-se que em 70,0% dos casos as atividades de lazer eram mais passivas e as mais ativas em 18,18%, sendo o aparecimento de UP para mais ativos. Auto-exame de pele e mudança de decúbito as medidas mais citadas. Uma abordagem holística por parte dos profissionais reabilitadores é de fundamental importância para a eficácia da prevenção de UP, sendo a triagem uma oportunidade terapêutica positiva para a prevenção de UP.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102569</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i1a102569</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 1 (2006); 21-25</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102569/100850</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102569/157776</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102572</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:34:14Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evolution of the functional independence of elderly patients from a home care service through the point of view of caregivers</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Evolução da independência funcional de idosos atendidos em programa de assistência domiciliária pela óptica do cuidador</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ricci, Natalia Aquaroni</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lemos, Naira Dutra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Orrico, Karine Fróes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gazzola, Juliana Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aging Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Frail Elderly</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Homebound Patients</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Home Care Services</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Functional Independence Measure</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde do Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso Débil</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pacientes Domiciliares</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Serviços de Assistência Domiciliar</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medida de Independência Funcional</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The knowledge of the performance of the aged one in its activities have a major importance in the home care services, because it is the objective of professionals and caregivers during health care. The objective of this study was to evaluate the functional independence evolution of patients included under home care, through the caregiver’s point of view of the Functional Independence Measure (FIM) instrument, at two moments, with one year between them. A follow up study was designed. The data had been gotten in recorded case histories of 22 patients, who contained the evaluation of FIM at the two studied moments (October 2003 and October 2004). The recorded of the patients who presented changes of caregiver between the evaluations, exclusion of the program and death were excluded. Simple descriptive analyses were made and statistical differences were tested using Paired- T Test and Wilcoxon test. The association of the results of the MIF with gender, age and diseases of the patients had been analyzed by means of Paired- T Test and correlation of Pearson. The features of the sample were composed by a feminine majority, with advanced age and multiple associated illnesses. Statistically significant differences were not found between the evaluations by the perception of the caregiver, in the averages of the motor, cognitive and total FIM, of the medium of six dimensions and eighteen categories of the FIM. The maintenance in the expression activity was associated with the feminine sort, while that the social interaction activity and the cognition area correlated with the number of diseases. Maintenance of the functional capacity of the patients in the studied period was observed. The results suggest that the home care attendance was revealed as a capable modality to keep or to delay the functional decline from elderly.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O conhecimento do desempenho do idoso em suas atividades é de grande importância na assistência domiciliar, pois é o que norteia os profissionais e o cuidador no monitoramento dos cuidados prestados. O objetivo deste estudo foi avaliar a evolução da independência funcional de idosos inclusos em um programa de assistência domiciliária, sob a ótica do cuidador pela Medida de Independência Funcional (MIF), em dois momentos, com intervalo de um ano entre eles. Foi realizado estudo de seguimento, no qual os dados foram obtidos pelos prontuários de 22 pacientes, que continham a avaliação da MIF nos dois momentos estudados (outubro de 2003 e outubro de 2004). Foram excluídos os prontuários que apresentaram mudança de cuidador entre as avaliações, exclusão do programa e óbito. Realizou-se análise descritiva simples e para verificar as diferenças estatísticas o teste t-pareado e teste de Wilcoxon. A associação dos resultados da MIF com as variáveis de gênero, idade e comorbidades dos idosos foram analisadas por meio do test t - pareado e correlação de Pearson. A amostra caracterizou-se por uma maioria feminina, com idade avançada e múltiplas doenças associadas. Não foram encontradas diferenças significantes entre as avaliações, das médias da MIF motor, cognitivo e total, das medianas das seis áreas e das dezoito atividades da MIF. A manutenção na atividade expressão se associou com o gênero feminino, enquanto que a atividade interação social e a área cognição com o número de comorbidades. Observou-se manutenção da independência funcional dos pacientes no período estudado. Os resultados sugerem que no período de um ano os idosos foram capazes de manter ou retardar seu declínio funcional.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102572</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i1a102572</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 1 (2006); 26-31</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102572/100852</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102572/157779</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102574</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:33:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Confiabilidade de dois métodos de avaliação da amplitude de movimento ativa de dorsiflexão do tornozelo em indivíduos saudáveis</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Reliability of two evaluation methods of active range of motion in the ankle of healthy individuals</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Venturini, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>André, Alex</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Aguilar, Bruna Prates</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Giacomelli, Bruno</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Goniometria</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Amplitude de Movimento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tornozelo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Confiabilidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisiologia Articular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Goniometry</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Range of Motion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ankle</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Reliability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Joint Physiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A medida da amplitude do movimento é um importante parâmetro utilizado na avaliação e no acompanhamento fisioterápico. Portanto, a confiabilidade destas medidas e dos instrumentos utilizados para esta finalidade deve ser avaliada. Objetivo: Avaliar e comparar a confiabilidade intra-examinador e interexaminador da medida de amplitude do movimento (ADM) de dorsiflexão ativa do tornozelo utilizando um goniômetro universal e um inclinômetro digital. Métodos: Dois estudantes avaliaram a amplitude de dorsiflexão de 28 voluntários com idade entre 18 e 30 anos utilizando um inclinômetro digital e um goniômetro universal. Resultados: Os resultados demonstram média e desvio padrão da amplitude do movimento de 18,1±3,1 e 18,6±3,8 graus para as medidas obtidas pelo goniômetro e inclinômetro, respectivamente. O coeficiente de correlação intraclasse (CCI) encontrado para a condição na mesma sessão para as medidas obtidas com o inclinômetro foi de 0.91 e 0.83, para os examinadores A e B, respectivamente. Já o CCI obtido pelo goniômetro foi de 0.91 e 0.97 para os examinadores A e B, respectivamente. Os resultados da confiabilidade entre as sessões de teste demonstraram confiabilidade moderada para as medidas de goniometria e alta confiabilidade para a inclinometria. Já a confiabilidade interexaminador foi moderada para as medidas obtidas pelo goniômetro e alta para as medidas obtidas pelo inclinômetro. Conclusão: Os resultados do presente estudo demonstraram uma maior confiabilidade para as medidas de amplitude de movimento obtidas pelo inclinômetro digital quando comparado com o goniômetro universal, principalmente quando a confiabilidade interexaminador foi avaliada.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The measurement of the range of motion is an important parameter used in physical therapy evaluation and follow up. Thus, the reliability this measurements as well as instruments utilized to this purpose to need be evaluated. Objective: to evaluate and compare the intra-tester and inter-tester reliability of the range of motion measure (ROM) of active ankle dorsiflexion utilizing a universal goniometer and a digital inclinometer. Methods: Two students evaluated the range of dorsiflexion of the 28 volunteers with aged between 18 and 30 years utilized a digital inclinometer and a universal goniometer. Results: The results displayed mean and standard deviation the range of motion the 18.1±3.1 e 18.6±3.8 degrees to the measures obtained for the goniometry and inclinometer, respectability. The intraclass coefficient (ICC) obtained to the intra-session condition to the measures with the inclinometer was the 0.91 to 0.97 for the examiners A and B, respectively. ICC for the goniometry was the 0.91 and 0.97 to the examiners A and B, respectively. The inter-session condition demonstrated moderate reliability to the measures of the goniometry and adequate reliability to the inclinometer measurements. However, the interexaminers reliability was moderate to the measures of the goniometry and high for measures with the inclinometer. Conclusion: The results of this study demonstrated the big reliability to the measures of the digital inclinometer when compared with universal goniometry, principle when the inter-examiner was evaluated.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102574</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i1a102574</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 1 (2006); 39-43</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102574/100854</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102574/157781</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2023-08-08T14:49:03Z" completeListSize="935" cursor="175">4a718e00a4fafbe5ba263a69d09e2b80</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
