<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-08-07T14:49:13Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="actafisiatrica">https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103310</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-30T14:27:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Tend.+Refle.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A medicina física e reabilitação no século XXI: desafio e oportunidades</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Physical and rehabilitation medicine in the XXI century: challenges and opportunities</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Faria, Filipa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pessoas com Deficiência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina Física</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Políticas Públicas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disabled Persons</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Medicine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Public Policies</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Neste trabalho efetua-se uma reflexão sobre algumas das questões que estão a influenciar a reabilitação na atualidade. As alterações demográficas e a epidemiologia das doenças, o aumento das expectativas dos doentes, o crescimento dos custos dos cuidados de reabilitação, e também a dificuldade em estabelecer os limites entre a MFR, as outras especialidades médicas e outros profissionais de saúde, são alguns dos desafios da nossa prática diária. Por outro lado, as mudanças nos conceitos, mentalidades e políticas relacionadas com a deficiência tal como a evolução tecnológica, são oportunidades para alargar o campo de intervenção da Medicina de Reabilitação, confirmando o seu papel decisivo na promoção do entendimento social sobre a deficiência. Finalmente, abordam-se algumas novas perspectivas para a reabilitação no século XXI.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This paper addresses some of the issues that are shaping rehabilitation nowadays, such as changes in demographics and epidemiology of diseases, raising patients’ expectations, increasing costs of rehabilitation care and also the difficulties in establishing boundaries between PMR, other medical specialties and rehabilitation professionals. Some contextual changes which have occurred in the last years in concepts, mentalities and policies related to disability and rehabilitation will be pointed out, as well as the benefits of technological evolution as a tool for enhancing social inclusion of people with disabilities. The recently created network for continued and integrated care, which is being set up in Portugal, will be referred, as a response to the need of providing integrated services. These changes may represent opportunities to enlarge PMR field of intervention and to confirm its role on promoting social understandings of disability. Finally, some new perspectives for rehabilitation on the edge of the 21st are suggested.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-03-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103310</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i1a103310</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 1 (2010); 44-48</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103310/101754</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103310/101755</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103312</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-07T13:17:36Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Functionality evaluation of children with spastic cerebral palsy</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da funcionalidade da criança com paralisia cerebral espástica</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sposito, Maria Matilde de Mello</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Espasticidade Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Escalas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Spasticity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Scales</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral palsy is the result of a non-progressive lesion on the developing central nervous system and can lead to motor dysfunction, movement disorders, mental and functional changes. Spasticity is a motor and postural abnormality most commonly seen in cerebral palsy. Considering the multiple spasticity effects on the functionality of the individual with cerebral palsy, it becomes clear that a clinical evaluation must be precise and direct itself to the specific aspects that require intervention. This text is intended as a guide to the doctors or therapists in choosing the quantitative and qualitative measurements.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A paralisia cerebral é resultante de uma lesão não progressiva sobre o sistema nervoso central em desenvolvimento e que pode levar a disfunções motoras, distúrbios no movimento, deficiências mentais e alterações funcionais. A espasticidade é a anormalidade motora e postural mais comumente vista na paralisia cerebral. Considerando as múltiplas repercussões da espasticidade sobre a funcionalidade do indivíduo com paralisia cerebral, torna-se claro que uma avaliação do quadro clínico deve ser precisa e direcionar-se aos aspectos específicos que exigem intervenção. Este texto tem como objetivo servir de guia aos médicos ou terapeutas na escolha de instrumentos de medição quantitativa e qualitativa.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103312</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i2a103312</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 2 (2010); 50-61</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103312/101756</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103312/101757</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103313</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-07T12:57:59Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Tratamento farmacológico da espasticidade na paralisia cerebral</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Pharmacological spasticity treatment on cerebral palsy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sposito, Maria Matilde de Mello</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Albertini, Simone Bio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Espasticidade Muscular/efeitos de drogas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Toxina Botulínica Tipo A</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Spasticity/drug effects</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Botulinum Toxin Type A</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A espasticidade é uma desordem motora caracterizada por aumento dos reflexos de estiramento tônicos (tônus muscular), velocidade &amp;nbsp;dependente , resultado da hiper excitabilidade deste reflexo, como um componente da Síndrome de Neurônio Superior, extremamente comum a várias condições neuropatológicas. Neste artigo faremos uma revisão da fisiopatologia da espasticidade e dos principais fármacos utilizados no seu tratamento.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Spasticity is a movement disorder characterized by a velocity dependant tonic stretch reflex (muscle tone) increase as a result of the reflex’s hyper-excitability and as a component of the Upper Neuron Syndrome, extremely common to in many neuropathological conditions. In this article we will review the physiopathology of espasticidade and the main drugs used in its treatment.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103313</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i2a103313</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 2 (2010); 62-67</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103313/101758</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103313/101759</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103314</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-07T13:18:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Bloqueios químicos para o tratamento da espasticidade na paralisia cerebral</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Chemical blockage for cerebral palsy spasticity treatment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sposito, Maria Matilde de Mello</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Spasticity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Botulinum Toxin Type A</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Espasticidade Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Toxina Botulínica Tipo A</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The chemical blockades are considered important weapons in the modern treatment of the espasticidade even in adults as in children. They can be carried through with phenol, botulinum toxin of the type A or both (called mixing blockades). In this article we will review in details the different types and uses of chemical blockades for the treatment of the spasticity.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Os bloqueios químicos são considerados armas importantes no moderno tratamento da espasticidade tanto em adultos como em crianças. Eles podem ser realizados com fenol, com toxina botulínica do tipo A ou ainda com ambos, os chamados bloqueios mistos. Neste artigo discutiremos em detalhes os diferentes tipos de bloqueios químicos utilizados para o tratamento da espasticidade.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103314</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i2a103314</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 2 (2010); 68-83</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103314/101760</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103314/101761</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103315</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-07T13:19:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Surgeries and physical interventions in the treatment of cerebral palsy spasticity</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Cirurgias e intervenções físicas no tratamento da espasticidade na paralisia cerebral</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sposito, Maria Matilde de Mello</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Espasticidade Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Toxina Botulínica Tipo A</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Spasticity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Botulinum Toxin Type A</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Although the espasticidade treatment in patients with cerebral palsy is based essentially on cinesioterapia and drugs administrated as chemical blockades infiltration or orally, there are situations where such aid doesnot have the desired effect, either because of the seriousness of the espasticidade or contra-indications and adverse effects of the botulinum toxin. We can also see human musculoskeletal apparatus deformities resulting from constant deforming stimulus of espasticidade and amendment biomechanics that it imposes on the member positioning during the gait, ortostatismo or other rest positions. In this situation, are indicated surgical procedures which aim at improving the condition of positioning biomechanics, adequacy and efficiency of movement in general. This review article has the aim to provide alternative forms of drug administration for the control of espasticidade, as baclofen bump that requires a chirurgical procedure and others indications and surgeries for the control of espasticidade and its consequences as deformities.We will discuss also the indications for physiotherapy procedures and ortheses indications with the indication to reduce spasticity.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Apesar de o tratamento da espasticidade em pacientes com paralisia cerebral fundamentar-se, essencialmente, na cinesioterapia e medicamentos administrados com inflitrações ou por via oral, ocorrem situações nas quais tais intervenções não surtem os efeitos desejados, seja em virtude da gravidade da espasticidade ou da contra-indição e efeitos adversos ao uso da toxina botulínica. Também podem ocorrer distorções do aparelho locomotor resultantes do constante estímulo deformante da espasticidade e da alteração biomecânica que ela impõe ao posicionamento de membros durante a marcha, ortostatismo ou outras posições de repouso. Nestas últimas situações, estão indicados procedimentos cirúrgicos que visam a melhoria da condição biomecânica, adequação do posicionamento e maior eficiência da movimentação em geral. Este artigo de revisão tem por objetivo apresentar as formas alternativas de administração de drogas para o controle&amp;nbsp; da espasticidade, como a bomba de baclofeno, cujo implante exige procedimento cirúrgico, outras indicações e intervenções cirúrgicas para o controle da espasticidade e de suas consequências como deformidades e alteração de função além de procedimentos fisioterápicos e uso de órteses sempre com o objetivo de redução dos quadros espásticos.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103315</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i2a103315</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 2 (2010); 84-91</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103315/101764</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103315/101765</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103327</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-29T23:14:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Edit</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Mudança dos critérios Qualis!</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Andriolo, Adagmar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barbosa, Alfredo José Afonso</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Hernandez, Arnaldo José</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Camargos, Aroldo F.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barraviera, Benedito</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kadunc, Bogdana Victoria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Caramelli, Bruno</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brites, Carlos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nascimento, Dejair Caitano do</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Braile, Domingo M.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Goldenberg, Dov Charles</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Baracat, Edmund Chada</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marchiori, Edson</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vieira, Eduardo de Paula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Eros Antônio de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jotz, Geraldo Pereira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kirsztajn, Gianna Mastroianni</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Camanho, Gilberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gusso, Gustavo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Duarte, Ivomar Gomes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Izelda Maria Carvalho</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mello Júnior, João Ferreira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Faintuch, Joel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martinez, José Antônio Baddini</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Livramento, José Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Manso, José Eduardo Ferreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cabral Filho, José Eulálio Eulálio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Montal, José Heverardo da Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Amaral, José Luiz Gomes do</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martins, José Luiz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Andrade, Jurandyr Moreira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Savassi, Leonardo Cançado Monteiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Machado, Luís dos Ramos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Casulari, Luiz Augusto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leme, Luiz Eugenio Garcez</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gebrim, Luiz Henrique</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Madeira, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bastos, Marcus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Falcão, Mário Cícero</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Conceição, Mario J. da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Mauricio Rocha e</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ruiz, Milton Artur</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Shibata, Milton K.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santiago, Mittermayer Barreto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Andreollo, Nelson Adami</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alonso, Nivaldo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Malafaia, Osvaldo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Camargo, Olavo Pires de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fernandes, Paulo Manuel Pêgo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martins, Regina Helena Garcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Procianoy, Renato Soibelmann</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Antunes, Ricardo César Pinto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Viebig, Ricardo Guilherme</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nitrini, Ricardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dedivitis, Rogério</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Damião, Ronaldo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Monteiro, Rosângela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lianza, Sergio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rode, Sigmar de Mello</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barros Filho, Tarcisio E.P.</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chamon, Wallace</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yoshida, Winston Bonetti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Handar, Zuher</dc:creator>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103327</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 3 (2010); 92-93</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103327/101772</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103331</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-29T23:22:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Uma abordagem qualitativa das interações entre os domínios da Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">A qualitative approach of interactions between the domains of the International Classification of Functionality, Disability, and Health</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Alexandra de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Viegas, Carina Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Paula, Maria Elizarda Machado de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Fabiana Caetano Martins</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sampaio, Rosana Ferreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pessoas com Deficiência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Apoio Social</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Políticas Públicas de Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">International Classification of Functioning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disability and Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disabled Persons</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Social Support</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Public Policy</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The International Classification of Functionality, Disability, and Health (ICF) is based on the bio-psycho-social model and enables understanding of the processes of functionality and disability through the interaction of its components. The aim of this study was to analyze the interrelationships between the domains of the ICF, describing the process of functionality and disability from the perspective of the individual. A qualitative approach was used with interviews and a life grid, built out of ICF domains, applied to 11 patients, and followed by filling in a diary of weekly activities. Most respondents made use of products and technologies such as canes, prostheses, or orthoses, and they had no difficulty in acquiring them through the SUS system. Personal factors that stood out were the ways of coping with new health conditions and new meaning in their lives. During the interviews, the importance of social support, particularly that offered by family and friends, the barriers encountered in the use of public transport, in addition to access of health care and Social Security benefits were prominent. Developing day-to-day strategies was a topic that showed how respondents reorganized their lives to minimize the difficulties they experienced. The data analysis from the interviews confirmed the existence of interaction between the components of ICF. This model was shown to be an important tool for understanding the process of human functionality and disability from the standpoint of the patient’s subjectivity and individuality, as well as for developing interventions and guiding public policy and health research.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde (CIF) baseia-se no modelo biopsicossocial e permite a compreensão dos processos de funcionalidade e incapacidade. O objetivo deste estudo foi analisar as interrelações entre os domínios da CIF, descrevendo o processo de funcionalidade e de incapacidade a partir da percepção do indivíduo. Utilizou-se abordagem qualitativa com realização de entrevistas e de grade de vida, construídas a partir dos domínios da CIF, aplicadas a 11 pacientes, seguida por preenchimento de um diário de atividades semanais. A maioria dos entrevistados fez ou faz uso de produtos e tecnologias como bengalas, prótese ou órteses, e não teve dificuldade na aquisição dos mesmos através do SUS. Os fatores pessoais que se destacaram foram as formas de enfrentamento da nova condição de saúde e a ressignificação de suas vidas. Durante as entrevistas, a importância do suporte social, sobretudo aquele oferecido pelos familiares e amigos, as barreiras encontradas na utilização do transporte público, além do acesso aos serviços de saúde e benefícios da Previdência Social foram ressaltados. A elaboração de estratégias foi um tema que aponta para a reorganização do cotidiano e que os entrevistados desenvolveram para minimizar as dificuldades vivenciadas em seu dia-a-dia. A análise das entrevistas permitiu confirmar a existência de interação entre os componentes da CIF. Este modelo mostrou-se uma ferramenta importante para compreender o processo de funcionalidade e incapacidade humana a partir da subjetividade e individualidade do paciente, bem como para elaborar intervenções e nortear políticas públicas e pesquisas na área de saúde</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103331</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i3a103331</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 3 (2010); 94-102</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103331/101776</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103339</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-29T23:32:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Relationships between subjective well-being, mobility, and independence as a function of age bracket and gender among the elderly ENDEREÇO</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Relações entre bem-estar subjetivo e mobilidade e independência funcional por função de grupo de faixas etárias e de gêneros em idosos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sposito, Giovana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Diogo, Maria José D’Elboux</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cintra, Fernanda Aparecida</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Neri, Anita Liberalesso</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guariento, Maria Elena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sousa, Maria da Luz Rosário de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividades Cotidianas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Activities of Daily Living</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este estudo teve como objetivo investigar as associações de bemestar subjetivo, a independência nas atividades cotidianas e as medidas de mobilidade e flexibilidade de membros inferiores em idosos em acompanhamento ambulatorial, em relação a grupos etários e de gêneros. Foram avaliados 125 idosos de ambos os gêneros com idade igual ou superior a 60 anos. Os instrumentos utilizados foram: Medida da Independência Funcional (MIF) para avaliar as atividades cotidianas, Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB) para o desempenho físico, Bem-estar Subjetivo (BES) para satisfação com a vida. Os resultados revelaram que mulheres têm pior desempenho físico e menor independência funcional do que os homens. Os idosos mais velhos tiveram pior pontuação no desempenho físico e são mais dependentes nas atividades de vida diária que os idosos mais jovens. Entretanto eles são mais satisfeitos com vida do que os demais. Os resultados sugerem que indivíduos mais velhos e mulheres têm maior limitação funcional. Entretanto os idosos mais velhos apresentam maior satisfação com a vida.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The aim of this study was to investigate the associations of subjective well-being, independence in daily activities, and the measures of mobility and flexibility in the lower limbs of elderly outpatients, according to age groups and gender. 125 people over 60 of both genders were chosen and evaluated. The instruments used were: Functional Independence Measure (FIM) to evaluate their daily activities, Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB) for their physical performance, and Subjective Well-Being (SWB) for satisfaction with life. The results revealed that women have poorer physical performance and less functional independence than men. The older subjects had lower scores in physical performance and were more dependent in daily life activities than the younger ones, however they were more satisfied with life. The results suggest that older individuals and women have greater functional limitation. Meanwhile the older seniors show greater satisfaction with life</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103339</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i3a103339</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 3 (2010); 103-108</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103339/101784</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103339/101785</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103343</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-30T11:34:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeito da exposição cirúrgica de nervos e músculos no teste neurofisiológico em ratos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The effect of surgical exposure of nerves and muscles in neurophysiologic tests on rats</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Stipp-Brambilla, Elisangela Jeronymo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Romão, Adriana Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Garbino, José Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Salgado, Manoel Henrique</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Viterboz, Fausto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neurofisiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Eletromiografia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Nervo Ciático/ cirurgia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Nervo Fibular/cirurgia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ratos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neurophysiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electromyography</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sciatic Nerve/surgery</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Peroneal Nerve/surgery</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rats</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O estudo neurofisiológico, na modalidade da eletroneuromiografia (ENMG), determina e quantifica a integridade de componentes da unidade motora. Os principais dados fornecidos pelo exame eletroneuromiográfico são os estudos de condução nervosa motora, sensitiva e eletromiografia. No entanto, vários fatores podem interferir sobre a resposta nervosa à eletroestimulação, tais como: idade, sexo, temperatura, umidade e outros. O objetivo deste trabalho foi verificar o efeito da exposição cirúrgica dos nervos ciático, fibular comum, tibial e do músculo tibial cranial no teste neurofisiológico em ratos. Foram utilizados 20 ratos, Wistar, machos com aproximadamente 80 dias, divididos em dois grupos. No grupo normal o exame foi realizado sem a exposição cirúrgica do nervo fibular. No grupo cirúrgico houve a exposição do nervo fibular comum. Com o modelo experimental utilizado, concluiu-se que o teste neurofisiológico realizado em animais com nervos e músculos expostos cirurgicamente é viável, uma vez que a alteração da temperatura do animal não interferiu significativamente nos valores dos parâmetros eletrofisiológicos observados. Além disso, a exposição de nervos e músculos permite estimular um ponto exato no nervo alvo.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The neurophysiologic study in the modality of electroneuromyography (ENMG) determined and quantified the components in the motor ambit. The main data supplied by the examination was from the motor and sensory nerve conduction studies and by electromyography. However, many factors can interfere with the nervous response to electrostimulation, such as: age, gender, temperature, humidity, and other things. The aim of this work was to verify the effect of surgical exposure of the sciatic, common fibular, tibial, and cranial tibial muscle nerves in a neurophysiologic test on rats. Twenty (20) Wistar male rats were utilized, with approximately 80 days of age, divided into two groups. In the normal group the exam was made without the surgical exposure of the fibular nerve. In the surgical group the common fibular nerve was exposed. With the experimental model utilized, it was concluded that the neurophysiologic test done on animals with nerves and muscles surgically exposed is viable, since the alteration in animal temperature did not interfere significantly with the values of the electrophysiological parameters observed. In addition, the exposure of nerves and muscles allows stimulation of an exact point on the target nerve.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103343</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i3a103343</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 3 (2010); 109-111</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103343/101788</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103343/101789</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103347</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-30T11:40:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudo do tratamento da lombalgia crônica por meio da Escola de Postura</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Study of chronic low back pain treatment using the Back School</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tobo, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>El Khouri, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cordeiro, Quirino</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Moisés da Cunha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brito Junior, Carlos Alexandrino de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor Lombar</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Questionários</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Resultado de Tratamento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Low Back Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Questionnaires</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Treatment Outcome</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The aim of the present study was to quantitatively analyze the response of patients with chronic low back pain to treatment at the Back School at the IMREA-HCFMUSP. The following scales were used to measure the therapeutic response: the Oswestry Low Back Pain Disability Questionnaire, a Visual Analog Scale (VAS), and a corporal diagram of the pain. The sample was composed of 43 patients with chronic low back pain evaluated, treated, and referred to by the Back School program. The results showed significant improvement among those who completed the program in all three scales applied. Since the period of study was only two months, the results do not support any claim that the Back School is also this effective on long-term treatment of chronic low back pain. Further qualitative and quantitative studies must be carried out in order to support the development of specialized multi-professional teams, who will carry out alterations and improvements in therapeutic resources to the management of chronic low back pain.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo do presente trabalho foi analisar a resposta ao tratamento dos pacientes com dor lombar crônica, atendidos pela “Escola de Postura” do IMREA-HCFMUSP. Os questionários utilizados para avaliação da resposta terapêutica foram a escala “Oswestry Low Back Pain Disability Questionnaire”, a Escala Visual Analógica (EVA), e um diagrama corporal de dor. A amostra foi composta por 43 pacientes com lombalgia crônica encaminhados, avaliados e tratados pela Escola de Postura. Observou-se que os indivíduos que concluíram a Escola apresentaram melhora significativa com relação às três escalas de avaliação aplicadas. Cabe ressaltar que o período de estudo de avaliação da Escola de Postura foi de dois meses, sendo que os resultados não possibilitam afirmar que tal método terapêutico também é eficaz em longo prazo. Mais estudos, quantitativos e qualitativos, devem ser realizados de modo a oferecer subsídios à equipe multiprofissional da Escola que permitam operar mudanças e ampliar recursos terapêuticos no tratamento de pacientes com lombalgia crônica.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103347</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i3a103347</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 3 (2010); 112-116</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103347/101795</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103347/101796</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103353</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-30T11:44:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Medo do idoso em sofrer quedas recorrentes: a marcha como fator determinante da independência funcional</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Fear among the elderly of suffering recurring falls: the gait as a determining factor of functional independence</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rezende, Adriana Arruda Barbosa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Iris Lima e</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cardoso, Fabrício Bruno</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Beresford, Heron</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidentes por Quedas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividades Cotidianas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Accidental Falls</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Activities of Daily Living</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This study was carried out with 60 sedentary elderly females, aged between 68 and 70 years and with histories of falls, registered in the “Idoso Feliz” Program in the city of Rio de Janeiro/RJ, and sought to identify the fear of having repeated falls. Initially, an inquiry was done about the occurrence of falls in the group participating in the research. Interviews were then made by means of the Falls Efficacy Scale- International-Brazil to evaluate the group in relation to the concern with falling during the practice of 16 daily activities. Their dynamic gait profile was also evaluated using the Dynamic Gait Index.&#160; In relation to the concern by the elderly with falling, 40.11% mentioned no concern, 30% reported some concern, 25.33% moderate concern, and 4.6% were very concerned. The activities for which they showed more concern: taking a bath, walking on slippery or irregular surfaces, walking in a crowded place, and going out to social events. On evaluating the dynamic gait index, the majority of the population had a result considered predictive of falls since most of the elderly scored less than 19 points. It could be concluded that the majority of the investigated population showed at least low or moderate concern for suffering recurrent falls in the practice of everyday life activities, physical activities, and social activities, especially when these require muscular strength and balance. This can be justified, in part, by the unsatisfactory dynamic gait index detected, which implies the presence of abnormalities in that biomechanical function.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo deste estudo, efetuado com 60 idosas, sedentárias, com idades entre 68 e 70 anos, com relatos de quedas, cadastradas no Programa “Idoso Feliz” na cidade do Rio de Janeiro/RJ, foi identificar o medo de sofrer quedas recidivantes no relato de pessoas idosas. Inicialmente foi feito um questionamento acerca da ocorrência de quedas no grupo participante da pesquisa. Em seguida, uma entrevista por meio da Falls Efficacy Scale-International-Brasil para avaliar o grupo com relação à preocupação em cair durante a prática de 16 atividades diárias. Foi também avaliado o perfil da marcha dinâmica utilizando-se o teste de Índice de Marcha Dinâmica. Em relação à preocupação das idosas em cair, 40,11% não referiu preocupação, 30% relatou um pouco de preocupação, 25,33% moderada preocupação e 4,6% muita preocupação. As atividades para as quais se mostraram mais preocupadas foram: tomar banho, andar em superfícies escorregadias ou irregulares, andar em um local onde haja multidão e sair para eventos sociais. Na avaliação do índice de marcha dinâmica a maioria da população teve um resultado considerado preditivo de quedas, já que todas as idosas perfizeram menos que 19 pontos. Pôde-se concluir que a maioria da população investigada apresentou preocupação, mesmo que pouca ou moderada, em sofrer quedas recorrentes na prática de atividades da vida diária, atividades físicas e atividades sociais, especialmente quando estas requerem força muscular e equilíbrio. Isto pode ser justificado, em parte, pelo insatisfatório índice da marcha dinâmica detectado, o que faz subentender-se a presença de anormalidades naquela função biomecânica.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103353</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i3a103353</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 3 (2010); 117-121</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103353/101803</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103353/101804</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103359</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-30T11:50:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The client’s perspective regarding their welcoming at a rehabilitation clinic ENDEREÇO</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O olhar do usuário sobre o acolhimento em um serviço de reabilitação</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cruz, Sirlaine Vieira da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro, Liliane Dias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cabral, Lúcia Helena de Assis</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sampaio, Rosana Ferreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation Services</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Occupational Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hand Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">User Embracement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Serviços de Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia Ocupacional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos da Mão</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acolhimento</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The new healthcare measures proposed by the Brazilian National Humanization Policy stress the patients’ welcoming, which constantly seeks to recognize the needs of clients and the forms of satisfying these needs. Studies have demonstrated the importance of humanized care, in which listening to the client is a valuable tool for assessing the efficacy of the service of-fered to a particular population. The aim of the present study was to describe how clients per-ceive the manner in which they are received at a hand rehabilitation clinic and to analyze the most important factors. A qualitative approach was adopted, with semistructured interviews in which clients were asked about how they were received at the clinic in terms of access, posture, and technique. Content analysis consisted of arranging, classifying and analyzing the results. Twelve patients from a public hospital in the city of Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais, Brazil, participated in the study. The patients considered good reception to be the most hu-manized manner of being received–– with care, politeness, and fondness. Communication between therapist and client proved to be important in building a trusting relationship, generating client satisfaction and favoring progress in the treatment. It was evident that a warm reception was a valuable therapeutic instrument for the rehabilitation professional. Having listening skills and revealing oneself to be sensitive to the needs of the client helps reduce the natural fear and anxiety experienced at the beginning of physical therapy treatment and facili-tates the entire process.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Dentre as novas medidas de atenção aos usuários propostos na Política Nacional de Humanização, destaca-se o acolhimento, que consiste na busca constante do reconhecimento das necessidades dos usuários e das formas possíveis de satisfazê-las. Estudos têm demonstrado a importância de um atendimento humanizado, onde a escuta do usuário torna-se um valioso instrumento para avaliar a efetividade do serviço oferecido à determinada população. O objetivo deste estudo foi descrever, a partir da perspectiva dos usuários, como é realizado o acolhimento em um serviço de reabilitação da mão e analisar os fatores mais relevantes. Foi adotada abordagem qualitativa e o recurso metodológico utilizado foi a entrevista semiestruturada onde os usuários foram questionados em relação ao acolhimento, considerando suas três dimensões: acesso, postura e técnica. A análise de conteúdo foi o método escolhido e consistiu em ordenação, classificação e análise final dos resultados. Participaram do estudo 12 usuários de um hospital público da cidade de Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais. Os usuários consideraram que um bom acolhimento refere-se à forma mais humanizada de ser recebido, isto é, com atenção, educação e carinho. A comunicação entre terapeuta e usuário demonstrou ser importante para se criar um vínculo entre ambos, construindo uma relação de confiança, gerando a satisfação do usuário e favorecendo a evolução do tratamento. Evidenciouse que realizar um bom acolhimento é um valioso instrumento terapêutico para o profissional de reabilitação. Apresentar boa capacidade de escuta e mostrar-se sensível às necessidades do usuário ajuda na redução dos medos e ansiedades naturais no início da reabilitação, facilitando todo o processo.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103359</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i3a103359</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 3 (2010); 122-125</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103359/101810</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103359/101811</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103364</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-30T11:54:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Mirror box therapy in the complex regional pain syndrome type I</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia com caixa de espelhos na síndrome dolorosa regional complexa tipo I</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gaspar, Ana Teresa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Castro, André</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Antunes, Filipe</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Síndromes da Dor Regional Complexa</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Extremidade Superior</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapêutica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia Ocupacional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Complex Regional Pain Syndromes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Upper Extremity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Therapeutics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Occupational Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Complex regional pain syndrome (CRPS) type I is a neuropathic pain condition, commonly affecting a limb extremity after a traumatic event and/or a period of immobilization, in the absence of nerve injury. Besides pain, the clinical features include regional vasomotor alterations and usually a decreased range of motion in the affected extremity. Its actual cause remains somewhat obscure and there are few agreements on optimal treatment. The mirror box is a therapeutic approach based on visual feedback as a way to achieve a new mental imagery of the affected limb by promoting cortical reorganization. This approach has been used for the motor recovery or pain relief in conditions such as stroke or type-I CRPS.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Síndrome dolorosa regional complexa (SDRC) tipo I é um quadro de dor neuropática, que afeta, sobretudo as extremidades dos membros após evento traumático e/ou período de imobilização, na ausência de lesão nervosa. Para além da dor, as características clínicas incluem alterações vasomotoras regionais e freqüentemente limitação da mobilidade da extremidade envolvida. Não está totalmente esclarecida a sua causa e existem poucos consensos em relação ao tratamento ideal. A caixa de espelhos é uma modalidade terapêutica baseada no feedback visual, como forma de construção de uma nova imagem mental do membro afetado, promovendo a reorganização cortical. Esta técnica tem sido utilizada na recuperação motora ou no controlo da dor em situações como o acidente vascular cerebral e o SDRC tipo I.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103364</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i3a103364</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 3 (2010); 126-129</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103364/101817</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103364/101818</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103369</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-22T20:13:15Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Tend.+Refle.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The triage process in rehabilitation centers</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Sobre o processo de triagem em centros de reabilitação</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jucá, Sueli Satie Hamada</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Miyazaki, Margarida Harumi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation Centers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Administration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Triage</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disabled Persons/rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Centros de Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Administração em Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Triagem</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pessoas com Deficiência/reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The triage process in rehabilitation centers consists of an evaluation of the conditions of a patient who might use the services of these units in the health system. In general it takes place at first contact with the clinical team. By schedule a patient is interviewed by a doctor, a social worker, and a psychologist at the same time whereby they verify the clinical conditions, relationship dynamics and psychopathological aspects, as well as the social requirements for regular supervised participation in the prescribed activities. The object of the triage process is not to obstruct access of anyone to the services available, but to guide the potential user either to the easiest form of treatment or to that most appropriate to his needs. At the end of the triage process the patient may be chosen for multi-professional intervention several days a week or other alternative interventions, either therapeutic or guiding, with the recruitment of any number of professionals or weekly contacts. Considering the reality of rehabilitation in Brazil, which does not include internment, one can expect full service of the rehabilitation program only under optimal conditions. Resources for rehabilitation are limited, therefore its optimization is necessary, and the triage process enables the best use of these resources with a fair and ethical distribution.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O processo de triagem em centros de reabilitação consiste numa avaliação das condições do paciente potencial usuário dos serviços prestados nessas unidades do sistema de saúde. Em geral ela ocorre no primeiro contato com a equipe clínica. Por meio de agendamento, o paciente é submetido a entrevista com um médico, um assistente social e um psicólogo num só momento, onde são verificadas as condições clínicas, aspectos de dinâmica de relacionamento e psicopatológicos, bem como requisitos sociais para participação regular e supervisionada nas atividades propostas. O objetivo do processo de triagem não é obstruir o acesso de qualquer pessoa aos serviços disponíveis, mas sim direcionar o potencial usuário para a forma mais ágil de atendimento ou mais apropriada às suas necessidades. Ao final do processo de triagem o paciente pode ser eleito para intervenção multiprofissional em vários dias da semana, outras alternativas de intervenção, seja terapêuticas ou de orientação, com recrutamento de número diferente de profissionais ou contatos semanais. Considerando a realidade de reabilitação no Brasil, que não contempla a internação, pode-se esperar um aproveitamento integral do programa de reabilitação somente em condições otimizadas. Os recursos para reabilitação não são ilimitados, assim, a sua otimização é necessária e o processo de triagem viabiliza o melhor aproveitamento desses recursos, e uma distribuição mais justa e ética dos mesmos.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103369</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i3a103369</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 3 (2010); 130-133</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103369/101824</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103369/101825</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103374</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-30T12:06:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Techniques of proprioceptive evaluation of the anterior cruciate knee ligament</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Técnicas de avaliação proprioceptiva do ligamento cruzado anterior do joelho</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Alonso, Angélica Castilho</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brech, Guilherme Carlos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Greve, Julia Maria D’Andréa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Proprioception</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Postural Balance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Anterior Cruciate Ligament</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Propriocepção</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Postural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ligamento Cruzado Anterior</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The increasing interest in sports activities, combined with the knee’s anatomical vulnerability and complexity, justifies the increasing number of patients with ligament injuries, especially the anterior cruciate ligament (ACL). What then would be the best way to evaluate the knee proprioception? The objective of this study was to identify the techniques of proprioceptive evaluation of the anterior cruciate knee ligament (ACL), and to determine whether a better technique is available. The method was to review the literature, including only those studies published in indexed scientific journals that referred to evaluation tools and/or knee proprioception measurement. The discussion of the different methods of evaluating ACL proprioception, according to the literature, included: morphological anatomical studies; neurophysiologic evaluation, and clinical evaluation which was divided into three types: a) sense of static position; b) kinesthetic posture; and c) postural balance. Although proprioception is important to the final results of a treatment involving ligament injury, its evaluation is still a problem. The conclusion was that the ideal method should have high sensitivity and specificity, in addition to good reproducibility and accuracy. There is lack of consensus in literature regarding the best evaluation technique and the results are also contradictory, despite the balance evaluation being a modern technique used in major research centers, it was not possible to isolate the proprioceptive system from other systems: visual and vestibular.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Com o aumento do interesse por atividades esportivas, bem como a vulnerabilidade e complexidade anatômica do joelho justificam um aumento crescente do número de pacientes com lesões ligamentares, principalmente do ligamento cruzado anterior (LCA). Entretanto qual é a melhor forma de avaliar a propriocepção do joelho? Objetivo: Desta forma este estudo teve como objetivo identificar as técnicas de avaliação proprioceptivas do LCA do joelho, e se existe a melhor técnica. Métodos: Foi realizada uma revisão de literatura, tendo como critérios de inclusão os estudos publicados em revistas científicas indexadas, que se referiam a instrumentos de avaliação e/ ou mensuração da propriocepção do joelho. Discussão: De acordo com a literatura revisada, existem diferentes técnicas de avaliação da propriocepção do LCA, dentre elas: estudos morfológicos anatômicos; avaliação neurofisiológica; e avaliação clínica que é dividida em três subtipos: a) sentido da posição estática; b) cinestesia; e c) equilíbrio postural. Ainda que a propriocepção seja importante no resultado final de um tratamento que envolva uma lesão ligamentar, sua avaliação ainda é uma dificuldade. Conclusão: O método ideal deve ter alta sensibilidade e especificidade, além de boa reprodutibilidade e precisão. Porém não houve consenso na literatura referente à melhor técnica e os resultados são contraditórios, apesar da avaliação do equilíbrio ser uma técnica moderna e utilizada nos grandes centros de pesquisa, não é possível isolar o sistema proprioceptivo dos outros sistemas: visual e vestibular.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i3a103374</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 3 (2010); 134-140</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103374/101829</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103374/101830</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103378</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T15:39:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Investigation of therapeutic exercise effects on peripheral nerve regeneration</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Investigação dos efeitos do exercício terapêutico sobre a regeneração nervosa periférica</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Possamai, Fernanda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Siepko, Cristiane Márcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>André, Edison Sanfelice</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sistema Nervoso Periférico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Regeneração Nervosa</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ratos Wistar</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Peripheral Nervous System</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Nerve Regeneration</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Wistar Rats</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The peripheral nervous system exhibits a remarkable ability to regenerate after injury. The sciatic nerve reactions following axonotmesis produce morpho-functional responses at the target muscle, injury epicenter and at certain retrograde neuronal districts. Despite therapeutic advancements, the functional restoration is incomplete in most cases. In this context, we tested if exercise (swimming) is able to interfere in both functional gait recovery and plastic reactions in the motoneurons of the spinal cord. Forty Wistar rats were divided into four groups (n=10 each), submitted to a 30 min/day swimming routine, beginning 1, 7, 14 or 21 days after the sciatic nerve injury. All groups exhibited functional recovery, significant differences were not observed in the number of spinal motoneurons among the groups studied. According to both functional and histological analysis, therapeutic exercise, in the conditions of the present study, was unable to accelerate the regeneration process.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O sistema nervoso periférico apresenta relativa capacidade de rege- neração após uma lesão. Após a axonotmese o nervo ciático produz respostas morfo-funcionais, no músculo alvo, no epicentro da lesão e alguns distritos neuronais retrógrados. Apesar dos avanços terapêuti- cos, a restauração funcional é incompleta na maioria dos casos. Neste contexto, nós testamos se o exercício (nado) é capaz de interferir na marcha funcional e reações de plasticidade nos motoneurônios da medula espinhal. Quarenta ratos foram divididos em quatro grupos (n=10 cada), submetidos a 30 min/dia de nado, iniciando no 1, 7, 14, 21 dias após lesão do nervo ciático. Todos os grupos apresentaram recuperação funcional, não observamos diferenças significantes nos números de motoneurônios da medula espinhal entre os diferentes grupos estudados. De acordo com a análise funcional e histológica, o exercício terapêutico, nas condições do presente estudo, foi incapaz de acelerar o processo regenerativo.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103378</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i4a103378</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 4 (2010); 142-147</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103378/101838</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103380</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T15:39:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevalência de lombalgia em trabalhadores submetidos ao programa de Reabilitação Profissional do Instituto Nacional do Seguro Social (INSS), São Luís, MA</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Prevalence of low back pain among employees undergoing the Occupational Rehabilitation program at Instituto Nacional do Seguro Social (INSS), São Luís, MA</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Abreu, Ana Teresa de Jesus Brito de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro, Camila Almeida Bezerra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Low Back Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Prevalence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Workers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Occupational Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lombalgia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevalência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Trabalhadores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação Profissional</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O presente estudo avalia a prevalência de lombalgia na população de trabalhadores inseridos no Programa de Reabilitação Profissional do Instituto Nacional do Seguro Social (INSS), na cidade de São Luís/ MA. Este programa apresenta como funções básicas a avaliação do potencial laborativo e a definição da real capacidade de retorno ao trabalho dos segurados atendendo aproximadamente 400 pessoas por mês. Através dos registros em prontuários, foi realizado um es- tudo de corte transversal retrospectivo em que foram separados 264 prontuários, válidos de 1995 a 2009, de trabalhadores afastados do trabalho e ainda com vínculo empregatício. Aqueles apresentados como desempregados foram excluídos do trabalho. Dessa amostra, selecionou-se somente os trabalhadores com diagnóstico de lombal- gia, totalizando 88 prontuários, em que foram encontrados 83 casos do sexo masculino (94,3%), média de idade de 41 anos, variando de 24 a 53 anos. A prevalência de lombalgia foi de 33,3% em relação aos diagnósticos encontrados na amostra inicial. Observou-se que em sua maioria, a amostra era composta por trabalhadores casados, com bai- xa escolaridade, do sexo masculino, em idade produtiva e afastados do trabalho há mais de um ano, associada à realização de atividades profissionais às quais exigem postura estática, movimentos repetiti- vos e carregamento de peso.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The present study evaluates the prevalence of low back pain in a population of employees participating in the Occupational Rehabilitation Program at the Instituto Nacional do Seguro Social (INSS) in the city of Sao Luis, located in the state of Maranhao, Brazil. The basic functions of this program are the evaluation of labor potential and the definition of the real capacity to return to work of employees, and it serves approximately 400 people per month. Through the records in the medical registers, a retrospective cross-sectional study was carried out with 264 records, from 1995 to 2009, of employees off work and of employees still working. Those shown as unemployed were excluded from this study. From this sample, only employees with low back pain were selected, totaling 88 records, in which 83 male cases (94.3%) were found with an average age of 41 years, ranging from 24 to 53. The prevalence of low back pain was 33.3% compared to the medical registers found in the initial sample. Of those in the sample, it was noticed that most were married, with little schooling, male, at a productive age, and had been off work for more than a year. They had occupations that required static posture, repetitive motion, and strenuous physical activity.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103380</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i4a103380</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 4 (2010); 148-152</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103380/101843</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103382</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T15:39:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Uso de testes clínicos para verificação do controle postural em idosos saudáveis submetidos a programas de exercícios físicos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Use of clinical tests for verification of postural control in healthy elderly submitted to physical exercise programs</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Alfieri, Fábio Marcon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gatz, Lucila Silveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro, Carla Paschoal Corsi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Envelhecimento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Postural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aging</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Postural Balance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">With aging, postural control diminishes, but the practice of physical exercises can improve this important function. Various tests can be used to measure these possible improvements. The objective of this study is to analyze the use of clinical tests of indirect measurements to verify the alterations in the postural control of healthy elderly submitted to physical exercise programs. The study's design is a randomized, simple-blind clinical test with the subjects' arms parallel. In the research there were 46 elderly divided randomly into two groups of exercises: multi-sensorial (MSG, n=23, 68.8±5.9 years) and strengthening (resistance training) (RTG, n=23, 70.18±4.8). Both groups performed 12 weeks (2 days/week, 50minutes/day) of exercises. To evaluate their postural control the following tests were utilized: Timed up and go (TUG), unipodal support test, battery of Guralnik tests, and the Berg functional balance scale. The MSG individuals showed significant improvement in the TUG tests and Guralnik battery of tests, and the RTG individuals did not show improvement in any of the tests. The improvement in the time of execution of the TUG test of the MSG group was 9.1±8.04 to 8.0±1.0 seconds after intervention, and it was statistically higher than the RTG group result. We believe the TUG test and the Guralnik battery of tests are good options to evaluate the postural control of the elderly submitted to the intervention programs. Although the TUG cannot have its time diminished indefinitely, it allows the verification, even within a normalcy time, of alterations brought on by physical exercises.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O controle postural no envelhecimento diminui e a prática de exercícios físicos pode melhorar esta importante função. A fim de medir estas possíveis melhoras, podem ser usados diversos testes. O objetivo deste estudo foi o de analisar o uso de testes clínicos de medidas indiretas para verificar as alterações sobre o controle postural de idosos saudáveis submetidos a programas de exercícios físicos. O desenho do estudo foi um ensaio clínico simples-cego e aleatorizado com braços paralelos. Participaram da pesquisa 46 idosos divididos aleatoriamente em dois grupos de exercícios: multissensoriais (GMS, n=23, 68,8±5,9 anos) e de fortalecimento (treino resistido) (GR, n=23, 70,18±4,8). Ambos os grupos realizaram 12 semanas (2dias/semana, 50m/dia) de exercícios. Para avaliação do controle postural foram utilizados os testes: Timed up and go (TUG), teste de apoio unipodal, bateria de testes de Guralnik e escala de equilíbrio funcional de Berg. Os indivíduos do GMS apresentaram melhora significativa nos testes TUG e bateria de testes de Guralnik e o GR não apresentou melhora em nenhum dos testes. A melhora no tempo de execução do teste TUG do GMS que foi de 9,1±8,04 para 8,0±1,0 segundos após a intervenção, foi estatisticamente superior ao resultado do GR. Acreditamos que o teste TUG e a bateria de testes de Guralnik são boas opções para avaliar o controle postural de idosos submetidos a programas de intervenção. Embora o TUG não possa ter seu tempo diminuído indefinidamente, permite verificar até mesmo dentro de um tempo de normalidade, alterações promovidas por exercícios físicos.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103382</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i4a103382</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 4 (2010); 153-158</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103382/101848</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103383</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T15:39:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Biofeedback eletromiográfico e parâmetros da dinamometria isocinética de joelho e tornozelo de jogadores de futebol amador</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Baron, Carina Elias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Secchi, Leonardo Luiz Barretti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Greve, Júlia Maria D´Andréa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Vasthi Oliveira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Viviane Ribeiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Athletes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electromyography</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Articular Range of Motion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Knee</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atletas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Eletromiografia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Amplitude de Movimento Articular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Joelho</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Electromyography has been used to evaluate the voluntary control of muscular activity. One of the highlights among the techniques is electromyography biofeedback (EMGBio), which works as a facilitator of neuromotor development, including playing sports. Objective: To analyze the effect of EMGBio within the isokinetic parameters of knee flexion and extension and ankle inversion and eversion in amateur soccer players. Subjects: Two randomized groups of fourteen male amateur soccer players: Training group (TG) – seven athletes, with an age of 23 ± 2 (22 and 28) years old, body mass 75.7kg ± 4.0kg (72 and 80), height 182cm ± 4cm (176 and 188) and Control Group (CG) – seven athletes, with an age of 24 ± 2 (21 and 28) years old, body mass 72.3kg ± 9.4kg (59 and 79), height 175cm ± 5cm (169 and 180). Methods: all athletes were evaluated by a clinical protocol: anamnesis, occurrence of injuries and visual analogue scale of pain and were subjected to knee flexion and extension and ankle inversion and eversion isokinetic dynamometry. The training group had twelve sessions of EMGBio once a week. At the end of the sessions, all athletes were revaluated. Results: At a velocity of 30 deg/s, the ankle eversion peak torque of 0.18 seconds (PT of 0.18s) was higher in the training group and at a velocity of 60 deg/s, the knee flexion PT of 0.18s was higher in the training group. Conclusion: Electromyographic biofeedback improved the isokinetic parameters of the amateur soccer players.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A eletromiografia tem sido utilizada para avaliar o con- trole voluntário da atividade muscular. Dentre as técnicas destaca-se o biofeedback eletromiográfico como facilitador do aprendizado neuromotor, inclusive na prática esportiva. Objetivo: Analisar o efeito do biofeedback eletromiográfico nos parâmetros isocinéticos dos fle- xores e extensores do joelho e inversores e eversores do tornozelo em jogadores de futebol amador. Casuística: 14 atletas de futebol amador do gênero masculino randomizados em dois grupos: Gru- po Treino (GT) - sete atletas, idade de 23 ± 2 (22 e 28) anos, massa corpórea 75,7 ± 4,0(72 e 80) kg , estatura 182 ± 4 (176 e 188) cm e Grupo Controle (GC) - sete atletas com idade 24 ± 2 (21 e 28) anos, massa corpórea 72,3± 9,4 (59 e 79) kg, estatura 175± 5 (169 e 180) cm. Método: Todos os atletas foram avaliados por um protocolo clínico: anamnese, incidência de lesões e escala visual análoga de dor e foram submetidos à dinamometria isocinética dos inversores e eversores do tornozelo e flexores e extensores do joelho. O GT realizou 12 sessões de biofeedback eletromiográfico, uma vez por semana. No final das sessões, todos os atletas foram reavaliados. Resultados: Na velocidade de 30º/ seg., o pico de torque 0,18 segundos (PT 0,18s) dos eversores do tornozelo foi maior no GT e no joelho, na velocidade de 60º/seg. o PT 0,18s dos flexores de joelho foram maiores no GT. Conclusão: O biofeedback eletromiográfico melhorou os parâmetros isocinéticos dos jogadores de futebol amador.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103383</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 4 (2010); 159-163</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103383/101849</dc:relation>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103385</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T15:45:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Adaptação da pessoa após acidente vascular encefálico e seu cuidador: ambiente domiciliar, cadeira de rodas e de banho</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Adaptation of the person after stroke and their caregivers: home environment, wheelchair and bath chair</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Garanhani, Márcia Regina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alves, Jaqueline Frazão</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fugisawa, Dirce Shizuko</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Garanhani, Mara Lúcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Activities of Daily Living</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Access Structures</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Wheelchairs</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Cerebral Vascular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividades Cotidianas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estruturas de Acesso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cadeiras de Rodas</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O acidente vascular encefálico causa incapacidade funcional. O envolvimento dos familiares influencia na recuperação dos pacientes e as barreiras arquitetônicas no domicílio dificultam a acessibilidade. O estudo qualitativo procurou identificar as dificuldades das pessoas após o acidente vascular encefálico em relação às barreiras arquitetônicas, ao manuseio da cadeira de rodas e de banho, por meio de entrevista semi-estruturada e roteiro de medidas de acessibilidade. Nove pacientes e seus cuidadores foram entrevistados e da análise dos discursos emergiram três categorias empíricas: acessibilidade andando, acessibilidade com a cadeira de rodas e de banho e o papel das orientações. As principais barreiras encontradas foram os corredores estreitos e circulação interna inadequada. As barreiras arquitetônicas dificultam o uso da cadeira de rodas e de banho no domicílio, sobrecarregando os cuidadores. O conhecimento da realidade destas pessoas facilita programas de orientações de atividades de vida diária centradas na realidade.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Stroke causes functional disability. Family involvement influences patient recovery and architectural barriers at home make accessibility difficult. The qualitative study sought to identify the difficulties of people after stroke in relation to architectural barriers, wheelchair and bath chair handling, through semi-structured interviews and accessibility measurement guideline. Nine patients and their caregivers were interviewed and discussion analysis revealed three empirical categories: walking accessibility, wheelchair and bath chair accessibility, and the role of the guidelines. The main barriers encountered were narrow corridors and inadequate internal circulation. The architectural barriers impede the use of wheelchairs and bath chairs at home, overburdening caregivers. Knowing the reality of these people allows program guidelines of activities of daily living to be centered in reality.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103385</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i4a103385</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 4 (2010); 164-168</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103385/101852</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103386</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T15:39:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">SALSA scale and disability grading system of the World Health Organization: evaluation of physical activity limitations and disability of individuals treated for leprosy</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Escala Salsa e grau de Incapacidades da Organização Mundial de Saúde: avaliação da limitação de atividades e deficiência na hanseníase</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ikehara, Eliyara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nardi, Susilene Maria Tonelli</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferrigno, Iracema Serrat Vergotti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pedro, Heloisa da Silveira Paro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Paschoal, Vânia Del’Arco</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Leprosy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Activities of Daily Living</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Morbidity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hanseníase</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividades Cotidianas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epidemiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Morbidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Verificar o grau de incapacidades da OMS (GI-OMS) e a limitação de atividades avaliada pela escala Screening of Activity Limitation and Safety Awareness (SALSA) pós-alta medicamentosa dos pacientes que tiveram hanseníase. Estudo transversal que incluiu pacientes tratados entre 2007 a 2009, em São José do Rio Preto-SP, Brasil. Utilizouse protocolo próprio para coletar dados gerais e clínicos, construído com base no Check List da Classificação Internacional Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde. A deficiência foi medida pelo GI-OMS e a limitação de atividades pelo SALSA que tem variação de 10 a 80 e ponto de corte ≥25. De 84 pessoas tratadas no período, 54(64,3%) foram entrevistadas, sendo 31(57,4%) homens, idade 53,8(dp16,3) e 33(61,2 %) possuía até 6 anos de educação formal. A forma clinica dimorfa predominou 17(32,1%), 21(38,9%) considerou sua saúde física “boa”. A analise dos escores SALSA e variáveis estudadas resultou em significância aos que relataram lesão significante (valor-p=0,04), baixa renda familiar (valor-p=0,04), baixa escolaridade (valor-p=0,00), formas clínicas multibacilares (valor-p=0,01) e deficiências avaliadas pelo GI-OMS (valor-p=0,01). As limitações de atividades são freqüentes (57,4%), assim como as deficiências medidas pelo GI-OMS (68,5%), atingem as formas multibacilares, pessoas que relataram lesão significante, de baixa renda e escolaridade.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">To verify the disability grading system of the World Health Organization (DG-WHO) and activity limitations evaluated by the Screening of Activity Limitation and Safety Awareness (SALSA) scale of individuals who completed treatment for leprosy. A cross-sectional study that included patients treated from 2007 to 2009 in Sao José do Rio Preto, Brazil. A questionnaire, designed using the International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health checklist, was used to collect general and clinical data. Disability was measured by the DG-WHO and activity limitations by SALSA, using a score of 10 to 80 with a cutoff point of 25. Of 84 individuals treated, 54 (64.3%) were interviewed: 31 (57.4%) were men, mean age was 53.8 (SD 16.3) and 33 (61.2%) had up to 6 years of schooling. Borderline leprosy predominated in 17 (32.1%) participants, and 21 (38.9%) participants considered their physical health 'good'. The analysis of the SALSA scores and studied variables were significant for individuals who reported important injuries (p=0.04), low family income (p=0.04), little schooling (p=0.00), multibacillary clinical form (p=0.01) and disabilities evaluated by DG-WHO (p=0.01). Activity limitations are common (57.4%) in this population, as are disabilities identified by DG-WHO (68.5%) and are directly associated to the multibacillary clinical form, important injuries, low family income and little schooling.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103386</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20100001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 4 (2010); 169-174</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103386/101853</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103388</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T15:53:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Benefits of physical exercise for children and adolescents with cerebral palsy: a literature review</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Benefícios do exercício físico para crianças e adolescentes com paralisia cerebral: uma revisão bibliográfica</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Paiva, Marcel dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nardi, Marcia Galasso</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Streiff, Tatiana Galante</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chamlian, Terezinha Rosane</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Fitness</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Review</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Aptidão Física</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Revisão</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Existem fortes evidências demonstrando que a aptidão física e o estado de saúde das crianças e adolescentes são realçados substancialmente pela prática de atividade física freqüente e, por outro lado, há poucos estudos que evidenciam os benefícios desta prática em populações com deficiência ou mobilidade reduzida. Com o objetivo de relatar as alterações geradas pela aplicação de programas de exercícios físicos em crianças e adolescentes com paralisia cerebral com GMFCS I a III, focando as variáveis de força, função motora, espasticidade e qualidade de vida, foi realizada esta revisão bibliográfica utilizando as bases MEDLINE, PubMed e Lilacs. Além de palavras-chave em português e em inglês para busca de artigos, os trabalhos foram selecionados a partir de uma análise prévia obedecendo aos critérios de inclusão a partir do ano de publicação, análise de título e resumo, sendo excluídos os estudos de revisão e revisão sistemática. Dos 8 estudos incluídos, 3 são randomizados variando a quantidade da amostra estudada entre 8 e 65 indivíduos com paralisia cerebral com idades de 6 a 18 anos. Estes estudos contrariam o paradigma de que o exercício físico com carga para pessoas com desordens neurológicas pode causar aumento da espasticidade. O trabalho também retrata os benefícios gerados pelo aumento de força muscular principalmente em membros inferiores através de exercícios que utilizam o princípio da sobrecarga. Resultados são favoráveis com relação a melhora da função motora grossa além da qualidade de vida expressa em diversos fatores como maior motivação, participação em atividades, socialização e auto percepção.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">There is strong evidence showing that the physical fitness and health of children and adolescents are substantially enhanced by frequent physical activity and, on the other hand, there are few studies that highlight the benefits of this practice in populations with disabilities or reduced mobility. Aiming to report changes generated by the application of physical exercise programs in children and adolescents with cerebral palsy (GMFCS levels I to III), focusing on the variables of strength, motor function, spasticity and quality of life, this literature review was carried out using MEDLINE, PubMed and Lilacs databases. In addition to using keywords in Portuguese and English to search for articles, papers were selected from a preliminary analysis following the criteria of inclusion by publication year, title and abstract analysis, excluding the review studies and systematic review. Out of the 8 studies included, only 3 randomly vary the sample amount studied between 8 and 65 individuals with cerebral palsy from the ages of 6 to 18. These studies contradict the paradigm that exercise, using weights for people with neurological disorders, can result in increased spasticity. This research also illustrates the benefits generated by increased muscular strength especially in the lower limbs through exercises using the overload principle. The results are favorable with regards to improvement in gross motor function as well as quality of life expressed in several factors such as increased motivation, participation in activities, socialization and self-perception.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103388</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i4a103388</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 4 (2010); 175-179</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103388/101856</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103389</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T16:02:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Manipulative orthopedic therapy for chronic spinal pain: a systematic review</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia manipulativa ortopédica na dor vertebral crônica: uma revisão sistemática</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Marcondes, Freddy Beretta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lodovichi, Samuel Satraceri</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cera, Milton</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Manipulação Ortopédica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Manipulação da Coluna</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Revisão</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Manipulation Orthopedic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Manipulation Spinal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Review</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Analisar a eficácia da Terapia Manipulativa Ortopédica (TMO) nos casos de dores vertebrais crônicas. Métodos: Uma busca sistematizada foi realizada nas bases de dados PEDro, Medline e Science Direct no mês de junho de 2010, reunindo ensaios clínicos randomizados recentes que documentassem os efeitos da TMO na Dor Vertebral Crônica. Resultados: Foram revisados oito artigos sobre dor cervical crônica e onze sobre dor lombar crônica. Quanto a dor cervical crônica, seis estudos mostraram que a TMO associada a exercícios são eficazes, mantendo a melhora dos sintomas por até 24 meses. Um estudo mostrou que a TMO (sem exercícios) é superior à massagem e outro estudo mostrou que a TMO proporciona alívio imediato da dor. Quanto a dor lombar crônica, cinco ensaios clínicos mostraram que a TMO associada a exercícios são eficazes a curto e longo prazo; dois trabalhos mostraram que a TMO é mais eficaz do que analgésicos e anti-inflamatórios. Três estudos mostram que a TMO como único tratamento é eficaz, um estudo mostra que a manipulação não é mais eficaz que exercícios de extensão. Conclusão: As técnicas de TMO (exceto osteopatia) são recursos eficazes nos casos de dores crônicas da coluna. Entretanto, seus efeitos de redução da dor ocorrem somente a curto prazo, sendo necessário a associação de exercícios terapêuticos para um resultado eficaz a longo prazo. Mais estudos devem ser feitos para comparar diferentes técnicas de TMO e diferentes técnicas de exercícios entre si nos casos de dores crônicas da coluna.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To examine the effectiveness of Manipulative Orthopedic Therapy (MOT) in cases of Chronic Vertebral Pain. Methods: A systematic search was performed in PEDro, Medline, and Science Direct databases in June 2010, retrieving recent randomized clinical trials that documented the effects of MOT in Chronic Vertebral Pain. Results: Eight articles about chronic cervical pain and eleven articles about chronic low back pain were reviewed. On chronic cervical pain, six papers showed that MOT associated with exercises was effective, maintaining the improvement of symptoms for up to 24 months. One study showed that MOT (with no exercises) was better than massage and another study showed that MOT provided immediate pain relief. In chronic low back pain, five clinical trials showed that MOT associated with exercises was effective in the short and long term; two papers showed that MOT was more effective than analgesics and anti-inflammatory drugs. Three studies showed that MOT is effective as a single treatment and one study showed that MOT is no more effective than stretching exercises. Conclusion: The MOT techniques (except osteopathy) are effective remedies in cases of chronic spinal pain. However, its effects in reduction of pain occur only in the short term and the combination of therapeutic exercises is needed for an effective long term result. More studies should be made to compare different MOT techniques and different exercise techniques with each other in cases of chronic spinal pain.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103389</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i4a103389</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 4 (2010); 180-187</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103389/101857</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103392</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T16:05:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Eletroneuromiografia na avaliação das radiculopatias cervicais e lombossacrais</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Electromyography in the evaluation of cervical and lumbosacral radiculopathy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Balbinot, Luciane Fachin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Garbino, José Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Radiculopathy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electromyography</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Intervertebral Disk Displacement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Low Back Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Radiculopatia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Eletromiografia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Deslocamento do Disco Intervertebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor Lombar</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A eletroneuromiografia (ENMG) é empregada como método de diagnóstico complementar no diagnóstico de radiculopatia desde 1950, contribuindo com importantes informações para o esclarecimento diagnóstico, planejamento do tratamento e acompanhamento evolutivo dos pacientes. A presente revisão baseada em evidências buscou referências com ênfase na indicação, sensibilidade, especificidade, reprodutibilidade e limitações do uso desse exame na avaliação das radiculopatias cervicais e lombossacrais. As referências apontam a ENMG como um exame bastante útil tanto na triagem quanto no diagnóstico diferencial na suspeita de radiculopatia cervical ou lombossacra, bem como na avaliação do grau e extensão da lesão, quando respeitadas as limitações da técnica.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Electromyography (EMG) has been employed as a complementary method in the diagnosis of radiculopathy since 1950, contributing important information for diagnostic clarification, treatment planning and patient follow-up. This evidence based review sought references with emphasis on the recommendation, sensibility, specificity, reproducibility and limitations of the use of this test in the evaluation of cervical and lumbosacral radiculopathy. The references point to EMG as being an extremely useful test both in the screening and in the differential diagnosis in the suspicion of cervical or lumbosacral radiculopathy, as well as in the evaluation of the degree and extent of the injury, when the limitations of the technique are considered.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103392</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i4a103392</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 4 (2010); 188-192</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103392/101861</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103393</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T15:39:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Tend.+Refle.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Stress in rehabilitation: the general adaptation syndrome and the adaptation of the individual to the reality of the disability</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O estresse na reabilitação: a síndrome da adaptação geral e a adaptação do indivíduo à realidade da deficiência</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chagas, Maria Inês Orsoni</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Deficiência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estresse</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Resiliência Psicológica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Adaptação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stress</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Psychological Resilience</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Adaptation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The aim of this article is to explore the idea of human beings having in their DNA, their ancestral heritage, the capacity to adapt to drastic changes that may occur in their lives. Such a capacity enables them to survive in difficult situations, such as disabling sequelae. In addition to this, if we consider resilience as the capacity to resist and overcome adversity there may come a resumption of development as well as an improvement in quality of life of individuals despite the sequelae.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O presente artigo explora a idéia de que o ser humano possui em seu DNA a capacidade para a adaptação às mudanças drásticas que ocorrem na vida, propiciando-lhe a sobrevivência em situações adversas, neste contexto, a aquisição de seqüelas incapacitantes. E se a isso estiver somada a resiliência, enquanto capacidade de transcender à crise com vantagens pode ocorrer uma retomada do desenvolvimento e uma melhora na qualidade de vida do indivíduo, a despeito das seqüelas.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2010-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103393</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v17i4a103393</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 17 n. 4 (2010); 193-199</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103393/101862</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2010 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2023-08-08T14:49:13Z" completeListSize="935" cursor="350">56f24886dc6b1337314311095f169e0d</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
