<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-08-07T14:48:58Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="actafisiatrica">https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102258</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T22:56:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação cinética e cinemática da marcha de adultos do sexo masculino</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chung, Tae Mo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait Analysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Kinetic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Kinematic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Analise de Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cinética</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cinemática</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A avaliação cinética e cinemática da marcha de 44 voluntários adultos do sexo masculino, com idades entre 18 e 40 anos, sem lesões no sistema musculoesquelético, foi realizada pelo sistema computadorizado tridimensional Motion Analysis. Foram selecionados os dados relativos a seis percursos de cada indivíduo, em que se podia observar cada pé efetuar isoladamente o apoio completo na plataforma de força com sincronia de movimento. O padrão de marcha desse grupo foi caraterizado por uma velocidade média de 116,46 cm/s ± 9,43 cm/s no membro inferior direito e 116,61 cm/s ± 9,81 cm/s no membro inferior esquerdo, diferenças que não foram estatisticamente significantes. Observou-se uma correlação direta existente entre o comprimento do passo e da passada com o comprimento dos membros inferiores, assim como entre a velocidade da caminhada e o comprimento da passada. Não houve diferença significante entre os dados cinéticos e cinemáticos obtidos e aqueles relatados na literatura, exceto quanto ao parâmetro velocidade de caminhada, que foi menor.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Kinetic and kinematic evaluation of male adults gait A three-dimensional analysis of kinetic and kinematic gait parameters of 44 adult male volunteers between the ages of 18 and 40 years, without lesions of the musculoskeletal system was performed by using the computerized Motion Analysis system. The data were taken from six selected walks of each individual in which each foot could be observed stepping separately on the force plate platform with synchronized body movements. The average velocity was 116.46 cm/s ± 9.43 cm/s at the right lower limb and 116.61 cm/s ± 9.81 cm/s at the left lower limb, with differences not statistically significant. A close correlation was observed between the step length and stride length versus the length of the limb, as well as, the gait velocity versus the length of the stride. There was no significant difference between our kinetic and kinematic data and those reported in the literature, except for the velocity of the gait, which was slow.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2000-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102258</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v7i2a102258</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 7 n. 2 (2000); 61-67</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102258/100638</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2000 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102259</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T22:56:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Níveis de lactato sanguíneo, em futebolistas profissionais, verificados após o primeiro e o segundo tempos em partidas de futebol</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Paulo Roberto Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Inarra, Luís Antonio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vidal, José Roberto Rivelino</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oberg, Alexandre Augusto Ribeiro Barros</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fonseca Junior, Alcides</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Roxo, Carla Dal Maso Nunes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Machado, Gilberto Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Teixeira, Alberto Azevedo Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Soccer Players</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Blood Lactate</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Soccer Matches</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sports Medicine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Jogadores de Futebol</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lactato Sanguíneo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Partidas de Futebol</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina Esportiva</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo desse estudo foi verificar o envolvimento do metabolismo anaeróbio lático por meio de medidas de lactato sanguíneo em futebolistas profissionais imediatamente após o término do primeiro e do segundo tempos, em partidas de futebol. Foram avaliados 26 jogadores, todos do sexo masculino e pertencentes ao Departamento de Futebol Profissional da Associação Portuguesa de Desportos de São Paulo. O grupo foi composto por 4 laterais, 13 meio-campistas e 9 atacantes. A idade variou de 18 a 33 anos, o peso de 56,5 kg a 78,5 kg e a estatura de 164 cm a 185 cm. A escolha dos futebolistas durante os procedimentos foi aleatória. Foi utilizado um analisador de lactato portátil (modelo Accusport®, Boehringer Mannheim®, GER). Os seguintes resultados foram verificados: a média de lactato em todos os jogadores verificados ao final do primeiro e do segundo tempos das partidas analisadas foi de 7,1 mM ± 0,6 mM e 5,7 mM ± 1,3 mM (p &amp;lt; 0,05). Quando divididos por posição, os laterais apresentaram respectivamente: 6,9 mM ± 2,9 mM e 4,7 mM ± 3,0 mM; os meiocampistas: 6,4 mM ± 1,8 mM e 5,6 mM ± 1,2 mM e os atacantes: 7,7 mM ± 1,8 mM e 7,2 ± 2,1 mM. Quando comparamos a produção de lactato pelas posições, somente houve diferença estatística significante (p &amp;lt; 0,05) no segundo tempo entre os atacantes 7,2 mM ± 2,1 mM e os meio-campistas 5,6 mM ± 1,2 mM, respectivamente. Conclusão: Fatores subjetivos como grau de movimentação, recuperação rápida e disposição constante na partida, relacionados a fatores primários como atividade glicolítica reduzida e a diminuição da concentração de glicogênio muscular, motivados por pouco treinamento anaeróbio lático específico e/ou uma dieta deficiente, são evidências que podem explicar, em parte, porque o lactato sanguíneo no segundo tempo tem sido freqüentemente mais baixo quando comparado ao término do primeiro tempo em uma partida de futebol.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Lactate blood levels in professional socer players after end of the first and second half in soccer matches The main purpose of this study was to assess the participation of the anaerobic lactic metabolism by measuring the lactate blood level in professional soccer players shortly after the end of the first and second half in soccer matches. The assessment was carried out in 26 male soccer players belonging to the Department of Professional Soccer at Associação Portuguesa de Desportos in São Paulo – Brazil. The group was composed of 4 full-backs, 13 midfielders and 9 forwards. Whose age, weight and stature ranged, respectively, from 18 to 33, from 56.5 kg to 78.5 kg and from 164 cm to 185 cm. The soccer players were piecked at random during the procedure. The lactate analyser used to this end was a portable (Accusport model, Boehringer Mannheim, Germany). These were the results: the average lactate level in all soccer players examined after the end of the first half and the second half of the matches analyzed was 7.1 mM ± 0.6 mM and 5.7 mM ± 1.3 mM (p &amp;lt; 0.05). When divided according to their position, the full-backs showed, respectively, 6.9 mM ± 2.9 mM and 4.7 mM ± 3.0 mM; the midfielders 6.4 mM ± 1.8 mM and 5.6 mM ± 1.2 mM and the forwards 7.7 mM ± 1.8 and 7.2 ± 2.1 mM. When we compared the lactate production according to the position, there was only significant statistic (p &amp;lt; 0.05) in the second half between the forwards 7.2 mM ± 2.1 mM and the midfielders 5.6 mM ± 1.2 mM, respectively. Conclusion: Subjective factors, such as movement rate, quick recovery and constant disposition during the match related to primary factors, such as reduced glycolitic activity and diminished muscular glycogen concentration caused by little specific lactic anaerobic training and/or poor diet, are evidences that can partly explain why the lactate blood level in the second half has often been lower when compared with the end of the first half of a soccer match.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2000-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102259</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v7i2a102259</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 7 n. 2 (2000); 68-74</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102259/100639</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2000 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102260</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T22:56:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Bloqueio do nervo obturador como proposta terapêutica analgésica para osteoartrose de coxofemoral: técnica simplificada</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira e Silva, Milene</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Masiero, Danilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chamlian, Therezinha Rosane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wasserstein, Silvia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Osteoarthritis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hip</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Obturator Nerve Blockade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Osteoartrose</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Osteoartrite do Quadril</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Bloqueio Nervoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Nervo Obturador</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Apresentar uma nova abordagem terapêutica na dor por osteoartrose de quadril por meio de uma técnica simplificada de bloqueio do nervo obturador; com a vantagem de ser mais fácil, rápida e com menor risco que a técnica descrita em literatura. Será enfatizada também a necessidade de um tratamento global, nos casos de dor crônica. Sendo aqui relatado o caso clínico da primeira paciente a ser submetida a esse procedimento a qual apresentou grande melhora do quadro álgico (com base na escala visual analógica) e funcional (segundo relatos da paciente).</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Obturator nerve blockage as an analgesic proposal for hip osteoarthritis – a simplified technique To introduce a new terapeutic approach to pain related to hip osteoarthrites consisting of a simplified technique of obturator nerve blockade. The advantages are: it’s easier faster and with lower rinks than the literature’s techniques. We also emphasize the necessity of a global treatment in cases of chronic pain. So we report the case of the first patient submitted to this procedure showing relevant improvement of pain (using visual scale) and also functional status.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2000-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102260</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v7i2a102260</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 7 n. 2 (2000); 75-77</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102260/100640</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2000 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102261</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T22:56:37Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Est.+Prel.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da dor no ombro em paciente com acidente vascular cerebral</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Cláudia de Oliveira e</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Shoulder</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Scapular Girdle</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ombro</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cintura Escapular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Shoulder pain evaluation in stroke patients The purpose of this pilot study is to evaluate the causes of the shoulder pain in the hemiplegic patient as well as the evolution of the miofascial pain syndrome after treatment. Six patients, with 55, 85 +/- 1, 50 years old with an average period from the stroke of 6, 85 +/- 2, 54 months and shoulder pain for 13, 33 +/- 1, 69 weeks, were studied by simplified MacGuill questions; VAS (visual analogue scale), pressure dolorimetry, active and passive goniometric evaluation. Five were spastic grade II and one was flaccid according to Ashworth scale. Six patients had miofascial pain and were submitted by lidocaine 1% injection in trigger points: four in the back shoulder muscles, one in biceps and another in the large pectoral muscles. The characteristics of pain were: burning in four, heavy in three and undefined in two patients. None of them complained of “pins or needles” and “electrical shock” sensation. Three patients referred good results, two regular and one bad. The VAS, the dolorimetric pressure and the goniometric evaluations didn’t show significant improvement after injection (p &amp;gt; 0.05). This study found one patient with adhesive capsulitis; one with supraspinatus tendinitis and another with bicipital tendonitis, by clinical and ultrassonografic evaluation, respectively. There weren’t any patient with shoulder subluxation nor brachial plexus injury. Although with few patients, this study indicates the importance of the approach to miofascial pain syndrome in shoulder pain of hemiplegic patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo desse estudo preliminar é avaliar as causas de dor no ombro de pacientes hemiplégicos, bem como verificar a ocorrência e a evolução do tratamento da síndrome dolorosa miofascial (SDMF). Para isso, seis pacientes hemiplégicos (cinco espásticos grau II, segundo Ashworth e um flácido) com idade: 55, 85 +/- 1, 50 anos, tempo de AVC de 6, 85 +/- 2, 54 meses, e queixas de dor no ombro paralisado há 13, 33 +/- 1, 69 semanas, foram submetidos a um protocolo de avaliação qualitativa (questionário de MacGuill simplificado e quantitativa por meio da escala visual analógica – EVA e dolorimetria de pressão), além da avaliação goniométrica ativa e passiva do ombro. Todos os pacientes apresentaram à palpação muscular, SDMF associada e foram infiltrados com lidocaína a 1% em pontos-gatilho (PGs) intramusculares. As queixas predominantes foram dor em queimor em quatro, peso em três e incaracterística em dois. Nenhum paciente referiu queixas de formigamento, choque, adormecimento e agulhadas. Quatro pacientes foram infiltrados em PGs na musculatura posterior do ombro, um em bíceps e outro em peitoral maior. Não houve melhora significativa na evolução dolorimétrica de pressão e na goniometria após a infiltração desses PGs (p &amp;gt; 0,05). Nesse estudo, diagnosticamos por meios clínicos e/ou radiológicos (RX e USG): um paciente com capsulite adesiva, um com tendinite bicipital e outro com tendinite no supra-espinhal. Não se diagnosticou subluxação na articulação glenoumeral, nem sinais clínicos de lesão nervosa periférica.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2000-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v7i2a102261</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 7 n. 2 (2000); 78-83</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102261/100641</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2000 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102262</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T22:58:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil dos pacientes hemiplégicos atendidos no Lar Escola São Francisco - Centro de Reabilitação</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bruno, Auri de Abreu</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Farias, Carolinne Atta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Iryia, Guilherme Tsutomu</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Masiero, Danilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epidemiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Realizamos um estudo retrospectivo por meio do levantamento de 147 prontuários de pacientes hemiplégicos atendidos na Disciplina de Fisiatria do Departamento de Ortopedia e Traumatologia da Universidade Federal de São Paulo/Escola Paulista de Medicina – Lar Escola São Francisco – Centro de Reabilitação. O período escolhido, janeiro de 1995 a dezembro de 1998, foi posterior à implantação dos grupos de hemiplegia, com o objetivo de conhecermos o perfil dos hemiplégicos atendidos na instituição, compararmos o tempo de permanência entre o atendimento individual e o em grupo, para auxiliar na otimização do tratamento. Os autores observaram predomínio da hemiplegia no sexo masculino e no hemicorpo direito. A maioria era constituída de pacientes atendidos pelo Sistema Único de Saúde, tendo freqüentado terapias 2 vezes por semana com duração de 1 hora, em grupo de 4 a 6 pacientes. A principal etiologia encontrada foi a lesão isquêmica. O tempo de permanência na instituição variou de 2 meses a 2 anos, com a média de permanência muito acima dos critérios de prognóstico descritos na literatura mundial, o que deveremos rever para os tratamentos futuros.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Review of hemiplegic patient treatment at a rehabilitation centre By review of 147 hemilegic pacient data a retrospective study was realized at Lar Escola São Francisco (São Paulo – Brasil) , with the objective of knowing our patient characteristics and assess the treatment they received during the period from 1995 (Jan) to 1998 (Dec). 38,8% were female from which 39 have had isquemic attack and 18 hemorrhagic type. Between male (61,2%) 67 were isquemic type while 23 have had hemorrhagic stroke. 53% of the total with isquemic stroke received individual therapy whereas 38% of those with hemorrhagic attack received this type of therapy. The mean of durability of individual therapy was 10,8 months and for group therapy it was 11,2 months. We concluded that our patient are similar to those described in the literature (sex, type of attack, side of lesion) but the duration of therapy still longer if compared to that.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2000-12-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102262</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v7i3a102262</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 7 n. 3 (2000); 92-94</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102262/100642</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2000 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102263</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T22:58:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Relação entre lordose lombar e desempenho da musculatura abdominal em alunos de fisioterapia</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pinto, Roberta Ramos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guerino, Christiane de Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Consolin, Daniela Bittencourt</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cunha, Ana Cláudia Violino da</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Lordosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Lumbosacral Region</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lordose</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Região Lombar</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Knowing that the middle of the corporal weight is in stable balance on lumbar spine, all muscles that estebilize this place are important, in special abdominals muscles. This muscles attire lateral, anterior and posterior walls of trunk, they work that on band that contains all visceras, they help in balance and work directement in the static and dynamic of pelvis, been much important for body’s posture. There isn’t cientific prove that the habilit of the abdominals muscles is realy connect with the relax erect posture and consequently with the lumbar lordose angle. With the object to connect the abdominal strength and the angle of lumbar lordose was use for measure the angle of lumbar lordose using radiographys of lumbar spine maked with ortostatic position, and the abdominal performance with help of the esfigmomanometryc. For this study, evaluated fifty physiotherapy’s students of University State of Londrina without symptoms, with median age of 22.08; this, five were men and fourty five were women. Like result, wasn’t meet significant correlation between these parameters analised.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Sabendo-se que a metade do peso corporal está em equilíbrio estável sobre a coluna lombar, toda a musculatura estabilizadora desta região é importante, em especial os músculos abdominais. Esses músculos revestem as paredes laterais, anterior e posterior do abdome, agindo como uma espécie de cinta que contém as vísceras, auxiliam no equilíbrio e atuam diretamente na estática e na dinâmica da pelve, sendo muito importante para a postura do corpo. Não há comprovação científica de que a habilidade da musculatura abdominal esteja realmente relacionada com a postura ereta relaxada e conseqüentemente com a angulação lordótica lombar. Com o objetivo de relacionar a força abdominal e o ângulo da lordose lombar, foi utilizado como medida o ângulo da lordose lombar com o auxílio de radiografias da região lombar realizadas com o indivíduo em posição ortostática, e a performance abdominal com o auxílio de um esfigmomanômetro. Para esse estudo foram avaliados 50 alunos assintomáticos do curso de fisioterapia da Universidade Estadual de Londrina, com idade média entre 22,08 anos; destes, 5 eram homens e 45, mulheres. Como resultado, não foi encontrada correlação significante entre os parâmetros analisados.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2000-12-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v7i3a102263</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 7 n. 3 (2000); 95-98</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102263/100643</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2000 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102264</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T22:58:26Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação psicossocial da criança com traumatismo cranioencefálico: conseqüências na afetividade e no emocional</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Alves, Vera Lúcia Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kaihami, Harumi Nemoto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos Cranioencefálicos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Psicologia da Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Craniocerebral Trauma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Psychology, Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The authors refer to psychossocial rehabilitation of brain injured children, considering physical, cognitive deficits and affective/emotional aspects. They give special attention to the position parents occupy in the crisis moment, soon after the accident, and to the further consequences of it in the emotional ambit. They also enphasize the violence against children and parents due to social and cultural rules, stressing the responsability shared by parents, children and society on the matter of prevention.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">As autoras colocam em pauta a reabilitação psicossocial da criança com traumatismo cranioencefálico, em suas diferentes facetas, considerando-se os déficits físicos, cognitivos e os aspectos afetivos/emocionais. Destacam a posição que os pais ocupam no momento de crise e as conseqüências posteriores no âmbito emocional. Ressaltam a violência que ocorre com as crianças e com os pais, decorrentes de normas culturais e sociais. Concluem, enfatizando a responsabilidade partilhada entre pais, crianças e sociedade com respeito à questão da prevenção.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2000-12-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102264</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v7i3a102264</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 7 n. 3 (2000); 99-102</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102264/100644</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2000 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102265</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T22:58:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudo da marcha em idosos: resultados preliminares</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Castro, Carmen Lúcia Natividade de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Jucyleide Antonia de Castro Borba</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leifeld, Paula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bizzo, Luciana Velasco</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Leonardo da Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Tatiana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bueno, Anna Paula Chagas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Teixeira, Renata Duarte</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Velocidade de Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Walking Speed</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The objectives of this pilot study, were the evaluation of, time-spatial, parameters of Brazilian elderly gait and to compare comfortable gait speed’s value with foreign reference data (from Oberg). Methods: Subjects were 15 healthy volunteers (8 men, 7 women) 60 to 79 years of age. The measurements were made in theirs building playground. Gait was timed over a 6 m distance; step length, stride width and foot angle were measured from footprints. Cadence was calculated from velocity and step length. Results: mean comfortable speed was ranged from 1,05 + 0,14 m/s for women in their sixties to 1,10 + 0,13 m/s for men in their seventies. Mean step length, stride width, cadence and foot angle were respectively 52,1 + 8,75 cm; 11,2 + 3,49 cm; 119,4 + 11,07 step/min and 13,5 + 8,53 degree for men and 46,6 + 8,08 cm; 6,75 + 7,07cm; 137,4 + 22,64 step/min and 7,5 + 5,1 degree for women. Conclusion: The lowest elderly’s gait speed obtained despite the sample’s small number in confronting with Oberg data, suggest the importance of comprehensive studies to supply the lack of normative gait data for the Brazilian population.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Os objetivos foram avaliar parâmetros tempo-espaciais da marcha de idosos brasileiros e comparar o valor médio da velocidade confortável da marcha com um banco de dados estrangeiro (de Oberg) de parâmetros básicos da marcha. Metodo: Foram estudados 15 voluntários saudáveis (8 homens, 7 mulheres) dos 60 aos 79 anos de idade. As medidas foram realizadas no playgroung dos prédios onde residiam. A velocidade da marcha foi medida para uma distância de 6 m; o comprimento do passo, a largura da passada e o ângulo dos pés foram medidos a partir de impressões plantares. A cadência foi calculada a partir da velocidade da marcha e do comprimento do passo. Resultados: O valor médio da velocidade confortável da marcha variou de 1,05 + 0,14 m/s para mulheres da faixa etária de 60 anos a 1,10 + 0,13 m/s para homens da faixa etária de 70 anos. Os valores médios do comprimento do passo, da largura da passada, do ângulo dos pés e da cadência foram respectivamente 52,1 + 8,75 cm; 11,2 + 3,49 cm; 119,4 + 11,07 passos/min e 13,5 + 8,53 graus para os homens e 46,6 + 8,08 cm; 6,75 + 7,07cm; 137,4 + 22,64 passos/min e 7,5 + 5,1 graus para as mulheres. Conclusão: O menor valor da velocidade da marcha encontrado para os nossos idosos (apesar da casuística pequena), quando confrontado com os dados de Oberg, sugere a importância de estudos completos para suprir a falta de dados normativos de parâmetros da marcha para a população brasileira.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2000-12-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102265</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v7i3a102265</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 7 n. 3 (2000); 103-107</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102265/100645</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2000 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102266</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T22:58:33Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fortalecimento muscular e condicionamento físico em hemiplégicos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Muscle strengthening and physical conditioning in chronic stroke subjects</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Teixeira-Salmela, Luci Fuscaldi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Edênia Santos Garcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santana, Eneida Geralda Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Resende, Gessione Patricia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Conditioning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Spasticity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Condicionamento Físico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Espasticidade Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudos da literatura demonstram um agravamento do déficit funcional do processo de envelhecimento pelas manifestações clínicas do Acidente vascular cerebral (AVC), como fraqueza muscular, descondicionamento e espasticidade. Pacientes hemiplégicos crônicos submetidos a treinamento de força muscular e condicionamento aeróbico apresentam melhora da velocidade da marcha, maior capacidade de geração de força, aumento do VO2 máximo, melhora da performance funcional e da qualidade de vida, sem, entretanto, alterar o tônus muscular.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Muscle strengthening and physical conditioning in chronic stroke subjects Studies found in the literature show an aggravation of the functional decline of the ageing process due to the clinical manifestations of the Cerebral vascular accident (CVA), including muscle weakness, deconditioning and spasticity. Chronic hemiplegic patients submitted to programs of muscle strengthening and physical conditioning showed improvements in walking speed, in muscle strength, VO2max, functional performance, and quality of life without adverse effects on the degree of spasticity.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2000-12-04</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102266</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20000001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 7 n. 3 (2000); 108-118</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102266/100646</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2000 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102269</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:00:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores ambientais que influenciam a plasticidade do SNC</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Claudia Eunice Neves de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Salina, Maria Elisabete</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Annunciato, Nelson Francisco</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Plasticidade Neuronal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos do Sistema Nervoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Adulto</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neuronal Plasticity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Trauma, Nervous System</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Adult</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O SNC possui uma rede neural complexa, com células altamente especializadas, que fazem milhares de conexões a todo momento e determinam a sensibilidade e as ações motoras, traduzindo-as em comportamento. Na presença de lesões, há um desarranjo nesta rede neural e o SNC inicia seus processos de reorganização e regeneração. A plasticidade neural refere-se à capacidade que o SN possui em alterar algumas das suas propriedades morfológicas e funcionais em resposta às alterações do ambiente. A análise dos aspectos plásticos do SNC permite-nos relacioná-los a vários fatores, como a influência do meio ambiente, o estado emocional, o nível cognitivo, entre outros, que interferem direta ou indiretamente na plasticidade do SNC e, conseqüentemente, na reabilitação do paciente neurológico. Assim, por meio da revisão da literatura, procuramos uma fundamentação teórica, a qual trará bases para a prática clínica, buscando uma nova visão sobre as perspectivas de reabilitação do paciente neurológico adulto.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The central nervous system (CNS) possesses a complex neural net, with highly specialized cells, making thousands of connection at every moment; these cells determine sensitivity and motor activity, translated into behavior. Following lesion, a derangement of this neural net occurs, and the CNS begins processes of reorganization and regeneration. Neural plasticity refers to the NS’s capacity to alter some of its morphological and functional properties in response to environmental changes. Analysis of the plastic aspects of the CNS, allows us to relate them to factors like among others, environmental influences, emotional condition, and cognitive level interfering direct or indirectly with CNS plasticity and the rehabilitation of the neurological patient. By searching for theoretical support, we now expect to bring basic knowledge to clinical practice and new views on the perspectives for rehabilitation of this patient.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102269</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i1a102269</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 1 (2001); 6-13</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102269/100647</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102270</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:00:48Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação das funções corticais superiores em pessoas acometidas por lesão cerebral</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Sandra Schewinsky de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kaihami, Harumi Nemoto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lesão Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Família</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Brain Injury</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Family</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O artigo aborda a importância de se considerar as pessoas com acometimentos mórbidos cerebrais que podem apresentar hemiplegia como seqüela incapacitante, que pode afetar os atos motores voluntários no hemicorpo contralateral, problemas nas funções corticais superiores, distúrbios nas esferas emocional e comportamental. O paciente ao ser inserido no processo de reabilitação na Divisão de Medicina de Reabilitação do Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo é avaliado na Assistência Psicológica, a fim de se averiguar a dinâmica afetivo-emocional, o desempenho intelecto-cognitivo, os déficits das funções neuropsicológicas e a dinâmica familiar. O entrelaçamento dos dados permite traçar um perfil do paciente e possibilita delimitar a intervenção psicológica pertinente, bem como traduzir suas dificuldades e eficiências para a equipe e familiares.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This article refers to the understanding of persons with brain injury who may present hemiplegia as an incapable sequela, which may affect motor volunteer acts in the opposite side of the body, problems in the cortical superior functions, disturbances in the emotional and conductal spheres. When the patient is introduced in the rehabilitation process at Divisão de Medicina de Rehabilitação do Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo, he is evaluated in the Psychological Assistance in order to investigate the affective-emotional dynamics, intellectual-cognitional performance, deficit of neuropsychological functionns and family dinamics. The interlacement of data permits to delineate a profile of the patient and enables to delimit a pertinent psychological intervention, as much as translate theirs difficulties and efficiences to the team and the relatives.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102270</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i1a102270</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 1 (2001); 14-17</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102270/100648</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102271</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:00:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeito do treinamento muscular realizado com pesos, variando a carga contínua e intermitente em jogadores de futebol</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Paulo Roberto Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Treinamento Físico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Futebol</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscular Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Soccer</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Muscular training effect with weights varying continuous and intermittent load in soccer (football) players. The purpose of this investigation was to compare the effect of muscular exercise training with weights varying continuous and intermittent load. This is a study covering twenty soccer players with ages ranging from 18 to 20 (junior category) before and after 12 weeks of physical muscular training. They were all submitted to maximum load tests through a repetition of the knee extensors muscular group, by using the Leg Press exercise in horizontal position with equipment (model Cybex, USA). They were divided into two groups: group I (continuous) and group II (intermittent). The exercises were performed twice a week on alternate days. The group I players underwent continuous training while those belonging to group II only trained intermittently. The players whose training was continuous carried out 3 sets of 12 repetitions at 70% and soon after a 2-min-long recovery, they performed 3 sets of 25 repetitions at 50%. During the same training session, the players who trained intermittently carried out 3 sets of 12 repetitions at 70% and 3 sets of 25 repetitions at 50% alternately. In other words, they carried out a repetition at 70% followed by another at 50%, and so on. Recovery between each repetition for both forms of work ranged from 30 to 60 seconds. The following results were recorded: the strength values in the knee muscular extensors reached by group I were 132.0 ± 4.0 kg and 145.0 ± 5.0 kg with a 10% gain (p &amp;lt; 0.05) and group II reached values of 131.0 ± 7.0 kg and 161.0 ± 9.0 kg with a 23% gain (p &amp;lt; 0.05). When we compared the differential delta between the two forms of work, the intermittent training was 11% greater (p &amp;lt; 0.05). In conclusion, both forms of training proved their efficacy by increasing the muscular strength. The intermittent form, however, seems to adjust it self better to the characteristics of movement requirements by soccer players during a match.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo deste estudo foi comparar o efeito do treinamento físico muscular com pesos, realizando exercícios de maneira contínua e intermitente. Foram estudados 20 jogadores de futebol, com idade variando entre 18 e 20 anos, categoria juniores, antes e após 12 semanas de treinamento. Todos foram submetidos a teste máximo por repetição do grupo muscular extensores dos joelhos, utilizando o exercício LegPress na posição horizontal em equipamento (modelo Cybex, EUA). Eles foram divididos em dois grupos: (I) contínuo e (II) intermitente. Os exercícios foram realizados duas vezes por semana, em dias alternados. Ambos os grupos treinaram somente nas formas contínua e intermitente até o final do estudo. Na forma contínua, os futebolistas realizaram 3 séries de 12 repetições a 70% e após recuperação de 2 minutos mais 3 séries de 25 repetições a 50%. Na forma intermitente, os futebolistas realizaram também, na mesma sessão, 3 séries de 12 repetições a 70% e 3 séries de 25 repetições a 50% de maneira alternada, ou seja, uma série a 70% e logo após outra a 50%, e assim sucessivamente. Em ambas as formas de trabalho, a recuperação entre as repetições variou de 30 a 60 segundos. Antes e após o período de treinamento, os seguintes resultados foram verificados: o grupo I atingiu valores de força nos extensores dos joelhos de 132,0 ± 4,0 kg vs. 145,0 ± 5,0 kg, ganho significante de 10% (p &amp;lt; 0,05); o grupo II atingiu valores de 131,0 ± 7,0 kg vs. 161,0 ± 9,0 kg, ganho significante de 23% (p &amp;lt; 0,05). Quando comparamos o delta diferencial entre as duas modalidades de trabalho, o treinamento intermitente foi 11% maior (p &amp;lt; 0,05). Concluindo, ambas as formas de treinamento aumentaram a força muscular. Contudo, a alternância de intensidade dos exercícios, realizada na mesma sessão pela forma intermitente, foi mais eficiente e parece se ajustar melhor às características de solicitação motora realizada pelos futebolistas durante uma partida de futebol.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102271</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i1a102271</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 1 (2001); 18-23</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102271/100649</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102272</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:00:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Padrões mínimos de conduta em medicina eletrodiagnóstica</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carneiro, Armando Pereira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neuropatia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Eletrodiagnóstico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Treinamento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diretrizes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Miopatia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neuropathy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Myopathie</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electrodiagnosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Guidelines</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">As principais situações em que um exame eletroneuromiográfico e de potenciais evocados são necessários foram alinhadas com justificativas para sua realização. Limites mínimos foram definidos para a extensão do exame em miopatias, doenças da placa motora, dos nervos periféricos, das raízes e dos plexos, do SNC, dos neurônios motores, dos esfíncteres e da função sexual. Elaborados critérios para formação de pessoal especializado e exigências para os serviços de neurofisiologia, como relatórios, esterilizações e descarte de materiais, e atendimento às complicações. A SBMFR – cap. Neurofisiologia Clínica – emitirá selos de qualidade e certificados a seus membros e serviços que estejam cumprindo esses padrões mínimos de conduta em medicina eletrodiagnóstica.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The main indications of a Electrodiagnostic examination were listed with their objectives. Guide lines were estabilished according to the pattology of muscles, motor end plates, peripheral nerves, roots and plexus, motor neurons, central neurons system, sphincter, sexual dysfunctions. Criteria for trainning especialized personnel and requiriments for the Electrodiagnostic clinics as medical records, sterilizations, conditions for reusable materials and special medical emergencies were defined. The SBMFR – Clinical Neurophysiology Chapter – is supposed to keep under control their associates and Electrodiagnostic Clinics throught certificates of quality as soon as they follow these guide lines.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102272</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i1a102272</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 1 (2001); 24-33</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102272/100650</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102273</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:01:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemartroses recidivantes do tornozelo em hemofílicos – Diagnóstico funcional pela podobarometria dinâmica computadorizada e uso profilático de órteses para os pés: relato de um caso</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lourenço, Claudete</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jorge Filho, Donaldo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemophilia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemarthrosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Foot</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemofilia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemartrose</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pé</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Devido ao grande número depacientes hemofílicos, com hemartroses de repetição no tornozelo, que se apresentavam freqüentemente para tratamento no Ambulatório de Reabilitação de Hemofílicos da (DMR) – Divisão de Medicina de Reabilitação do (HCFMUSP) Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo, os autores decidiram avaliá-los mediante um protocolo em que, além do exame físico de rotina e de algumas medidas radiológicas, se procedesse à podoscopia estática e à podobarometria dinâmica computadorizada. Os resultados obtidos serviram de base para a elaboração de palmilhas ortopédicas e/ou para a prescrição de órteses para a estabilização do tornozelo todas as vezes que uma instabilidade médio-lateral do tornozelo e/ou uma discrepância no comprimento dos membros inferiores eram observadas. O uso continuado dessas órteses vem impedindo, nos últimos seis meses, a ocorrência de novos episódios de hemartrose no tornozelo dos pacientes avaliados. Essa constatação levou os autores a acreditar que os desvios articulares nas atividades repetitivas, como a marcha, é que predispõem à ocorrência das hemartroses. Desse modo, a estabilização das articulações, pelo uso das órteses para os pés, seria a melhor maneira de evitar as hemartroses de repetição nos tornozelos. Os bons resultados obtidos até agora, nos pacientes avaliados e reavaliados após seis meses, animaram os autores a desenvolver duas diferentes linhas de pesquisa: para hemofílicos com tornozelos instáveis e para hemofílicos com joelhos instáveis.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Due to a great number of haemophilic patients with repetitive ankle haemartrosis, who attended frequently for treatment on Haemophilic Outpatients Rehabilitation Clinic of the Reabilitation Department of General Hospital School of Medicine of São Paulo State University, the authors decided to examine them by a protocol where, along with the physical exams and some radiographic measurements, it would proceed a static and dynamic pedometric exams. The results were the baseline for the manufacturing of orthopedics insoles as well as for the prescription of ankle stabilizers, everytime that an ankle lateral instability or lenght discrepancies was presented in the patient’s limb. The continuous use of these orthoses has avoided, for the last six month, the occurrance of other ankle haemarthrosis in the evaluated patients. The noticing of this event allow the authors to assert that the articular deviations in the repetitive activities , like the gait , establish proper conditions to the occurrence of haemarthrosis. Therefore , the correction of these deviations by the use of feet orthosis, stabilizing the joints, would be the better way to avoid repetitive haemarthrosis. The good results obtained until nowadays, after observing the patients during six month , motivates the authors to develop two different researches: for unstable haemophilic ankles and for unstable haemophilic knees.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102273</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i1a102273</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 1 (2001); 34-44</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102273/100651</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102274</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:01:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Reprodutibilidade da versão brasileira da Medida de Independência Funcional</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Miyazaki, Margarida Harumi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jorge Filho, Donaldo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sakamoto, Hatsue</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Functional Independence Measure</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Reproductivity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cultural Equivalence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Functional Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Translation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medida de Independência Funcional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reprodutibilidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equivalência Cultural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação Funcional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tradução</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">A Brazilian version of Functional Independence Measure (FIM) was developed in a translation process to Brazilian Portuguese by a bilingual medical team and a professional translator, followed by a reverse translation to English by an independent traslator. No problems of cultural equivalence were identified in the resultant version when it was presented to a group of 25 clinicians trained in its use. Eight rehabilitation centers participated in the gathering of data for the study of reproductibility. Two independent observers evaluated, between December 1999 and January 2000, all adult stroke patients with more than 4 months of impairment onset at the same day and only one of these clinicians repeated the observation after one week (test/retest). A total of 164 patients were examined, kappa agreement values in each of the FIM items varied between two observers form 0,50 (feeding) to 0,64 (bladder control), at test/retest they varied from 0,61 (dressing below waist) to 0,77 (toilet transfer). MIF subscales showed good correlation at test/retest (Pearson: 0,91 – 0,98; ICC: 0,91 – 0,98) and between two observers (Pearson: 0,87 – 0,98; ICC: 0,87 – 0,98). Analysis of variance shows good agreement for these subscales between two observers and at test/retest condition. We conclude that the Brazilian version of FIM has good cultural equivalence and reproductivity.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A versão brasileira da Medida de Independência Funcional (MIF) foi desenvolvida por meio de um processo de tradução para o português do Brasil por equipe médica bilíngüe familiarizada com o instrumento e tradutor profissional, seguido de tradução reversa para o inglês por tradutor independente. Não foram identificados problemas de equivalência cultural quando a versão obtida foi apresentada a um conjunto de 25 profissionais de saúde treinados no seu uso. Oito centros de reabilitação participaram da captação de dados para a obtenção de medidas de reprodutibilidade. Todos os pacientes adultos com história de pelo menos 4 meses de acidente vascular cerebral, consultados no período entre dezembro de 1999 e janeiro de 2000, foram avaliados por dois avaliadores treinados na aplicação da MIF, de forma independente, e reavaliados por apenas um desses examinadores após uma semana (teste/reteste). Uma amostra de 164 pacientes foi examinada e os valores de kappa para concordância em cada um dos itens da MIF variaram entre dois observadores de 0,50 (alimentação) a 0,64 (controle da urina) e no teste/reteste entre 0,61 (vestir abaixo da cintura) a 0,77 (transferência para o vaso sanitário). As subescalas da MIF apresentaram no teste/reteste boa correlação (Pearson: 0,91–0,98; ICC: 0,91–0,98); a reprodutibilidade interobservadores também foi boa (Pearson: 0,87–0,98; ICC: 0,87–0,98). Análise de variância mostra boa concordância entre as médias dos resultados de dois avaliadores na primeira avaliação e na medida após uma semana. Concluímos que a versão brasileira da MIF tem boa equivalência cultural e boa reprodutibilidade. &#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102274</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20010002</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 1 (2001); 45-52</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102274/100652</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102345</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:03:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Dispositivo para emulação de mouse dedicado a pacientes tetraplégicos ou portadores de doença degenerativa do sistema neuromuscular</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Müller, André Frotta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zaro, Milton Antônio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva Junior, Danton Pereira da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sanches, Paulo Roberto Stefani</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferlin, Elton Luiz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Thomé, Paulo Ricardo Oppermann</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Antônio Cardoso dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tarrago, Maria da Graça</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Quadriplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Esclerose Amiotrófica Lateral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Interface Usuário-Computador</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Disartria</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quadriplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">User-Computer Interface</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Dysarthria</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O trabalho descreve o desenvolvimento de um dispositivo que emula um mouse serial MicrosoftÒ. Este dispositivo permite ao deficiente físico tetraplégico acessar os recursos de informática em ambiente WindowsÒ 95/98 (ler e editar textos, navegar na Internet e utilizar o correio eletrônico) e auxilia o paciente de doenças degenerativas do sistema neuromuscular, como a esclerose lateral amiotrófica (ELA), com disartria, a comunicar-se com as pessoas ao seu redor. O movimento do cursor na tela do computador é produzido a partir do movimento de flexão e extensão da cabeça do usuário, sendo utilizado para medir os ângulos de inclinação um sensor de aceleração estática e dinâmica de dois eixos. Para emular o botão do mouse, são captados os sinais EMG (eletromiográficos) produzidos a partir do movimento voluntário dos músculos mímicos da região frontal do usuário. O processamento digital é realizado por um microcontrolador de oito bits e os dados são transmitidos para um computador padrão IBM-PC através da interface RS232C.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This work describes the development of a pointing data entry device that emulates a MicrosoftÒ serial mouse. The device is aimed to individuals with a spinal cord injury or amyotrophic lateral sclerosys (A.L.S.), a degenerative disease of the neuromuscular system. This equipment allows individuals without hand movements to acess some computing resources such as reading, writing, surfing on the web, etc. The user’s head tilt, measured by a dual axis accelerometer, is responsible for the cursor movements on the computer screen. The click and double-click are produced by the voluntary movement of the user’s forehead muscle, which are acquired using electromyographic techniques. An eight bit microcontroller is used for the digital processing and interface to the computer via a RS232 port.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102345</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i2a102345</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 2 (2001); 63-66</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102345/100659</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102346</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:03:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O significado do discurso de risco na área de reabilitação</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Alves, Vera Lúcia Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pessoas com Deficiência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Risco</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disabled Persons</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Risk</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A autora busca neste artigo analisar o discurso e as intervenções governamentais na atenção à pessoa portadora de deficiência. Nesse sentido discute-se o conceito de “risco” no contexto de saúde pública e o seu significado em reabilitação.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">In this article, the author searches to analyse the governamental’s speeches and interventions which focus on the handicapped people. In this sense, it was discussed the concept of “risk” in the context of public health and its importance to the rehabilitation.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102346</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i2a102346</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 2 (2001); 67-70</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102346/100660</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102347</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:03:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação de parâmetros clínicos de pacientes com fibromialgia após 5 anos de evolução</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Martinez, José Eduardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Xavier, Fellipe Mendes de Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>André, Mariana Zacharias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ramalho, Marcelo Viceconte</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fibromialgia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Evolução</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fibromyalgia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Follow-up</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Fibromyalgia is a syndrome of unknown etiology characterized by diffuse pain and presence of tender points on digital palpation. In 1995, it was published, by our group, a clinical study showing that fibromyalgia causes a negative impact on patient’s quality of life. In certain ways, this impact is similar to the one caused by rheumatoid arthritis. The main purpose of the present study is to evaluate the same patients after 5 years of evolution. Methods: It was made a phone interview which included questions about evolution, numerical analogic scales of pain, fatigue, depression and anxiety (0 – 10) and the disability scale of the Health Assessment Questionnaire (HAQ). The scores were compared to the ones of the 1995 study by the Wilcoxon test. Patients: It was studied 18 female patients, who had participated in the 1995 survey. All patients then fullfilled the American College of Rheumatology Criteria for Classification of Fibromyalgia. Results: Ten patients referred to be better, 3 worst and 5 unchanged. Twelve patients keep on treatment and 6 patients are not on treatment at all. The scores of the scales applied in 1995 and now are respectively: Numerical Pain Scale: 5,72 – 5,77; Numerical Fatigue Scale: 4,66 – 5,70; Numerical Depression Scale: 5,50 – 5,22; Numerical Anxiety Scale: 6,61 – 3,72; and HAQ: 0,75 – 1,08. The statistical analysis showed significant difference just on the Anxiety Scale. Conclusion: We concluded that fibromyalgia has a stable course at the clinical and physical capacity parameters used at this study, although most patients referred being better. Anxiety scores improved probably by the better knowledge of patients about this syndrome. Patients, opinion could be influenced by the improvement on anxiety.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Fibromialgia é uma síndrome clínica de causa desconhecida caracterizada por dor difusa e presença de pontos dolorosos musculares à dígito-pressão. Em 1995, foi publicado, por nosso grupo de pesquisa, um estudo clínico mostrando que a fibromialgia causa impacto negativo na qualidade de vida dos pacientes. Em alguns aspectos, esse impacto é semelhante em intensidade àquele causado pela artrite reumatóide. O objetivo deste estudo é avaliar os mesmos parâmetros utilizados, após 5 anos de evolução. Métodos: Realizou-se entrevista telefônica que incluía questões sobre a evolução da sintomatologia, escalas analógicas numéricas para dor, fadiga, depressão e ansiedade (0 – 10) e a escala de incapacidade física Health Assessment Questionnaire (HAQ). As pontuações atuais foram comparadas com as do estudo de 1995 por meio do teste de Wilcoxon. Pacientes: Estudaram-se 18 mulheres que participaram do estudo de 1995. Todas as pacientes preenchiam os critérios para Classificação de Fibromialgia do American College of Rheumatology (Colégio Americano de Reumatologia) na época do estudo de 1995. Resultados: Dez pacientes referiram estar melhor; 3, pior; e 5 permaneceram inalteradas. Doze pacientes se mantêm em algum tipo de tratamento e 6 estão sem qualquer tipo de tratamento. As pontuações das escalas aplicadas em 1995 e agora são, respectivamente: Escala Numérica de Dor: 5,72 – 5,77; Escala Numérica Fadiga: 4,66 – 5,70; Escala Numérica de Depressão: 5,50 – 5,22; Escala Numérica de Ansiedade: 6,61 – 3,72; e HAQ: 0,75 – 1,08. A análise estatística mostrou diferença estatisticamente significativa apenas na escala de ansiedade. Conclusão: Conclui-se que a fibromialgia tem uma evolução estável nos parâmetros clínicos e de capacidade física estudados neste trabalho. As pontuações de ansiedade melhoraram provavelmente por causa do melhor conhecimento da fibromialgia pelas pacientes.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102347</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i2a102347</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 2 (2001); 71-74</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102347/100661</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102348</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:03:14Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Dores na coluna em profissionais de enfermagem</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pinho, Lucinéa de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Araújo, Maralu Gonzaga de Freitas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Goes, Soraya Rocha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sampaio, Rosana Ferreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Enfermagem</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores de Risco</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor Lombar</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Low Back Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Nursing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Risk Factors</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The purpose of literature review was to better understand the working organization and the working processes of nursing staffs, identifying the main risk factors associated with the back pain in these professional, and analysing various prevention strategies described by the other authors. For this purpose, mainly Brazilian papers were reviewed, which considered the reality of the nursing profession in our country. The professional caracterization indicated that the majority were females of low social economic status and have two jobs. The main risk factors associated with pain were divided into ergonomic and traumatic ones. The traumatic factor was subdivided into both individuals and professionals. Related to the prevention measures, it was observed that most studies priorized the postural and ergonomic orientations, in addition to those related to the physical activities. Finally, it is important to point out that the working organizations and processes of these professionals, as well as the risk factors associated with the occurence of pain, were studied in detail. With respect to the prevention measures, it appears important to direct them to various professional courses and work sectors. Considering the high incidence of pain among nursing professionals, other studies that focus on the prevention of pain should be carried with objective of improving their quality of life and work conditions.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo desta revisão bibliográfica foi conhecer a organização e o processo de trabalho do pessoal de enfermagem, identificando os principais fatores de risco associados às dores na coluna desses profissionais, além de analisar as propostas de prevenção descritas pelos autores estudados. Para tanto, foram pesquisadas principalmente publicações de autores brasileiros, considerando a realidade da enfermagem em nosso País. A caracterização desses profissionais mostrou que a maioria é do sexo feminino, de nível socioeconômico baixo e que trabalha em dupla jornada. Os fatores de risco associados às dores na coluna mais destacados foram divididos em ergonômicos e traumáticos, e os traumáticos se subdividiram em individuais e profissionais. Com relação às medidas preventivas, constatou-se que a maioria dos autores prioriza a promoção de cursos de orientações posturais e ergonômicas, além de orientações referentes às atividades físicas. Por último, é importante ressaltar que a organização e o processo de trabalho desses profissionais, assim como os fatores de risco associados à ocorrência de dores na coluna, foram mais exaustivamente estudados. Quanto às medidas preventivas, seria importante direcioná-las para as diferentes categorias profissionais e setores de trabalho. Considerando o número de casos de dores na coluna entre os profissionais de enfermagem, é importante que outros estudos se aprofundem na prevenção do problema, objetivando, assim, uma melhor qualidade de vida e de trabalho desses profissionais.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i2a102348</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 2 (2001); 75-81</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102348/100662</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102349</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:03:19Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Tend.+Refle.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O fisiatra trata do quê?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Saad, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical and Rehabilitation Medicine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina Física e Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisiatria</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Physiatry is perhaps the medical specialty which most focus on the bio-psycho-social integration of the human being. Besides concerning the disease, concerns also with how this disease detains the individual in being a complete person. Perhaps Physiatry has been a revolution among medical specialties. It introduced such an innovator concept that, even past so many decades, still is tried to exactly delimitate the action field of Physiatry. Maybe Physiatry is the opportunity to exert Medicine in one of the most spiritualized ways. The problem of informing the population and the medical colleagues about Physiatry asks for our patient dedication in facing misinformation.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Fisiatria é talvez a especialidade médica que mais traga para o centro da atenção a integração biopsicossocial do ser humano. Além de se preocupar com a doença, preocupa-se também com o modo como esta doença impede o indivíduo de ser uma pessoa completa. Talvez a Fisiatria tenha sido uma revolução entre as especialidades médicas. Ela trouxe um conceito tão inovador que, mesmo passadas tantas décadas, ainda tentam delimitar exatamente qual o campo de atuação da Fisiatria. Ela talvez dê oportunidade de se exercer a medicina de uma forma mais espiritualizada. O problema do esclarecimento da população e da classe médica sobre a Fisiatria exige nosso empenho paciente e desprovido de irritação diante da desinformação.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i2a102349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 2 (2001); 82-83</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102349/100663</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102350</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:06:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A avaliação do uso da toxina botulínica A e da cinesioterapia na melhora da marcha do portador de paralisia cerebral do tipo hemiparético</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Faria, Tereza Cristina Carbonari de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Masiero, Danilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Spósito, Maria Matilde de Melo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Saad, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Toxinas Botulínicas Tipo A</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Botulinum Toxins, Type A</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">It was studied 14 spastic hemiparetic patients, with dynamic equines and age between 3 and 9 years old. The patients were distributed in 2 groups: Group I – 7 children that received botulinum toxin type A (BTX A) injections in the gastrocnemius and soleus muscles and also kinesiotherapic treatment; Group II – 7 children that received only the kinesiotherapic treatment. The data analysed were: the ankle range of motion, muscle tone, the action of tibialis anterior muscle, the velocity, cadence and the gait observational analysis and the parents degree of satisfaction. The statistical analysis showed that in Group I all data were improved in a short time. In Group II the data were not improved in the same period of time, but there were some improvements on some data in a longer period of time.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Foram estudados 14 pacientes com paralisia cerebral do tipo hemiparético, eqüinismo dinâmico e idade entre 3 e 9 anos, com média de 5,93 anos. Os pacientes foram distribuídos em dois grupos: Grupo I – 7 crianças que foram tratadas com toxina botulínica tipo A (TBA) nos músculos gastrocnêmios e solear e tratamento cinesioterápico; Grupo II – 7 crianças que receberam apenas tratamento cinesioterápico. Avaliaram-se: a amplitude de movimento do tornozelo, o tônus muscular, a ação do músculo tibial anterior, a velocidade, a cadência da marcha, além da análise observacional da marcha e grau de satisfação dos pais. A análise estatística dos resultados mostrou, com significância, que no Grupo I houve melhora de todas as medidas avaliadas num intervalo mais curto de tempo. No Grupo II não houve melhora de todas as medidas avaliadas e o ganho em algumas medidas ocorreu num tempo mais longo.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102350</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i3a102350</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 3 (2001); 101-106</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102350/100664</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102355</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:06:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Espiritualidade baseada em evidências</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Saad, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Masiero, Danilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Religião e Ciência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Espiritualismo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Religion and Science</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spiritualism</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Spirituality may be defined as a belief system that focus on intangible elements that transmit vitality and meaning to life. Such belief may mobilize highly positive energies and initiatives, with ilimited potential to improve person’s quality of life. Implications of spirituality on health have being scientificaly studied and documented in hundreds of papers. There is relationship between spiritualist engagement and many aspects of mental health, so that people experience better mental health and can copy with more success to stress if they are religious. Religious people are physically healthier, have more healthy lifestyles and demand less health assistance. There is an association between spirituality and health which is likely valid and possibly causal. It is fully recognized that people’s health is determined by interactions of physical, mental, social and spiritual factors. Health professionals already count on with scientific indications of the benefits of spiritual exploration on the therapeutic program of virtually any disease. The current paper cites the most relevant references about this issue.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Espiritualidade pode ser definida como um sistema de crenças que enfoca elementos intangíveis, que transmite vitalidade e significado a eventos da vida. Tal crença pode mobilizar energias e iniciativas extremamente positivas, com potencial ilimitado para melhorar a qualidade de vida da pessoa. As implicações da espiritualidade na saúde vêm sendo estudadas cientificamente e documentadas em centenas de artigos. Há relação entre envolvimento espiritualista e vários aspectos da saúde mental, sendo que pessoas vivenciam melhor saúde mental e se adaptam com mais sucesso ao estresse se são religiosas. Pessoas religiosas são fisicamente mais saudáveis, têm estilos de vida mais salutares e requerem menos assistência de saúde. Existe uma associação entre espiritualidade e saúde que provavelmente é válida, e possivelmente causal. É plenamente reconhecido que a saúde de indivíduos é determinada pela interação de fatores físicos, mentais, sociais e espirituais. Os profissionais da saúde já contam com indicações científicas do benefício da exploração da espiritualidade na programação terapêutica de virtualmente qualquer doença. O presente artigo cita os trabalhos mais relevantes sobre o assunto.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102355</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i3a102355</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 3 (2001); 107-112</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102355/100673</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102359</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:06:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Geometria do fêmur proximal em ossos de brasileiros</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mourão, Ana Lúcia Mourão</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vasconcellos, Henrique Ayres de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fraturas do Fêmur</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores de Risco</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Femoral Fractures</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Risk Factors</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Fornecer dados sobre a morfometria do fêmur proximal adulto para que se estabeleçam parâmetros e correlações entre as diversas medidas dessa porção do osso de brasileiros. Material e Método: Realizamos a avaliação da geometria da extremidade proximal de 183 fêmures secos de adultos brasileiros, de ambos os sexos, sem idade cronológica determinada. A morfometria constou da obtenção das medidas: comprimento do colo do fêmur (CCF); largura do colo do fêmur (LCF); comprimento do eixo femoral (CEF); ângulo colodiafisário (ACD). Foi realizada também a densitometria óssea (DEXA) de 18 fêmures. A análise estatística constou do cálculo da média aritmética (X); desvio-padrão (SD) e mediana (Me), sendo testadas essas variáveis quanto ao lado através dos testes t de Student e Não- Paramétrico de Mann Whitney. Realizamos a correlação e a regressão linear simples entre as variáveis que apresentavam associação com o CEF. Resultado: Correlacionamos as medidas morfométricas com a densidade mineral óssea (DMO) e as densidades entre si. Encontramos os seguintes valores médios para os lados direito e esquerdo: CCF = 24,9 ± 4,5 mm e 24,3 ± 4,2 mm; LCF = 26,7 ± 3,1 mm e 26,3 ± 3,3 mm; CEF = 92,1 ± 6,9 mm e 92,0 ± 7,1 mm; ACD = 111,2° ± 5,9 e 114,2° ± 5,5. A correlação entre CEF x ACD não foi significante. As correlações entre morfometria e DMO foram menos significativas que as correlações das densidades entre si. Conclusão: Podemos acreditar que a associação entre o CEF e as outras medidas pode ter valor preditivo no risco de fratura. Considerando a importância desse fator, procedemos a este estudo para podermos fornecer dados da geometria femoral de ossos de brasileiros, bem como possibilitar aplicação desses dados na prática clínica.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">On this work, the evaluation of the proximal extremity of 183 dry femurs, taken from corpses of Brazilian adults, collected, randomly, in the Anatomic Department of the State University of Rio de Janeiro has been analyzed; either sex status or chronological age of the sample were not considered on this work. Morphometric measurements were taken, and bony densiometry (DEXA) done on 18 of then. The morphometric measurements were: length of the femoral neck (CCF); width of the femoral neck (LCF); length of femoral axis (CEF); neck-shaft angle (ACD). The measurements were then submitted to arithmetic average (X), standard deviation (SD) and medium (Me), the Student t and Non-Parametric Mann Whitney tests, as well as the linear regression and correlation analysis between the variables that presented in association with CEF. A correlation analysis morphometric measurements and the mineral bone density (DMO) were also done, as well as the density itself. The average values found for the right and left sides were: CF = 436.9 ± 26.3 mm and 441.7 ± 27.7 mm; CCF = 24.9 ± 4.5 mm and 24.3 ± 4.2 mm; LCF = 26.7 ± 3,1 mm and 26.3 ± 3.3 mm; LDF = 29.8 ± 2.9 mm and 30.7 ± 2.6 mm; DCF = 43.5 ± 3.3 mm and 43.9 ± 3.7 mm; CEF = 92.1 ± 6.9 mm and 92.0 ± 7.1 mm; AI = 111.2° ± 5.9 and 114.2° ± 5.5; AT= 16 ° and 18°. The results have shown no significant differences regarding the femur side (right and feft) , but those have been shown when CEF versus DCF and CEF versus LDF have been compared. The morphometry has also been correlated to the densiometry and no significance has been found. A positive significance has been found in the densiometry itself. The literature review has mentioned differences in race, bone mass and proximal extremity architecture and has postulated their relevance regarding the potential fracture risk. Based on this work, the authors have concluded that such a study could be used as a parameter for the Brazilians femurs, and it could be related to the clinical practice.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102359</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i3a102359</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 3 (2001); 113-119</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102359/100680</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102363</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:06:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação podobarométrica nas amputações do médio e antepé</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chamlian, Therezinha Rosane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nery, Caio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Réssio, Cibele</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Masiero, Danilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Amputation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Foot</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Orthotic Devices</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Amputação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pé</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Aparelhos Ortopédicos</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Os autores estudaram a marcha de 14 pacientes com amputações unilaterais parciais do pé, Chopart e transmetatarsiana, através do podobarômetro F-Scan®, para determinar a duração do passo, a distribuição do pico de pressão máxima, o impulso vertical, a velocidade e a trajetória do baricentro (COP), nas situações: sem calçado, com palmilha plana e com prótese de Chopart. A análise dos resultados demonstrou que o tempo total do passo do lado amputado, nos dois grupos, é menor do que o dos pés não-amputados, nas três situações. A utilização de palmilhas não produz alterações e o uso de próteses aumenta significantemente o tempo de duração do passo, em ambos os pés. Os picos de pressão máxima nos pés amputados são superiores aos dos pés não-amputados, nos dois grupos de pacientes, nas três situações estudadas. O uso de palmilhas e próteses reduz significantemente os níveis de pressão máxima, em ambos os pés, sendo a intensidade dessa redução proporcional à rigidez imposta pelo equipamento utilizado. A localização dos picos de pressão máxima pode ser modificada na dependência do tipo de órtese ou prótese utilizada, em ambos os pés. O impulso vertical do solo é menor no lado amputado nos dois grupos; no entanto, é constantemente maior na amputação do tipo Chopart que na transmetatarsiana. A velocidade de deslocamento do baricentro no retropé dos pacientes amputados, nos dois grupos, é menor do que a observada nos pés não-amputados, e não varia com a utilização das órteses e próteses estudadas.Os pés não-amputados dos pacientes dos dois grupos apresentam alterações funcionais importantes manifestadas por desvios das velocidades do baricentro no retro, médio e antepé.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Gait was analysed in fourteen unilateral partial foot amputees – Chopart and transmetatarsal levels – using F-Scan® podobarometer to determine stance time, peak plantar pressure, vertical ground impulse, speed and trajectory of the centre of pressure (COP), in 3 different conditions: without shoe, flat insole and Chopart’s prosthesis. The results showed reduction in the mean duration of stance time at the affected side, in both groups, in all conditions. The use of insoles does not influence the stance time, but prosthesis increases the mean duration at ipsilateral and contralateral side in these 3 different conditions. Amputees feet maximum peak pressure is greater than no amputees feet. The use of insole and prosthesis decreases this pressure in 3 situations at both feet significantly. The intensity of this reduction is proportional to the stiffness imposed by the equipment. Maximum peak pressure location is variable at both feet and could be modified depending on the type of orthosis and prosthesis, either at no amputee and amputee feet. Vertical ground impulse is lower at amputee side in both groups, however always greater in Chopart group. The deslocation of COP is slower at affected hindfoot in both group and this velocity does not change with insoles or prosthesis. No amputee feet of both group show important functional disturbs manifested by deviations of normal COP velocity at hind, mid and forefoot.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2001-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102363</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v8i3a102363</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 8 n. 3 (2001); 120-129</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102363/100687</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2001 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102364</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T23:21:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Pêndulo: um teste simples de medida de espasticidade</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Pendulum: a simple test to measure spasticity</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Teixeira-Salmela, Luci Fuscaldi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nadeau, Sylvie</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Olney, Sandra Jean</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brouwer, Brenda</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Espasticidade Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tônus Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Spasticity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Tonus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo deste estudo foi investigar a confiabilidade do teste de pêndulo para avaliar o tônus muscular e comparar os dados obtidos entre um grupo de idosos saudáveis e um grupo de pacientes hemiplégicos crônicos da mesma faixa etária. Vinte idosos e 20 hemiplégicos crônicos foram recrutados na comunidade, de forma voluntária. O tônus muscular foi investigado utilizando o índice de relaxamento corrigido (IRC) obtido pelo teste de pêndulo. Para avaliar a confiabilidade do IRC, os dados foram obtidos em dois dias diferentes para ambos os grupos. Testes-t foram empregados para avaliar diferenças entre os grupos e entre os lados afetado e não afetado do grupo hemiplégico. A média do IRC para o lado afetado foi 0,65 (± 0,20) no primeiro dia e 0,66 (± 0,11) no segundo dia. Para o lado não afetado, as médias foram 1,03 (± 0,09) e 1,02 (± 0,11) para os primeiro e segundo dias, respectivamente. Coeficientes de correlação significativos foram observados entre as duas medidas obtidas (r = 0,93 e r = 0,70) para os lados afetado e não afetado, respectivamente. Os resultados do teste-t demonstraram diferenças significativas entre os valores do IRC obtidos no lado afetado comparados com os valores do lado não afetado e os valores de referência. Entretanto, não foram observadas diferenças significativas entre os valores do IRC obtidos no lado não afetado e os valores de referência. Pode-se concluir que o teste de pêndulo apresenta o potencial de ser incluído como um método eficaz de medida de tônus muscular em reabilitação.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The aim of this study was to investigate the reliability of the pendulum test in assessing muscle tone and compare the data obtained from a healthy elderly group with a group of chronic stroke subjects of similar age. Twenty healthy elderly and 20 chronic stroke subjects were recruited on a volunteer basis from the community. The muscle tone was measured by the corrected relaxation index (CRI) obtained from the pendulum test. To assess the reliability of the CRI, data were obtained from both groups on two different days. T-tests were used to assess differences between groups and between affected and non-affected sides of the stroke group. The mean CRI value for the affected side was 0.65 (± 0.20) for day one and 0.66 (± 0.11) for day two. For the unaffected side, the mean CRI value was 1.03 (± 0.09) and 1.02 (± 0.11) for day one and two, respectively. Significant correlation coefficients between the two measures were obtained (r= 0.93, p = 0.000 and r= 0.70, p = 0.000) for the affected and unaffected sides, respectively. The results of the t-tests showed significant differences between the CRI values of the affected leg compared with the non-affected leg and the reference values of the elderly group. However, no significant differences were observed between the CRI values of the non-affected leg and the reference values. It can be concluded that the pendulum test presents the potential to be included as an efficient method of assessing muscle tone.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2002-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102364</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v9i2a102364</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 9 n. 2 (2002); 63-70</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102364/100688</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2002 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2023-08-08T14:48:58Z" completeListSize="935" cursor="100">b972cbf48640b1e201dcc68ea9033451</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
