<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-08-07T14:49:42Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="actafisiatrica">https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/181801</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-15T17:11:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Systemic scleroderma patient education: a booklet report</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação de pacientes com esclerodermia sistêmica: relato de cartilha</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Chaves, Caio Carvalhais</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marcelino, Ana Leticia Fontes de Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Laura Cristine Carmo da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Andrade, Júnia Amorim</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Flavia Patrícia Sena Teixeira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Gilda Aparecida</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Calderaro, Débora Cerqueira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Escleroderma Sistêmico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia Ocupacional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Autocuidado</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Materiais Educativos e de Divulgação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Educação de Pacientes como Assunto</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Scleroderma, Systemic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Occupational Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Self Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Educational and Promotional Materials</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Patient Education as Topic</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: This study aims to describe the development and online distribution of a patient education booklet about systemic scleroderma focused on occupational therapy orientations.&#160;Methods: The research-action methodology was applied and divided into the following five steps: analysis of patients' requests, preparation of the content, choice of illustrations and graphic design, developers' approval of the education booklet, and online distribution.&#160;Results: The education booklet entitled "Occupational Therapy Guidelines for People with Systemic Sclerosis" was developed, and its online distribution reached nearly 5000 people.&#160;Conclusion: Educational materials serve as adjuncts to the treatment of chronic diseases, as systemic scleroderma. The online distribution of these materials expands its reach among these patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Este estudo visou descrever o desenvolvimento e distribuição online de uma cartilha educativa para pacientes com esclerodermia sistêmica com foco em orientações da terapia ocupacional. Métodos: A metodologia de pesquisa-ação foi aplicada e dividida em cinco etapas: análise das solicitações dos pacientes, elaboração do conteúdo, escolha das ilustrações e do projeto gráfico, aprovação dos autores da cartilha educativa e distribuição online. Resultados: Foi desenvolvida a cartilha educativa intitulada "Orientações da Terapia Ocupacional para Pessoas com Esclerose Sistêmica" e sua distribuição online atingiu quase 5.000 pessoas. Conclusão: Os materiais educativos constituem recurso útil no tratamento de doenças crônicas, como a esclerodermia sistêmica. A distribuição online desses materiais expande seu alcance entre os pacientes.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/181801</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i2a181801</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 2 (2021); 92-96</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/181801/174313</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/181882</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-09-27T14:54:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The profile of health professionals of a public hospital and their perception of the physiotherapist's role and performance during the COVID-19 pandemic</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil dos profissionais de saúde de um hospital público e sua percepção acerca da atuação do fisioterapeuta no enfrentamento da COVID-19</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Menezes, Georgia Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Sávylla Sklabrynne Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Azevedo, Gustavo Silva de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">COVID-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equipe de Assistência ao Paciente</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisioterapeutas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">COVID-19</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Patient Care Team</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapists</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The current COVID-19 pandemic is a milestone in the history of recent global health. Other health professionals' knowledge of the physiotherapist's performance can increase health care accessibility. Objective: To describe the profile and analyze the perception of health professionals in a public hospital regarding the role and performance of the physiotherapist in dealing with COVID-19 infected patients. Method: This is an epidemiological, descriptive, cross-sectional study conducted with health professionals of a general hospital. The participants answered a pre-structured questionnaire with questions about physiotherapists common practices in the hospital setting. Results: Thirty professionals were included, with an average of 36.83 years of age, and 86.7% were female. The physiotherapy performance was considered necessary in dealing with COVID-19 (100%), despite the different places where the interviewees worked, different health professions, and their educational levels. Motor (100%) and respiratory (100%) rehabilitation were highlighted as a contribution of physiotherapy to treating patients infected by the coronavirus. Procedures such as the implementation of oxygen therapy (96.7%), non-invasive mechanical ventilation (80%), adjustment of mechanical ventilation parameters (100%), and extubation (70%) were mainly considered as the physiotherapy role. The procedures shared by the multi-professional team were also described, such as the implementation of oxygen therapy (80%), adjustment of ventilatory parameters (86.7%), and aspiration of the airway and artificial airway (90%). Conclusion: The physiotherapist has an essential role in dealing with patients infected with COVID-19, associated with a multidisciplinary team, especially in cardiorespiratory and musculoskeletal rehabilitation of patients affected by the coronavirus.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A pandemia atual pelo COVID-19 é um marco na história da saúde mundial recente. O conhecimento da atuação do fisioterapeuta por outros profissionais de saúde torna acessível a assistência em saúde pela equipe. Objetivo: Descrever o perfil e analisar a percepção dos profissionais de saúde de um hospital público acerca da atuação do fisioterapeuta no enfrentamento do COVID-19. Método: Trata-se de estudo epidemiológico, descritivo, transversal. O estudo teve aprovação do CEP pelo parecer 4078528/2020 e todos os participantes apresentaram aceite no TCLE. Os voluntários responderam ficha pré-estruturada, contendo indagações sobre práticas comuns ao fisioterapeuta na área hospitalar. Resultados: Participaram 30 profissionais, com idade média de 36,83 anos, sendo 86,7% do sexo feminino. A atuação da fisioterapia foi considerada importante no enfrentamento da COVID-19 (100%), apesar dos diferentes locais de atuação dos entrevistados, diferentes profissões de saúde e nível de escolaridade dos participantes. Em destaque a reabilitação motora (100%) e respiratória (100%) foi vista como uma contribuição da fisioterapia em pacientes acometidos pelo coronavírus. Procedimentos como a implementação da oxigenoterapia (96,7%), ventilação mecânica não invasiva (80%), ajuste de parâmetros da ventilação mecânica (100%) e extubação (70%), foram considerados majoritariamente como das atribuições da fisioterapia. Foram descritos também os procedimentos compartilhados pela equipe multiprofissional, como a implementação de oxigenoterapia (80%), ajuste de parâmetros ventilatórios (86,7%) e aspiração de via aérea e via aérea artificial (90%). Conclusão: O fisioterapeuta tem papel importante no enfrentamento do COVID-19, associado a equipe multiprofissional, em especial na reabilitação cardiorrespiratória e musculoesquelética dos pacientes afetados pelo coronavírus.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-06-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/181882</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v29i2a181882</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 29 n. 2 (2022); 75-80</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/181882/186171</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/181882/183519</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/181986</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-23T18:11:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Factors associated with the clinical use of the International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health by physical therapists: an exploratory survey</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores associados ao uso clínico da Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde por fisioterapeutas: estudo survey exploratório</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dias, Fernanda Moura Vargas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Albuquerque, Bruna Emanoela Moraes de Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leopoldino, Amanda Aparecida Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gabler, Fernando Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nascimento, Lucas Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisioterapeutas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Capacitação Profissional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapists</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Professional Training</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To identify the contextual factors (i.e., personal, and work-related factors) associated with the clinical use of the International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF) by physical therapists. Method: A cross-sectional exploratory survey was carried out. The questionnaire Personal and environmental barriers for the implementation of the ICF by physical therapists was mailed to physical therapists living in Espírito Santo, Brazil. Logistic regression analysis was used to explore associations between personal and work-related characteristics with education, attitudes, beliefs, interest, and perception related to work resources for applying the ICF. Results: The response rate for most analyses was 46% (n= 59). Six characteristics explained 35% of the variance associated with interests, attitudes, and beliefs for the use of the ICF (X²= 16.6, p= 0.01). Three characteristics explained 24% of the variance associated with education for the use of ICF (X²= 8.9, p= 0.03). Three characteristics explained 61% of the variance associated with the perception of support and availability of resources for the use of the ICF (X²= 30.5, p&amp;lt;0.01). The most cited barrier was difficulty in applying the ICF for assessments of patients (62%). Conclusions: Physical therapists have positive attitudes towards the use of ICF, but most respondents did not receive satisfactory academic training and reported insufficient self-efficacy for using ICF in clinical practice. The adoption of an organizational infrastructure that endorses the clinical use of the ICF in association with an updated and continued education is required.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Identificar os fatores contextuais (i.e., fatores pessoais e fatores relacionados ao trabalho) associados ao uso clínico da Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde (CIF) por fisioterapeutas. Métodos: Foi realizado um estudo exploratório do tipo survey. O questionário Barreiras pessoais e ambientais para implementação da CIF por fisioterapeutas” foi enviado aos fisioterapeutas do Espírito Santo, Brasil. Análise de regressão logística foi usada para explorar associações entre características pessoais e organizacionais com educação, atitudes, crenças, interesses, percepção de suporte e disponibilidade de recursos no ambiente de trabalho para uso da CIF na prática clínica.&#160; Resultados: A taxa de resposta para a maioria das análises foi 46% (n= 59). Seis características explicaram 35% da variação associada a interesses, atitudes e crenças para o uso da CIF (X²= 16.6, p= 0.01). Três características explicaram 24% da variação associada à educação para o uso da CIF (X²= 8.9, p= 0.03). Três características explicaram 61% da variação associada à percepção de suporte e disponibilidade de recursos para o uso da CIF (X²= 30.5, p&amp;lt;0.01). A barreira mais citada foi dificuldade ao aplicar a CIF para avaliar pacientes (62%). Conclusão: Os fisioterapeutas possuem atitudes positivas em relação ao uso da CIF, mas a grande maioria não recebeu formação acadêmica adequada e reporta autoeficácia insuficiente para seu uso na prática clínica. É necessária a adoção de uma infraestrutura organizacional que endosse o uso clínico da CIF alinhada à modificação nos currículos de formação e capacitação continuada.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/181986</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i1a181986</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 1 (2021); 36-42</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/181986/171811</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/182017</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-23T18:11:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Análise da postura, mobilidade e força da coluna vertebral em indivíduos saudáveis com e sem discinese escapular</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Analysis of the spine posture, mobility and strength in healthy individuals with and without scapular dyskinesis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nascimento, Ruthe de Góes Xavier do</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Maciel, Nícia Farias Braga</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Liziane Mafra Vale de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Thaís Brazão Siqueira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Andrade, Sandra Cristina de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sousa, Catarina de Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Shoulder Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Scapula</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Posture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor de Ombro</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Escápula</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Postura</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Spine posture, mobility and strength can be associated with changes in scapular movement and shoulder pain. However, these aspects have not been assessed in healthy individuals with scapular dyskinesis without shoulder and/or back pain. Objective: To analyze spine posture, mobility and strength in healthy individuals with and without scapular dyskinesis. Method: Cross-sectional study, fifty-two college-aged individuals were divided into two groups, according to scapular dyskinesis testing: a group without scapular dyskinesis (n= 19; age= 22.95±2.86 years; BMI= 22.97±3.12 kg/m²; 10 males) and another with scapular dyskinesis (n= 33; age= 22.06±2.73 years; BMI= 22.14±3.22 kg/m²; 10 males). Posture of the head and shoulders was analyzed from photographs by a postural assessment software (PAS/SAPO). Thoracic kyphosis and range of motion of the cervical and thoracolumbar spine were measured by a digital inclinometer, and the strength of the cervical and thoracolumbar spine muscles by a hand-held dynamometer. Intergroup comparison for all the variables was conducted using analysis of variance (one-way ANOVA), considering p≤0.05 as significant. Results: No intergroup difference was found for spine posture (p= 0.18-0.99), mobility (p= 0.23-0.96) and strength (p= 0.42-0.99). Conclusion: Spine posture, mobility and strength do not differ between healthy individuals with and without scapular dyskinesis. The outcomes suggest that scapular dyskinesis may be related to interpersonal variations. Future prospective studies be conducted in order to verify if these variables can change and influence the development of shoulder pain. &#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A postura, mobilidade e força da coluna&#160; podem&#160; estar associadas com mudanças no movimento da escápula e dor no ombro. Objetivo: Analisar a postura da coluna vertebral, mobilidade e força em indivíduos saudáveis com e sem discinese escapular. Método: Estudo transversal com cinquenta e dois indivíduos em idade universitária foram divididos em dois grupos, de acordo com o teste de discinese escapular: um grupo sem discinese escapular (n= 19; idade= 22,95±2,86 anos; IMC= 22,97±3,12 kg/m²; 10 masculino) e outro com discinese escapular (n= 33; idade= 22,06±2,73 anos; IMC= 22,14±3,22 kg/m²; 10 masculino). A postura da cabeça e dos ombros foi analisada a partir de fotografias por um software de avaliação postural (PAS/SAPO). A cifose torácica e a amplitude de movimento da coluna cervical e torácica foram medidas por um inclinômetro digital, e a força dos músculos cervical e torác lombar por um dinamômetro portátil. A comparação intergrupo para todas as variáveis foi realizada utilizando-se a análise de variância (ANOVA unidirecional), considerando p≤0,05 como significativa. Resultados: Não foi encontrada diferença entre grupos postura (p= 0,18-0,99), mobilidade (p= 0,23-0,96) e força da coluna (p= 0,42-0,99). Conclusão: Postura, mobilidade e força da coluna vertebral não diferem entre indivíduos saudáveis com e sem discinese escapular. Os resultados sugerem que a discinese escapular pode estar relacionada a variações interpessoais. Estudos prospectivos futuros devem ser conduzidos afim de verificar&#160; se essas variáveis podem modificar e influenciar o desenvolvimento da dor no ombro.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/182017</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i1a182017</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 1 (2021); 7-14</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/182017/171808</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/182437</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-15T17:11:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Treinamento com realidade virtual não imersiva é efetivo na melhora da funcionalidade de idosos institucionalizados e uma opção de atividade física segura nos momentos de restrição: um estudo piloto</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Non-immersive Virtual Reality training is effective in improving the functionality of institutionalized elderly and an option for safe physical activity in times of restriction: a pilot study</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Diene Gomes Colvara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Myskiw, Jociane de Carvalho</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bós, Ângelo José Gonçalves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Vanice Hohemberge de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Perpétuo, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Patrícia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Realidade Virtual</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Instituição de Longa Permanência para Idosos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividade Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Isolamento Social</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Virtual Reality</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Homes for the Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Social Isolation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O envelhecimento é um processo dinâmico e progressivo que proporciona a diminuição gradual da capacidade funcional, aumentando a dependência dos idosos e culminando, muitas vezes, na sua institucionalização. Neste contexto, a Realidade Virtual Não Imersiva (RVNI) vem se mostrando uma ferramenta segura e efetiva para estimular a funcionalidade em idosos, inclusive diante da situação de distanciamento social que vivemos atualmente. Objetivo: Avaliar, preliminarmente, o efeito do treinamento com jogos de RVNI sobre a funcionalidade de idosos institucionalizados. Método: Estudo intervencional randomizado, com amostra composta por 17 idosos de quaisquer gêneros (idade 87 anos ±5,4 anos), residentes em uma instituição de Porto Alegre, divididos em dois grupos: Grupo Treinamento (GT) e Grupo Controle (GC). Foram avaliadas a escala de independência funcional (MIF) e a circunferência da panturrilha e do braço, bem como foram realizados o teste de Força de Preensão Palmar (FPP) e o Timed Get Up and Go (TUG). O protocolo de intervenção teve duração de 8 semanas, com duas sessões semanais de 30 minutos. Resultados: Os grupos demostraram ser homogêneos em relação ao gênero e idade. O GT apresentou melhora significante em 4 das 5 variáveis analisadas, já o GC apenas no teste de FPP.&#160; O GT no FPP apresentou uma diferença estatisticamente significativa de 21,1 ± 12,60 kg para 23,8 ± 13,51 kg (p&amp;lt;0,003). Conclusão: O presente estudo sugere que o treinamento com RVNI é efetivo na melhora da funcionalidade de idosos institucionalizados e pode ser uma opção de intervenção física segura, especialmente em momentos de restrição.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Aging is a dynamic and progressive process leading to reduction in functional capacity, dependence, and institutionalization in many cases. In this context, Non-Immersive Virtual Reality (RVNI) has been proposed as a safe and effective tool to stimulate functionality in the older adults, even in situations of social distance, similarly we are currently experiencing. Objective: To evaluate, preliminally, the effect of RVNI training on functional outcomes of institutionalized older adults. Method: Randomized interventional study, with a sample composed of 17 participants of any gender (age 87 ± 5.4 years), living in a home-institution for the aged in Porto Alegre, divided into two groups: Training Group (TG) and Control Group (CG). The functional independence scale (FIM) and the circumference of the calf and arm were evaluated, as well as the Palmar Grip Strength test (FPP) and the Timed Get Up and Go (TUG). The intervention protocol lasted 8 weeks, with two weekly sessions of 30 minutes. Results: Both groups were homogeneous in relation to gender and age. The TG showed a significant improvement in 4 of the 5 variables analyzed, whereas the CG only in the FPP test. The FPP showed a statistically significant difference from 21.1 ± 12.60 kg to 23.8 ± 13.51 kg (p &amp;lt;0.003) in the TG. Conclusion: The present study suggests RVNI training may be effective in improving functional outcomes in institutionalized older adults and should be considered as a safe physical intervention, especially in times of restriction.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/182437</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i2a182437</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 2 (2021); 86-91</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/182437/174312</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/182604</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-11-30T19:50:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Reproducibility of the test of 10 maximum repetitions in elderly</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Reprodutibilidade do teste de 10 repetições máximas em idosas</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Vieira, Elciana de Paiva Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Deserto, Abílio Douglas Valadares</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alves Júnior, Edmundo Drummond</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gurgel, Jonas Lírio</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Treino de Resistência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reprodutibilidade dos Testes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idosos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Endurance Training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Reproducibility of Results</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Pouco se sabe sobre o número de sessões necessárias para estabilização da carga máxima em 10 repetições em idosos não treinados. Objetivo: Verificar a reprodutibilidade do teste de 10 RM em mulheres com mais de 60 anos que não apresentam experiência prévia com treinamento de força. Método: Vinte e duas idosas (67,73 ± 5,43 anos) participantes somente da ginástica do programa Prev Quedas realizaram as sessões de teste-reteste de 10 RM em quatro exercícios: cadeira extensora, tríceps no pulley, mesa flexora e rosca direta bíceps. O programa Prev Quedas é um programa de extensão que oferece atividades físicas ao público de todas as idades de forma gratuita visando contribuir para prevenção de quedas. Foram utilizados os testes de ANOVA unidirecional com post hoc de Bonferroni, plotagem de Bland-Altman e Coeficiente de Correlação Intraclasse (CCI) com intervalo de confiança de 95%. Resultados: Os níveis de reprodutibilidade foram excelentes em todos os exercícios variando de 0,83 a 0,95 não havendo diferença significativa entre as sessões. A concordância entre as sessões teste-reteste foi classificada como boa para todos os exercícios. A literatura apresenta uma carência com relação à reprodutibilidade dos testes de 10 RM, principalmente para idosos. Porém, os dados de reprodutibilidade do presente estudo concordam com aqueles referentes aos testes de 1 RM aplicados em adultos jovens. Conclusão: Com base nos achados apresentados, parece haver necessidade da realização de 2 sessões de avaliação para estabilização da carga em 10 repetições máximas para idosas não treinadas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Little is known about the number of sessions required to stabilize the maximum load in 10 repetitions in untrained older adults. Objective: The objective of the study was to verify the reproducibility of the 10 MR test in women over 60 years of age who have no previous experience with strength training. Method: Twenty-two elderly women (67.73 ± 5.43 years) participating only in the Prev Quedas gymnastics program performed the 10 MR test-retest sessions in four exercises: extension chair, triceps in the pulley, flexor table, and biceps curl. The Prev Quedas program is an extension program that offers physical activities to the public of all ages free of charge to contribute to the prevention of falls. One-way ANOVA tests with Bonferroni post hoc, Bland-Altman plot, and Intraclass Correlation Coefficient (ICC) with a 95% confidence interval were used. Results: Reproducibility levels were excellent in all exercises, varying from 0.83 to 0.95, with no significant difference between sessions. The agreement between the test-retest sessions was classified as good for all exercises. The literature shows a lack regarding the reproducibility of the 10 MR tests, mainly for the elderly. However, the reproducibility data of the present study agree with those referring to the 1 MR tests applied to young adults. Conclusion: Based on the findings presented, there seems to be a need for 2 evaluation sessions to stabilize the load in 10 maximum repetitions for untrained elderly women.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-09-27</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/182604</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v29i3a182604</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 29 n. 3 (2022); 184-189</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/182604/186956</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/182740</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-01T13:27:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effects of aquatic aerobic training on an individual's cognition after traumatic brain injury: a case study</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeitos do treino aeróbico aquático sobre a cognição de um indivíduo após traumatismo crânio encefálico: estudo de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Castro, Caio Roberto Aparecido Paschoal</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sousa, Cristiane Dias dos Anjos de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Poletti, Andreia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Shimano, Suraya Gomes Novais</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Braga, Douglas Martins</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lesões Encefálicas Traumáticas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hidroterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Treino Aeróbico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cognição</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Brain Injuries, Traumatic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hydrotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Endurance Training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cognition</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Verificar a interferência do exercício aeróbico realizado no ambiente aquático na cognição de um indivíduo com Traumatismo Crânio Encefálico (TCE). Método: Trata-se de um estudo de caso experimental realizado no Setor de Fisioterapia Aquática da AACD, após a aprovação pelo CEP da instituição. Participou do estudo um indivíduo do sexo masculino, de 31 anos, que sofreu um TCE há quase de 12 meses da data da avaliação. Na anamnese, o indivíduo não relatou hidrofobia e, ao exame físico, o indivíduo não apresentou dor ou disfunções que comprometessem a realização dos exercícios do protocolo. Comprometeu-se a não realizar outra atividade física durante a realização do estudo. Foi submetido à avaliação neuropsicológica detalhada antes e após a intervenção de um protocolo de treino aeróbico aquático. O protocolo foi constituído de 12 sessões de 45 minutos, uma vez por semana, de treino aeróbico em uma bicicleta subaquática com acompanhamento de um fisioterapeuta. A temperatura da água foi de 33°C e imersão ao nível do processo xifóide. O monitoramento da intensidade do treino foi realizado através da frequência cardíaca (FC) e a FC alvo foi estipulada pela fórmula de Karvonenn. Resultados:&#160; O participante melhorou a pontuação nos testes de funções intelectuais, processos atencionais e velocidade de processamento de informações, habilidades viso espaciais, linguagem, raciocínio lógico, cálculo mental, raciocínio abstrato. Conclusão: O exercício aeróbico aquático interferiu positivamente nas funções cognitivas de um indivíduo com sequelas de um TCE.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To verify the interference of aerobic aquatic exercise performed in the cognition of an individual with Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI). Method: This is experimental case study occured in the Aquatic Physiotherapy Sector of the AACD. It was aprroved by the institution's Research Ethics Committee, protocol number 3,171,742. A 31-year-old male who underwent a TBI (almost 12 months from the evaluation date) participated in the study. The participant did not report hydrophobia and, on physical assessment, he did not present pain or dysfunctions that compromised his physical performance. He undertook not to perform another physical activity during the study. A neuropsychological evaluation was carried out before and after the intervention. The protocol consisted of 12 sessions of 45 minutes, once a week, aerobic training on an underwater bike with a physiotherapist monitoring. The water temperature was 33°C and immersion at the level of the xifoid process. The training intensity monitoring was performed through heart rate (HR) and target HR was stipulated by Karvonenn formula. Results: The participant improved the score in the tests of intellectual functions, intentional processes and speed of information processing, spatial vision skills, language, logical reasoning, mental calculus, abstract reasoning. Conclusion: Aquatic aerobic exercise positively interfered with the cognitive functions of an individual with sequelae of an TBI.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/182740</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i3a182740</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 3 (2021); 201-206</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/182740/176473</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/183118</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-15T17:11:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of peripheral muscle strength alterations of elderlies admitted at an ICU</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da diferença na força muscular periférica entre admissão e alta em idosos hospitalizados</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva Junior, Mario Cezar Macedo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Marilucia Reis dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jesus, Sergio Luis Figueredo de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Mychelle Regina Melo de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rocha, Júlio David Nascimento da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Neves, Janmille de Sá</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Anjos, Jorge Luis Motta dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martinez, Bruno Prata</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Old Age Assistance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hospitalization</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Assistência a Idosos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hospitalização</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A mensuração da força muscular periférica (FMP) no ambiente hospitalar direciona a reabilitação e contribui para predição da mortalidade dos idosos. Objetivo: Avaliar a variação da força muscular ao longo da internação em idosos hospitalizados. Métodos: Trata-se de um estudo longitudinal prospectivo, com idosos estáveis das enfermarias e UTI´s de um hospital de grande porte da rede pública estadual, em Salvador-BA. Foram realizadas 3 medidas de dinamometria de preensão palmar, sendo considerado para análise o maior valor.&#160; Outras variáveis coletadas foram a função cognitiva (MEEM) e índice de comorbidades de Charlson (ICC). Para comparação da variação da FPP entre a admissão e alta realizado o teste T de Student. Resultados: A amostra foi composta por 80 idosos com média de idade 68,1 ± 5,8 anos, majoritariamente do sexo masculino (77.5%) e com perfil cirúrgico (92,5%). Na comparação entre a FPP na admissão e alta não foram encontradas diferenças significativas (29,8±7,5 kgf; 30,0±7,8 kgf; valor de p= 0,698). Entretanto, observou-se formas distintas de variação ao longo da internação, sendo que 36,2% dos pacientes apresentaram aumento da FPP(27,8 ± 9,3 kgf para 32,3 ± 9,6 kgf), enquanto que 38,7% tiveram perda da FPP(30,9 ± 6,7 kgf para 26,8 ± 6,9 kgf) entre a admissão e a alta. Conclusão: Existem diferentes trajetórias da FMP desde admissão até a alta em idosos hospitalizados. Compreender quais são os fatores que favorecem essas variações é algo importante para o processo de reabilitação.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The measurement of peripheral muscle strength in the hospital environment directs rehabilitation and contributes to predicting mortality in the elderly. Objective: To evaluate the variation of muscle strength during hospitalization in hospitalized elderly. Methods: This is a retrospective longitudinal study with stable elderly admitted at an ICU of a large public hospital in Salvador, Bahia State, Brazil. Three measurements of handgrip strength (HGS) were performed, and the highest value was considered for analysis. Other variables collected were cognitive function (MMSE) and Charlson's comorbidity index (CCI). Student T-test was used to test the variation of HGS between admission and discharge. Results: The sample consisted of 80 elderlies with an average age of 68.1 ± 5.8 years, mostly male (77.5%) and with surgical profiles (92.5%). In the comparison between HGS at admission and discharge, no significant differences were found (29.8 ± 7.5 kgf; 30.0 ± 7.8 kgf; p-value= 0.698). However, different forms of variation were observed 36.2% of participants had an increase in HGS (27.8 ± 9.3 kgf to 32.3 ± 9.6 kgf), whereas 38, 7% had a loss of HGS (30.9 ± 6.7 kgf to 26.8 ± 6.9 kgf) between admission and discharge. Conclusion: There are different trajectories in HGS from admission to discharge in hospitalized elderly, and understanding the factors that favor these variations is important for the rehabilitation process.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/183118</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i2a183118</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 2 (2021); 73-77</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/183118/174310</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/183160</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-15T17:11:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Responsividade de dois instrumentos de avaliação do equilíbrio em pacientes pós-AVE trombolisado na fase aguda</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Responsiveness of two instruments for assessing balance in patients after thrombolyzed stroke in the acute phase</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Bernardes, Lemuel Victor da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Maso, Iara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Marilucia Reis dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Alana das Mercês</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Francisco Robson</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Motta dos Anjos, Jorge Luís</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Postural Balance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Postural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Escala de Equilíbrio de Berg (EEB) e a Escala de Avaliação Postural para Pacientes com Sequelas de AVE (EAPA) são ferramentas de medida úteis e válidas na prática clínica. Objetivo: Comparar a responsividade da EEB e EAPA na avaliação do equilíbrio de indivíduos pós-AVE trombolisado na fase aguda. Métodos: Trata-se de um estudo longitudinal analítico, realizado em uma Unidade de AVC, no qual foram aplicados a EEB e a EAPA nas primeiras 24 horas e no sétimo dia de internamento ou no dia da alta. Para determinação da responsividade adotou-se o Índice de Tamanho de Efeito (TE) e a Média de Resposta Padronizada (MRP), sendo calculados efeito solo e teto de ambas as escalas. Resultados: 44 pacientes, predominantemente do sexo masculino, média de idade 60 (±13) anos e mediana NIHSS 3,5 [1-6]. Ambos os instrumentos de avaliação detectaram melhora do equilíbrio. As escalas apresentaram TE pequeno, sendo o TE da EEB igual a 0,2 e o da EAPA igual a 0,3. A MRP foi moderada para as duas escalas, sendo a MRP da EEB igual a 0,7 e da EAPA igual a 0,6. A EAPA apresentou efeito solo menor do que a EEB nas primeiras 24 horas, enquanto no sétimo dia, a EEB apresentou efeito teto menor. Conclusão: A EAPA pode ser uma melhor opção para avaliação do equilíbrio em pacientes pós-AVE nas primeiras 24 horas, à medida em que a EEB pode ser uma melhor escolha para avaliação a partir do sétimo dia nessa população específica.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The Berg Balance Scale (BBS) and Postural Assessment for Stroke Scale (PASS) are useful and valid measurement tools in clinical practice. Objective: To compare the responsiveness of BBS and PASS in assessing the balance of post-stroke thrombolyzed individuals in the acute phase. Methods: This is a longitudinal analytical study, conducted in a Stroke Unit, in which BSS and PASS were applied in the first 24 hours and on the seventh day of hospitalization or on the day of discharge. To determine responsiveness, the Effect Size Index (ES) and the Standardized Response Mean (SRM) were adopted, and the soil and ceiling effect of both scales were also calculated. Results: 44 patients, predominantly male, mean age 60 (±13) years and median NIHSS 3.5 [1-6]. Bothassessment instruments detected improved balance. Both scales presented small ES, with the BBS ES being equal to 0.2 and PASS equal to 0.3. The SRM was moderate for both scales, with the SRM of the BBS equal to 0.7 and the PASS equal to 0.6. The PASS had a lower soil effect than BBS in the first 24 hours, and on the seventh day, BBS had a lower ceiling effect. Conclusion: PASS can be a best option for balance assessment in patients post-stroke in the first 24 hours, while BBS may be a better choice for evaluation from the seventh post-stroke in this specific population.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-07-23</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/183160</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i2a183160</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 2 (2021); 111-115</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/183160/174326</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/183314</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-01T13:27:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O uso da terapia laser no tratamento da dor crônica difusa: uma revisão sistemática</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Laser therapy in the treatment of chronic multi-site pain: a systematic review</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Nicole Pantojo da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moretti, Mariana Pedrazzi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Igor Pereira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Aranha, Ana Lucia Batista</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Beloni, Paola Vieira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Maciel, Marcella Ferreira Bento</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cecatto, Rebeca Boltes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia a Laser</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fototerapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor Crônica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Laser Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Phototherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Chronic Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Laser therapies are noninvasive techniques with painless, safe, and low-cost therapeutic procedures for chronic pain. No systematic review has evaluated the effects of laser in the treatment of multi-site chronic pain. Objective: To evaluate the effects of laser in the treatment of generalized multi-site chronic pain. Methods: This pioneering study presents a PRISMA systematic review protocol designed to up-to-date the current literature on Laser Therapy in patients with chronic multi-site pain from all founded etiologies. This protocol was registered on the PROSPERO website before data extraction (registration no. CRD42019152345). Results: About 1391 articles met the inclusion criteria and 15 studies were selected for the data extraction. We found 12 studies in patients with fibromyalgia, 01 study about myofascial pain syndrome, 01 study about rheumatoid arthritis and 01 study about diabetic sensorimotor polyneuropathy. Homogeneity was not found in the Laser protocols, clinical conditions studied, the evaluation methods, or in the controlled groups but together studies suggested that Laser could have benefits in the treatment of pain severity, quality of life, fatigue, stiffness, depression, and anxiety compared to placebo and other therapies for fibromyalgia and for pain at Rheumatoid Arthritis and Diabetic Polyneuropathy. Conclusion: Laser therapy plus the standardized exercise or amitriptilyne provided no extra advantage in the relief of symptoms at fibromyalgia. For TMD myofascial pain no benefits were founded. Studies showed numerous different points and locations of light application but none of the selected studies used spinal stimulation as the Laser application site.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">As terapias a laser são técnicas não invasivas, indolores, seguras e de baixo custo e de utilidade no tratamento da dor crônica. Nenhuma revisão sistemática avaliou os efeitos do laser no tratamento da dor crônica em múltiplos locais simultâneos. Objetivo: Avaliar os efeitos do laser no tratamento da dor crônica multifocal generalizada. Métodos: Revisão sistemática PRISMA sobre o uso do laser em pacientes com dor crônica multifocal de diversas etiologias. Este protocolo foi registrado no site PROSPERO antes da extração dos dados (registro nº. CRD42019152345). Resultados:&#160; 1.391 artigos atenderam aos critérios de inclusão e 15 estudos foram selecionados para a extração de dados, sendo 12 estudos em pacientes com fibromialgia, 01 estudo sobre síndrome dolorosa miofascial, 01 estudo sobre artrite reumatoide e 01 estudo sobre polineuropatia sensório-motora diabética. Não foi encontrada homogeneidade nos protocolos do laser, nos métodos de avaliação ou nos grupos controlados, mas em conjunto os estudos sugeriram que o laser poderia ter benefícios no tratamento da intensidade da dor, qualidade de vida, fadiga, rigidez, depressão e ansiedade em comparação com placebo e outras terapias para fibromialgia e para dor na artrite reumatóide e polineuropatia diabética. A terapia a laser mais o exercício padronizado ou amitriptilina não proporcionou nenhuma vantagem extra no alívio dos sintomas da fibromialgia. Para dor miofascial DTM, nenhum benefício foi encontrado. Conclusão: Os estudos mostraram vários pontos e locais diferentes de aplicação de luz, mas nenhum dos estudos selecionados usou a estimulação espinhal como local de aplicação do laser.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/183314</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i3a183314</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 3 (2021); 173-183</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/183314/176469</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/183523</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-01T13:27:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Development of an evaluation instrument for the Pilates method based on the International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Desenvolvimento de um instrumento de avaliação para o método Pilates baseado na Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Andréa Costa de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barbosa, Yanna Menezes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Tiago Pinheiro Vaz de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alves, Maria de Carvalho Dantas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Farias Neto, Jader Pereira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Araújo, Karina Conceição Gomes Machado de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise Movement Techniques</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy Modalities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Técnicas de Exercício e de Movimento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Modalidades de Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">There is a lack of scientific evidence on validated and standardized evaluation instruments applied to Pilates. Given the importance of an individualized and holistic analysis of each patient/client for a better application of the method, it is necessary to build instruments that have a bio-psychosocial approach. Objective:&#160;To&#160;develop an evaluation instrument for Pilates, based on the International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF). Methods: The research was carried out in four stages. This is a survey of information about the assessment in the Pilates method, association of information with ICF categories, Delphi study, construction of the instrument. The information was obtained through a scoping review and interviews with physical therapists who work with Pilates. For the construction of the instrument, the information obtained was independently linked to the ICF categories by two researchers, and in case of disagreement a third party would judge the most pertinent. Next, a Delphi study was carried out to select the most relevant categories to compose the instrument; finally, the construction of the instrument by three researchers with knowledge about Pilates and ICF. Results: The instrument was made up of 49 ICF categories, distributed among 33 questions, being ten of body functions, two of body structures, 16 of activity and participation, and five of environmental factors.&#160;Conclusion: The study allowed the construction of an instrument that aims to facilitate the understanding of the patient's health status from an evaluation already performed in each service and, at the end, will provide a common language.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Há uma escassez em evidências científicas acerca de instrumentos de avaliação validados e padronizados aplicados ao Pilates. Diante da importância de uma análise individualizada e holística de cada paciente/cliente para melhor aplicação do método, faz-se necessário a construção de instrumentos que possuam uma abordagem biopsicossocial. Objetivo: Desenvolver um instrumento de avaliação para o Pilates, baseado na da Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde (CIF). Métodos: A pesquisa foi realizada em quatro etapas. Levantamentos de informações sobre a avaliação no método Pilates, associação das informações com categorias da CIF, estudo Delphi, construção do instrumento. As informações foram obtidas por meio de um a scoping review e entrevistas com fisioterapeutas que trabalham com o Pilates, para construção as informações obtidas foram vinculadas com as categorias da CIF por dois pesquisadores de forma independente, em caso de discordância um terceiro julgaria a mais pertinente. Em seguida, foi realizado um estudo Delphi, para selecionar as categorias mais relevantes para compor o instrumento. Por fim, a construção do instrumento por três pesquisadores com conhecimento em Pilates e CIF. Resultados: O instrumento foi constituído por 49 categorias da CIF, distribuídas em 33 questões, sendo, 10 de funções do corpo, duas de estruturas do corpo, 16 de atividade e participação e, cinco dos fatores ambientais. Conclusão: O estudo possibilitou a construção de um instrumento que visa facilitar a compreensão do estado de saúde do paciente a partir de uma avaliação já realizada em cada serviço e, ao final será proporcionado uma linguagem comum.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/183523</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i3a183523</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 3 (2021); 156-166</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/183523/177435</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/183523/176467</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/184308</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-23T18:11:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Attitudinal barriers from the perspective of people with physical disabilities</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação das atitudes frente a incapacidades na perspectiva de pessoas com deficiências físicas</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cabral, Flávia Canale</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sugawara, Andre Tadeu</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imamura, Marta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pessoas com Deficiência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atitude</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Barreiras ao Acesso aos Cuidados de Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Inquéritos e Questionários</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disabled Persons</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Attitude</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Barriers to Access of Health Services</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Surveys and Questionnaires</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To quantify attitudes toward disabilities, perceived by persons with disabilities (PWDs) treated at a university hospital in Brazil, as well as to determine whether PWD-perceived attitudinal barriers correlate with various factors. Methods This was a cross-sectional, observational study of PWDs who completed the Attitudes to Disability Scale for persons with physical disabilities (ADS-D), which quantifies the perceived attitudinal barrier, the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale and the Functional Independence Measure (FIM). The data were correlated with sex, income, depression, FIM score, type of disability and time since the onset of disability. Results: We evaluated 68 patients - 50.0% with a spinal cord injury, 38.2% with one or more amputated limbs and 11.8% with hemiplegia - of whom 66.2% were male, with a mean age of 39.33 ± 12.89 years, a mean of 10.95 ± 4.25 years of schooling, a median time since the onset of disability of 20.5 months (range, 10.5–33.5 months) and a median FIM score of 110.5 (range, 94–116.5). Of the 68 patients, 55.9% perceived their income to be below the national average, and depression was observed in 11.76%. The mean ADS-D total score (61.29 ± 8.75) did not correlate with sex, functionality, type of disability or time since the onset of disability. The perceived magnitude of the attitudinal barrier correlated with income (β-coefficient: −3.91; p = 0.001) and depression (β = −1.74; p &amp;lt; 0.0001). Conclusion: Attitudinal barriers are influenced by income as a facilitator of inclusion and by depression as a barrier to inclusion.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Quantificar as atitudes frente a incapacidades, percebidas pelas pessoas com deficiências (PCDs) atendidas em hospital universitário no Brasil, assim como determinar se as barreiras atitudinais percebidas se correlacionam com outros fatores. Métodos: Este é um estudo observacional transversal, onde a amostra de PCDs completou a Escala de Atitudes Frente a Incapacidades para Pessoas com Incapacidades Físicas (ADS-D), que quantifica a barreira atitudinal percebida, a Escala Hospitalar de Ansiedade e Depressão e a Medida de Independência Funcional (MIF). Os dados foram correlacionados com sexo, renda, depressão, valor da MIF, tipo de deficiência e tempo de deficiência. Resultados: Foram avaliados 68 pacientes – 50,0% com lesão medular, 38,2% com amputações e 11,8% com hemiplegia – dos quais 66,2% eram do sexo masculino, com média de idade de 39,33 (±12,89) anos, média de 10,95 (±4,25) anos de estudo, mediana de 20,5 meses (intervalo de 10,5-33,5 meses) de tempo de deficiência, mediana de valor da MIF de 110,5 (intervalo de 94-116,5). Dos 68 pacientes, 55,9% declararam renda abaixo da média nacional e depressão foi observada em 11,76%. A média da ADS-D total (61,29 ± 8,75) não foi associada ao sexo, nível funcional, tipo ou tempo de deficiência. Renda (β-coefficient: -3,91; p: 0,001) e sintomas depressivos (β = -1,74; p &amp;lt; 0,0001) se correlacionaram com a magnitude da barreira atitudinal percebida. Conclusão: As barreiras atitudinais são influenciadas pela renda, como facilitador de inclusão, e pela depressão, como entrave à inclusão.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/184308</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i1a184308</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 1 (2021); 1-6</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/184308/171798</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/184547</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-15T17:11:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Functional mobility in Parkinson’s disease: associations with motor and non-motor symptoms</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Mobilidade funcional em indivíduos com doença de Parkinson: associações com alterações motoras e não motoras</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Scalzo, Paula Luciana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Faria-Fortini, Iza de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pereira, Jéssica Ramos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Azevedo, Lílian Viana dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cruz, Ana Carolina de Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Parkinson Disease</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Mobility Limitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fatigue</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Depression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doença de Parkinson</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Limitação da Mobilidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fadiga</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Depressão</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Functional mobility (FM) is the ability of people to move in different environments, including at home, at work, and in the community, in order to perform functional activities or tasks, independently and safely. Objective: The aim of the present study was to investigate which motor and/or non-motor symptoms (severity of the motor symptoms, depressive symptoms, and fatigue) have the greatest impact on FM assessed by Modified Parkinson Activity Scale (mPAS) in individuals with Parkinson’s disease (PD). Method: The outcome of interest was FM assessed by mPAS, which includes 14 activities covering three domains (chair transfers, gait akinesia, and bed mobility). Unified Parkinson’s Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) Part III, Beck Depression Inventory (BDI), and Parkinson’s Disease Fatigue Scale-16 (PFS-16) were used. Results: Forty-four individuals (age: 65±11 years) with PD (PD duration: 7±4 years) were eligible to take part in this cross-sectional, exploratory study. The motor symptoms alone explained 36% (F= 17.85, p&amp;lt;0.001) of the variance in the FM scores. When depressive symptoms were included in the model, the explained variance increased to 45% (F= 12.77, p&amp;lt;0.001). This indicated that individuals who had lower motor and depressive symptoms were less likely to have limitations in FM. Conclusion: The findings of the present study demonstrated that motor symptoms were the best potential predictor of FM in individuals with PD, according to mPAS scores. Additionally, the presence of depressive symptoms should not be overlooked.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Mobilidade funcional (MF) é a capacidade das pessoas de se movimentarem em diferentes ambientes, incluindo em casa, no trabalho e na comunidade, a fim de realizar atividades ou tarefas funcionais, de forma independente e segura. Objetivo: Investigar quais variáveis (gravidade das alterações motoras, sintomas depressivos e fadiga) têm maior impacto na MF avaliada por meio da Escala Modificada de Atividade em Parkinson (mPAS) em indivíduos com doença de Parkinson (DP). Método: A MF avaliada por meio da mPAS, que inclui 14 atividades em três domínios (transferências de cadeira, acinesia da marcha, mobilidade na cama). Escala Unificada de Avaliação da Doença de Parkinson (UPDRS) Parte III, Inventário de Depressão de Beck (BDI) e Escala de Fadiga da Doença de Parkinson-16 (PFS-16) foram usados. Resultados: 45 indivíduos (idade: 65 ± 11 anos) com DP (duração do DP: 7 ± 4 anos) participaram deste estudo transversal e exploratório. A gravidade das alterações motoras explicou 36% (F= 17,85, p &amp;lt;0,001) da variância nos escores de MF. Quando os sintomas depressivos foram incluídos no modelo, a variância explicada aumentou para 45% (F= 12,77, p &amp;lt;0,001). Isso indicou que indivíduos com menor gravidade das alterações motoras e sintomas depressivos eram menos propensos a ter limitações na MF. Conclusão: As alterações motoras foram o principal preditor da MF em indivíduos com DP, de acordo com os escores da mPAS. Além disso, a presença de sintomas depressivos não deve ser negligenciada.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/184547</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i2a184547</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 2 (2021); 105-110</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/184547/174325</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/184634</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-23T18:11:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effects of physical training and dual task on ptophobia and balance in the elderly</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeitos do treinamento físico e de dupla tarefa na ptophobia e no equilíbrio de idosos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Aguiar, Renan Nunes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barcellos, Carolina Milhim</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rocha Júnior, Luiz Duarte de Ulhôa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Daniel Vicentini de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nascimento, Lilian Cristina Gomes do</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidentes por Quedas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cognição</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício Físico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Accidental Falls</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cognition</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fear</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">As quedas ocasionam aos idosos diversas alterações na sua função biopsicossocial, podendo ocasionar o surgimento da ptophobia e declínio do equilíbrio, sendo necessários programas preventivos que ofereçam suporte para essa população. Objetivo: Este estudo comparou o efeito de dois protocolos de treinamentos em relação ao medo de quedas e o equilíbrio de idosos. Métodos: Foram selecionados 30 idosos que se enquadravam nos critérios de inclusão e não inclusão, os mesmos foram divididos aleatoriamente em três grupos (grupo de treinamento físico, dupla tarefa e controle) e tiveram como instrumento para a coleta de dados a Escala Internacional de Eficácia de Quedas (FES-I) e a Escala de Equilíbrio de Berg (EEB). Esses dados foram analisados pela ANOVA e pelo teste t-Student. Resultados: Todos os participantes foram do sexo feminino com média de idade de 67,4±6,69. Não se evidenciou diferenças significativas entre os grupos analisados tanto nos escores da FES-I como da EEB. Em relação a comparação entre os grupos de intervenções e grupo controle foram encontradas diferenças apenas nos escores da FES-I após às intervenções, possuindo p= 0,00. Na comparação entre os grupos, a FES-I e a EEB após as intervenções obtiveram escores significativos, ambas possuindo p= 0,00 e tamanho de efeito de 11,54 e 4,54, respectivamente. Conclusão: Observou-se que nos grupos que tiveram intervenções, o medo de quedas diminuiu em relação ao grupo que não recebeu nenhuma intervenção e o equilíbrio melhorou diante ambos protocolos, demonstrando que o exercício físico associado ou não à atividade cognitiva é benéfico aos idosos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Falls cause to the elderly several alterations in their biopsychosocial function, which may cause the appearance of ptophobia and decline in balance, thus requiring preventive programs that offer support to this population. Objective: This study compared the effect of the training protocols in relation to fear of falls and the balance of elderly. Methods: Thirty elderly people who met the inclusion and non-inclusion criteria were selected. They were randomly divided into three groups (physical training group, dual task and control group). The Falls Efficacy Scale - International (FES-I) and the Berg Balance Scale (BBS) were used as instruments for data collection. Data were analyzed by ANOVA and t-Student test. Results: All participants were female, with an average age of 67.4 ± 6.69. There were no significant differences between the groups analyzed in both FES-I and BBS scores. Regarding the comparison between the intervention groups and the control group, differences were found only in the FES-I scores after the interventions, with p= 0.00. In the comparison between the groups, FES-I and BBS after the interventions obtained significant scores, both having p= 0.00 and effect size of 11.54 and 4.54, respectively. Conclusion: In the groups that had interventions, the fear of falls decreased in relation to the group that did not receive any intervention, and the balance improved with both interventions, thus demonstrating that physical exercise associated or not with cognitive activity is beneficial to the elderly.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/184634</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i1a184634</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 1 (2021); 49-53</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/184634/171804</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/184634/171803</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/184746</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-04-01T15:27:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Cirurgias de amputação por causas externas realizadas em hospitais públicos de Santa Catarina, Brasil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Amputation surgeries due to external causes performed in public hospitals in Santa Catarina, Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Luz, Soraia Cristina Tonon da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sarmento, Tuane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Branco, Ruy Luiz Lorenzetti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Siqueira Ruy, Tayla</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Honório, Gesilani Júlia da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Kadine Bender dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Amputation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">External Causes</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hospitalization</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Information Systems</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Amputação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Causas Externas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hospitalização</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sistemas de Informação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Caracterizar o perfil das cirurgias de amputação de membros inferiores por causa externa, realizadas em hospitais públicos do estado de Santa Catarina. Método: Estudo descritivo, epidemiológico e de base hospitalar analisou as permissões de internação hospitalar (AIH) (N= 4158) no período de 2008-2014. Resultados: Houve predomínio da população masculina (79,1%), faixa etária entre 18 e 29 anos (17,7%). A forma de amputação mais incidente foi por lesão traumática parcial ou completa com envolvimento de um dedo. Os três municípios mais afetados foram Chapecó, Criciúma e Brusque. Houve uma diminuição no número de amputações principalmente nos últimos quatro anos. Apesar disso, as amputações são um problema de saúde pública reconhecido mundialmente. Conclusão: O acompanhamento epidemiológico por meio das AIH's se traduz como um indicador para monitorar e desencadear ações de melhoria da assistência especializada ao paciente amputado com vistas à prevenção, organização dos serviços e treinamento de equipes multiprofissionais.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: In order to characterize the profile of lower limb amputation surgeries by external cause, performed in public hospitals in the state of Santa Catarina. Method: This descriptive, epidemiological and hospital based study analyzed hospital admissionpermits (AIH) (N= 4158) in between 2008-2014. Results: There has been a prevalence of male population (79,1%), age group between 18 and 29 years (17,7%). The most incident form of amputation was by partial or complete traumatic injury with involvement of a finger. The three most affected counties were Chapecó, Criciúma and Brusque. There has been a decrease in the number of amputations mainly in the last four years. Conclusion: Despite this fact, amputations are a globally recognized public health problem. Epidemiological follow-up the AIH´s translates as an indicator to monitor and trigger improvement actions of specialized assistance to amputated patients with a view to prevention, organization of services, and training of multi professional teams.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-12-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/184746</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i4a184746</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 4 (2021); 280-284</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/184746/179808</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/184818</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-09-27T14:54:06Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effects of a warm-up-cool-down protocol on muscle flexibility</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeitos de um protocolo de aquecimento-alongamento-resfriamento sobre a flexibilidade muscular</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sanchez, Hugo Machado</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sousa, Cibele Cristhine Santos de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vieira, Naiara Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sanchez, Eliane Gouveia de Morais</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Gustavo Gerolami de Melo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hipertermia Induzida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Crioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Amplitude de Movimento Articular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercícios de Alongamento Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hyperthermia, Induced</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cryotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Range of Motion, Articular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Stretching Exercises</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Investigar os efeitos da associação entre alongamento e recursos termoterapêuticos sobre o ganho de flexibilidade e amplitude de movimento. Métodos: Este ensaio clínico, controlado, não randomizado e cego teve duração de três semanas, com duas sessões semanais e incluiu 27 indivíduos do sexo feminino, as quais compuseram tanto o grupo experimental quanto o controle, de forma que um de seus membros inferiores recebeu a intervenção terapêutica dos recursos termoterapêuticos e o membro oposto foi submetido apenas ao alongamento.&#160; A análise angular foi realizada através do software de avaliação postural Kinovera.&#160; Resultados: Os efeitos do alongamento associado ao calor prévio e resfriamento pós intervenção se mostraram mais eficazes comparado ao grupo controle pré-intervenção (p&amp;lt;0,000), grupo controle pós intervenção (p= 0,003) e grupo experimental pré-intervenção (p&amp;lt;0,000). Conclusão: A aplicação de calor prévio ao alongamento, seguido pelo emprego imediato de resfriamento propicia ganhos de flexibilidade muscular e amplitude de movimento maiores que o alongamento simples.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To investigate the effects between stretching and thermotherapeutics resources on gaining flexibility and range of motion. Methods: This controlled, non-randomized, blinded clinical trial lasted three weeks, with two weekly sessions and included 27 female individuals, who made up both the experimental and the control group, so one of their legs received therapeutic intervention from chemotherapeutic resources and the opposite one was submitted to stretching only. Angular analysis was performed using the Kinovera postural assessment software. Results: The effects of stretching associated with pre-intervention heat and post-intervention cooling were more effective compared to the pre-intervention control group (p&amp;lt;0.000), post-intervention control group (p= 0.003) and pre-intervention experimental group (p&amp;lt;0.000). Conclusion: The application of heat prior to stretching followed by immediate cooling provides gains in muscle flexibility and range of motion greater than simple stretching.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-06-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/184818</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v29i2a184818</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 29 n. 2 (2022); 124-128</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/184818/183536</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185059</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-15T17:11:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A idade e o índice de massa corporal estão relacionados com os critérios de diagnóstico de sarcopenia em mulheres idosas?</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Are the age and the body mass index related with sarcopenia diagnosis criteria in elderly women?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Korn, Rafaela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mello, Bárbara Antonacci de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Marilda Morais da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sali, Mauren da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Júnior, Yoshimasa Sagawa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Soares, Antonio Vinicius</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde do Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação Geriátrica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sarcopenia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health of the Elderly</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Geriatric Assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sarcopenia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O envelhecimento traz modificações na composição corporal do idoso, caracterizadas pela redução da massa muscular e densidade óssea, aumento da redistribuição de gordura corporal, e diminuição de massa corporal. Essas alterações estão associadas à falta de hábitos saudáveis, como exercício físico regular e boa alimentação, podendo levar a um provável diagnóstico de Sarcopenia. Objetivo: Observar a relação da idade e composição corporal de idosas comunitárias ativas e institucionalizadas com os critérios diagnósticos da Sarcopenia. Método: Foram selecionadas 132 idosas, com idade ≥70 anos, sem traços demenciais e/ou depressivos. Após a determinação do índice de massa corporal (IMC) foram classificadas em três grupos (n= 13 com baixo peso &amp;lt;22 kg/m2, n= 43 eutróficas de 22 a 27 kg/m2, e n= 76 com sobrepeso &amp;gt;27 kg/m2). Foram avaliados ainda, o índice de massa muscular total (IMMT) por equação preditiva, e a força de preensão manual (FPM) por dinamometria. Resultados: Foi observado que com o avançar da idade ocorre redução do IMC, assim como diminuição do IMMT e FPM no grupo baixo peso. Também houve uma correlação positiva muito forte entre o IMC e o IMMT no sobrepeso, mostrando que quanto maior o IMC, maior será o IMMT. Conclusão: Idade e IMC estão relacionados com os critérios diagnósticos da Sarcopenia. Assim, é de extrema importância a avaliação minuciosa da composição corporal, estado nutricional e da força muscular em idosos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Aging brings changes in the body composition of the elderly, characterized by reduced muscle mass and bone density, increased redistribution of body fat and decreased body mass. These changes are associated with the lack of healthy habits, such as regular exercise and good nutrition, and can lead to a probable diagnosis of sarcopenia. Objective: To evaluate the relationship between the age and body composition of active community-dwelling and institutionalized elderly women with the diagnostic criteria for sarcopenia. Method: 132 elderly women, aged ≥70 years, without dementia and/or depressive features were selected. After determining body mass index (BMI) they were classified into three groups (n= 13 underweight &amp;lt;22 kg/m2 n= 43 eutrophic from 22 to 27 kg/m2 and n= 76 overweight &amp;gt;27 kg/m2). Total muscle mass index (TMMI) by predictive equation, and handgrip strength (HGS) by dynamometry were also evaluated. Results: It was observed that with advancing age there is a reduction in BMI, as well as a decrease in TMMI and HGS in the underweight group. There was also a very strong positive correlation between the BMI and the TMMI in the overweight group, showing that the higher the BMI, the higher the TMMI. Conclusion: Age and BMI are related to the diagnostic criteria of sarcopenia. Thus, a thorough evaluation of body composition, nutritional status and muscle strength is extremely important in the elderly.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185059</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i2a185059</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 2 (2021); 121-125</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185059/174328</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185148</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-10-21T14:13:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Res.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">XXVII Brazilian Congress of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">XXVII Congresso Brasileiro de Medicina Física e Reabilitação</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fisiátrica, Acta</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical and Rehabilitation Medicine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Congress</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina Física e Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Anais de Congressos</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo da Associação Brasileira de Medicina Física e Reabilitação (ABMFR) é o de sempre promover eventos com responsabilidade.&#160;&#160;Na organização do XXVII Congresso Brasileiro de Medicina Física e Reabilitação e preocupados com a possibilidade de sofrermos uma baixa no nosso público de médicos, profissionais da saúde e seu corpo de palestrantes internacionais e nacionais, entendemos que deveríamos nos organizar em um novo formato, agora virtual. Nosso evento aconteceu de 7 a 10 abril de 2021, através da plataforma virtual. A Comissão Cientifica preparou a melhor programação, contemplando os diversos aspectos da reabilitação, envolvendo profissionais nacionais e internacionais renomados e atuantes na área de Reabilitação, composta por Médicos Fisiatras e de outras especialidades afins, Fisioterapeutas, Terapeutas Ocupacionais, Psicólogos, Assistentes Sociais. Eduardo de Melo Carvalho Rocha PresidenteAssociação Brasileira de Medicina Física e Reabilitação&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-04-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185148</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28iSupl.1a185148</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. Supl.1 (2021); 1-53</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185148/171359</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185247</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-23T18:11:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The Geriatric Depression Scale be used to track falls in community-dwelling older adults?</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A Escala de Depressão Geriátrica pode ser utilizada para rastrear quedas em idosos comunitários?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fontanela, Laís Coan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Larissa Franciny de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leopoldino, Amanda Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Danielewicz, Ana Lúcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Avelar, Núbia Carelli Pereira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidentes por Quedas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Depressão</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Accidental Falls</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Depression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fear</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Sintomas depressivos estão associados a ocorrência de quedas em idosos, portanto, torna-se importante definir pontos de corte diferenciados entre os sexos na Escala de Depressão Geriátrica Abreviada (GDS-15) que discriminem maior propensão a quedas, para identificar e implementar estratégias de reabilitação preventivas precoces. Objetivo: Determinar a acurácia da GDS-15, com valores diferenciados entre os sexos, para rastrear quedas em idosos comunitários e verificar a associação entre sintomas depressivos e quedas utilizando-se os pontos de corte propostos. Método: Estudo transversal, com amostra probabilística, incluindo 308 idosos comunitários. Considerou-se o histórico de quedas nos últimos 12 meses, classificado de forma dicotômica (sim ou não) como variável dependente e a avaliação dos sintomas depressivos através da GDS-15 como variável independente. Utilizou-se a Receiver Operating Characteristic Curve para analisar a sensibilidade e especificidade da GDS-15, e a Regressão Logística Multivariável para verificar a associação entre sintomas depressivos e quedas. Resultados: Os pontos de corte que melhor discriminaram quedas na GDS foram ≥4 pontos para mulheres [AUC:0,61 (IC95%: 0,54;0,69)] e ≥3 pontos para homens [AUC:0,65 (IC95%: 0,57;0,74)]. Em ambos os sexos, os idosos com sintomas depressivos apresentaram maiores chances de sofrer quedas em comparação aos que não tiveram os sintomas, sendo 3,05 (IC95%: 1,16;8,05) vezes maior nos homens e 2,28 (IC95%: 1,21;4,31) vezes maior nas mulheres, mesmo após o ajuste para faixa etária, multimorbidade e nível de atividade física. Conclusão: A GDS-15 pode ser utilizada para o rastreio de quedas em idosos, sendo indicado utilizar valores discriminativos diferenciados entre os sexos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Depressive symptoms are associated with the occurrence of falls in older adults, therefore, it is important to define different cutoff points between the sexes in the Abbreviated Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS-15) that discriminate a greater propensity for falls, to identify and implement early preventive rehabilitation strategies. Objective: To determine the accuracy of GDS-15, with different values between sexes, to track falls in community-dwelling older adults and verify the association between depressive symptoms and falls using the proposed cutoff points. Method: Cross-sectional study, with random sampling including 308 older adults. The history of falls in the last 12 months, classified dichotomously (yes or no), was considered as a dependent variable and the assessment of depressive symptoms using the GDS-15 as an independent variable. Receiver Operating Characteristic Curve was used to analyze the sensitivity and specificity of GDS-15, and Multivariable Logistic Regression to verify the association between depressive symptoms and falls. Results: The cutoff points that best discriminated falls in the GDS were ≥4 points for women [AUC:0.61 (95%CI: 0.54;0.69)] and ≥3 points for men [AUC:0.65 (95%CI: 0.57;0.74)]. In both sexes, the older adults with depressive symptoms were more likely to suffer falls, compared to those who did not have the symptoms, being 3.05 (95%CI: 1.16;8.05) times higher in men and 2.28 (95%CI: 1.21;4.31) times higher in women, even after adjusting for age, multimorbidity and level of physical activity. Conclusion: GDS-15 can be used to screen falls in older adults, and it is indicated to use discriminative values differentiated between sexes.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185247</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i1a185247</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 1 (2021); 43-48</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185247/171812</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185349</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-10-21T14:35:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Res.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">XXVI Congresso Brasileiro de Medicina Física e Reabilitação</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">XXVI Brazilian Congress of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</dc:title>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical and Rehabilitation Medicine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Congress</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina Física e Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Anais de Congressos</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo da Associação Brasileira de Medicina Física e Reabilitação (ABMFR) é o de sempre promover eventos com responsabilidade. O XXVI Congresso Brasileiro de Medicina Física e Reabilitação aconteceu de 29 de Agosto a 1 de Setembro de 2018, em Salvador/BA.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">O objetivo da Associação Brasileira de Medicina Física e Reabilitação (ABMFR) é o de sempre promover eventos com responsabilidade. O XXVI Congresso Brasileiro de Medicina Física e Reabilitação aconteceu de 29 de Agosto a 1 de Setembro de 2018, em Salvador/BA.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2018-09-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185349</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 25 n. Supl.1 (2018); 1-33</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185349/171470</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2018 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185715</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-06-28T17:50:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Tradução e adaptação cultural da ferramenta de avaliação de riscos ergonômicos de membros superiores – Hand Arm Risk Assessment Method – HARM-BR</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Translation with cultural adaptation of the risk assessment tool for upper limbs – Hand Arm Risk Assessment Method HARM-BR</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mauad, Leonardo Dutra de Salvo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sartori, Natália</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Karime Saba</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Ester Rodrigues do Carmo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Suzuki, Karen Ayumi Kawano</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Natália Claro da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Castro, Vinícius Restani de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fonseca, Marisa de Cássia Registro</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Adaptação Transcultural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ergonomia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Extremidade Superior</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Inquéritos e Questionários</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tradução</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ergonomics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Upper Extremity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Surveys and Questionnaires</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Translating</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Lesões musculoesqueléticas nos membros superiores estão intimamente ligadas a limitações funcionais e incapacidades. Estas lesões podem estar relacionadas ao trabalho e são conhecidas como Lesões por Esforços Repetitivos (LER) ou Distúrbios Osteomusculares Relacionados ao Trabalho (DORT). A avaliação ergonômica visa detectar os fatores de riscos para o desenvolvimento das LER/DORT e assim, intervenções e/ou ações&#160; preventivas possam ser implementadas. Para isso, são necessárias ferramentas observacionais de avaliação traduzidas e validadas para que resultados fidedignos sejam alcançados. O questionário HARM 2.0 é uma ferramenta de avaliação específica que indica se há risco de lesão em diversas tarefas que utilizam majoritariamente os membros superiores durante sua jornada de trabalho. Objetivo: Conduzir a tradução e adaptação transcultural do questionário HARM 2.0 para ser usado para avaliação e prevenção de riscos de lesões relacionadas ao trabalho. Métodos: A tradução e adaptação transcultural seguiu um protocolo composto por quatro estágios: tradução, síntese, retrotradução, revisão pelo comitê de especialistas e aprovação do conteúdo pelas autoras da versão original. Resultados: O estágio inicial (Estágio I) de tradução do questionário HARM 2.0 transcorreu sem intercorrências. Com relação ao grau de dificuldade, o tradutor expert referiu facilidade ao traduzir os itens e instruções do instrumento, enquanto a tradutora leiga considerou a dificuldade como moderada. Conclusão: O instrumento HARM-BR 2.0 apresentou resultados satisfatórios no processo de tradução e adaptação transcultural, estando sua versão disponível para uso. Futuros estudos são necessários para analisar as suas propriedades de medidas para a população brasileira de trabalhadores.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Musculoskeletal injuries in the upper limbs are closely associated with limitations and disabilities. These injuries can be work-related and are known as Repetitive Strain Injuries (RSI) or Work-Related Musculoskeletal Disorders (WRMD). The ergonomic evaluation aims to detect the risk factors for the development of RSI/WRMD and, therefore, preventive or intervention strategies can be implemented. Translated and validated observational assessments are required to achieve reliable results. The HARM 2.0 questionnaire is a specific assessment tool that indicates the risk of injury in several tasks that use the upper limbs in the work environment. Objective: The objective of this study is to conduct the translation and cross-cultural adaptation of the HARM 2.0 questionnaire for the assessment and prevention of work-related injuries. Methods: Translation and cross-cultural adaptation protocol consisting of four stages: translation, synthesis, back-translation, review by the Expert Committee, and approval by the authors of the original version. Results: The initial stage (Stage I) of translation of the HARM 2.0 questionnaire was regular and had no significant issues. Regarding the difficulty, the expert translator referred that translating the HARM items and instructions was easy, whereas the lay translator considered the scale moderate. Conclusion: The scale HARM-BR 2.0 presents satisfactory results in the process of translation and cross-cultural adaptation and its version available to use. Future studies should be conducted to establish its measurement properties for the Brazilian population.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185715</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v29i1a185715</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 29 n. 1 (2022); 31-35</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185715/180833</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185715/180832</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185748</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-06-28T17:50:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Correlation between risk of falls, vulnerability and body composition of the elderly in a comprehensive health care center for the elderly</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Correlação entre risco de quedas, vulnerabilidade e composição corporal de idosos de um centro de atenção integral a saúde do idoso</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Miguel Jânio Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carneiro, Andréa Santana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Alisson Sousa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ibiapina, Elaine Farias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Simeão, Lisiane Fernanda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dibai Filho, Almir Vieira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dibai , Daniela Bassi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Maria Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Accidental Falls</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Body Composition</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Vulnerability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Obesidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Quedas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Vulnerabilidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To investigate the correlation of the risk of falling with the decrease in functional mobility, vulnerability and obesity in the elderly. Method: Cross-sectional study. Active elderly people of both sexes, aged between 60-85 years were evaluated, and volunteers who did not undergo the evaluative tests proposed to identify functional mobility and nutritional status were excluded.The Body Mass Index (BMI) tests were applied, which classified the nutritional status of malnutrition BMI ≤ 22, nutritional risk BMI= 22.1-24.0, ideal weight BMI= 24.1-27.0, overweight BMI 27.1-30 and obesity with BMI &amp;gt; 30.0, the Timed Up &amp;amp; Go (TUG) to identify functional mobility and functional risks related to falls in the elderly and the classification adopted for this study was ≥ 10s being risk indicators for falls and the Vulnerable Elders Survey (VES-13) that classified as vulnerable elderly, volunteers with a score &amp;gt; 2 points. Statistical analysis was performed at 95% confidence level and p&amp;lt;0.05. Results: 104 elderly people participated, classified as having no risk for falls (67.3%), non-vulnerable (67.3%) and as obese (24%). There was no correlation between obese subjects and the risk of falls in TUG time in seconds [ρ= - 0.115; p&amp;gt;0.05] and with the TUG classification [ρ= -0.152; p&amp;gt;0.05]. However, there was a correlation between vulnerability and the risk of falls in time in seconds of the TUG [ρ= 0.217; p&amp;lt;0.05]. Conclusion: No correlation was observed between obesity and risk of falls. However, it was found that the more vulnerable the greater the risk for falls.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Investigar a correlação do risco de queda com a diminuição da mobilidade funcional, vulnerabilidade e a obesidade em idosos. Método: Estudo transversal, foram avaliados idosos ativos de ambos os sexos, idade entre 60-85 anos e excluídos voluntários que não realizaram os testes avaliativos propostos para identificar a mobilidade funcional e o estado nutricional. Foram aplicados os testes Índice de Massa Corporal (IMC) que classificou o estado nutricional desnutrição IMC ≤ 22, risco nutricional IMC= 22.1-24.0, peso ideal IMC= 24.1-27.0, sobrepeso IMC 27.1-30 e obesidade com IMC &amp;gt; 30.0, o Timed Up &amp;amp; Go (TUG) para identificar a mobilidade funcional e os riscos funcionais relacionados a quedas em idosos e a classificação adotada para este estudo foi ≥ 10s sendo indicadores de risco de quedas e o Vulnerable Elders Survey (VES-13) que classificou como idoso vulnerável os voluntários com a pontuação &amp;gt; 2 pontos. A análise estatística foi realizada em 95% nível de confiança e p&amp;lt;0,05. Resultados: Participaram 104 idosos, classificados com ausência de risco para quedas (67.3%), não vulneráveis (67.3%) e como obesos (24%). Não foi observada correlação entre obesos com o risco de quedas no tempo em segundos do TUG [ρ= -0.115; p&amp;gt;0.05] e com a classificação do TUG [ρ= -0.152; p&amp;gt;0.05]. Porém, foi observada correlação entre a vulnerabilidade com o risco de quedas no tempo em segundos do TUG [ρ= 0.217; p&amp;lt;0.05]. Conclusão: Não foi observada correlação entre obesidade e risco para quedas. Contudo, verificou-se que quando mais vulnerável maior é o risco para quedas.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185748</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v29i1a185748</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 29 n. 1 (2022); 36-41</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185748/181078</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185748/180940</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185905</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-01T13:27:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Desempenho físico e força de preensão manual como preditores de qualidade de vida de idosos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Physical performance and handgrip strength as predictors of quality of life in the elderly</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Lara Andrade</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tavares, Darlene Mara dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Mobility Limitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Limitação da Mobilidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Verificar a influência do desempenho físico e da força de preensão manual na qualidade de vida de idosos. Método: Pesquisa quantitativa, longitudinal, do tipo inquérito domiciliar conduzida com 322 idosos residentes no interior de Minas Gerais. Os dados foram coletados em 2014 e 2017/2018 por meio dos instrumentos: Mini Exame do Estado Mental; questionários com dados sociodemográficos/econômico e clínico; Short Physical Performance Battery, dinamometria, World Health Organization Quality of Life-Bref e World Health Organization Quality of Life-Olders. Procedeu-se a análise descritiva, bivariada e regressão linear múltipla (p≤0,05). Resultados: Entre as duas coletas houve alteração do maior percentual do estado conjugal, com esposo(a) ou companheiro(a) na baseline para viúvos(as) no follow-up, além do aumento percentual de 5 ou mais morbidades. O menor desempenho físico foi preditor de piores escores de qualidade de vida nos domínios: físico (p&amp;lt;0,001) e relações sociais (p= 0,012); e nas facetas: autonomia (p= 0,001); atividades passadas, presentes e futuras (p= 0,005) e participação social (p&amp;lt;0,001). A menor força de preensão manual foi preditora de menor escore de qualidade de vida no domínio físico (p= 0,009). Conclusão: O menor desempenho físico e a menor força de preensão manual associaram-se com pior escore de qualidade de vida entre idosos da comunidade.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To verify the influence of physical performance and handgrip strength on the quality of life of the elderly. Method: Quantitative, longitudinal, household survey type survey conducted with 322 elderly people living in the interior of Minas Gerais. Data were collected in 2014 and 2017/2018 using the instruments: Mini Mental State Examination; questionnaires with sociodemographic/economic and clinical data; Short Physical Performance Battery, dynamometry, World Health Organization Quality of Life-Bref and World Health Organization Quality of Life-Olders. Descriptive, bivariate analysis and multiple linear regression (p≤0.05) were performed. Results: Between the two collections there was a change in the highest percentage of marital status, with husband or partner in the baseline for widowers at follow-up, in addition to the percentage increase of 5 or more morbidities. The lowest physical performance was a predictor of worse quality of life scores in the domains: physical (p &amp;lt;0.001) and social relationships (p= 0.012); and in the facets: autonomy (p= 0.001); past, present and future activities (p= 0.005) and social participation (p &amp;lt;0.001). The lower handgrip strength was a predictor of a lower quality of life score in the physical domain (p= 0.009). Conclusion: Lower physical performance and lower handgrip strength were associated with a worse quality of life score among elderly people in the community.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185905</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i3a185905</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 3 (2021); 149-155</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185905/176466</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/185921</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-15T17:11:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Relationship between handgrip strength, peripheral muscle strength, and respiratory muscle endurance in women with fibromyalgia: a cross-sectional study</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Relação entre força de preensão manual, força muscular periférica e resistência muscular respiratória em mulheres com fibromialgia: um estudo transversal</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Melian, Natasha Teixeira da Cunha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Branco, Joaquim Henrique Lorenzetti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Torres, Guilherme</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Andrade, Alexandro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Matte, Darlan Laurício</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fibromialgia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dinamômetro de Força Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força da Mão</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Músculos Respiratórios</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fibromyalgia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Strength Dynamometer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hand Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Respiratory Muscles</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Fibromialgia (FM) é uma doença caracterizada por dor musculoesquelética generalizada e crônica. É comum a presença de outros sintomas como fadiga, depressão, distúrbios do sono, levando os pacientes a adotarem um estilo de vida sedentário. Objetivo: Verificar a força muscular e respiratória de mulheres com FM. Método: Estudo transversal que avaliou 41 mulheres com FM. Analisamos a força de preensão manual (FPM), a força de membros inferiores e a resistência dos músculos respiratórios por meio da manobra espirométrica. Resultados: Pacientes com FM tiveram redução significativa da FPM, tanto no membro superior dominante quanto não dominante. A força muscular periférica dos membros inferiores foi reduzida porque, em média, os participantes excederam tempos normativos do teste de levantar e sentar estipulados para as faixas etárias. Aproximadamente dois terços da amostra apresentavam valores máximos de ventilação voluntária abaixo do limite inferior da normalidade. Detectamos correlação inversa e moderada entre força muscular periférica e FPM do membro superior não dominante (r= −0,472; p= 0,002) e correlação inversa e fraca com a FPM do membro superior dominante (r= −0,374; p= 0,016); correlações fracas entre resistência muscular respiratória e FPM do membro superior dominante (r= 0,299; p= 0,058), FPM do membro superior não dominante (r= -0,317; p= 0,043) e força muscular periférica (r= -0,372, p= 0,017); e forte correlação entre FPM de membro superior dominante e membro superior não dominante (r= 0,899; p&amp;lt;0,001). Conclusão: Mulheres com FM apresentam redução da força muscular de membros superiores e inferiores, bem como da resistência dos músculos respiratórios inferiores.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Fibromyalgia (FM) is a disease characterized by generalized and chronic musculoskeletal pain. It is common, the presence of other symptoms such as fatigue, depression, sleep disorders, leading patients to adopt a sedentary lifestyle. Objective: Verify the muscular and respiratory strength of women with FM. Method: Is a cross-sectional study that evaluated 41 women with clinical diagnosis of FM. We analyzed handgrip strength (HS), the strength of the lower limbs, and respiratory muscle endurance using the spirometric maneuver. Results: Patients with FM had a significant reduction in HS, both in the dominant and non-dominant upper limb. Furthermore, peripheral muscle strength in the lower limbs was reduced because on average, participants exceeded the normative five-repetition sit-to-stand test times stipulated for the age groups. Approximately two-thirds of the sample had maximal voluntary ventilation values below the lower limit of normality. We detected inverse and moderate correlation between peripheral muscle strength and HS of non-dominant upper limb (r= −0.472; p= 0.002) and inverse and weak correlation with the HS of dominant upper limb (r= −0.374; p= 0.016); weak correlations between respiratory muscle endurance and HS of dominant upper limb (r= 0.299; p= 0.058), HS of non-dominant upper limb (r= −0.317; p= 0.043), and peripheral muscle strength (r= −0.372, p= 0.017); and strong correlation between HS of dominant upper limb and non-dominant upper limb (r= 0.899; p&amp;lt;0.001). Conclusion: Women with FM present with reduced muscle strength in the upper and lower limbs, as well as lower respiratory muscle resistance.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185921</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i2a185921</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 2 (2021); 97-104</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/185921/174314</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/186736</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-06-28T17:50:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Comparison of different frequencies of transcutaneous electrical diaphragmatic stimulation in healthy subjects: a randomized crossover clinical trial</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Comparação de diferentes frequências da estimulação diafragmática elétrica transcutânea em indivíduos saudáveis: ensaio clínico randomizado cruzado</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Figueiredo, Renata Italiano da Nóbrega</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Plentz, Rodrigo Della Méa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lanferdini, Fabio Juner</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vaz, Marco Aurélio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sbruzzi, Graciele</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estimulação Elétrica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Diafragma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Voluntários Saudáveis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electrical Stimulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Diaphragm</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Healthy Volunteers</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A maioria dos estudos utilizam a estimulação diafragmática elétrica transcutânea (EDET) com frequência (F) de estímulo de 30Hz e testar diferentes frequências torna-se necessário para uma aplicação otimizada. Objetivo: Foi comparar o efeito agudo de duas frequências diferentes da EDET sobre a força muscular respiratória e endurance, ativação diafragmática, espessura muscular e mobilidade diafragmática, variáveis cardiovasculares e segurança em indivíduos saudáveis. Métodos: Estudo randomizado cruzado com 20 indivíduos saudáveis submetidos a duas intervenções: Grupo I com F= 30Hz e Grupo II com F= 80Hz. A aplicação foi nos pontos motores do diafragma, com duração do pulso de 500µs, durante 30 minutos. Foram avaliados a pressão arterial sistólica (PAS) e diastólica (PAD), frequência cardíaca (FC), força muscular respiratória pela pressão inspiratória máxima (PImax), pressão expiratória máxima (PEmax), endurance e espessura muscular em inspiração (EDI) e expiração (EDE), mobilidade e ativação diafragmática. Resultados: O GI apresentou redução significativa em comparação às condições basais para os desfechos de PAS (p= 0.04), FC (p&amp;lt;0.001), EDI (p= 0,02), PIF (p= 0.01), e S-Index (p= 0.03). O GII apresentou redução significativa em comparação às condições basais para FC (p&amp;lt;0.001) e aumento da PEmax (p&amp;lt;0.001). Porém, estas alterações não foram clinicamente importantes e não houve diferença entre os grupos para nenhum desfecho avaliado. Nenhuma intercorrência foi observada.&#160;Conclusão: A EDET com F-80Hz produz efeitos semelhantes a F-30Hz em indivíduos saudáveis e ambas as frequências provaram ser seguras (NCT03844711).</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Most transcutaneous electric diaphragmatic stimulation (TEDS) studies use a stimulation frequency (SF) of 30 Hz, although the reason for this SF value is not completely understood. Objective: The purpose of this study was to compare the acute effect of two TEDS frequencies on the respiratory muscle strength and endurance, muscle activation, muscle thickness, diaphragmatic mobility, cardiovascular variables and safety in healthy subjects. Methods: Randomized crossover clinical trial with 20 healthy subjects subjected to two interventions: SF=30 Hz group and SF=80 Hz group. TEDS was applied at the diaphragm motor points with a symmetric biphasic pulsed current (pulse duration= 500 µs) for 30 minutes. The evaluated outcomes were systolic blood pressure (SBP), diastolic blood pressure (DBP), heart rate (HR), respiratory muscle strength by maximal inspiratory pressure (MIP), maximal expiratory pressure (MEP), inspiratory peak flux (PIF), diaphragm thickness during inspiration (DTI) and expiration (DTE), diaphragm mobility and activation, and endurance (S-Index). Results: SF-30 Hz showed a reduction with respect to baseline values for SBP (p= 0.04), HR (p&amp;lt;0.001), DTE (p= 0.02), IPF (p= 0.01), and S-Index (p= 0.03). SF-80 Hz showed a reduction with respect to baseline values for HR (p&amp;lt;0.001) and an increase in MEP (p&amp;lt;0.001). However, these changes were not clinically important and there were no between-groups differences for any of the evaluated outcomes. No complications were observed. Conclusion: TEDS with SF-80 Hz produces similar effects to SF-30 Hz in healthy subjects and both frequencies proved to be safe (NCT03844711).</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/186736</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v29i1a186736</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 29 n. 1 (2022); 6-13</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/186736/180936</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2023-08-08T14:49:42Z" completeListSize="935" cursor="800">db5e0c66e589ccce142b5a044ba4d5bf</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
