<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-08-07T14:49:29Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="actafisiatrica">https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137661</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T13:50:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Virtual reality applied to the lower limb motor function in post-stroke individuals</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Realidade virtual na função motora de membros inferiores pós-acidente vascular encefálico</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Marcos Paulo Braz de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Daiane Marques</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Josie Resende Torres da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Andreia Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lobato, Daniel Ferreira Moreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kosour, Carolina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Reis, Luciana Maria dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Postural Balance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Lower Extremity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Virtual Reality Exposure Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Postural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Extremidade Inferior</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia de Exposição à Realidade Virtual</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O Acidente Vascular Encefálico (AVE) pode gerar importantes alterações motoras, de tônus e sensitivas. A realidade virtual (RV), voltada para reabilitação, pode trazer benefícios em relação à aptidão física, atividades motoras e de equilíbrio. Objetivo: Investigar o efeito da terapia por RV no equilíbrio estático e dinâmico, descarga de peso no membro inferior afetado, tônus e recrutamento muscular, independência funcional e função sensório-motora de indivíduos pós-AVE. Métodos: Trata-se de estudo clínico, quasi-experimental e prospectivo em 6 indivíduos com diagnóstico de AVE. Antes e após intervenção com Nintendo Wii Fit Plus os indivíduos foram avaliados pela Escala de Equilíbrio de Berg, Timed “Up and Go”, Índice do Andar Dinâmico; Teste de Marcha (TM); Escala Modificada de Ashworth (EMA); Eletromiografia; Índice de Barthel e Escala Fugl Meyer (EFM). Para análise estatística utilizou-se o teste Kolmogorov-Smirnov, teste t e Wilcoxon. Foi adotado P 80%. Resultados: No TM inicial da 1ª e 15ª sessão (p = 0,03; d = 1,96; P = 96%), EMA dos músculos extensores de quadril (p = 0,04; d = 3,77; P 99%) e joelho (p = 0,04; d = 3,23; P = 99%) e flexores plantares (p = 0,01; d = 3,18; P = 99%) e EFM nas dimensões coordenação/velocidade (p = 0,02; d = 6,74; P = 100%) e sensibilidade (p = 0,01), foram observados resultados significativos com grande efeito e Power &amp;gt; 90%. Nos demais instrumentos não foram encontrados valores significativos. Conclusão: O programa de reabilitação, por RV, foi eficaz na melhora da descarga de peso no membro inferior afetado, tônus muscular e função sensório-motora nos indivíduos do estudo</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Strokes can generate significant motor, tonic and sensitive changes. Virtual reality (RV), focused on rehabilitation, can bring several benefits such as improvements on physical fitness, motor skills and balance. Objective: To assess the effects of the RV intervention to the static and dynamic balance, weight load on the affected limb, tone and muscle recruitment, functional independence and sensorimotor function in post-stroke individuals. Methods: Quasi-experimental and prospective clinical study with 6 subjects with diagnosis of stroke. Before and after the intervention with Nintendo Wii Fit Plus, the subjects were assessed by the Berg Balance Scale, Timed “Up and Go” and Dynamic Floor Index; Gait Test (GT); Modified Ashworth Scale (MAS); Electromyography; Barthel Index and Fugl-Meyer Scale (FMS). The Statistical analysis used Kolmogorov-Smirnov test, t test and Wilcoxon. Results: The 1st and 15th session evaluations have shown that GT (p = 0.03, d = 1.96, P = 96%), MAS for hip extensor muscles (p = 0.04; d = 3.77; P = 99%), knee extensors (p = 0.04; d = 3.23; P = 99%), plantar flexors (p = 0.01; d = 3.18; P = 99%), FMS in coordination/velocity dimensions (p = 0.02; d = 6.74; P = 100%) and sensitivity (p = 0.01) presented significant results, large effect size and power above 90%. Significant values were not found to the other evaluations. Conclusion: The RV rehabilitation program was effective and improved the weight-load in affected limb, muscle tone and sensorimotor function of the subjects</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137661</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160026</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 3 (2016); 135-139</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137661/133304</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137661/133305</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137662</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T13:58:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Comparação da pontuação obtida por videogame com variáveis biomecânicas em pacientes pós-acidente vascular encefálico</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Comparison of scores obtained in videogame with biomechanical variables in stroke</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tarallo, Fernanda Botta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Jéssica Santos da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Mayara Luz Alcantara dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Castro, Pedro Claudio Gonsales de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moreira, Maria Cecília dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral/reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Jogos de Vídeo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Postural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke/rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Video Games</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Postural Balance</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Virtual reality (VR) promotes intensive training of a single task, enabling the motor learning, thereby affecting the recovery of postural control (PC) in individuals with stroke. Video game with balance platform are used as a form of intervention and, at the end of the game, a score is provided, but there is no evidence that it can be used as a quantitative parameter of PC. Objective: To determine whether there is a correlation between the score obtained by a video game and stabilometric variables. Methods: Nine individuals with stroke participated in an experimental protocol using the game Penguin Slide as intervention. The score was collected in the first and last sessions. The 2.0 AMTI force platform was used, with an acquisition frequency of 200Hz for evaluating before and after intervention. The volunteers were positioned with open eyes (OE) and closed eyes (CE) in the upright position for 1 minute, with one foot on each platform. Using the Matlab software, the variables of center of pressure (COP) were obtained: total COP area (ACOPt), COP area on the mediolateral (ACOPx) and anteroposterior (ACOPy) axis, average speed of COP (VCOP). The non-parametric paired Wilcoxon test (p &amp;lt; 0.05) was used to compare the initial and final results of Penguin Slide game score and the pre and post intervention data obtained by the force platform in the OE and CE conditions. The analysis were done with the software R. Results: Comparison of initial and final score (p = 0.003). In OE condition, the initial and final comparison: ACOPt (p = 0.91), ACOPx (p = 0.57), ACOPy (p = 0.49), VCOP (p = 0.09). In CE condition, the initial and final comparison: ACOPt (p = 0.73) ACOPx (p = 1.0), ACOPy (p = 0.73) VCOP (p = 0.73). Conclusion: The VR did not provide PC improvement of the patients despite the score of the Penguin Slide game have increased significantly at the end of the protocol. Thus, there was no correlation between the score obtained by video game and the stabilometric variables</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A realidade virtual (RV) promove treinamento intensivo de uma mesma tarefa, possibilitando a aprendizagem motora, podendo influenciar a retomada do controle postural (CP) em indivíduos com acidente vascular encefálico (AVE). Videogames (jogos de vídeo) com plataforma de equilíbrio são utilizados como forma de intervenção e, ao final dos jogos, uma pontuação é fornecida, porém não há evidências de que ela possa ser utilizada como parâmetro de quantificação do CP. Objetivo: Verificar se há correlação entre a pontuação obtida por um jogo de videogame e variáveis estabilométricas. Métodos: Nove indivíduos com histórico de AVE realizaram um protocolo experimental utilizando o jogo Penguim Slide do Nintendo Wii como intervenção. Coletou-se a pontuação obtida na primeira e na última sessão. Utilizou-se a plataforma de força AMTI 2.0, com frequência de aquisição de 200 Hz para as avaliações pré e pós-intervenção. Os voluntários foram posicionados de olhos abertos (OA) e fechados (OF) na postura ereta durante 1 minuto, com um pé em cada plataforma. Utilizando o Software Matlab® 7.0, obtiveram-se as variáveis do centro de pressão (COP): área COP total (ACOPt), área COP nos eixos médio-lateral (ACOPx) e ântero-posterior (ACOPy) e velocidade média do COP (VCOP). O teste de Wilcoxon pareado (p &amp;lt; 0,05), de natureza não paramétrica, foi utilizado para comparar os resultados da pontuação do jogo Penguim Slide e os dados obtidos pela plataforma de força nas condições OA e OF. As análises foram feitas com auxílio do software R. Resultados: Comparação inicial e final da pontuação (p = 0,003). Comparação inicial e final de OA: ACOPt (p = 0,91), ACOPx (p = 0,57), ACOPy (p = 0,49), VCOP (p = 0,09). Comparação inicial e final de OF: ACOPt (p = 0,73), ACOPx (p = 1,0), ACOPy (p = 0,73), VCOP (p = 0,73). Conclusão: A RV não proporcionou aos indivíduos aprimoramento do CP, porém a pontuação no jogo Penguim Slide aumentou significativamente. Desse modo, não houve correlação entre a pontuação obtida por um jogo de videogame e variáveis estabilométricas</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137662</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 3 (2016); 140-144</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137662/133306</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137662/133307</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137663</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T14:06:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Muscle training program in patients with severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Programa de treinamento muscular em pacientes com doença pulmonar obstrutiva crônica grave</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sagrillo, Luiza Minato</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Meereis, Estele Caroline Welter</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Marisa Pereira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pulmonary Disease</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Chronic Obstructive</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise Tolerance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doença Pulmonar Obstrutiva Crônica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tolerância ao Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: The objective of this study was to analyze the effects of a muscle training program with neuromuscular electrical stimulation (NMES) for lower limbs (LL) and active resisted exercises for upper limbs (UL) for patients with severe Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease. Methods: With a sample of 5 subjects (65.2 ± 6.09 years), the initial and final evaluations were: One-RepetitionMaximum testing; Sit-to-stand test; perimetry of the thigh; 6-minute walk test; Saint George’s Respiratory Questionnaire; Medical Research Council scale for dyspnea and the BODE index. The intervention was performed three times a week and was composed of 18 sessions of 30-minute NMES followed by 30 minutes of exercise for the UL based on the diagonal Kabat method. The NMES parameters were: 50Hz of frequency, 6s on and 8s off, increase slope of 2s and decrease slope of 2s, pulse width of 400µs, and intensity defined as patient tolerance and increased from 1 to 5mA each day. Results: The results have shown an increase in muscle strength (p = 0.01) and of muscle resistance (p = 0.01). There was an improvement tendency in the quality of life (p = 0.16) and in the cardiorespiratory fitness (p = 0.11). Conclusion: The association of physical exercises with diagonals and NMES can be a beneficial resource for the treatment of patients with severe COPD. It is suggested, however, the need for new researches with a wider sample size for assuring these benefits</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Este estudo que visou analisar os efeitos de um programa de treinamento muscular através da EENM de membros inferiores (MMII) e exercícios ativos resistidos de MMSS em pacientes portadores de Doença Pulmonar Obstrutiva Crônica (DPOC) grave. Métodos: A amostra foi constituída por 5 sujeitos com idade média de 65,2 ± 6,09 anos. As avaliações iniciais e finais, compreenderam os testes: uma repetição máxima; senta-levanta; perimetria das coxas; caminhada de seis minutos; questionário St George; escala de dispneia MRC; índice de BODE. A intervenção foi realizada três vezes/semana, totalizando 18 sessões de 30 min de Estimulação elétrica neuromuscular (EENM) e 30 min de treinamento membros superiores, com uso de diagonais do Método Kabat. Os parâmetros da EENM foram: frequência 50 Hz, Ton 6s, Toff 8s, rampa de subida 2s, rampa de descida 2s, largura de pulso 400 µs e intensidade conforme a tolerância do paciente, aumentada em 1 a 5 mA a cada dia. Resultados: Mostraram aumento da força muscular (p = 0,01) e da resistência muscular (p = 0,01). Verificou-se uma tendência à melhora na qualidade de vida (p = 0,16) e na aptidão cardiorrespiratória (p = 0,11). Conclusão: A associação de EENM e exercícios com diagonais pode ser um recurso valioso para o tratamento dos pacientes com DPOC grave. Entretanto, sugere-se pesquisas com um maior número amostral para comprovar seus benefícios</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137663</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160028</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 3 (2016); 145-149</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137663/133308</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137663/133309</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137664</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T14:25:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Neuromuscular block practice in the treatment of spasticity in Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Práticas de bloqueios neuromusculares para o tratamento da espasticidade no Brasil</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Crema, Chiara Maria Tha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Ana Paula Bertole Cirino dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Magário, Luiza Previato Trevisan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Caldas, Carla Andrea Cardoso Tanuri</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Botulinum Toxins</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Type A</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neuromuscular Blockade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Spasticity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Toxinas Botulínicas Tipo A</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Bloqueio Neuromuscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Espasticidade Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Botulinum toxin type A (TBA) is one of the most effective and safe treatments for spasticity. To evaluate some scales can be used, as the Modified Ashworth Scale (MAS). Therapeutic success in the application depends on the correct identification of the problem and biomechanical application of the affected muscle, which can be done by surface palpation techniques or auxiliary methods such as electromyography. Objective: To evaluate the methods of TBA applications for the treatment of spasticity performed in the practice of medical rehabilitation for children and adults. Methods: exploratory, cross-sectional study with a convenience sample size recruited in scientific events in Rio de Janeiro, São Paulo, Goiânia, Belo Horizonte, Curitiba and Ribeirão Preto (Brazil). Questionnaires regarding the treatment of spasticity containing multiple choice questions about groups of patients and treated muscles were applied. Responses were analyzed for frequency for each answer. No association test of variables or hypothesis were used. Results: 49 questionnaires were analyzed. 47% apply TBA for less than five years. The most used technique for locating points of application was muscular palpation (80%). To quantify the functional gains, 78% reported the use the MAS scale. 57% applies in adults and children. The most common children age group treated was 5-10 years (83%) and the most treated muscle group was the triceps surae (73.8%). Regarding the use of phenol, 16 used with a frequency of 1 to 5 patients per month. 45% of applicators used phenol associeted with TBA. Conclusion: The TBA is widely used in the treatment of spasticity, however there is no standardization in the form of application, method of analyzing the treatment success or the necessity of a combined agent</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A toxina botulínica do tipo A (TBA) é um dos tratamentos mais efetivos e seguros para espasticidade. Para a avaliação algumas escalas podem ser utilizadas como a Escala Modificada de Ashworth (MAS). O sucesso terapêutico na aplicação depende da correta identificação do problema biomecânico e aplicação no músculo acometido, o que pode ser feito por técnicas de palpação de superfície ou métodos auxiliares como eletromiografia. Objetivo: Avaliar os métodos de aplicações da TBA e outros tipos de bloqueios como fenol para tratamento da espasticidade realizados na prática de médicos de reabilitação infantil e de adultos. Métodos: Estudo exploratório, transversal, com amostra dimensionada pela conveniência em eventos científicos nas cidades Rio de Janeiro, São Paulo, Goiânia, Belo Horizonte, Curitiba e Ribeirão Preto com questionários a respeito do tratamento da espasticidade que continham questões de múltipla escolha sobre grupos de pacientes e músculos tratados. As respostas foram analisadas quanto à frequência para cada questão. Não foi foram realizados testes de associação de variáveis ou de hipótese. Resultados: Foram analisados 49 questionários. 47% aplicam TBA há menos de 5 anos. A técnica mais utilizada para localização de pontos de aplicação foi a palpação muscular (80%). Para quantificação dos ganhos funcionais 78% utilizam a escala MAS. 57% faz aplicação em adultos e crianças. A faixa etária de tratamento mais comum entre as crianças foi 5 a 10 anos (83%) com o grupo muscular mais aplicado o tríceps sural (73,8%). Em relação ao uso do fenol, 16 utilizam com uma frequência de 1 a 5 pacientes por mês. 45% dos aplicadores sempre utilizam fenol em conjunto com TBA. Conclusão: A TBA é largamente utilizada no tratamento de espasticidade, porém não existe uma padronização na forma de aplicação, método de avaliação ou sobre necessidade de outro agente combinado</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137664</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160029</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 3 (2016); 150-154</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137664/133311</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137664/133312</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137665</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T14:33:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Practice of mental protocols used in rehabilitation of patients with Parkinson’s disease: a systematic review</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Protocolos de prática mental utilizados na reabilitação motora de sujeitos com doença de Parkinson: revisão sistemática da literatura</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Douglas Monteiro da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Coriolano, Maria das Graças Wanderley de Sales</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Macêdo, João Gabriel Figuêredo de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Liliane Pereira da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lins, Otávio Gomes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doença de Parkinson</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Modalidades de Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Imaginação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Parkinson Disease</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy Modalities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Imagination</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Prática Mental (PM) consiste em um método de treinamento pelo qual um dado ato motor específico é cognitivamente reproduzido internamente e repetido com a intenção de promover aprendizagem ou aperfeiçoamento de uma habilidade motora, sem induzir qualquer movimento real. Os resultados das pesquisas com PM na doença de Parkinson (DP) ainda são ambíguos devido a várias razões como à diversidade de protocolos de intervenção. Os protocolos de intervenção com PM são cognitivamente complexos e desafiadores apresentando variações em sua aplicação relativas ao tipo de PM, tarefa/movimento a ser imaginada e tipo de instrução. Objetivo: Investigar na literatura os protocolos de PM utilizados para reabilitação motora de sujeitos com DP. Métodos: A busca desta revisão sistemática foi realizada nas bases de dados dos portais: PubMed, Scopus, Web of Science e Bireme. Os descritores foram: (“mental practice” or “motor imagery” or “imagery training” and “Parkinson”). Resultados: Foram encontrados 128 artigos, dos quais apenas 4 foram incluídos segundo os critérios de elegibilidade. Conclusão: Os protocolos que se mostraram eficazes para redução da bradicinesia, melhora da mobilidade e da velocidade da marcha utilizaram a associação da PM em 12 sessões, com duração de 5 à 30 minutos, imagética visual ou visual e cinestésica de atividades especificas e usaram vídeos da marcha dos pacientes ou da marcha normal para ajudar na familiarização e identificação dos componentes cinemáticos do movimento</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The Mental Practice (MP) consists of a training method by which a given specific motor act is cognitively reproduced internally and repeated with the intention of promoting learning or improvement of motor skills, without inducing any real movement. The results of MP to research in Parkinson’s disease are still ambiguous due to various reasons such as the diversity of the intervention protocols. The MP with intervention protocols are cognitively complex and challenging presenting variations in its application concerning the type of PM, task/movement to be imagined and type of instruction. Objective: The study aimed to investigate the literature MPs protocols used for motor rehabilitation of individuals with Parkinson’s disease. Methods: The searches of this systematic review was performed on the portals databases: PubMed, Scopus, Web of Science and Medicine. The descriptors were: (“mental practice” or “engine imagery” or “imagery training” and “Parkinson”). Results: 128 articles were found, of which only 4 were included according to the eligibility criteria. Conclusion: The protocols that have proven to be effective for reducing bradykinesia, improving mobility and gait speed used the MP combined with physical practice in 12 sessions, of 5 to 30 minutes, visual or visual and kinesthetic imagery of specific activities and used gait videos of patients or healthy subjects promote familiarization and identification of kinematic components of the movement</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137665</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160030</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 3 (2016); 155-160</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137665/133314</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137665/133315</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137666</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-05T18:27:57Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Cross-cultural adaptation of the ABILOCO: a measure of locomotion ability for individuals with stroke</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Adaptação transcultural do ABILOCO: uma medida de habilidade de locomoção, específica para indivíduos pós acidente vascular encefálico</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Avelino, Patrick Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Faria-Fortini, Iza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Basílio, Marluce Lopes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Menezes, Kênia Kiefer Parreiras de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Magalhães, Lívia de Castro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Teixeira-Salmela, Luci Fuscaldi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Locomoção</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Comparação Transcultural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Locomotion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cross-Cultural Comparison</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O ABILOCO, específico para adultos pós Acidente Vascular Encefálico (AVE), é um questionário para avaliação de habilidade de locomoção. Para sua aplicação na população brasileira, é necessário que seja realizada a sua adaptação transcultural. Objetivo: Realizar a adaptação transcultural do ABILOCO para uso no Brasil. Métodos: O processo de adaptação transcultural seguiu diretrizes padronizadas, sendo realizado em cinco etapas: tradução, retrotradução, síntese das traduções, avaliação pelo comitê de especialistas e teste da versão pré-final. A versão pré-final foi aplicada em 10 indivíduos pós- AVE, que responderam ao questionário e foram indagados sobre como interpretaram cada item. Resultados: O processo de adaptação transcultural seguiu todas as recomendações propostas, sendo necessários apenas acréscimos em dois itens, para possibilitar melhor compreensão. Resultados satisfatórios foram obtidos no teste da versão pré-final, uma vez que não houve nenhum problema quanto à redação e clareza dos itens ou ao objetivo do questionário. Conclusão: A versão final do ABILOCO, denominada ABILOCO-Brasil, demonstrou satisfatório grau de equivalência semântica, conceitual e cultural para uso em contextos clínicos e de pesquisa no Brasil. Estudos futuros devem ser conduzidos para dar continuidade ao processo de validação do questionário.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The ABILOCO, specific for adults with stroke, is a questionnaire for the assessment of locomotion ability. For the application with the Brazilian population, its cross-cultural adaptation is required. Objective: To translate the ABILOCO into the Brazilian-Portuguese language and adapt the questionnaire to the Brazilian culture. Methods: The process of cross-cultural adaptation followed standardized procedures and was conducted in five stages: translation, back-translation, synthesis of the translations, expert committee consultation, and testing of the pre-final version. The prefinal version was administered to 10 individuals with stroke, who were asked to interpret all of the items. Results: The cross-cultural adaptation process followed al of the recommended guidelines and minor modifications in two items were necessary to facilitate understanding. Satisfactory results were obtained during the test of the pre-final version, since there was not found any problem regarding the wording and clarity of the items or the objective of the questionnaire. Conclusions: The ABILOCO-Brazil showed satisfactory semantic, linguistic, cultural, and conceptual equivalence to be used within clinical and research contexts. Future studies should continue the process of validation of the questionnaire.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137666</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160031</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 4 (2016); 161-165</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137666/133318</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137666/133319</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137667</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-30T13:23:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Adaptação transcultural do “Pelvic Girdle Questionnaire” (PGQ) para o Brasil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Cross-cultural adaptation of “Pelvic Girdle Questionnaire” (PGQ) to Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Simões, Luan César Ferreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Teixeira-Salmela, Luci Fuscaldi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Wanderley, Elaine Lima Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barros, Raphaela Rodrigues de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Laurentino, Glória Elisabeth Carneiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lemos, Andrea</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pelvic Girdle Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Surveys and Questionnaires</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Translating</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Validation Studies</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor da Cintura Pélvica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Inquéritos e Questionários</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tradução</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudos de Validação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The Pelvic Girdle Questionnaire (PGQ) has good test-retest reliability, internal consistency and construct validity. The instrument consists of 25 items divided into two subscales (activities and symptoms). Objective: The aim of this study was cross-culturally adapted for the Brazilian population “Pelvic Girdle Questionnaire” (PGQ). Method: The process of cross cultural adaptation occurred in 5 stages: translation, back translation, analysis of the expert committee, Delphi Study and pretest. A Delphi study was added to the process for submission of the instrument to the opinion of 17 physiotherapists experts from different regions of the country. Results: From the results of translation and back translation was developed a version of the PGQ synthesized in Portuguese. During the stage of the expert committee not semantic differences between the synthesized compared to the original version were observed. After consensus of more than 80% of the Delphi experts, study the version of PGQ-Brazil was applied to the target population during the pretest. Without further changes, the final version of the QMP-Brazil was completed. Conclusion: The PGQ-Brazil proved to be well adapted to the cultural reality of the Brazilian population, adding up, including the Delphi study as an additional tool to further ensure the reliability of this process</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O Pelvic Girdle Questionnaire (PGQ) possui boa confiabilidade teste-resteste, consistência interna e validade de construto. O instrumento é composto de 25 itens distribuídos em duas subescalas (atividades e sintomas). Objetivo: Adaptar transculturalmente para a população brasileira o “Pelvic Girdle Questionnaire” (PGQ). Método: O processo de adaptação transcultural ocorreu em 5 etapas: tradução, retrotradução, análise do comitê de especialistas, Estudo Delphi e pré-teste. Um Estudo Delphi foi adicionado ao processo para a submissão do instrumento à opinião de 17 fisioterapeutas especialistas de diversas regiões do país. Resultados: A partir dos resultados da tradução e retrotradução foi desenvolvida uma versão do PGQ sintetizada em português. Durante a etapa do comitê de especialistas não foram observadas diferenças semânticas entre a versão sintetizada quando comparada à original. Após consenso de mais de 80% dos especialistas do estudo Delphi, a versão do PGQ-Brasil foi aplicada na população-alvo durante o pré-teste. Sem mais alterações, a versão final do PGQ-Brasil foi concluída. Conclusão: O PGQ-Brasil demosntrouse bem adaptado para a realidade cultural da população brasileira, acrescentando-se, inclusive, o Estudo Delphi como ferramenta adicional para assegurar ainda mais a confiabilidade desse processo</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137667</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160032</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 4 (2016); 166-171</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137667/133320</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137667/133321</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137668</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T11:26:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Development and validation of a quality of life questionnaire in individuals with spinal cord injury</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Desenvolvimento e validação de um questionário de qualidade de vida em indivíduos com lesão da medula espinal</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Feniman, Sibele Pelloso</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cardoso, Jefferson Rosa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Villegas, Isabela Lucia Pelloso</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bela, Lais Faganello Dela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Suhaila Mahmoud Smaili</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lavado, Edson Lopes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spinal Cord Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Surveys and Questionnaires</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos da Medula Espinal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Inquéritos e Questionários</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Criar e testar as propriedades psicométricas de um instrumento específico para quantificação da qualidade de vida de indivíduos com lesão da medula espinal. Método: A partir dos métodos de consenso existentes, foi escolhida a técnica Delphi para criação do questionário e o SF-36 como método critério. Resultados: A consistência interna foi α=0,827. A confiabilidade intra e interavaliadores se mostram alta pelo coeficiente de correlação intraclasse e teste de bland e altman pela diferença da média. Pode-se observar correlações fortes entre o QVLM e SF-36 nos domínios capacidade funcional e aspectos físicos e correlação moderada nos domínios estado de saúde e aspectos emocionais. Houve diferença significante entre as quatro aplicações do QVLM demonstrando que o questionário é sensível à mudança. Conclusão: O QVLM foi criado com metodologia adequada e a avaliação das propriedades psicométricas traduzem em um instrumento válido, confiável, consistente e sensível a mudanças</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Create and test the psychometric proprieties of the specific instrument for the quantification of the quality of life in subjects with spinal cord injuries. Methods: From the existing consensus methods was chosen the Delphi technique for the creation of the questionnaire and the SF-36 for criteria method. Results: The internal consistence was α=0,827. The intra and inter evaluators confidence shows itself high by the intra class correlation coefficient and the Brand and Altman test by the difference of average. Can be observed strong correlations between the QVLM and SF-36 in the functional capacity and physical aspects domains and moderate correlation in the health state and emotional aspects domains. There was a significant difference between the four applications of QVLM, demonstrating that the questionnaire is sensible to change. Conclusion: The QVLM was created with a suitable methodology and the evaluation of the psychometrics proprieties turn out to be on a valid, reliable, consisting and sensible to changes instrument</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137668</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160033</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 4 (2016); 172-179</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137668/133322</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137668/133323</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137669</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T11:33:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeitos da intervenção fisioterapêutica na amplitude de movimento do ombro e no mapa termográfico de idosas submetidas à cirurgia para tratamento de câncer de mama</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Intervention effects on shoulder physiotherapeutic range of motion and old map thermography submitted to surgery for breast cancer treatment</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Petry, Débora Melissa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Honório, Gesilani Julia da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Keyla dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Saionara dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Luz, Clarissa Medeiros da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Luz, Soraia Cristina Tonon da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Palú, Marina</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Breast Neoplasms</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Range of Motion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Articular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy Modalities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Thermography</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neoplasias da Mama</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Amplitude de Movimento Articular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Modalidades de Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Termografia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Age is the main risk factor for developing breast cancer and clinically, older women have a more difficult rehabilitation process. Objective: The aim of the study was to evaluate the effects of physiotherapy intervention in range of motion (ROM) of shoulder and thermographic map of elderly postoperative treatment of breast cancer. Methods: A total of 10 elderly, undergoing surgery for breast cancer. The evaluation was done before and after the intervention by means of the goniometer for ADM measures and thermographic camera Eletrophysics PV320T, to identify the temperature of the thoracic region. We used the Wilcoxon test and Spearman correlation, with a 0.05 significance level. Results: The patients showed significant improvement in range of all movements of the affected limb, except internal rotation. When comparing the assessment of temperature values with the revaluation, there was an increase in temperature of the thoracic regions, and only significant values preserved breast. By comparing the temperature of the region preserved with compromised in the evaluation, there was a significant difference, since the revaluation, there was an approximation of these values. Conclusion: The correlation between increased temperature and ADM was significant for both members adduction and internal rotation member preserved in the evaluation. Intervention assured resolution or reduction of amendments on physical examination, improved ROM, increased temperature of the thoracic regions, and correlation between temperature increase and ROM bilateral adduction and internal rotation member preserved in the initial evaluation</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A idade é o principal fator de risco para o desenvolvimento do câncer de mama e clinicamente, as mulheres idosas apresentam um processo de reabilitação mais difícil. Objetivo: Avaliar os efeitos da intervenção fisioterapêutica na amplitude de movimento (ADM) do ombro e no mapa termográfico de idosas em pós-operatório de tratamento do câncer de mama. Métodos: Participaram 10 idosas, submetidas a tratamento cirúrgico para câncer de mama. A avaliação foi feita antes e após a intervenção através do goniômetro, para medidas de ADM, e da câmera termográfica Eletrophysics PV320T, para identificação da temperatura da região torácica. Utilizou-se o teste Wilcoxon e a correlação de Spearman, com nível de significância de 0,05. Resultados: As pacientes apresentaram melhora significativa da amplitude de todos os movimentos do membro comprometido, exceto a rotação interna. Ao comparar os valores de temperatura da avaliação com a reavaliação, houve um aumento da temperatura das regiões torácicas, sendo significativos apenas os valores da mama preservada. Ao comparar a temperatura da região preservada com a comprometida na avaliação, houve diferença significativa, já na reavaliação, ocorreu uma aproximação destes valores. A correlação entre o aumento de temperatura e ADM foi significativa para adução de ambos os membros e rotação interna do membro preservado, na avaliação. Conclusão: A intervenção garantiu resolução ou diminuição das alterações apresentadas no exame físico, melhora da ADM, aumento da temperatura das regiões torácicas, e correlação entre aumento da temperatura e ADM de adução bilateral e rotação interna do membro preservado na avaliação inicial</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137669</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160034</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 4 (2016); 180-185</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137669/133324</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137670</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T11:38:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of respiratory muscle strength and functional capacity in patients with cystic fibrosis</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da força muscular respiratória e capacidade funcional em pacientes com fibrose cística</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Cássio Magalhães da Silva e</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Araujo, Adriele Mascarenhas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Anna Lúcia Lima Diniz da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sousa, Valdívia Alves de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gomes Neto, Mansueto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Saquetto, Micheli Bernadone</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cystic Fibrosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Respiratory Muscles</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise Tolerance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fibrose Cística</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Músculos Respiratórios</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tolerância ao Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To correlate the respiratory muscle strength and functional capacity in patients with CF. Method: Cross-sectional study in adults with cystic fibrosis. Sampling data were cataloged in Microsoft Office Excel 2007 and the variables analyzed by SPSS version 20.0 using the Student t test and the Spearman coefficient. The level of significance adopted was p &amp;lt; 0.05. Results: We assessed 35 patients with cystic fibrosis (44.6 ± 19.0 years), the great majority of patients in FC (n=22) did not present weakness of the inspiratory muscles (MIP -90,7 ± 27.4 cmH2O). It was not found statistically significant differences only between the adult and elderly patients. There was a positive correlation between MIP and MEP and a six-minute walk test (6MWT) in participants with respiratory muscle weakness and in the elderly. There was statistically significant difference between the averages of the distance covered on the 6MWT and the maximal respiratory pressures with the average of what was envisaged for these variables. Conclusion: All groups presented limitation of respiratory strength and functional capacity. The correlations between the respiratory pressures with the 6MWT were low and small in adults and individuals without respiratory muscle weakness; moderate to high in the elderly; small to moderate in women; small and negative in men; and high in patients with respiratory muscle weakness.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Correlacionar a força muscular respiratória e a capacidade funcional em pacientes com FC. Métodos: Estudo transversal em adultos com fibrose cística. Os dados amostrais foram catalogados no Microsoft Office Excel 2007 e as variáveis analisadas pelo SPSS versão 20.0 através do teste t de Student e do coeficiente de Spearman. O nível de significância adotado foi p &amp;lt; 0,05. Resultados: Foram avaliados 35 pacientes com fibrose cística (44,6 ± 19,0 anos), grande parte dos pacientes de FC (n=26) não apresentaram fraqueza da musculatura inspiratória (PImáx -90,7 ± 27,4 cmH2O). Não foi encontrada estatística significativa apenas entre os pacientes adultos e idosos. Houve correlação positiva entre PImáx, PEmáx e teste de caminhada de 6 minutos (TC6) nos participantes com fraqueza muscular respiratória e nos idosos. Houve diferença estatisticamente significativa entre as médias da distância percorrida no TC6 e das pressões respiratórias máximas com a média do que foi previsto para estas variáveis. Conclusão: Todos os grupos apresentaram limitação da força respiratória e da capacidade funcional. As correlações entre as pressões respiratórias com o TC6 foram baixas e pequenas nos adultos e indivíduos sem fraqueza muscular respiratória; moderadas à alta nos idosos; pequenas à moderada nas mulheres; pequenas e negativas nos homens; e, altas naqueles com fraqueza muscular respiratória.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137670</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160035</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 4 (2016); 186-190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137670/133326</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137670/133327</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137671</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T12:09:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio e ajuste postural antecipatório em idosos caidores: efeitos da reabilitação virtual e cinesioterapia</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Balance and antecipatory postural adjustments in elderly fallers: effects of kinesiotherapy and virtual rehabilitation</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Franciulli, Patrícia Martins</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Gislene Gomes da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bigongiari, Aline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barbanera, Márcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Razi Neto, Semaan El</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mochizuki, Luis</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Postural Balance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy Modalities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Virtual Reality Exposure Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Postural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Modalidades de Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia de Exposição à Realidade Virtual</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Aging causes a number of changes in motor control of the individual and consequently in postural adjustments. Objective: To evaluate the balance and anticipatory postural adjustments of the agonist muscles and the ankle joint antagonists and compare the effect of rehabilitation virtual and kinesiotherapy in the elderly. Methods: Twenty four elderly participated of this study divided into two groups. 12 participants and the kinesiotherapy group by 12 participants composed the virtual rehabilitation group, equally. The treatment protocol was conducted for six weeks. Virtual rehabilitation group used Xbox 360 with kinect and Your Shape Fitness Evolved game. In the kinesiotherapy group the same protocol exercises were performed. Results: The results indicated a statistically significant difference between pre and post intervention phases in Berg Balance Scale in both groups. There was decreased activation of tibialis anterior muscle in the right functional range of task after interventions, and increased lateral gastrocnemius muscle activation rights in the trunk flexion after training. No differences were observed in muscle activation between the two types of intervention. Conclusion: Protocols with therapeutic exercise and virtual rehabilitation were effective in improving balance and functional capacity of fallers, with no differences between the two types of intervention</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O envelhecimento provoca uma série de alterações no controle motor do indivíduo e consequentemente nos ajustes posturais. Objetivo: Comparar o efeito da reabilitação virtual e cinesioterapia em idosos caidores no equilíbrio e no ajuste postural antecipatório dos músculos agonistas e antagonistas da articulação do tornozelo. Métodos: Participaram 24 idosos que foram alocados em dois grupos: 12 participantes no grupo reabilitação virtual e 12 participantes no grupo cinesioterapia. O protocolo foi realizado durante seis semanas, sendo duas sessões por semana. No grupo reabilitação virtual foi utilizado o console Xbox 360 com kinect e o jogo Your Shape Fitness Evolved. No grupo cinesioterapia foram realizados exercícios de equilíbrio e propriocepção. Resultados: Ambos os grupos apresentaram maior pontuação na escala de equilíbrio de Berg após a intervenção. Houve diminuição da ativação do músculo tibial anterior direito no alcance funcional após a intervenção realizada, e aumento da ativação músculo gastrocnêmio lateral direito na flexão de tronco após o treinamento. Não encontrou-se diferenças na ativação muscular entre os dois tipos de intervenção. Conclusão: Os protocolos cinesioterapia e reabilitação virtual foram eficazes na melhora do equilíbrio e na capacidade funcional de idosos caidores, não havendo diferenças entre os dois tipos de intervenção</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137671</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160036</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 4 (2016); 191-196</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137671/133328</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137671/133329</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137672</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-24T12:14:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A multidisciplinaridade na redução da levodopa na pessoa com doença de Parkinson avançada</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Multidisciplinarity in reducing levodopa in person with advanced Parkinson’s disease</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Yamaguchi, Bruna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Manoela de Paula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Israel, Vera Lúcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doença de Parkinson</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapias Complementares</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Levodopa</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Parkinson Disease</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Complementary Therapies</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Levodopa</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To identify and compare people with Parkinson Disease (PD) doing multidisciplinary activities with those who do not realize. Method: Participants were evaluated for the Hoehn and Yahr (HY) (1-4), age, daily dose of levodopa, what activities they participate in and quality of life (PDQ-39), UPDRS activities of daily living and motor (UPDRS). They compared participants and non-practicing multidisciplinary activities stratifying the levels of HY between those with balance deficit (levels 3 and 4 HY), and those who do not have balance problems (levels 1 and 2 HY). Results: Attended by 49 participants of both genders (21 women, 28 men), these 17 do not participate in other therapies and 32 perform at least one multidisciplinary activity. There were no differences between groups participants and non-participating multidisciplinary activities. However, when stratifying the levels of HY, we realized that there was a statistical difference at the highest level of HY, the daily dose prescribed levodopa, between participants and non-participating multidisciplinary activities (P=0.017). Conclusions: The finding points that for this group of people with PD, with greater severity of PD, those who practice multidisciplinary activities need a statistically lower dose of levodopa</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Identificar e comparar as pessoas com Doença de Parkinson (DP) que fazem atividades multidisciplinares com aqueles que não fazem. Método: Os participantes foram avaliados quanto ao estadiamento Hoehn e Yahr (HY) (1-4), idade, dose diária de levodopa, que atividades que participa, qualidade de vida (PDQ-39), atividade de vida diária e motor (UPDRS). Eles compararam os participantes e não participantes de atividades multidisciplinares quanto a estratificação dos níveis de HY entre aqueles com déficit de equilíbrio (níveis 3 e 4 HY), e aqueles que não têm problemas de equilíbrio (níveis 1 e 2 HY). Resultados: Avaliados 49 participantes de ambos os sexos (21 mulheres, 28 homens), destes 17 não participam de terapias multidisciplinares e 32 realizam pelo menos uma atividade interdisciplinar. Não houve diferenças entre os grupos. No entanto, ao estratificar os níveis de HY, percebemos que houve uma diferença estatística no nível de HY mais elevado quanto a dose diária de levodopa prescrita, entre participantes e não participantes de atividades multidisciplinares (P = 0,017). Conclusões: O achado aponta que para esse grupo de pessoas com maior gravidade da DP, que praticam atividades multidisciplinares precisam de dose de levodopa estatisticamente menor</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137672</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160037</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 4 (2016); 197-200</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137672/133330</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137672/133331</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137673</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T20:10:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Forças de reação ao solo durante a marcha de pacientes com linfedema de membro inferior</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Ground reaction force patterns during gait in patients with lower limb lymphedema</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Forner-Cordero, Isabel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Furtado, Fabianne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cervera-Deval, Juan</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Forner-Cordero, Arturo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Lymphedema</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Lower Extremity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Obesity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Linfedema</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Extremidade Inferior</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Obesidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Although gait problems have been reported in patients with lower limb lymphedema (LLL), the gait pattern (GP) changes have not been documented yet. However, it is possible that patients with LLL show abnormal GP that can be related to biomechanical complications related to osteoarthritis or falls affecting the quality of life. Ground reaction force analysis during gait allows objective assessment of the patients and it can be used to plan a rehabilitation approach. Objective: To analyze the GRF during gait in patients LLL. Methods: An experimental descriptive study was realized with twenty-three LLL patients, both unilateral and bilateral and classified as moderate and severe, participated in the experiments. The patients walked on a force plate while the three ground reaction force (GRF) components, vertical, mediolateral (M-L) and anteroposterior (A-P), under their feet were recorded and analyzed. Results: In the patients with unilateral lymphedema, either moderate or severe, the vertical GRF components of the affected limb were similar to the sound one and also resembling those found in healthy adults. The M-L GRF was smaller in the non-affected side. In patients with bilateral lymphedema gait speed was significantly slower. More interestingly, the vertical GRF pattern was flat, not showing the typical 2-peak shape. Finally, the large M-L forces found suggest gait stability problems. Conclusions: The patients showed abnormal GRF patterns, including compensation with the non-affected leg. The GRF variability was higher in the patients with severe unilateral lymphedema. Bilateral lymphedema results in lower A-P forces. Stance phase duration was longer in patients with bilateral and severe lymphedema</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137673</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160038</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 4 (2016); 201-207</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137673/133332</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137674</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T20:18:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Análise do desenvolvimento psicomotor e nível de atividade física de crianças em atividades físicas extracurriculares</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Analysis of psychomotor development and level of physical activity of children with extracurricular physical activities</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Prado, Maria Tereza Artero</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Masset, Thais</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fernani, Deborah Cristina Gonçalves Luiz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Veríssimo, Caroline Mariana Albertin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Romanini, Maelis de Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Talita Dias da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alvarez, Mayra Priscila Boscolo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Monteiro, Carlos Bandeira de Mello</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividade Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos Psicomotores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Psychomotor Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Avaliar o desenvolvimento psicomotor nas áreas de habilidades motoras globais, equilíbrio e estrutura corporal e nível de atividade extracurricular escolar. Método: A amostra foi constituída por 30 indivíduos de ambos os sexos de 6 a 10 anos de idade, divididos em dois grupos: Grupo Extracurricular Ativo e Grupo Extracurricular Sedentário. A coleta de dados incluiu a caracterização dos sujeitos, os dados antropométricos e os testes Development Scale Motor e a versão curta do IPAQ. As variáveis ​​foram expressas em frequências e proporções, sendo o teste de Shapiro-Wilk utilizado e o teste t de Student para determinar a significância estatística. Quanto aos dados não normais, utilizou-se o teste de Mann Whitney, que foi considerado estatisticamente significativo p &amp;lt;0,05. Resultados: Mostraram que a classificação de IMC / idade de ambos os grupos foi eutrófica (53,3%) e o restante (46,6%) apresentou sobrepeso. O grupo sedentário apresentou melhores resultados no desenvolvimento motor global, e o grupo ativo no esquema do equilíbrio e do corpo. Conclusão: As crianças que realizam atividade extracurricular apresentaram melhor desenvolvimento de equilíbrio e estrutura corporal, quando comparadas com aquelas que não o fizeram.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: The objective was to evaluate the psychomotor development in the areas of global motor skills, balance and body structure and level of school extracurricular physical activity. Method: The sample consisted of 30 individuals of both sexes from 6 to 10 years old, divided into two groups: Active Extracurricular Group and Sedentary Extracurricular Group. Data collection included the characterization of the subjects, anthropometric data, and the tests Development Scale Motor and the IPAQ short version. The variables were expressed as frequencies and proportions, the normality was tested with the Shapiro-Wilk test. Student t test was used to determine the statistical significance of normal data and Mann Whitney test for the non-normal data. Statistical significance was set at p0.05. Results: The classification of BMI / age of both groups was eutrophic (53.3%) and the remainder (46.6%) were overweight. The sedentary group had better results in overall motor development, and the active group in balance and body scheme. Conclusion: The children who engage in extracurricular physical activity showed better development in balance and body structure, when compared to those that do not</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137674</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 4 (2016); 208-212</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137674/133333</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/137691</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-02T14:58:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A força muscular corrigida pela massa corporal é um preditor melhor da baixa função física do que a força muscular absoluta em mulheres na pós-menopausa</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Muscle strength to body weight ratio is a better predictor of low physical function than absolute muscle strength in postmenopausal women</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Aletéia de Paula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martins, Fernanda Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carneiro, Marcelo Augusto da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nunes, Paulo Ricardo Prado</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Erick Prado de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Orsat, Fábio Lera</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aging</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Obesity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Mobility Limitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Envelhecimento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Obesidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Limitação da Mobilidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Correlacionar a força muscular respiratória e a capacidade funcional em pacientes com FC. Métodos: Estudo transversal em adultos com fibrose cística. Os dados amostrais foram catalogados no Microsoft Office Excel 2007 e as variáveis analisadas pelo SPSS versão 20.0 através do teste t de Student e do coeficiente de Spearman. O nível de significância adotado foi p &amp;lt; 0,05. Resultados: Foram avaliados 35 pacientes com fibrose cística (44,6 ± 19,0 anos), grande parte dos pacientes de FC (n=26) não apresentaram fraqueza da musculatura inspiratória (PImáx -90,7 ± 27,4 cmH2O). Não foi encontrada estatística significativa apenas entre os pacientes adultos e idosos. Houve correlação positiva entre PImáx, PEmáx e teste de caminhada de 6 minutos (TC6) nos participantes com fraqueza muscular respiratória e nos idosos. Houve diferença estatisticamente significativa entre as médias da distância percorrida no TC6 e das pressões respiratórias máximas com a média do que foi previsto para estas variáveis. Conclusão: Todos os grupos apresentaram limitação da força respiratória e da capacidade funcional. As correlações entre as pressões respiratórias com o TC6 foram baixas e pequenas nos adultos e indivíduos sem fraqueza muscular respiratória; moderadas à alta nos idosos; pequenas à moderada nas mulheres; pequenas e negativas nos homens; e, altas naqueles com fraqueza muscular respiratória.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To correlate the respiratory muscle strength and functional capacity in patients with CF. Method: Cross-sectional study in adults with cystic fibrosis. Sampling data were cataloged in Microsoft Office Excel 2007 and the variables analyzed by SPSS version 20.0 using the Student t test and the Spearman coefficient. The level of significance adopted was p &amp;lt; 0.05. Results: We assessed 35 patients with cystic fibrosis (44.6 ± 19.0 years), the great majority of patients in FC (n=22) did not present weakness of the inspiratory muscles (MIP -90,7 ± 27.4 cmH2O). It was not found statistically significant differences only between the adult and elderly patients. There was a positive correlation between MIP and MEP and a six-minute walk test (6MWT) in participants with respiratory muscle weakness and in the elderly. There was statistically significant difference between the averages of the distance covered on the 6MWT and the maximal respiratory pressures with the average of what was envisaged for these variables. Conclusion: All groups presented limitation of respiratory strength and functional capacity. The correlations between the respiratory pressures with the 6MWT were low and small in adults and individuals without respiratory muscle weakness; moderate to high in the elderly; small to moderate in women; small and negative in men; and high in patients with respiratory muscle weakness.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2016-12-29</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137691</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20160040</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 23 n. 4 (2016); 213-218</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/137691/133349</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2016 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/144575</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-25T20:17:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Prevalence of mobility impairment in institucionalized elderly</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevalência de dificuldade de locomoção em idosos institucionalizados</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Giaquini, Franciane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lini, Ezequiel Vitório</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Doring, Marlene</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Locomoção</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Instituição de Longa Permanência para Idosos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Locomotion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Homes for the Elderly</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Identificar a prevalência de dificuldade de locomoção em idosos institucionalizados e sua correlação com o perfil clínico-funcional, realizou-se um estudo transversal com 191 pessoas com idade ≥ 60 anos residentes em 13 instituições de longa permanência para idosos de Passo Fundo, no ano de 2014. Método: Utilizou-se um questionário estruturado, aplicado aos idosos ou aos responsáveis técnicos das instituições. Foram contempladas variáveis sociodemográficas, relacionadas à saúde e questões específicas sobre dificuldades na deambulação. Considerou-se dificuldade de locomoção a necessidade de qualquer ajuda ou apoio para caminhar, seja bengala, andador ou mesmo restrição ao leito. Realizou-se análise descritiva e bivariada dos dados. Para verificar a associação entre as variáveis categóricas foram aplicados os testes qui-quadrado de Pearson e exato de Fisher a um nível de significância de 5%. Resultados: A prevalência de dificuldade de locomoção foi de 50,3%. Utilizavam cadeira de rodas 41,7%, acamados 24%, andador 16,7%, bengala 14,6% e muletas 3,1%. Dos idosos com dificuldade de locomoção, 89,6% eram dependentes para as atividades básicas de vida diária e 62,5% consideraram sua saúde como regular, ruim ou muito ruim. Conclusão: A alta prevalência de dificuldade de locomoção, inclusive com muitos idosos restritos ao leito, alerta para a necessidade de intervenções preventivas antes da institucionalização e a minimização das complicações que estas condições podem trazer.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To identify the prevalence of mobility impairment in institutionalized elderly people and its correlation with the clinical and functional conditions, a cross-sectional study was carried out with 191 people aged ≥ 60 years residing in 13 long-stay institutions for the elderly in Passo Fundo, year of 2014. Method: A structured questionnaire was used, applied to the elderly or to the technical managers of the institutions. Sociodemographic variables related to health and specific questions about walking difficulties were considered. It was considered mobility impairment the need of any help or aid to walk, be it a cane, a walker or even restriction to bed. A descriptive and bivariate analysis of the data was performed. To verify the association between the categorical variables Pearson’s chi-square test and Fisher’s exact test were applied at a significance level of 5%. Results: The prevalence of mobility impairment was 50.3%. They used wheelchairs 41.7%, walkers 16.7%, canes 14.6% and crutches 3.1% and were bedridden 24%. Of the elderly with mobility impairment, 89.6% were dependent to perform daily living basic activities and 62.5% considered their health as fair, poor or very poor. Conclusion: The high prevalence of mobility impairment, including many bedridden elderly people, highlights the need for preventive interventions before institutionalization and the minimization of the complications that these conditions can bring.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144575</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20170001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 24 n. 1 (2017); 1-6</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144575/138878</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144575/138879</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2017 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/144576</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-23T17:43:14Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da funcionalidade e qualidade de vida em pacientes críticos: série de casos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of functionality and quality of life in critical patients: case series report</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wiethan, Jéssica Rosa Vargas</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Soares, Janice Cristina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Juliana Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Unidades de Terapia Intensiva</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Recuperação de Função Fisiológica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Modalidades de Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Intensive Care Units</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Recovery of Function</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy Modalities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A hospitalização em Unidade de Terapia Intensiva (UTI), geralmente resulta em declínio funcional e da qualidade de vida. Riscos de sequelas a longo prazo decorrem de fatores relacionados a doença, tratamento realizado e repouso no leito. Objetivo: Avaliar a funcionalidade e qualidade de vida de pacientes que realizaram fisioterapia durante a internação na UTI e correlacionar essas variáveis após 30 dias de alta. Métodos: Foi realizado um estudo descritivo, do tipo série de casos com 15 pacientes. Avaliou-se a funcionalidade pela Medida de Independência Funcional-MIF (antes da UTI, após alta e após 30 dias) e a qualidade de vida pelo questionário SF-36 (após 30 dias). Resultados: A média de idade da amostra foi de 43,20±16,92 anos, predominaram causas de internação neurológicas, o tempo de ventilação mecânica foi de 14(9-14) dias e de UTI 15,80±7,16 dias, todos pacientes apresentaram complicações durante a internação. A avaliação de funcionalidade mostrou que antes da UTI os indivíduos possuíam nível de independência completa a modificada (MIF=126), após a alta houve um declínio para dependência modificada (MIF=48) e após 30 dias houve melhora da funcionalidade, mas ainda compreendendo dependência modificada (MIF=92). Os domínios de funcionalidade autocuidado, mobilidade e locomoção tiveram maiores alterações após a UTI e uma melhora significativa aos 30 dias, controle de esfíncteres, comunicação e cognição social tiveram menores alterações após a UTI e nos 30 dias seguintes os valores se aproximaram aos prévios. A qualidade de vida foi afetada no decorrer de 30 dias, o que foi observado pelos baixos escores em todos os domínios, quando comparados ao valor total que poderia ser alcançado e os domínios mais comprometidos foram capacidade funcional, limitação por aspectos físicos, dor e aspectos sociais. Ao correlacionar os domínios da MIF e SF-36, destacaram-se principalmente as correlações positivas entre os domínios controle de esfíncteres, locomoção e mobilidade (funcionalidade) e capacidade funcional (qualidade de vida). Conclusão: A internação em UTI afetou negativamente a funcionalidade, principalmente na alta imediata. Após 30 dias, houve uma melhora, o que em partes, pode-se atribuir à fisioterapia, já que todos os pacientes receberam este tipo de tratamento durante a estadia na UTI e grande parte deles continuou a realizar apósa alta. Entretanto, alguns déficits ainda permaneceram, comprometendo também, a qualidade de vida.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Hospitalization in Intensive Care Unit (ICU) usually results in decreased functionality and quality of life. Risk long-term sequelae may result from factors related to disease, treatment performed and time staying in bed. Objective: To evaluate the functionality and quality of life of patients who received physiotherapy in the ICU and correlate these variables after 30 days of discharge. Methods: A case series report study was conducted with 15 patients. Evaluation of functionality by the Functional Independence Measure - FIM (before ICU, at immediate release and after 30 days), evaluation of quality of life by Short-Form (SF-36) Health Survey (after 30 days). Results: The mean age was 43.20 ± 16.92 years, predominant causes of hospitalization were neurological, mechanical ventilation time was 14 (9-14) days and ICU 15.80 ± 7.16 days and all had complications. Before the ICU the patients were with full or modified independence (FIM 1=126), after discharge there was a decline to modified dependence (FIM 2=48) and after 30 days there was improvement, but functionality continued as modified dependence (FIM 3=92). The functionality areas like self-care, mobility and locomotion had major changes after the ICU and a significant improvement at 30 days; sphincter control, communication and social cognition had minor changes after the ICU and after 30 days the values approached the previous ones. The quality of life was affected 30 days after discharge with reduction in scores for all areas, the most affected ones were functional capacity, limitation by physical aspects, pain and social aspects. There were positive correlations between the areas of sphincters control, mobility and mobility (functionality) and functional capacity (quality of life). Conclusion: ICU negatively affected the functionality, especially at immediate release. After 30 days, there was an improvement, in part, that can be attributed to physical therapy, because all patients received this treatment in the ICU and many continued it after discharge. However, some deficits still remained, also affecting their quality of life.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144576</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20170002</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 24 n. 1 (2017); 7-12</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144576/138880</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144576/138881</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2017 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/144577</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-23T19:36:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Caracterização do paciente acometido por acidente vascular encefálico atendido no Centro de Reabilitação Lucy Montoro de São José dos Campos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Characterization of patients with stroke treated at Lucy Montoro Rehabilitation Center of São José dos Campos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dias, Karina Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Duarte, Maria Angélica Nader Miranda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Nathália Borloni</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Maria Izabel Romão</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nogueira, Maria Angélica Ratier Jajah</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Centros de Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epidemiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation Centers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Vascular Accident (CVA) is the neurological event that most affects society in recent years, causing disabilities in the population and death. It can be defined as a set of neurological disorders causing similar symptoms, but with different etiologies. Currently, Lucy Montoro Rehabilitation Center of São José dos Campos is a reference in the treatment of patients neurologically squealed. Thus, the aim of this study was to make an epidemiological survey of the profile of patients affected by CVA in this region and seen at this center. Methods: The records of patients received in this center between September 2011 and December 2014 were used during this research. Patients with hemiplegia caused by other etiologies were not analyzed. Results: Of the 230 valid records for the study, 60% were men and the socio-demographic profile showed that of these, 76% were older than 50 years. Considering the type of event, ischemic stroke was the most prevalent in our sample. It was found the same involvement of body parts affected, right and left 46% and 8% classified into double hemiparesis, since the prevailing motor pattern of the sample was paresis 87%. Conclusion: It was found that the population served by Lucy Montoro Rehabilitation Center of SJC consists most of men above 50 years of age affected by ischemic stroke (right or left) and prevalent paretic motor pattern.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O Acidente Vascular Encefálico (AVE) é o evento neurológico que mais acomete a sociedade nos últimos anos, gerando incapacidades na população e morte. Pode ser definido como um conjunto de afecções neurológicas de causa vascular com sintomatologia semelhante, mas com etiologias diferentes. Atualmente o Centro de Reabilitação Lucy Montoro de São José dos Campos é referência no tratamento de pacientes com lesões neurológicas do Vale do Paraíba. Objetivo: Realizar um levantamento epidemiológico do perfil dos pacientes acometidos pelo AVE na região e atendidos neste centro. Métodos: Foram analisados os prontuários dos pacientes recebidos neste centro entre setembro de 2011 e dezembro de 2014. Foram excluídos pacientes com hemiplegia causada por outras etiologias. Resultados: Dos 230 prontuários válidos para o estudo, 60% eram homens e o perfil sócio demográfico mostrou que destes, 76% tinham idade superior a 50 anos. Tratando-se do tipo de evento, o AVE isquêmico foi o mais prevalente em nossa amostra. Foi constatada equivalência de acometimento da amostra, hemicorpos direito e esquerdo acometidos igualmente, 46% e 8 % classificados em dupla hemiparesia, já o padrão motor predominante da amostra foi de paresia 87%. Conclusão: Foi verificado que a população atendida pelo Centro de Reabilitação Lucy Montoro de SJC é constituída por maioria de homens acima dos 50 anos de idade, acometidos pelo AVE isquêmico (direito ou esquerdo) e com padrão motor parético prevalente.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144577</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20170003</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 24 n. 1 (2017); 13-16</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144577/138882</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144577/138883</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2017 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/144579</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-23T17:56:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores associados ao nível de atividade física de idosos usuários das academias da terceira idade</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Factors associated with physical activity level of elderly users of the third age gyms</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Daniel Vicentini de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Maria do Carmo Correia de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Contessoto, Luana Caroline</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cremonez, Jean Carlos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Antunes, Mateus Dias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nascimento Júnior, José Roberto Andrade do</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Promotion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fitness Centers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividade Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Promoção da Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Academias de Ginástica</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Analisar os fatores associados ao nível de atividade física de idosos usuários das Academias da Terceira Idade (ATIs). Método: Participaram 115 idosos de ambos os sexos, com média de idade de 67,5 anos (±6,42), usuários das ATIs. Foi utilizado um questionário sócio demográfico e o International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ). A análise dos resultados foi realizada mediante abordagem de estatística descritiva e inferencial por meio do teste Qui-quadrado de Pearson, com cálculo dos odds ratios brutos, análise de regressão logística binária, utilizando-se análise hierarquizada e um modelo final de regressão com cálculo dos odds ratios ajustado. Resultados: Foi encontrada associação significativa do nível de atividade física com o sexo (p=0,004), nível de escolaridade (p=0,048), percepção de saúde (p=0,046) e com a importância do exercício para a saúde (p&amp;lt;0,001). Ressalta-se que a mulheres apresentaram um fator de proteção de 0,262, ou seja, possuem 73,8% de chance a mais de serem ativas/muito ativas em comparação aos homens. Além disso, os idosos que possuem percepção de saúde boa/muito boa e que consideram o exercício como importante para a saúde apresentaram um fator de proteção de 0,276 e 0,097, respectivamente. Conclusão: Diante dos resultados obtidos, conclui-se o sexo feminino, a alta escolaridade, a percepção de boa saúde e o conhecimento da importância do exercício para a saúde estiveram associados ao nível ativo/muito ativo de atividades física nas ATIs.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: This study aimed to analyze the factors associated with the level of physical activity in older adults users of the Third Age Gyms (TAGs). Method: A total of 115 elderly people of both sexes participated, with mean age of 67.5 years (± 6.42), users of TAGs. A socio-demographic questionnaire and the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) were used. The analysis of the results was performed using a descriptive and inferential statistical approach using the Pearson Chi-square test, with gross odds ratios, binary logistic regression analysis, using a hierarchical analysis and a final regression model with the adjusted odds ratios. The analysis was made by means of descriptive and inferential statistics using Pearson's chi-square test, with calculation of odds gross ratios, binary logistic regression analysis, using hierarchical analysis and a final regression model to calculate the odds ratios adjusted. Results: There was a significant association between physical activity level with sex (p = 0.004), educational level (p = 0.048), perceived health (p = 0.046) and the importance of health to exercise (p &amp;lt;0.001). It is noteworthy that the women showed a 0.262 protection factor, have 73.8% chance of being the most active/very active compared to men. Also, seniors who have perception of good health/very good and consider exercise as important for the health showed a protection factor of 0.276 and 0.097 respectively. Conclusion: In conclusion, the female sex, the high level of education, the perception of good health and the knowledge of the importance of exercise for health were associated with the active/very active level of physical activities in the TAGs.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144579</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20170004</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 24 n. 1 (2017); 17-21</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144579/138884</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144579/138885</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2017 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/144580</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-23T19:39:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Higher body mass index and lower waist circumference are associated to higher physical performance (SPPB) solely in dynapenic elderly women</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Maior índice de massa corporal e menor circunferência da cintura estão associados com maior desempenho físico (SPPB) somente em idosas dinapênicas</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Biloria, Bruno Teodoro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Ana Alice Neves da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Aletéia de Paula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martins, Fernanda Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Anselmo Alves de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nunes, Paulo Ricardo Prado</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tavares, Darlene Mara dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Erick Prado de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Orsat, Fábio Lera</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sarcopenia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Mulheres</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividades Cotidianas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força da Mão</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sarcopenia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Women</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Activities of Daily Living</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hand Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Analisar o grau de incapacidade física na população idosa afetada pela hanseníase no estado da Bahia, entre 2001 e 2012. Métodos: Os dados referentes aos casos de hanseníase foram obtidos do Sistema Nacional de Agravos de Notificação. Variáveis analisadas: sexo, faixa etária, raça/cor, escolaridade, classificação clínica e operacional, grau de incapacidade física no diagnóstico e na alta. Foram calculados indicadores epidemiológicos relacionados à incapacidade física. Resultados: A hanseníase apresenta elevada magnitude na população idosa, com coeficiente de detecção de casos novos superior ao da população geral, situando-se em nível hiperendêmico. Quanto ao perfil epidemiológico da hanseníase em idosos, destaca-se: homens, faixa etária 60 a 69 anos, raça branca, baixa escolaridade, forma clínica dimorfa e classificação operacional multibacilar. 36,25% dos casos diagnosticados apresentavam incapacidade física no momento do diagnóstico, com destaque para o gênero masculino. Conclusão: A elevada proporção de indivíduos com incapacidades físicas no momento do diagnóstico sugere diagnóstico tardio e prevalência oculta da doença, sobretudo em indivíduos do gênero masculino.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To analyze the degree of physical disability in the elderly population affected by leprosy in Bahia State, between 2001 and 2012. Methods: The data relating to cases of leprosy was obtained from National System of Notifiable Diseases. Variables analyzed gender, age, race/color, education level, clinical and operational classification, degree of physical incapacity in diagnosis and discharge. Epidemiological indicators related to physical incapacity were calculated. Results: The leprosy features high magnitude in the elderly population, with a coefficient of detection of new cases higher than the general population, situated at a hyperendemic level. As to the epidemiological profile of leprosy in elderly, stands out: men, age 60 to 69 years, white race, low education level, dimorphic clinical manifestation and multibacillary operational classification. 36.25% of diagnosed cases had a physical incapacity at the time of diagnosis, with emphasis on the masculine gender. Conclusion: The high proportion of individuals with physical incapacity at the time of diagnosis suggests late diagnosis and hidden prevalence of the disease, mostly in Individuals of the male gender.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144580</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20170005</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 24 n. 1 (2017); 22-26</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144580/138886</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144580/138887</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2017 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/144581</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-23T19:49:32Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Physical disability degree in the elderly population affected by leprosy in the state of Bahia, Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Grau de incapacidade física na população idosa afetada pela hanseníase no estado da Bahia, Brasil</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Carlos Dornels Freire de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fernandes, Tania Rita Moreno de Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Matos, Thais Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro Filho, José Maurício</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Grayce Kelly Alencar de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Jefferson César Bezerra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Adriana Rodrigues Sousa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Antonelli, Bruna Ângela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Denilson José de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Leprosy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Immunity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disabled Persons</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hanseníase</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Imunidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pessoas com Deficiência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To analyze the degree of physical disability in the elderly population affected by leprosy in Bahia State, between 2001 and 2012. Methods: The data relating to cases of leprosy was obtained from National System of Notifiable Diseases. Variables analyzed gender, age, race/color, education level, clinical and operational classification, degree of physical incapacity in diagnosis and discharge. Epidemiological indicators related to physical incapacity were calculated. Results: The leprosy features high magnitude in the elderly population, with a coefficient of detection of new cases higher than the general population, situated at a hyperendemic level. As to the epidemiological profile of leprosy in elderly, stands out: men, age 60 to 69 years, white race, low education level, dimorphic clinical manifestation and multibacillary operational classification. 36.25% of diagnosed cases had a physical incapacity at the time of diagnosis, with emphasis on the masculine gender. Conclusion: The high proportion of individuals with physical incapacity at the time of diagnosis suggests late diagnosis and hidden prevalence of the disease, mostly in Individuals of the male gender.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Analisar o grau de incapacidade física na população idosa afetada pela hanseníase no estado da Bahia, entre 2001 e 2012. Métodos: Os dados referentes aos casos de hanseníase foram obtidos do Sistema Nacional de Agravos de Notificação. Variáveis analisadas: sexo, faixa etária, raça/cor, escolaridade, classificação clínica e operacional, grau de incapacidade física no diagnóstico e na alta. Foram calculados indicadores epidemiológicos relacionados à incapacidade física. Resultados: A hanseníase apresenta elevada magnitude na população idosa, com coeficiente de detecção de casos novos superior ao da população geral, situando-se em nível hiperendêmico. Quanto ao perfil epidemiológico da hanseníase em idosos, destaca-se: homens, faixa etária 60 a 69 anos, raça branca, baixa escolaridade, forma clínica dimorfa e classificação operacional multibacilar. 36,25% dos casos diagnosticados apresentavam incapacidade física no momento do diagnóstico, com destaque para o gênero masculino. Conclusão: A elevada proporção de indivíduos com incapacidades físicas no momento do diagnóstico sugere diagnóstico tardio e prevalência oculta da doença, sobretudo em indivíduos do gênero masculino.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144581</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20170006</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 24 n. 1 (2017); 27-32</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144581/138888</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144581/138889</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2017 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/144583</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-23T19:04:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Physiotherapy in severe polytrauma patients: a therapeutic care model</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisioterapia nos pacientes politraumatizados graves: modelo de assistência terapêutica</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Padovani, Cauê</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Janete Maria da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tanaka, Clarice</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Trauma Centers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Intensive Care Units</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Wounds and Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy Modalities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Centros de Traumatologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Unidades de Terapia Intensiva</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ferimentos e Lesões</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Modalidades de Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia por Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: In view of the high degree of complexity that the polytrauma patient represents to the multiprofessional team in the elaboration and execution of their care plan in the intensive care unit (ICU), combined with the lack of evidence on the subject, this study suggests a model of early physiotherapeutic assistance to critical polytrauma patients based on the clinical experience of recent years. Method: The model was elaborated based on the practices verified in the records of 6,388 physiotherapy sessions performed in 198 patients hospitalized between December 2009 and September 2011 in polytraumas-specialized ICU. The activities/care were inserted in the model after approved in discussion with the multiprofessional team. All patients enrolled were aged 18 years or older and were victims of severe trauma according to the Injury Severity Score (ISS). Results: The proposed model was structured in such a way that the physical therapy activities/ care were organized according to the injured body region (traumatic brain injury, face fractures, spine fractures, thoracic trauma, abdominal trauma, pelvic fracture and extremities fractures). The routine of the ICU encouraged daily discussions with the medical team to know the particularities of each clinical case, to establish therapeutic goal and to design the rehabilitation program. Conclusion: The proposed model became routine and consolidated the physiotherapeutic action in the respective care unit. The physiotherapy team started working 24 hours a day. The model made possible the standardization of physical therapy assistance and greater safety for the severe polytrauma patient.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Conhecendo-se o alto grau de complexidade que o paciente politraumatizado representa à equipe multiprofissional na elaboração e execução do seu plano assistencial na unidade de terapia intensiva (UTI), aliado à carência de evidencias sobre o tema, o presente estudo sugere um modelo de assistência fisioterapêutica precoce aos pacientes críticos politraumatizados com base na experiência clínica dos últimos anos. Método: O modelo foi elaborado a partir das práticas verificadas nos registros de 6388 sessões de fisioterapia realizadas em 198 pacientes internados entre dezembro de 2009 e setembro de 2011 em UTI especializada em politrauma. As atividades/ cuidados foram inseridas no modelo após aprovadas em discussão com a equipe multiprofissional. Todos os pacientes atendidos tinham idade igual ou maior que 18 anos e eram vítimas de trauma grave de acordo com o Injury Severity Score (ISS). Resultados: O modelo proposto foi estruturado de forma que as atividades/cuidados da assistência fisioterapêutica fossem organizadas de acordo com a região corpórea lesada do paciente (traumatismo cranioencefálico, fraturas de face, fraturas de coluna, trauma torácico, trauma abdominal, fratura de pelve e fraturas de extremidades). A rotina da unidade apregoava discussões diárias com a equipe médica para se conhecer as particularidades de cada caso clínico, estabelecer meta terapêutica e traçar o programa de reabilitação. Conclusão: O modelo proposto se tornou rotina e consolidou a atuação fisioterapêutica na respectiva unidade assistencial. A equipe de fisioterapia passou a atuar 24 horas por dia. O modelo possibilitou padronização da assistência fisioterapêutica e maior segurança para o paciente politraumatizado grave.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144583</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20170007</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 24 n. 1 (2017); 33-39</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144583/138890</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144583/138891</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2017 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/144584</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-23T19:59:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Secondary hyperalgesia in chronic nonspecific low back pain</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Hiperalgesia secundária na lombalgia crônica inespecífica</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Alfieri, Fabio Marcon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bernardo, Karoline Mayara de Aquiles</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hyperalgesia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Low Back Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pain Measurement</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hiperalgesia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor Lombar</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medição da Dor</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Secondary hyperalgesia may be present in chronic nonspecific low back pain. The study compared pressure pain threshold (PPT) in the lumbar and thoracic paravertebral muscles in individuals with non-specific chronic low back pain correlating them with disability, functional mobility, age and body mass index. Method: This is a cross-sectional study involving individuals of both sexes diagnosed with non-specific chronic low back pain, aged between 18 and 65 years, with pain of moderate to severe intensity and with pain time of ≥ 12 weeks. The volunteers were evaluated for pain intensity through the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), disability by the Roland Morris questionnaire, functional mobility by the Timed Up and Go test, and pressure pain threshold (PPT) by algometry. We used the t-test and made Pearson’s correlation for data analysis that was done in the Graph Pad Instat program. Results: Fifty individuals (53.75 ± 13.65 years) participated in the study, and when comparing PPT values between the thoracic and lumbar regions, no significant difference was observed (p = 0.19). Moderate correlation was observed only between lumbar and thoracic PPT (r = 0.65). Other correlations, though some significant, were all weak. Conclusion: The data from this study allow us to conclude that individuals with chronic low back pain may present with secondary hyperalgesia, since the individuals presented similar values between the lumbar and thoracic PPTs, in addition to having a significant correlation between these two measures.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: A hiperalgesia secundária pode estar presente na lombalgia crônica inespecífica. O estudo comparou o limiar de tolerância de dor à pressão (LTDP) nos músculos paravertebrais lombares e torácicos em indivíduos com lombalgia crônica inespecífica correlacionando-as com a incapacidade, mobilidade funcional, idade e índice de massa corporal. Método: Trata-se de um estudo transversal no qual participam indivíduos de ambos os sexos diagnosticados com lombalgia crônica não específica, com idade entre 18 a 65 anos, possuindo dor de intensidade moderada a grave e com o tempo de dor de ≥ 12 semanas. Os voluntários foram avaliados em relação a intensidade da dor por meio da Escala Visual Analógica (EVA), incapacidade pelo questionário Roland Morris, mobilidade funcional pelo teste Timed Up and Go e limiar de tolerância de à dor à pressão (LTDP) pela algometria. Foram usados o teste t e feita Correlação de Pearson para análise dos dados que foi feita no programa Graph Pad Instat. Resultados: Participaram do estudo, 50 indivíduos (53,75±13,65 anos) e quando comparados os valores de LTDP entre a região torácica e lombar não foi verificada diferença significativa (p=0,19). Foi observada correlação moderada apenas entre o LTDP lombar e torácica (r=0,65). Outras correlações embora algumas significantes, todas foram fracas. Conclusão: Os dados deste estudo permitem concluir que provavelmente indivíduos com lombalgia crônica apresentam hiperalgesia secundária, pois os indivíduos apresentaram valores semelhantes entre o LTDP lombares e torácicas, além de apresentar correlação significante entre estas duas medidas.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20170008</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 24 n. 1 (2017); 40-43</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144584/138892</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144584/138893</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2017 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/144585</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-09-23T20:02:53Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Intensive hospital rehabilitation model for patients with stroke in a developing country</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Modelo de reabilitação hospitalar após acidente vascular cerebral em país em desenvolvimento</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Filippo, Thais Raquel Martins</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alfieri, Fabio Marcon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Daniel, Christiane Riedi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Daniel Rubio de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Serviços de Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pacientes Internados</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação de Resultados (Cuidados de Saúde)</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation Services</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Inpatients</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Outcome Assessment (Health Care)</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Intensive rehabilitation services with standardized treatment for stroke survivors are desirable once they contribute to the patients' functional improvement even in facilities with restricted financial resources. Objective: To verify whether the stroke program at our public inpatient Rehabilitation Center contributes to improvements in functional outcome. Method: This is a retrospective cross-sectional study of the first and last 100 neurological patients (2009-2010 and 2014-2015) admitted at the Lucy Montoro Rehabilitation Network (Morumbi Unit). For this study, the patients were analyzed at admission and at discharge by the modified Rankin Scale (mRS). After testing for normality, an unpaired t-test was on the patients' clinical and demographic characteristics. Intragroup analysis was performed by the nonparametric Wilcoxon test. The intergroup analysis used the Mann-Whitney nonparametric test. Functional outcome scores &amp;lt; 3 at discharge were considered favorable. Results: The modified Rankin Scores (mRS) were assessed just before the initiation of the therapies and at the patients' discharge. Median mRS score at admission was 4 compared to 3 at discharge (p=0.0001), after 4 to 6 weeks in the stroke program. Conclusions: Short term, standardized intensive rehabilitation program with multidisciplinary therapies, in which the patient remains hospitalized, promote functional improvements of patients with stroke sequelae.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Os serviços de reabilitação intensiva para os sobreviventes de acidente vascular cerebral (AVC) com tratamento padronizado são desejáveis porque esses programas de reabilitação contribuem para a melhoria funcional em contextos com menos recursos. Objetivo: Verificar se o programa de reabilitação hospitalar contribui para a melhora da funcionalidade em indivíduos com sequela de AVC. Método: Trata-se de um estudo transversal retrospectivo dos primeiros (2009-2010) e últimos 100 (2014-2015) pacientes neurológicos consecutivos admitidos na Rede de Reabilitação Lucy Montoro (Unidade Morumbi). Para esta análise, os pacientes foram analisados no dia da admissão e no dia de alta, utilizando a Escala de Rankin modificada (mRS). Para a comparação dos resultados foi utilizado o teste t para amostras independentes. A análise intragrupal com base no mRS foi realizada com o teste não paramétrico de Wilcoxon. Por outro lado, a análise intergrupos utilizou o teste não paramétrico de MannWhitney. O nível de significância para todos os testes estatísticos foi p &amp;lt;0,05. Os resultados funcionais ≤ 3 na alta foram considerados favoráveis. Resultados: As Pontuações de Rankin modificadas (mRS) foram avaliadas imediatamente antes do início das terapias e na alta dos pacientes. O escore mRS mediano na admissão foi de 4 e 3 no momento da alta (p=0,0001), após 4 a 6 semanas no programa de AVC para ambos os grupos. Conclusão: O modelo de admissão em um serviço de reabilitação hospitalar que inclui terapias multidisciplinares promove ganhos funcionais em indivíduos com sequelas de AVC e ressaltase que esses ganhos são obtidos em um curto espaço de tempo.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144585</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20170009</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 24 n. 1 (2017); 44-47</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144585/138894</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144585/138895</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2017 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/144586</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-25T20:12:50Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Eficácia de intervenções para a melhora da resistência muscular em idosos: revisão sistemática de literatura</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effectiveness of interventions in the improvement of muscle resistance in the elderly: a systematic review</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Luiz, Gesylâine Marques</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Faria, Christina Danielli Coelho de Morais</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Resistance Training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Fatigue</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Treinamento de Resistência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fadiga Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Global population aging has been much discussed in the last decade. China, Japan, and countries in Europe and North America have long lived with a large contingent of elderly people and all the problems associated with this aging process. However, the Brazilian elderly population, more specifically the female population, has been growing rapidly: the aging process in Brazil is occurring in a short period of time. With aging, loss of skeletal muscle mass as a whole is common. The impairment of muscle strength in the elderly individual is evident, since the loss of type II fibers is greater than type I. However, loss of type I muscle fibers also occurs during aging, and therefore, characteristics related to this type of fiber, such as muscular endurance, should also be considered by health professionals. Objective: The primary objective of this study was to perform a systematic review of the literature to determine the efficacy of intervention programs in improving muscular endurance in the elderly. The secondary objective was to evaluate the efficacy of these programs in improving other functional and health outcomes in this population. Method: Systematic review of literature based on the Prisma protocol (Pre- sent Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta- Analyzes), with searches in the MEDLINE, PEDro, LILACS and SCIELO databases, using a specific search strategy involving descriptors related to the elderly And muscular endurance. We included studies published in Portuguese and English, of the quasi-experimental (EQ) or randomized clinical trial (RCT), which involved elderly individuals and approached the skeletal muscles of lower limbs, upper limbs or trunk, and evaluated the efficacy of interventions for Improvement of muscular endurance. Results: A total of 133 studies were found with the electronic search. Of these, only 13 met the inclusion criteria, being 7 RCTs and 6 QE. The mean score obtained by the RCTs on the PEDro scale was 5.57, while the mean score obtained by the TRENDs was 18.57. Among the seven RCTs, all were classified as having adequate methodological quality. Conclusion: According to the results of most of the included studies, intervention programs elaborated according to the specific characteristics of the muscular endurance concept are effective in improving muscular endurance and other functional and health outcomes of healthy elderly. Further studies are needed to investigate the efficacy of interventions aimed at improving the muscular endurance of elderly individuals who have some associated health condition or specific disability.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O envelhecimento populacional mundial vem sendo muito discutido na última década. China, Japão e países da Europa e da América do Norte já convivem há muito tempo com um grande contingente de idosos e com todos os problemas associados a este processo de envelhecimento. Porém, a população idosa brasileira, mais especificamente a feminina, vem crescendo de forma acelerada: o processo de envelhecimento no Brasil está ocorrendo em um curto período de tempo. Com o envelhecimento, é comum a perda da massa muscular esquelética como um todo. O comprometimento da força muscular no indivíduo idoso é evidente, uma vez que a perda de fibras do tipo II é maior do que do tipo I. Entretanto, a perda de fibras musculares do tipo I também ocorre durante o envelhecimento e, portanto, características relacionadas a este tipo de fibra, como a resistência muscular, também devem ser consideradas pelos profissionais da área da saú- de. Objetivo: Realizar uma revisão sistemática da literatura para determinar a eficácia de programas de intervenção na melhora da resistência muscular em idosos. O objetivo secundário foi avaliar a eficácia destes programas na melhora de outros desfechos funcionais e de saúde nesta população. Método: Revisão sistemática de literatura elaborada conforme o protocolo Prisma (Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses), com buscas nas bases de dados MEDLINE, PEDro, LILACS e SCIELO, utilizando-se estratégia de busca específica envolvendo descritores relacionados a idoso e resistência muscular. Foram incluídos estudos publicados em português e inglês, do tipo quase-experimental (QE) ou ensaio clinico aleatorizado (ECA), que envolveram idosos e abordaram a musculatura esquelética de membros inferiores, superiores ou tronco, e que avaliaram a eficácia de intervenções para a melhora da resistência muscular. Resultados: Foi encontrado um total de 133 estudos com a busca eletrônica. Destes, apenas 13 atenderam aos critérios de inclusão, sendo 7 ECA e 6 QE. A média da pontuação obtida pelos ECA na escala PEDro foi de 5,57, enquanto a média obtida pelos QE na escala TREND foi de 18,57. Dentre os sete ECA, todos foram classificados como tendo adequada qualidade metodológica. Conclusão: Segundo os resultados da maioria dos estudos incluídos, os programas de intervenções elaborados seguindo as características específicas do conceito de resistência muscular são eficazes para melhora da resistência muscular e de outros desfechos de funcionalidade e de saúde de idosos saudáveis. São necessários mais estudos que investiguem a eficácia de intervenções direcionadas para a melhora da resistência muscular de idosos que apresentam alguma condição de saúde associada ou incapacidade específica.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2017-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144586</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20170010</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 24 n. 1 (2017); 48-55</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144586/138896</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/144586/138897</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2017 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2023-08-08T14:49:29Z" completeListSize="935" cursor="600">79b20f2c404470af00da71972d93dc73</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
