<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-08-07T14:49:04Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="actafisiatrica">https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102576</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:33:43Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Analysis of durability of hamstring stretching effect in two forms of intervention</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Análise da durabilidade do efeito do alongamento muscular dos isquiotibiais em duas formas de intervenção</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Renata Cristina Magalhães</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pessoa, Bruna Ferreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Martins, Bruna Letícia Tamietti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Freitas, Daniela Bicalho Nogueira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Alongamento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Flexibilidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Treinamento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Durabilidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stretching</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Flexibility</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Training</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Durability</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Uma das maiores causas de disfunção do movimento é a falta de flexibilidade muscular, podendo interferir na funcionalidade dos indivíduos. Flexibilidade pode ser alterada por meio de alongamento, mas sabe-se que os efeitos do treinamento são, em geral, transitórios - aumentos duráveis resultam de remodelamento adaptativo e não simplesmente de deformação mecânica. Objetivo: Analisar a durabilidade dos efeitos de um programa de alongamento dos isquiotibiais e verificar se há diferença quando associado à esteira elétrica (aquecimento profundo) anteriormente. Métodos: Treze mulheres e sete homens entre 18 e 39 anos, divididos em dois grupos: alongamento (A) e esteira e alongamento (EA), foram submetidos a seis semanas, cinco vezes/semana, de alongamento estático ativo dos isquiotibiais em quatro séries de 30s e esteira elétrica, somente no EA, antes do alongamento. Foi realizada medida do ângulo poplíteo utilizando-se goniometria no pré e pós-treinamento durante um mês. Resultados: Os grupos obtiveram ganho significativo (p=0.000), mas não houve diferença significativa entre eles. A diminuição desse ganho em ambos aconteceu a partir do primeiro dia pós-treinamento, retornando à medida inicial em 72 horas. Discussão: Os achados sugerem que os benefícios do treinamento em longo prazo existem, porém, assim que se interrompe, eles vao deixando de existir, e não se pode afirmar se foram devido a um remodelamento adaptativo ou deformação mecânica. Conclusão: O ganho obtido foi transitório, mas deve-se considerar que não houve demanda funcional para que ele se mantivesse.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">One of the biggest causes of movement dysfunction is the lack of muscle flexibility, what can interfere in the individual’s functionality. Flexibility can be altered through stretching but the training effects are, in general, transitory – durable increases results of adaptative remodeling and not only for mechanical deformation. Objective: To analyze the durability of the effects of a stretching training program of the hamstrings and verify if it has difference when associated with an electric treadmill (deep warming) before. Methods: Thirteen women and seven men between 18 and 39 years, divided into two groups: stretching (A) and treadmill and stretching (EA), was submitted to a six weeks, five times/week, of active static stretching of the hamstrings with four series of 30s and electric treadmill, only at EA, before the stretching. Measurement of the popliteal angle was made through goniometry in the pre and post training for one month. Results: The groups obtained significant gains (p=0.000), but no have significant difference between them. The decreased of the gains in both groups occurred in the first day post training, returning to the initial measurement in 72 hours. Discussion: The finds suggest that the benefits of the long-term training exists, however when interrupted they stop, and it was impossible to affirm if they occurred because an adaptative remodeling or mechanical deformation. Conclusion: The obtained gain was transitory, but it is necessary to consider that wasn’t functional demand for it remained.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-04-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102576</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i1a102576</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 1 (2006); 32-38</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102576/100856</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102576/157784</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102578</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:36:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Identification of bronchoaspiration due to oropharyngeal dysphagia in patients with community pneumonia</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Identificação de broncoaspiração por disfagia orofaríngea em pacientes com pneumonia comunitária</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Yonatta Salarini Vieira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Xerez, Denise Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Araújo, Abelardo Queirós Campos de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pneumonia Aspirativa</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação Clínica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fonoaudiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Deglutição</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Desordens Neuromusculares</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aspiration Pneumonia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Clinical Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Speech Pathology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Swallowing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neuromuscular Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Pneumonia is a pulmonary parenchyma inflammation that results from an infectious or inflammatory process, responsible for 5% of all deaths reported in the world; it usually affects individuals whose defense mechanisms are compromised. The close association between swallowing abnormalities and the predisposition to repetitive bacterial pneumonia and its association with neuromuscular disorders have been the aim of many studies. Aim: To propose a clinical protocol to detect bronchoaspiration in patients with pneumonia, without videofluoroscopy. Method: 70 patients with mean age of 67.5±16.3 years were submitted to two swallowing evaluation protocols, previously validated in literature: Tohara (2003) and Xerez (2002). Results: 62.9% (44/70) of the patients were considered aspirators by the clinical examination, which showed a significant statistical correlation with the presence of neurological disorders and reduction in the state of alertness (p &amp;lt;0.001). Conclusion: The clinical examination was able to detect the patients at risk for aspiration pneumonia. The association of risk factors should lead the healthcare team to exercise more caution when planning the diet of the patient with pneumonia, as it can be the aspiration type.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A pneumonia é uma inflamação do parênquima pulmonar resultante do processo infeccioso ou inflamatório, responsável por 5% do total das mortes notificadas no mundo, instalando-se geralmente em indivíduos cujos mecanismos de defesa encontram-se comprometidos. A relação estreita entre as alterações da deglutição e a predisposição para pneumonias bacterianas de repetição e sua associação com desordens neuromusculares tem sido objeto constante de pesquisas. Objetivo: propor um protocolo clínico para detecção de broncoaspiração entre pacientes com pneumonia sem realização de videofluoroscopia. Metodologia: 70 pacientes com média de idade de 67,5±16,3 anos, foram submetidos a 2 protocolos de avaliação da deglutição validados na literatura: Tohara (2003) e Xerez (2002). Resultados: Foram considerados aspiradores pelo exame clínico 62,9% (44/70). Ser classificado aspirador pelo exame clínico mostrou correlação estatística significativa com a presença de doença neurológica e redução do estado de alerta (p&amp;lt;0,001). Conclusão: o exame clínico foi capaz de detectar os pacientes em risco para pneumonia aspirativa. A presença da associação de fatores deve levar a equipe a adotar cautela maior no manuseio da alimentação do paciente com pneumonia que pode ser de origem aspirativa.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102578</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i2a102578</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 2 (2006); 59-62</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102578/100858</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102578/157046</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102579</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T19:28:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102582</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:36:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação longitudinal da Escola de Postura para dor lombar crônica através da aplicação dos questionários Roland Morris e Short Form Health Survey (SF-36)</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Longitudinal evaluation of Posture School for low back pain by the questionnaires Rolland Morris and Short Form Health Survey (SF-36)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tsukimoto, Gracinda Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Riberto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brito, Carlos Alexandrino de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Low Back Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Questionnaires</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lombalgia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Questionários</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo desse trabalho foi analisar quantitativamente a resposta ao tratamento dos pacientes com dor lombar crônica atendidos pela “Escola de Postura” da DMR-HCFMUSP no período de outubro de 2001 a julho 2004, usando os questionários Roland-Morris (RM) e Short Form Health Survey (SF-36). A intensidade da queixa dolorosa foi avaliada pela Escala Visual Analógica (EVA). A amostra inicial foi composta por 244 prontuários de pacientes encaminhados e avaliados para a Escola de Postura no período de outubro de 2001 a julho de 2004, tendo completado o programa 110 pacientes desse total. Algum dados referentes a estes pacientes foram coletados, tais como: diagnósticos etiológico, tempo de evolução da doença e origem do encaminhamento; dados sócio-demográficos como sexo, idade, escolaridade, estado civil, ocupação; e, também, o comparecimento aos retornos após o primeiro mês, quarto mês, e um ano a contar da avaliação inicial. Observou-se que os indivíduos que concluíram a Escola de Postura apresentaram melhora significativa nos domínios do SF-36 para Capacidade Funcional, Aspectos Físicos, Dor, Estado Geral de Saúde, Vitalidade, bem como na avaliação pela EVA e questionário RM. Não foram observados ganhos estatisticamente significantes nos domínios Aspectos Sociais, Emocionais e Saúde Mental. Cabendo ressaltar que o período de alcance da Escola de Postura, não possibilita afirmar mudanças significativas quanto a aspectos afetivo-emocionais e novas posturas em seu relacionamento social. Novos estudos, quantitativos e qualitativos devem ser realizados de maneira a oferecer subsídios á equipe multiprofissional da Escola de Postura que permitam operar mudanças e ampliar recursos terapêuticos se necessário.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The objective of this study was to analyze quantitatively the response of patients with chronic low back pain to treatment at the Back School in DMR-HCFMUSP between October 2001 and July 2004, using the Roland-Morris (RM) and Short Form Health Survey (SF-36) questionnaires. Pain intensity was measured by the visual analogue scale (VAS). The initial sample consisted of 244 medical charts of patients referred to the Back School program for initial evaluation between October 2001 and July 2004; of this initial sample, 110 patients completed the program. Data were collected from these patients such as: etiologic diagnosis, history of disease and referring institution; socio-demographic information such as gender, age, education level, marital status, occupation, and also attendance to clinical interviews scheduled for the first and fourth months after treatment and one year after the first evaluation. The group that completed the Back School Program showed improvement at SF-36 domains: Functional Capacity, Physical Conditions, Pain, General Health Status, Strength, as well as in VAS and RM evaluations. No statistically significant changes in Social, Emotional, and Mental domains were observed. The Back Pain School allowed fewer changes regarding affective emotional conditions and social relationships. Further qualitative and quantitative studies must be carried out in other to support the development of specialized multiprofessional teams, who will carry out alterations and add to therapeutic resources, if necessary.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i2a102582</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 2 (2006); 63-69</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102582/100860</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102582/157097</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102583</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T20:07:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102584</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:36:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudo da associação entre dor patelofemoral e retropé varo</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Study of the association between rear-foot varus and patellofemoral pain</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Venturini, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Morato, Flávio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Michetti, Henrique</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Russo, Mayra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Vanice de Paula</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Joelho</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Tornozelo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pé</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Knee</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ankle</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Foot</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A dor patelofemoral, também denominada dor anterior do joelho está presente em 25% da população, onde 36% são adolescentes e com maior prevalência no sexo feminino e atletas. Objetivo: Verificar a associação entre a presença de retropé varo a partir da posição neutra da subtalar e a dor patelofemoral. Métodos: Foram recrutados 10 voluntários com dor patelofemoral unilateral ou bilateral. Os voluntários foram submetidos à avaliação do alinhamento do retropé a partir da posição neutra da subtalar. Para isso, os voluntários foram posicionados em decúbito ventral, com o pé pendente para fora da mesa. Os ângulos formado pelas retas que dividem as pernas e os calcâneos ao meio foram medidas através de um goniômetro universal. O teste de Fisher foi utilizado para verificar a associação entre dor patelofemoral e varismo de retropé maior ou igual ou menor que 8 graus. Resultados: Os resultados do presente estudo demonstraram que todos os membros com grau de retropé maior que 8 (75%) apresentavam dor, totalizando 15 joelhos. Já os joelhos avaliados com retropé menor ou igual a 8; 2 (10%) apresentavam dor e 3 (15%) não apresentaram dor. Associação estatisticamente significativa entre o grau de retropé e a presença de dor foram encontrados (p= 0,009). Discussão: O varismo de retropé leva a pronação excessiva da subtalar associada à rotação interna da tíbia com conseqüente alteração do alinhamento do membro inferior e dor patelofemoral, Conclusão: Os resultados desse estudo sugerem que existe a associação entre o retropé varo e a dor patelofemoral.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Patellofemoral pain, also called anterior knee pain, is present in 25% of the population with 36% of them being adolescents, and with a higher prevalence among females and athletes. Objective: To assess the association between the presence of rear-foot varus, from the subtalar neutral position, and patellofemoral pain. Methods: Ten volunteers with unilateral or bilateral patellofemoral pain were assessed. The volunteers were submitted to the evaluation of rear-foot alignment from the subtalar neutral position. In order to do so, the volunteers were positioned in the ventral decubitus position, with the foot hanging parallel to the table. The angles formed by the straight lines that divide the legs and the calcanei were measured through a universal goniometer. Fisher test was used to assess the association between patellofemoral pain and rear-foot varus ≥ or &amp;lt; 8o. Results: The results of this study showed that all limbs with rear-foot varus &amp;gt; 8o (75%) presented pain, totaling 15 knees. Of the knees that presented rear-foot varus ≤ 8,2 (10%) presented pain and 3 (15%) did not. A statistically significant association between the degree of rear-foot varus and pain was demonstrated (p= 0.009). Discussion: Rear-foot varus causes an excessive pronation of the subtalar joint associated to the internal rotation of the tibia, with a consequent alignment alteration of the lower limb and patellofemoral pain. Conclusion: The results of this study suggest that there is an association between the presence of rear-foot varus and patellofemoral pain.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i2a102584</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 2 (2006); 70-73</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102584/100862</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102584/157098</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102585</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T20:08:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102586</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:36:34Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Applicability of the Brazilian version of the McGill pain questionnaire in elderly patients with chronic pain</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Aplicação da versão brasileira do questionário de dor Mcgill em idosos com dor crônica</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Clarissa Cardoso dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pereira, Leani Souza Máximo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Resende, Marcos Antônio de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Magno, Frederico</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Aguiar, Vanessa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor Crônica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Questionário da Dor de McGill</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">McGill Pain Questionnaire</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Chronic Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Chronic pain is a multidimensional experience that involves sensory-perceptual affective-motivational and cognitive-evaluation aspects, which interact and contribute to the ultimate painful response. The characteristic changes of the aging process on each of these aspects can interfere with the experience of pain, thus making appropriate assessment more difficult. The use of multidimensional scales, such as the McGill Pain Questionnaire (MPQ) makes more appropriate evaluations possible. The aims of this study were to assess the intra- and inter-examiner reliability of the Brazilian Version of the MPQ (Br-MPQ) and characterize the perceptions of chronic pain in elderly individuals with orthopedic and neurological diseases. The sample consisted of 19 elderly individuals (71.21 ± 7.51 yrs) with orthopedic (G1) and 19 (69.79 ± 5.30 yrs) with neurological diseases (G2), all with a clinical diagnosis of chronic pain but no cognitive alterations. The general intra- and inter- examiner reliability was 0.86 and 0.89 for G1, and 0.71 and 0.68 for G2, respectively (p&amp;lt;0.05). The results showed that the Br-MPQ was easily applied to a group of elderly individuals with chronic pain (8.54 ± 2.35 minutes). The present study demonstrated that the Br-MPQ can be more effective to assess pain in the elderly, as the perception of this symptom is more associated to sensorial, affective, and subjective aspects than to pain intensity.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A dor crônica é uma experiência multidimensional que envolve aspectos sensório-perceptual, afetivo-motivacional e cognitivo-avaliativo que se interagem e contribuem para a resposta dolorosa final. As alterações características do processo do envelhecimento em cada um desses aspectos podem interferir na experiência da dor, dificultando a sua avaliação adequada. O uso de uma escala multidimensional como o Questionário de dor McGill (MPQ) possibilita uma avaliação mais adequada desse sintoma. Os objetivos desse estudo foram verificar a confiabilidade intra e inter examinadores da aplicação do Br-MPQ em idosos com dor crônica em decorrência de doenças ortopédicas e neurológicas.Participaram desse estudo 19 idosos com doenças ortopédicas (71,21 ± 7,51 anos) e 19 idosos com doenças neurológicas (69,79 ± 5,30 anos) apresentando o diagnóstico de dor crônica, encaminhados pelo serviço médico, sem alterações cognitivas. A confiabilidade geral intra e interexaminadores nos idosos com doenças ortopédicas foram 0,86 e 0,89, respectivamente, e para idosos com doenças neurológicas de 0,71 e 0,68, respectivamente (Spearman, p&amp;lt;0,05). Os resultados mostraram que o Br-MPQ foi de fácil aplicação (8,54 ± 2,35 minutos) nessa amostra. O presente estudo demonstrou que o Br-MPQ pode ser mais adequado para avaliar a dor crônica em idosos, uma vez que a percepção desse sintoma está mais relacionada aos aspectos sensoriais, afetivos e cognitivo-avaliativos e não somente à intensidade.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102586</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i2a102586</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 2 (2006); 75-82</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102586/100864</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102586/157050</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102587</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T20:07:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102588</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:36:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A interferência dos aspectos percepto-cognitivos nas atividades de vida diária e nas atividades instrumentais de vida diária, em clientes com sequelas por lesão neurológica</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The influence of the perceptual-cognitive difficulties on the activities of daily living and instrumental activities of daily living in patients with neurological injuries</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Conti, Juliana</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Occupational Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Activities of Daily Living</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Brain Injury, Chronic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia Ocupacional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividades Cotidianas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lesão Encefálica Crônica</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este artigo é um levantamento bibliográfico sobre a interferência dos aspectos percepto-cognitivos durante a realização das atividades de vida diária (AVDs) e atividades instrumentais de vida diária (AIVDs) em clientes com seqüelas por lesão neurológica. Com o objetivo de indicar o quanto esses déficits interferem na reabilitação do cliente e no retorno às atividades cotidianas, o artigo mostra que essas atividades — que aparentemente são simples e já conhecidas por eles — têm de ser aprendidas outra vez. Por outro lado, o artigo revela que não apenas esses aspectos interferem nessas tarefas durante o tratamento e no final dele (no qual o cliente apresentará uma maior ou menor independência), mas também há fatores — como os motores, emocionais, culturais, sociais, econômicos e principalmente a família — que influenciarão de maneira positiva ou negativa o cliente e seu processo de reabilitação. Para ilustrar esta pesquisa, foram apresentados três casos clínicos atendidos no serviço de Terapia Ocupacional.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This is a literature review on the influence of perceptual-cognitive aspects in the performance of activities of daily living (ADL) and instrumental activities of daily living (IADL) in patients with neurological injury sequelae. In order to show how much these deficits impair the clients’ rehabilitation and their return to routine activities, the review shows that such activities - which seem apparently simple and are previously known by them - have to be learned again. On the other hand, the review shows that these aspects not only interfere with these tasks (for which the client can be more or less independent), but also that there are factors – motor, emotional, cultural, social, economic, and, mainly, familial – that can positively or negatively influence the patient and his rehabilitation. Three clinical cases seen at the Occupational Therapy Service will be presented in order to illustrate this review.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102588</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i2a102588</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 2 (2006); 83-86</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102588/100866</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102588/157099</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102589</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T20:07:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102591</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:36:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Habilidades funcionais de comunicação: idoso saudável</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Functional communication assessment: the healthy elderly</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Garcia, Flavia Helena Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mansur, Letícia Lessa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Comunicação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Communication</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O Questionário de Habilidades Funcionais de Comunicação (ASHA-Facs) é um instrumento básico de avaliação das habilidades comunicativas no ambiente natural do indivíduo, considerando compensações, adaptações e tempo necessário para a comunicação. Pode ser usado como complemento das avaliações tradicionais de linguagem para planejar orientações ao cuidador, ajudar ao clínico nas decisões e registrar estabilização de doenças ou progresso de quadros patológicos. Este artigo caracteriza o perfil comunicativo funcional do idoso saudável a partir do questionário ASHA-Facs. Sessenta e seis idosos saudáveis foram avaliados por meio de seus cuidadores (familiares). O questionário é composto de 43 itens divididos em quatro domínios: 21 itens sobre comunicação social, 7 itens de comunicação de necessidades básicas, 10 itens de leitura, escrita e conceitos numéricos e 5 itens de planejamento diário. O questionário fornece informações quantitativas em uma escala de sete pontos (sendo pontuação 7 para o indivíduo que não necessita de ajuda para realizar a atividade e pontuação 1 se houver necessidade de ajuda máxima). O desempenho dos idosos no ASHA-Facs mostrou que os idosos saudáveis atuam melhor em Comunicação Social e Necessidades Básicas. Isto sugere que os idosos compensam possíveis falhas na compreensão auditiva/expressão oral que possam ocorrer durante o declínio da função cognitiva que acontece no processo de envelhecimento normal. O desempenho no domínio de planejamento diário mostrou dificuldades nas funções executivas de planejamento e organização. Ainda, houve uma importante correlação entre a comunicação funcional e a escolaridade.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Functional communication is the ability to receive or convey a message, regardless of the mode to communicate effectively and independently in a given environment. The Functional Communication Assessment Scale for Adults (ASHA-facs) is an instrument to evaluate the individual’s basic ability to communicate in an ecological context, considering proper modifications, adaptations and time needed for communication. It can be used to complement traditional language assessment, to plan caregiver orientation, to aid clinical decision-making and to register disease stabilization or treatment progress. This study characterizes the functional communication of the healthy elderly through the ASHA-facs scale. Sixty-six healthy elderly individuals were assessed trough their caregivers (family members). The scale consists of 43 items divided into four domains: 21 items on social communication; 7 items on communication of basic needs; 10 items on reading, writing and numerical concepts; 5 items on daily planning. The scale provides quantitative information in a 7-point scale (with score 7 for the individual who does not need help to perform the activity and score 1 when there is need of maximum help). The ASHA-facs results showed that healthy elderly individuals have better performances in social communication and basic needs. It suggests that elderly individuals compensate possible gaps in hearing comprehension and/or oral expression, which occur during cognitive function decline experienced along the normal aging process. The daily planning domain score showed difficulties in the executive functions of planning and organization. Additionally, there was an important correlation between functional communication and educational background.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102591</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i2a102591</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 2 (2006); 87-89</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102591/100868</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102591/157100</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102592</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T20:07:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102593</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:36:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Benefícios do treinamento com pesos para aptidão física de idosos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Strength training benefits on the physical fitness of elderly individuals</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Dias, Raphael Mendes Ritti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gurjão, André Luiz Demantova</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marucci, Maria de Fátima Nunes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Envelhecimento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Flexibilidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Aptidão Física</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aging</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pliability</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Fitness</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo desta revisão é elucidar os benefícios do treinamento com pesos (TP) sobre quatro componentes da aptidão física (AF) fundamentais para a qualidade de vida de idosos: força, flexibilidade, equilíbrio e resistência aeróbia. Foi realizada pesquisa bibliográfica nas bases de dados PUBMED e LILACS. Foram selecionados estudos que incluíam no título os descritores: strength training, resistance training, strength, balance, flexibility, power, aerobic, older e elderly. Modificações na força muscular são observadas após poucas semanas de TP. Essa melhoria pode auxiliar não só na independência dos idosos, mas também na diminuição da incidência de quedas. Além disso, a prática sistematizada do TP promove melhoria na flexibilidade e na resistência aeróbia de idosos. As modificações no equilíbrio, após programas de TP, ainda não estão bem esclarecidas na literatura. Desta forma, o TP consiste numa importante ferramenta para a melhoria da AF de idosos, haja vista que promove adaptações na força muscular, flexibilidade e na resistência aeróbia.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The objective of this review is to assess the benefits of strength training (ST) over four very important components of physical fitness (PF) of the elderly: strength, flexibility, balance and aerobic resistance. A literature search was carried out through PUBMED and LILACS. Articles which included the following words in their titles were selected: strength training, resistance training, strength, balance, flexibility, power, aerobic, older, and elderly. Strength modifications can be observed after a few weeks of ST. This improvement can help the elderly not only by providing independence, but also by reducing the incidence of falls. Moreover, the systematic practice of ST by the elderly promotes better flexibility and aerobic resistance. Balance modifications after ST programs have not been well established in the literature. Thus, ST is an important resource for the improvement of PF in the elderly, as it promotes adaptations in muscular strength, flexibility and aerobic resistance.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102593</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i2a102593</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 2 (2006); 90-95</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102593/100870</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102593/157101</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102594</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T20:08:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102595</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:36:56Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercícios resistidos em idosos portadores de insuficiência arterial periférica</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Resistance exercises in peripheral arterial diseased elders</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Câmara, Lucas Caseri</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santarém Sobrinho, José Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jacob Filho, Wilson</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kuwakino, Marcelo Hisato</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Weight Lifting</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Intermittent Claudication</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Arteriosclerosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health of the Elderly</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Levantamento de Peso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia por Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Claudicação Intermitente</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde do Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Arteriosclerose</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The aging of the world population has provoked an increase of chronic degenerative diseases, facing the scientific community with the challenge to search and choose the best and most feasible treatments. Peripheral arterial disease, which appears as a complication of arteriosclerosis, shows increased and continuous incidence as age progresses, therefore adding to several other diseases that ensue this portion of the population. The conclusive evidence of efficiency and cost-benefits in the use of exercise as a primary indication for the treatment of aging patients has become an excellent alternative for this population group, which already uses various medications due to other chronic diseases. The benefits of resistance exercise still have not been fully explored as an isolated treatment for peripheral arterial disease in aged persons, however has already indicated that this form of exercising can and should be used for the treatment of the referred pathology, since it can reverts or delays the associated degenerative alterations which commits their carriers, diminishing significantly the many limitations imposed by the disease in association with sedentary aging</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O envelhecimento da população mundial propiciou o incremento das doenças crônico degenerativas, colocando a comunidade científica diante de um grande desafio na busca e escolha dos melhores e mais econômicos tratamentos. A doença arterial periférica, que surge como complicação da aterosclerose, apresenta incidência que aumenta linearmente com o avançar da idade, somando-se, portanto, a diversas outras patologias que já acometem este grupo populacional. A documentação dos benefícios em custo e eficácia, da utilização de exercícios como indicação primária para o tratamento de pacientes idosos, tornou-se excelente alternativa para este grupo populacional, que já utiliza diversas medicações, devido a outras doenças crônicas. Os benefícios dos exercícios resistidos foram ainda pouco explorados como forma isolada de tratamento da doença arterial periférica em idosos, mas já deixam indícios que esta forma de exercícios pode e deve ser utilizada para o tratamento da patologia referida, pois pode reverter ou retardar as concomitantes alterações degenerativas que acometem seus portadores, diminuindo de forma significativa as muitas limitações impostas pela doença em associação com o envelhecimento sedentário.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102595</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i2a102595</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 2 (2006); 96-102</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102595/100872</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102595/157110</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102596</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T20:08:02Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102597</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:37:01Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O efeito da técnica de reeducação postural global em um paciente com hemiparesia após acidente vascular encefálico</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The effect of global postural reeducation technique in a hemiparetic stroke patient</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gomes, Bruna Moreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nardoni, Grace Cristina Gomes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Priscila Garcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Godoy, Ewerson de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Imagem Corporal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Postura</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Body Image</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Posture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A disfunção motora mais evidente do acidente vascular encefálico (AVE) é a hemiparesia. Os pacientes hemiparéticos apresentam uma tendência em manter-se em uma posição de assimetria postural. O objetivo deste trabalho foi avaliar e tratar as alterações posturais em um paciente portador de hemiparesia após um acidente vascular encefálico utilizando a técnica de Reeducação Postural Global (RPG). O participante foi um paciente hemiparético à direita, devido a um AVE há cinco anos, com boa cognição segundo o Mini Exame do Estado Mental e comprometimento motor moderado. Para avaliação postural foi utilizado o software Fisiologic. Foram aplicadas dez sessões com a técnica de RPG durante oito semanas. Embora o tratamento tenha sido enfatizado na inclinação pélvica e posicionamento da escápula os resultados apresentaram evoluções também quanto à base de apoio e segundo o relato do paciente, melhora no equilíbrio e na marcha. Concluiu-se que a técnica de RPG proporcionou resultados positivos em relação ao padrão postural do paciente hemiparético.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The most evident motor dysfunction in the Cerebrovascular Accident (CVA) is hemiparesis. Hemiparetic patients have a tendency to maintain an asymmetric posture. The aim of this study was to evaluate the posture in a hemiparetic stroke patient using the Global Postural Reeducation (GPR) technique. The participant was a right hemiparetic patient due to a CVA that had taken place 5 years before; his cognitive state was good, according to the Mini-Mental State Examination test and he presented moderate motor impairment. The postural evaluation was performed by a computer program, called FisioLogic. The patient underwent a treatment plan comprising ten sessions of GPR technique during eight weeks. Although the treatment was carried out with emphasis on the pelvic inclination and the scapula positioning, the results also showed improvement regarding the support base and, according to the patient, it also improved his balance and gait. We conclude that the GPR technique yielded positive results regarding the posture pattern of the hemiparetic patient.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-08-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102597</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20060001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 2 (2006); 103-108</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102597/100875</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102597/157112</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header status="deleted">
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102598</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-17T20:07:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
      </header>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102662</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:40:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The general hospital inpatient referred to Physical Medicine Department: functional level and epidemiological profile</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O paciente internado em um hospital geral encaminhado à Medicina Física: perfil epidemiológico e nível funcional</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jorge, Liliana Lourenço</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sugawara, André Tadeu</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carneiro, Margarida Sales Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hospitalização</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medida de Independência Funcional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hospitalization</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Functional Independence Measure</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Os efeitos da hospitalização, somados a condições clínicas prévias, levam os pacientes internados à deterioração funcional e perda de independência em atividades cotidianas. Nesta situação, a reabilitação durante o período de internação exerce papel fundamental no controle e prevenção dos efeitos do imobilismo. Segundo estudos prévios, a população internada é predominantemente idosa e portadora de comorbidades. Contudo, havia poucos dados acerca dos níveis funcionais de pacientes oriundos de hospitais gerais e suas demandas para reabilitação. Este estudo buscou traçar o perfil epidemiológico e funcional da população internada em um hospital terciário, encaminhada à Medicina Física, por meio de Medida de Independência Funcional, escala da ASA e outros dados descritivos. O estudo constatou que a população é dependente funcionalmente, necessita de cuidador e é idosa. Há correlação entre MIF e ASA, indicando pior funcionalidade à medida que aumentam comorbidades. Acredita-se que os pacientes seriam beneficiados na internação caso fossem encaminhados à reabilitação; porém, o médico fisiatra não é conhecido entre os demais médicos e seu papel não está claro dentro das especialidades clínico-cirúrgicas desses hospitais.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Hospitalization and severe previous diseases lead to functional decrease and independence loss during activities of daily living among inpatients. Rehabilitation during hospital care is thought to be crucial in immobilism syndrome prevention. According to previous data, ward patients are mainly comprised of elderly individuals who carry disabling diseases, although there is a lack in information regarding their functional levels and rehabilitation needs. This study aimed at verifying functional and social profiles of inpatients from a tertiary general hospital referred to the Physical Medicine Service. The applied measurements were FIM, ASA scale, and demographic data. It was observed that inpatients are physically impaired, need caregivers and are elderly. There is also a strong correlation between FIM and ASA: the worse the functional independence is, the higher the number of comorbidities. Patients might benefit from the hospital stay if they were systematically referred to rehabilitation. Nevertheless, the physician who does not usually deal with rehabilitation is neither aware of the physiatrists' role in health care provided in wards nor take advantage of their knowledge.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102662</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i3a102662</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 3 (2006); 124-129</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102662/100926</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102731</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:41:30Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Clinical effects of acupuncture and periarticular local infiltration of corticosteroids in the treatment of gonarthrosis</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeitos clínicos da acupuntura e infiltração periarticular de corticosteróides no tratamento de gonartrose</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Plavsic, Aleksandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brdareski, Zorica</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Djurovic, Aleksandar</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Gonartrose</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acupuntura</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Infiltração Local Periarticular de Corticosteróide</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gonarthrosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Acupuncture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Periarticular Local Infiltration of Corticosteroid</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Gonartrose é uma das doenças degenerativas mais comuns. Dor, deficiência e deformidade articular são os sinais clínicos dominantes. Objetivo do estudo: Comparar o efeito clínico obtido com três diferentesmodelos terapêuticos: 1. Acupuntura; 2. Infiltração local de corticosteróide; 3. Combinação de acupuntura e infiltração local de corticosteróide. Material e Métodos: Um estudo clínico prospectivo, aleatorizado, aberto incluiu 21 pacientes do sexo feminino em fase aguda de gonartrose. O diagnóstico foi feito através de exames clínicos e radiográficos. As pacientes foram divididas em três grupos: Grupo I: 7 pacientes com média de idade de 61,0 ± 6,8 anos, tratadas através de acupuntura com agulhas (pontas: Du20, Ex31, Ex32, St35, UB40, St44, UB60, Li4, Sp9,UB11), 10 tratamentos. Grupo II: 7 pacientes com 59,0 ± 10,1 anos, tratadas com infiltração de Betametasona – Diprofos, no primeiro dia de tratamento com abordagem frontal na parte lateral ou medial do tendão do músculo quadríceps. Grupo III: 7 pacientes, com 58,0 ± 6,07 anos, tratadas com uma combinação de infiltração inicial de Betametasona – Diprofos e acupuntura com agulhas, 10 tratamentos. A avaliação dos parâmetros de eficácia foi feita através dos seguintes parâmetros: 1. Dificuldades subjetivas – dor (Escala visual analógica – EVA de 0 a 100 mm); 2. tamanho do joelho, medido através do meio da patela em centímetros; 3. Amplitude de movimento articular (flexão), medida com um goniômetro. Todos esses parâmetros foram medidos no 1º, 8º e 21º dia de tratamento. ANOVA unifatorial, ANOVA de medida repetida e testes post hoc foram utilizados na análise estatística. Resultados: 1. Houve significativa melhora nos parâmetros de intensidade de dor e tamanho do joelho dentro dos grupos; ANOVA unifatorial,&amp;nbsp; p&amp;lt;0,01; 2. Não houve melhora significativa no parâmetro de movimento articular dentro dos grupos; ANOVA unifatorial, p=0,528; 3. Houve melhoras significativas em todos os parâmetros (intensidade da dor, tamanho do joelho, movimento articular) nos três grupos; ANOVA de medida repetida, p&amp;lt;0,01. Conclusão: O tratamento combinado de acupuntura e infiltração de corticosteróide tem melhor efetividade em intensidade da dor, tamanho do joelho e melhora do movimento articular em comparação com a monoterapia.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Gonarthrosis is one of the most frequently degenerative diseases. Pain, derange of function and= deformation of joint are dominating clinical signs. Aim of the study: To compare clinical effect obtained with three different therapeutic models: 1. Acupuncture; 2. Local infiltration of corticosteroid; 3. Combination of acupuncture and local infiltration of corticosteroid. Material and methods: An open, prospective, randomized clinical study included 21 female patients in acute phase of gonarthrosis. Diagnosis was made by clinical and radiographic examinations. Patients were divided into three groups: I group: 7 patients, average age 61.0 ± 6.8 years, treated with needle acupuncture (points: Du.20, Ex.31, Ex.32, St.35, UB.40, St.44, UB.60, Li.4, Sp.9,UB.11), 10 treatments. II group: 7 patients, average age 59.0 ± 10.1 years, treated with infiltration of Bethametasonum – Diprophos on the first day of treatment with frontal approach on the medial or the lateral side of m. quadriceps tendon. III group: 7 patients, average age 58 ± 6.07 years, treated with a combination of initial infiltration of Bethametasonum – Diprophos and needle acupuncture, 10 treatments. The evaluation of efficacy parameters were performed by following parameters: 1. Subjective difficulties – pain (VAS 0-100 mm); 2. Sizeof knee, measured across the middle of patella with centimeter band; 3. Range of joint motion (flexion), measured using a goniometer. All of these parameters were measured on 1st, 8th and 21st day of treatment. One way ANOVA, repeated measures ANOVA and post hoc tests were applied for statistic analysis. Results: 1. There were high significant improvements in the parameters of pain intensity and size of knee inside the groups; One way ANOVA test, p=0.000&amp;lt;0.01; 2. There were no significant improvements in the parameter of joint movement inside the groups; One way ANOVA test, p=0.528&amp;gt;0.05; 3. There were high significant improvements in all parameters (pain intensity, size of knee, joint movement) in all three groups; Repeated measures ANOVA test, p=0.000&amp;lt;0.01. Conclusion: Combined treatment of acupuncture and local infiltration of a corticosteroid has better effectiveness in pain intensity, size of knee and improvement of motion in comparison with monotherapy.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102731</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i3a102731</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 3 (2006); 130-135</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102731/100980</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102731/182182</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102735</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:41:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Communication and language disorders of patients with acquired brain injuries: a retrospective and descriptive study</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Alterações de comunicação e linguagem de pacientes portadores de lesão encefálica adquirida: estudo descritivo retrospectivo</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cecatto, Rebeca Boltes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jucá, Sueli Hamada</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nacarato, Maria Inês</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Maeda, Fabiana Regina Giacomini</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Prieto, Fernanda Franco</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação dos Transtornos da Fala e da Linguagem</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Cerebrovascular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos Cerebrais</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos da Comunicação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos Cognitivos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation of Speech and Language Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Traumatic Brain Injury</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Communication Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cognition Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">There are few Brazilian studies on communication and language of adults with acquired brain injuries, as well as their relation with motor and cognitive improvement during rehabilitation. This fact, added to the complex evaluation of these conditions, is the reason for this study. The aim of this study was to describe communication disorders in adults with acquired brain injuries and correlate them with biodemographic, clinical and image findings. One hundred and nineteen medical charts of rehabilitation patients seen between October 2002 and 2004 were reviewed. Biodemographic and clinical data were collected together with brain image findings and the pattern of communication disorder according to the speech therapy assessment. Disability was measured by the Functional Independence Measure (FIM). Stroke comprised 74% of the cases, followed by traumatic brain injury (TBI) in 20% and 6% of other etiologies. Fifty-one patients presented with language disorders, whereas 43 had other non-language speech disorders and 25 had no alterations. Aphasia was present in 30.9% of the cases (being 56% of the mixed type), 27.7% had dysarthria, 24.5% were apraxic, 22.3% presented cognitive-communicative impairment, 21.3% had voice disorders, 20.2% had dysphagia, 14.9% had sensorimotor disorders of the mouth, 3.2% had hypoacusia and 1.1% were anomic. There were no associations between gender in the comparison of subgroups with aphasia, linguistic-cognitive disorders, TBI or stroke, as well as no patient presenting right brain dominance for language. The prevalence of aphasia correlated with left side lesions and the linguistic-cognitive disorders with right side lesions and the presence of TBI, with a smaller number of aphasic patients among those with TBI than the remainder of the sample. FIM was associated with language alterations, suggesting that the latter influenced the patients' degree of independence. Conclusion:&amp;nbsp;Communication and its alterations are associated to the patient's other cognitive, motor, socio-cultural and personal alterations, which reinforces the importance of interdisciplinary teams in the functional diagnosis and rehabilitation of patients with acquired brain injuries.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Há poucos estudos brasileiros abordando a comunicação e linguagem dos pacientes adultos com lesões encefálicas adquiridas, bem como sua relação com as melhoras motoras e cognitivas durante a reabilitação. Esse fator, somado à complexidade da avaliação dessas alterações justifica este estudo. O objetivo deste estudo foi descrever as alterações de comunicação nos pacientes adultos com lesões encefálicas adquiridas atendidos pela equipe de reabilitação de pacientes com lesões encefálicas adquiridas e correlacionar esses dados com variáveis biodemográficas, clínicas e achados aos exames de imagem. Cento e dezenove prontuários médicos de pacientes hemiplégicos sob reabilitação, atendidos entre Outubro de 2002 e 2004 foram avaliados. Foram tabulados dados clínicos, biodemográficos, resultados de exame de imagem e o padrão de transtorno de comunicação de acordo com a avaliação realizada no serviço de fonoaudiologia. O grau de incapacidade foi avaliado pela medida de independência funcional (MIF). O AVE correspondeu a 74% dos casos, seguido pelo TCE em 20% e 6% de outras etiologias. Cinqüenta e um pacientes apresentaram alterações de linguagem, enquanto 43 tinham outras alterações fonoaudiológicas e não de linguagem e 25 sem alterações; 30,9% de afasias (sendo 56% dessas, mistas, a mais prevalente), 27,7% de disartrias, 24,5% de apraxias, 22,3% de alterações lingüístico-cognitivas, 21,3% de alterações de voz, 20,2% de disfagias, 14,9% de alterações sensoriomotoras orais, 3,2% de hipoacusias e 1,1% de anomias. Não foram encontradas associações entre o gênero na comparação dos subgrupos com afasia, portadores de distúrbio lingüístico-cognitivo, TCE ou AVE, bem como nenhum paciente sugerindo dominância cerebral para linguagem à direita. A prevalência das afasias apresentou relação com a lateralidade esquerda da lesão e a dos distúrbios lingüístico-cognitivos com a lateralidade direita e com a presença de TCE, sendo menor o número de afásicos entre os pacientes com TCE do que no resto da amostra. A MIF apresentou associação com as alterações de linguagem, sugerindo que estas influenciaram o grau de independência dos pacientes. Conclusões: A comunicação e suas alterações estão ligadas às outras alterações cognitivas, motoras, sócio-culturais e pessoais do paciente, o que reforça a importância das equipes interdisciplinares no diagnóstico funcional e reabilitação dos pacientes com lesões encefálicas adquiridas.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102735</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i3a102735</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 3 (2006); 136-146</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102735/100988</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102737</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:41:24Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Comparative study on the cervical range of motion in elderly individuals with different fitness levels</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudo comparativo das amplitudes de movimento da coluna cervical em idosos com diferentes níveis de aptidão física</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Cristiano Oliveira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Magalhães, Denis Aron dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva Junior, José Alberto Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bicalho, Luis Flávio Horta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Ana Paula Bitarães</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Leonardo Oliveira Pena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Figueiredo, Vânia Ferreira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Amplitude de Movimento</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Coluna Cervical</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Range of Motion</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cervical Spine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Elderly</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Este estudo tem como objetivo analisar e comparar as amplitudes de movimento (ADM) da coluna cervical em dois grupos de idosos com níveis diferentes de aptidão física. Métodos: Foram selecionados 40 voluntários assintomáticos com idade entre 60-75 anos e subdivididos pelo seu respectivo nível de aptidão física. Os voluntários então foram submetidos a mensuração de suas respectivas ADM pelo inclinômetro Cervical Range of Motion – CROM por um examinador que não tinha conhecimento prévio dos pacientes e seus respectivos grupos. Um teste de confiabilidade intra examinador foi realizado para avaliar a reprodutibilidade do examinador. Resultados: Foi observado que nos movimentos de flexão e extensão não houveram diferenças significativas entre os grupos avaliados. Os movimentos de inclinação lateral direita e esquerda e rotação direita e esquerda apresentaram valores de ADM estatisticamente significantes no grupo de voluntários ativos quando comparados com os sedentários. Conclusão: Conclui-se através deste estudo que o nível de atividade física pode ser um fator benéfico na preservação da ADM em idosos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The aim of this study was to analyze and compare the cervical range of motion (ROM) in elderly people with different fitness levels. Methods: Forty asymptomatic volunteers aged between 60-75 years old were recruited and classified based on their respective fitness level. The volunteers were then submitted to the measurement of cervical ROM with the Cervical Range of Motion (CROM) inclinometer by a blinded examiner. An intrarater reliability test was also performed to evaluate the examiner's reproducibility. Results: There were no significant differences regarding flexion and extension movements in both groups. The lateral right and left flexion and right and left rotation were statistically higher in the fitness group compared to the sedentary individuals. Conclusion: We concluded that the fitness level can be beneficial to preserve cervical ROM in elderly people.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102737</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i3a102737</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 3 (2006); 147-151</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102737/100992</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102740</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:41:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da sensibilidade de membros superiores em pacientes com linfedema pós mastectomia radical</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of upper limb sensitivity in patients with lymphedema after radical mastectomy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Greve, Patrícia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dalaruvera, Karin Luise</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Benvenuto, Fernando Barbosa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Guedes Neto, Henrique Jorge</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Lymphedema</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sensitivity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Monofilaments</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Linfedema</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sensibilidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Monofilamentos</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O objetivo deste trabalho foi avaliar a sensibilidade de membros superiores com linfedema pós- mastectomia radical. Foram avaliadas nove pacientes, com média de idade de 60,7 anos, para verificar se ocorre diferença de sensibilidade entre o membro com linfedema e o membro sem linfedema. Para o teste de sensibilidade foram utilizados 6 monofilamentos de Semmens-Weinstes (modelo de bolso) “sensi kit”. As áreas testadas foram aquelas correspondentes aos dermátomos ligados à distribuição dos nervos ulnar, mediano e radial. Como resultados tivemos que o tempo decorrido desde a cirurgia foi em média de 8,9 anos, e o aparecimento do linfedema ocorreu em média 5,5 anos após a cirurgia. Utilizou-se a estatística não-paramétrica, empregando-se o Teste de Fisher para pequenas amostras, das freqüências encontradas. Para cada lado testado evidenciou que a freqüência de pacientes que apresentaram sensibilidade no lado acometido foi significativamente menor (0,0045; p&amp;gt;0,005) do que a observada no lado controle, quando testado o Ponto 1, cor verde; não houve diferenças estatisticamente importantes entre os lados avaliados nos demais pontos e cores testados; com relação ao grau de incapacidade, conforme o Ministério da Saúde, não houve qualquer diferença significativa entre os lados acometido e controle em qualquer dos sete pontos testados.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The objective of this work was to evaluate the sensitivity of upper limbs with lymphoedema after radical mastectomy. Nine patients were evaluated, whose mean age was 60.7 years, to verify the presence of sensitivity difference between the limb with lymphedema and the control limb. For the sensitivity test, a six-monofilament Semmens-Weinstes "sensi kit" (pocket model) was used. The tested areas were those that corresponded to the dermatomes connected to the distribution of the ulnar, medianus and radialis nerves. Our results showed that the elapsed time since the surgery was on average 8.9 years and that the onset of lymphedema occurred on average 5.5 years after the surgery. Statistical analysis was non-parametrical and used Fisher's Test for small samples of the observed frequencies. For each tested side it was evidenced that the frequency of patients who presented sensitivity in the affected side was significantly smaller (0.0045; p&amp;gt;0.005) than the one observed in the control side, when Point 1, green color, was tested; there were no statistically significant differences between the evaluated sides in the remaining tested points and colors; regarding the incapacity degree, according to the Health Ministry, there were no significant differences between the affected and control sides in any of the seven tested points.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102740</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i3a102740</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 3 (2006); 152-156</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102740/100997</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102743</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-08-15T21:41:17Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor fantasma em amputados de membro inferior como fator preditivo de aquisição de marcha com prótese</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Phantom pain in lower limb amputees as a predictive factor for the acquisition oft gait with prosthesis use</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Karla Barros Bezerra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chamlian, Therezinha Rosane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Masiero, Danilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Phantom Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Amputees</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor Fantasma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Amputados</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A reabilitação do paciente amputado obedece a algumas fases: avaliação geral do paciente, reabilitação préprotética e reabilitação pós-protética. Para que todas essas etapas sejam alcançadas e cumpridas com sucesso, é indispensável que o paciente apresente um bom estado geral, sem alterações que possam comprometer a reabilitação. A presença de sinais e/ou sintomas patológicos impedem uma boa evolução do processo. A presença de dor fantasma persistente prejudica a reabilitação do paciente amputado, em especial, o processo de aquisição de marcha com a prótese. Esta é a hipótese sugerida nesta revisão de literatura, que apresenta como objetivo relacionar a presença de dor fantasma com a aquisição de marcha com prótese em pacientes amputados de membro inferior. Após analisar os 11 estudos selecionados, concluiu-se que a dor fantasma tende a dificultar a marcha com prótese, mas que, quando a protetização é alcançada de maneira eficiente, pode influenciar no alívio da mesma.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The amputees' rehabilitation follows distinct phases: the patient's general assessment, preparation for the prosthetic use and prosthetic fitting. For all these phases to be successful, it is essential for the patient to be in good health, with no alterations that would impair the rehabilitation. Pathological signs and/or symptoms that persist over time are an impediment for a good rehabilitation evolution. The presence of persistent phantom pain impairs the amputee's rehabilitation, especially the gait acquisition with the prosthesis fitting. This is the hypothesis suggested in this literary review and its objective is to show the relationship between phantom pain and gait improvement with prosthesis use in lower limb amputees. After analyzing 11 studies selected from MEDLINE, LILACS and other electronic sources, we concluded that phantom pain tends to complicate the prosthesis gait improvement; however, if the prosthesis fitting is successful, it can minimize the painful phantom sensations.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2006-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102743</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v13i3a102743</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 13 n. 3 (2006); 157-162</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102743/101002</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2006 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2023-08-08T14:49:04Z" completeListSize="935" cursor="200">1ba8c4ba2d5ac6a3e1bdb0971ef4c248</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
