<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-08-07T14:49:26Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="actafisiatrica">https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114510</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-15T11:29:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Atuação da fisioterapia nas disfunções sexuais femininas: uma revisão sistemática</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Physical therapy in sexually dysfunctional women: a systematic review</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Wolpe, Raquel Eleine</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Toriy, Ariana Machado</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Fabiana Pinheiro da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zomkowski, Kamilla</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sperandio, Fabiana Flores</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Disfunção Sexual Fisiológica/reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Mulheres</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Modalidades de Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sexual Dysfunction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physiological/rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Women</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy Modalities</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">As disfunções sexuais femininas (DSFs) são consideradas um problema de saúde pública pela Organização Mundial da Saúde (OMS). Consistem em inúmeras desordens, como distúrbio da excitação feminina, distúrbio do desejo sexual hipoativo, transtorno sexual do orgasmo feminino, dispareunia e vaginismo. As DSFs são detectadas em 67,9% das mulheres no mundo e estão presentes em 50% das asiáticas, em 30 a 50% das americanas e em 30% das brasileiras. Objetivo: Revisar sistematicamente a literatura sobre as diferentes técnicas de fisioterapia utilizadas no tratamento das DSFs. Métodos: Realizou-se uma busca sistemática, nas bases de dados EMBASE, PEDro e MedLine, de artigos publicados até junho de 2013, através da combinação entre palavras e descritores de tratamentos fisioterapêuticos e disfunções sexuais femininas. Foram excluídos os artigos sobre disfunção sexual masculina, estudos pilotos, papers ou projetos multicêntricos, que não estivessem disponíveis na íntegra ou duplicados em outra base de dado. Após a seleção final dos estudos, foi verificada a pontuação dos ensaios clínicos randomizados na Escala de Avaliação PEDro. Resultados: 11 artigos foram incluídos e, destes, seis passaram para a avaliação qualitativa na Escala PEDro. Este estudo seguiu a estruturação metodológica do PRISMA (Statement for Reporting Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses of Studies). Todos os estudos encontrados utilizaram questionários para avaliar os efeitos da intervenção fisioterapêutica nas DSFs. Foi verificado um total de cinco tipos de intervenções diferentes: cinesioterapia (exercícios de Kegel e treinamento muscular do assoalho pélvico - TMAP), terapia cognitivo-comportamental (CGBT), biofeedback, eletroterapia (TENS - eletroestimulação transcutânea e US - ultrassom terapêutico) e terapia manual. As limitações encontradas nesta revisão sistemática foram referentes a não disponibilização dos artigos na íntegra e à baixa qualidade metodológica dos estudos. Conclusão: Todos os estudos mostraram melhora na função sexual após intervenção fisioterapêutica. Não há um consenso sobre a intervenção com melhores resultados, no entanto, a cinesioterapia através do TMAP mostrou-se vantajosa por ser de fácil aplicação, baixo custo, aprendizado imediato e promover resultados duradouros em um curto período de tempo. No entanto, existem lacunas metodológicas que ainda precisam ser preenchidas para determinar o tratamento fisioterapêutico eletivo para as DSFs, assim como definir a melhor dosagem, o protocolo a ser seguido, a duração desta terapia, aliados ao melhor custo-benefício</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The World Health Organization (WHO) considers Female Sexual Dysfunctions (FSDs) to be a public health issue. There are a multitude of disorders such as female sexual arousal disorder, hypoactive sexual desire disorder, orgasmic disorder, dyspareunia, and vaginismus. FSDs are detected in 67.9% of the women in the world and are present in 50% of Asians, in 30-50% of Americans, and in 30% of Brazilians. Objective: To systematically review the literature on the different physiotherapy techniques used in the treatment of FSDs. Methods: A systematic search was conducted in the databases EMBASE, PEDro, and MedLine in data as recent as June 2013, by combining words and descriptors of physical therapy treatments and female sexual dysfunctions. Excluded from review were articles concerning male sexual dysfunction, pilot studies, multicentric papers of projects, and those which were either not available in their entirety or were duplicated in another database. After the selection of studies was complete, the randomized clinical trials were scored on the PEDro Evaluation Scale. Results: Eleven articles were included, six of which went on to be qualitatively evaluated on the PEDro scale. The present study followed the methodological structure of PRISMA (Statement for Reporting Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses of Studies). All studies found used questionnaires to assess the effects of physical therapy on FSDs. A total of five different types of interventions were verified: kinesiotherapy (Kegel exercises and pelvic floor muscle training - PFMT), Cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT), biofeedback, electrotherapy (transcutaneous electrical stimulation - TENS, and therapeutic ultrasound - US), and manual therapy. The limitations found in this systematic review were related to the unavailability of the articles in full and the low methodological quality of the studies. Conclusion: All studies showed improvements in sexual function after physical therapy intervention. There is no consensus on any intervention with better results; however, kinesiotherapy using PFMT proved to be advantageous because of its easy application, low cost, easy learning curve, and lasting results achieved in a short period. However, there are methodological shortcomings that still need to be dealt with to determine the most suitable physical therapy treatment for FSDs, as well as defining the best dosage, the protocol to be followed, and the duration of therapy, as well as the best cost-benefit</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114510</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150017</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 2 (2015); 87-92</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114510/112337</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114510/112338</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114512</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T21:26:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Neuroplasticidade e recuperação funcional na reabilitação pós-acidente vascular encefálico</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Neuroplasticity and functional recovery in rehabilitation after stroke</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Filippo, Thais Raquel Martins</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alfieri, Fabio Marcon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cichon, Flavio Rodrigo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imamura, Marta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neuronal Plasticity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Plasticidade Neuronal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The concept of rehabilitation in stroke is currently based on evidence of neuroplasticity, considered to be responsible for recovery after a stroke. The scarcity of information in the literature, especially concerning methods that specifically evaluate neuroplasticity, does not match its functional importance. In general, the literature discusses the functional evaluations of limbs after a stroke and a few studies focus on cerebral impairment. Objective: To review the literature and evaluate current rehabilitation programs for stroke and their potential to promote functional improvement and neuronal plasticity. Method: A literature review was conducted searching the PubMed database with articles published from 2000 to 2015. The descriptors used were: "Stroke/rehabilitation" OR "Stroke/therapy" AND "Neuronal Plasticity". Results: From the 86 studies found, 36 were classified as Therapy/Narrow, with 17 articles being excluded either for not meeting the inclusion criteria or for not presenting a theme relevant to the study. After the selection by title and abstract, 19 articles were read entirely. Of those, six were excluded for not addressing the objective of the present study. In all, 13 articles were reviewed. The evaluation instruments in those 13 articles varied between functional magnetic resonance, transcranial magnetic stimulation, and single photon emission computed tomography (SPECT). The interventions used were specific for the upper limbs, except for one article about an intervention through hyperbaric oxygen therapy. Conclusion: Few studies evaluated the neuronal plasticity in rehabilitation after a stroke, and most articles presented improvements in function as well as in neuroplasticity. However, larger studies should investigate and correlate both aspects in the rehabilitation of stroke patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O conceito de reabilitação no acidente vascular encefálico (AVE) atualmente é baseado em evidências da neuroplasticidade, considerada responsável pela recuperação após AVE. A escassez de informações na literatura e, principalmente, de métodos que avaliem especificamente a neuroplasticidade não condiz com a sua importância funcional. A literatura aborda, geralmente, as avaliações funcionais dos membros após o AVE e poucos estudos se concentram no comprometimento cerebral. Objetivo: Revisar a literatura para avaliar os programas de reabilitação atuais em AVE e seu potencial para promover melhorias funcionais e plasticidade neuronal. Método: Foi realizada uma revisão de literatura com busca na base de dados do PubMed de artigos publicados de 2000 a 2015. Os descritores utilizados para a pesquisa foram: "Stroke/rehabilitation" OR "Stroke/therapy" AND "Neuronal Plasticity". Resultados: Foram encontrados 86 estudos, 36 foram classificados como Therapy/Narrow, sendo 17 artigos excluídos por não preencherem os critérios de inclusão ou por não apresentarem tema relevante à pesquisa. Após a seleção por título e resumo, 19 artigos foram lidos na íntegra. Destes, 6 foram excluídos por não contemplarem o objetivo da presente pesquisa. No total, 13 artigos foram revisados. Dentre estes 13 artigos, os instrumentos de avaliação variaram entre a ressonância magnética funcional, estimulação magnética transcraniana e tomografia computadorizada por emissão de fóton único (SPECT). As intervenções utilizadas foram específicas para os membros superiores, exceto por um artigo que teve a intervenção através da terapia de oxigênio hiperbárica. Conclusão: Poucos estudos avaliam a plasticidade neuronal na reabilitação do AVE, e a maioria dos artigos apresentou melhorias tanto funcionais quanto na neuroplasticidade. Entretanto, maiores estudos devem investigar e correlacionar ambos os aspectos na reabilitação dos pacientes com AVE.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114512</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150018</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 2 (2015); 93-96</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114512/112339</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114512/112340</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114513</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-15T11:34:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Results of a physical fitness program for a patient with severe hemophilia A</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Resultados de um programa de condicionamento físico em um paciente com hemofilia A grave</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cruz, Leonardo Danelon da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mota, Cristiane Gonçalves da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cardoso, Cristiane Vieira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Miyahara, Katia Lina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yamamoto, Rodrigo Luis</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jorge Filho, Donaldo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hemophilia A</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Conditioning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Human</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemofilia A</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Condicionamento Físico Humano</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Hemophilia is a blood clotting disorder that causes the decrease or absence of blood coagulation factors VIII or IX. This disease causes a person to bleed longer than a normal person if it is not treated. A 31-year-old male with hemophilic arthropathy in the left elbow and right ankle was evaluated. The program lasted 20 months, with aerobic and muscle strength training. The muscles involved were the pectoralis major, latissimus dorsi, biceps brachii, triceps brachii, deltoideus, quadriceps femoris, and hamstring. The patient performed two series of 10 repetitions with 45 seconds between series. The intensity was based on the initial test of 10 maximum repetitions in accordance with the rate of perceived exertion on the Borg Scale. Aerobic exercise was performed on a horizontal stationary bike for 20 minutes. Pulse rate was registered at rest, after 10 and then 20 minutes of workout, and again after three minutes of recovery. Six months before the initiation of the fitness program the patient suffered three hemorrhages: two spontaneous in the left elbow and left ankle and one in the right leg due to a small unspecified trauma. All three hemorrhages were treated by means of clotting factors (CF’s). During the program period, the first hemorrhage treated with CF’s occurred in the left elbow by trauma after increasing the exercise load. Twelve months later, the patient had spontaneous bleeding in the same joint. The least improvement in strength was found for the triceps brachii with 33%, whereas the knee extensors improved the most with 257%. The average muscle strength increase was 121%. Monitored physical exercise is an important vehicle in treating of people with hemophilia, presenting the need for resistance training specific for hemophilic patients to prevent injuries and avoiding early wear of the musculoskeletal system. The objective of this study was to present the results of a physical activity program to prevent bleeding episodes in a person with severe hemophilia A and the prophylaxis without administering any clotting factors</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A hemofilia é uma doença que afeta a coagulação do sangue pela falta ou diminuição do fator de coagulação VIII ou IX. Esta deficiência faz com que a pessoa sangre por um tempo maior do que uma pessoa normal se não for medicada. Foi avaliado um indivíduo do sexo masculino de 31 anos com hemofilia A grave, artropatia hemofílica em cotovelo esquerdo e tornozelo direito. Foram realizadas 20 meses de treinamento resistido e aeróbio. As musculaturas envolvidas nos exercícios resistidos foram o peitoral maior, latíssimo do dorso, bíceps braquial, tríceps braquial, deltoide, quadríceps e isquiotibiais, sendo realizadas duas séries de 10 repetições para cada um e intervalo de 45 segundos, com intensidade de acordo com o teste inicial de 10 RM baseados na percepção de esforço de 11 a 13 da Escala de Borg. O exercício aeróbio foi realizado em bicicleta ergométrica horizontal com duração de 20 minutos, sendo aferida a frequência cardíaca de repouso, aos 10 e aos 20 minutos do exercício, e após três minutos do término. Nos seis meses antes de iniciar o programa o paciente sofreu três hemorragias, duas espontâneas, em cotovelo e tornozelo esquerdos e uma em coxa direita por pequeno trauma não identificado - em todas fazendo uso do FAH. Durante os 20 meses, o paciente teve uma hemorragia após oito meses de tratamento, no cotovelo esquerdo por trauma durante os exercícios após aumento de carga. Após este episódio, o paciente teve outro sangramento, porém espontâneo, na mesma articulação 12 meses depois. O menor ganho de força foi de tríceps braquial com 33% e o maior foi 257% em extensores de joelho, sendo a média de ganho geral de força muscular de 121%. A prática de exercícios físicos de forma supervisionada é um importante instrumento auxiliar no tratamento das pessoas com hemofilia, demonstrando a necessidade de treino de força e resistência muscular específico para este grupo de pessoas quanto à prevenção de lesões, evitando o desgaste e comprometimento do sistema musculoesquelético. O propósito deste estudo é apresentar os resultados obtidos em um programa de Condicionamento Físico, na prevenção de hemorragias de uma pessoa com hemofilia A grave e sua ação profilática, sem a administração do fator anti-hemofílico (FAH)</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114513</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150019</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 2 (2015); 97-100</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114513/112341</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114513/112342</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114517</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-14T14:50:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Investigação dos saberes quanto à capacidade funcional e qualidade de vida em idosas institucionalizadas, sob a ótica da CIF</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Investigating information regarding functional capacity and quality of life in institutionalized elderly according to the ICF</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Araujo, Luize Bueno de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moreira, Natália Boneti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Villegas, Isabela Lúcia Pelloso</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Loureiro, Ana Paula Cunha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Israel, Vera Lúcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gato, Simone Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kliemann, Gisele</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To evaluate the functional capacity and quality of life (QoL) of the institutionalized elderly from an ICF perspective. Method: A cross-sectional observational analytic study was conducted with 22 elderly residents (77.9 ± 9.41 years) of a long-stay care institution in Curitiba, Paraná. The following assessment instruments were applied: the Barthel Index, the Nottingham Health Profile Questionnaire, and the International Classification of Functioning, Disability, and Health (ICF). Analysis of the data was done by measures of central tendency (mean) and dispersion (standard deviation). The ICF was analyzed by the distribution of relative and absolute frequencies. Results: The majority of the sample had medium cognitive status and light functional dependency. The domain that most interfered with the elderly’s QOL was physical ability, energy level, sleep, and emotional and social pain, respectively. The ICF frequency distribution showed aspects not observed in the conventional assessment of the participants; in particular, it showed great specificity in the following functions: mental, sensory, and pain, the digestive, metabolic, and endocrine systems, psychomotor, movement, personal care, support and relationships, and individual activities. Conclusions: It is expected that the ICF will be adopted and used in various areas of health, including long-stay care facilities and multidisciplinary teams, so that professionals, through a unified and standard language, may intervene in the health of the individual as a whole.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Avaliar a funcionalidade por meio da capacidade funcional e qualidade de vida (QV), sob a ótica da CIF, de idosas institucionalizadas. Método: Foi realizado um estudo observacional transversal com 22 idosas (77,9 ± 9,41 anos) de uma instituição de longa permanência da cidade de Curitiba/Paraná. Foram aplicados os seguintes instrumentos de avaliação: Índice de Barthel, Questionário Perfil de Saúde de Nottingham e a Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde (CIF). A descrição dos dados foi feita por meio de medidas de tendência central (média) e dispersão (desvio-padrão). A CIF foi analisada de acordo com a distribuição de frequência relativa e absoluta. Resultados: A maioria das idosas apresentaram um médio estado cognitivo e dependência funcional leve. O domínio que mais interferiu a QV das idosas foi a habilidade física, nível energético, sono, dor, emocional e social, respectivamente. A distribuição de frequência da CIF evidenciou aspectos não observados na avaliação convencional das idosas, sobretudo, apresentou grande especificidade nas funções mentais, sensoriais e dor, sistema digestivo, metabólico e endócrino, psicomotora, movimento, cuidado pessoal, apoio e relacionamentos e atividades individuais. Conclusão: Espera-se que a CIF seja incorporada e utilizada em diversos setores da saúde, inclusive em instituições de longa permanência e equipes multidisciplinares, para que profissionais tenham ações de saúde que contemplem o indivíduo como um todo</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114517</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150022</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 3 (2015); 111-117</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114517/112344</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114517/112345</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114518</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-14T15:00:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Health profile of children diagnosed with cerebral palsy treated at the Lucy Montoro Rehabilitation Center in São José dos Campos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil epidemiológico de crianças diagnosticadas com paralisia cerebral atendidas no Centro de Reabilitação Lucy Montoro de São José dos Campos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Toledo, Carolina Abud Weber de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pereira, Cinthia Hermínia Carvalho Nascimento</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vinhaes, Marilia Menezes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Maria Izabel Romão</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nogueira, Maria Angélica Ratier Jajah</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil de Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Centros de Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Modalidades de Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Profile</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation Centers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy Modalities</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Paralisia Cerebral é um distúrbio da postura e do movimento decorrente de uma lesão cerebral podendo resultar em comprometimentos neuromotores, geralmente associados à gravidade da sequela e idade da criança. Objetivo: Avaliar o perfil epidemiológico das crianças diagnosticadas com Paralisia Cerebral atendidas no Centro de Reabilitação Lucy Montoro de São José dos Campos. Método: Foram revisados 83 prontuários no período de dezembro de 2011 até dezembro de 2014. Foram verificados os fatores como idade, gênero, procedência, realização prévia de fisioterapia, tipos de paralisia cerebral de acordo com a distribuição anatômica, crises convulsivas, órteses, aplicação de toxina botulínica, meios auxiliares de locomoção, pontuação no GMFM e nível no GMFCS. Resultados: Houve predominância do gênero masculino (55%) e com faixa etária de 4 a 6 anos (32%). A maioria foi proveniente de São José dos Campos (33 indivíduos). Quanto aos tipos de Paralisia Cerebral observamos maior prevalência para tetraplegia e diplegia (43% cada); 61% dos pacientes não apresentaram crises convulsivas e 30% aplicaram toxina botulínica. Os que faziam uso de meios auxiliares de locomoção totalizaram 41%. A pontuação prevalente do GMFM foi de 0 a 25% (22 indivíduos) e a maioria dos pacientes (29%) classificados como nível IV no GMFCS. Conclusão: São necessários mais estudos que definam o perfil epidemiológico das crianças com Paralisia Cerebral para melhor caracterização desta população e direcionamento de futuras pesquisas</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy is a disorder of posture and movement due to a brain injury and may result in neurological and motor dysfunction, usually associated with the severity of the sequelae and the child’s age. Objective: To evaluate the epidemiological profile of children diagnosed with Cerebral Palsy treated at the Lucy Montoro Rehabilitation Center in São José dos Campos in the state of São Paulo. Method: 83 medical records were reviewed from December 2011 through December 2014. Factors were recorded such as age, gender, origin, prior physical therapy, types of cerebral palsy according to anatomical distribution, seizures, orthoses, treatment with botulinum toxin, auxiliary means of locomotion, GMFM score, and GMFCS level. Results: There was a predominance of males (55%) and 32% of them were aged between 4 and 6 years. The majority were from São José dos Campos (33 individuals). As to the types of Cerebral Palsy, there was a higher prevalence for tetraplegia and diplegia (43% each); 61% of the patients did not have seizures, and 30% had applications of botulinum toxin. There were 41% who needed assistive devices for locomotion. The prevalent score of GMFM was 0-25% (22 individuals), and the largest portion (29%) classified as level IV in the GMFCS. Conclusion: Further studies are needed to define the epidemiological profile of children with Cerebral Palsy for a better characterization of this population and guidance for future research</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114518</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150023</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 3 (2015); 118-122</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114518/112346</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114518/112347</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114519</identifier>
        <datestamp>2017-11-27T10:26:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil, critérios de indicação e desfecho da inserção de gastrostomia em um hospital pediátrico universitário</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Profile, recommendation criteria, and outcome of gastrostomy tube insertions in a pediatric teaching hospital</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Soutinho, Luise Alexandre Rocha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fontes, Danyelle Araujo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Yonatta Salarini Vieira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brendim, Mariana Pinheiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marques, Charles Henrique Dias</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gastrostomy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Deglutition Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Nutritional Support</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Gastrostomia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos de Deglutição</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Apoio Nutricional</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Descrever o perfil dos pacientes submetidos à gastrostomia, os critérios de indicação e o desfecho dessa inserção em um hospital pediátrico universitário. Método: Estudo retrospectivo, quantitativo e descritivo, através de pesquisa em prontuários de pacientes submetidos à gastrostomia no período entre janeiro/2010 e dezembro/2012. Resultados: As doenças e condições de base mais frequentes foram: encefalopatia crônica da infância (77,5%), pneumonia (67,5%), crise convulsiva (57,5%) e desnutrição (42,5%). Apesar da maioria dos pacientes apresentar história de disfagia (62,5%), observou-se como via de nutrição mais frequente antes da inserção da gastrostomia a via oral (42,5%), seguida pela nasoenteral (40%). A introdução de dieta pela gastrostomia foi bem sucedida e ocorreu em média 2,82(± 1,19) dias após a sua inserção. Após seis meses de realização da gastrostomia, 80% dos pacientes permaneceram alimentando-se exclusivamente através desta via e somente 2,5% retirou a gastrostomia. 45% dos participantes apresentaram complicações da gastrostomia, sendo extravasamento do material gástrico (15%) e inflamação local (15%) as mais frequentes. Conclusão: O perfil dos pacientes submetidos à gastrostomia é de indivíduos, em sua maioria, com doença neurológica e respiratória, sem suporte respiratório, do sexo masculino e alimentando-se por via oral ou sonda nasoenteral por período prolongado. Os principais critérios de indicação foram doença neurológica e disfagia. Em relação ao desfecho, a introdução de dieta pela gastrostomia é bem sucedida, a maioria dos indivíduos permanece com este suporte nutricional a longo prazo e as complicações mais frequentes são extravasamento do material gástrico e inflamações na área da gastrostomia.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To describe the profile of patients undergoing a gastrostomy, the recommendations and outcome of this insertion in a Pediatric Teaching Hospital. Method: This was a retrospective, quantitative, and descriptive study that researched the records of patients who underwent a gastrostomy between January 2010 and December 2012. Results: The diseases and conditions most frequent were chronic infantile encephalopathy (77.5%), pneumonia (67.5%), seizures (57.5%), and malnutrition (42.5%). Although most patients presented a history of dysphagia (62.5%), oral feeding was observed most frequently as the most common form of nutrition, before the gastrostomy insertion (42.5%), followed by nasoenteric tube (40%). The introduction of nutrition by gastrostomy was successful and occurred an average of 2.82 (± 1.19) days after insertion. Six months after their gastrostomy, 80% of patients continued feeding only through this access tube and only 2.5% had removed the gastrostomy; 45% of the participants had gastrostomy complications, with extravasation of gastric material (15%) and local inflammation (15%) being the most frequent. Conclusion: The profile of patients undergoing gastrostomy is mostly of individuals with neurological and respiratory diseases, without respiratory support, of the male gender, and feeding by oral cavity or nasoenteric tube for a prolonged period. The main recommendation criteria were dysphagia and neurological diseases. Regarding the outcome, the introduction of nutrition by gastrostomy was successful; most individuals remained with this long-term nutritional support and the most common complications were gastric material extravasation and local inflammations.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114519</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150024</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 3 (2015); 123-129</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114519/112348</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114519/112349</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114520</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-14T15:05:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevalência de incontinência urinária entre idosos institucionalizados e sua relação com o estado mental, independência funcional e comorbidades associadas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Prevalence of urinary incontinence among institutionalized elderly and its relationship to mental state, functional independence, and associated comorbidities</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Quadros, Layse Biz de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Aguiar, Alessandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Menezes, Alessandra Vieira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alves, Elysama Fernandes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nery, Tatyana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bezerra, Poliana Penasso</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Institutionalization</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cognition</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Urinary Incontinence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Activities of Daily Living</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Institucionalização</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cognição</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Incontinência Urinária</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividades Cotidianas</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Incontinência urinária é definida como a perda involuntária de urina pela uretra podendo causar diversos problemas sociais e higiênicos, além de alterações que comprometem o convívio social como depressão, vergonha e isolamento, tendo maior prevalência nas mulheres do que nos homens. Objetivos: Determinar a prevalência de incontinência urinária em uma amostra de idosos institucionalizados e analisar sua relação com características sociodemográficas, comorbidades associadas, função cognitiva e independência funcional. Métodos: Estudo transversal, descritivo e exploratório. Participaram 27 idosos que atenderam aos critérios de inclusão, de ambos os sexos, residentes em uma instituição de longa permanência. Prevalência foi determinada pela porcentagem de idosos que apresentaram incontinência urinária; características sociodemográficas e comorbidades avaliadas através de uma ficha de anamnese padrão, revisados com os dados dos prontuários; função cognitiva avaliada através do Mini-Exame do Estado Mental e independência funcional através da escala de Barthel modificada. Comparação entre grupos - teste t de Student e associações - teste do qui-quadrado. Resultados: Nove idosos (33,33%) apresentaram incontinência urinária. Houve associação entre sexo e incontinência urinária, com prevalência maior para o sexo feminino (p = 0,029). A incontinência urinária possui associação com a baixa escolaridade (p = 0,014), o tempo de admissão na instituição (p = 0,004), classificação funcional (p = 0,003) e déficit cognitivo (p = 0,001). Conclusão: Incontinência urinária é frequente em idosos residentes em instituições de longa permanência, com maior prevalência no sexo feminino, havendo relação com a baixa escolaridade, maior tempo de admissão, maior dependência na realização das atividades e pior déficit cognitivo.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Urinary incontinence is defined as the involuntary loss of urine through the urethra, which may cause many social and hygienic problems and changes that compromise social life such as depression, shame, and isolation, with higher prevalence in women than in men. Objectives: To determine the prevalence of urinary incontinence in a sample of institutionalized elderly and analyze its relationship with sociodemographic characteristics, comorbidities, cognitive function, and functional independence. Methods: Cross-sectional, descriptive, and exploratory study. It included 27 seniors of both genders, living in a long-term care facility who met the inclusion criteria. Prevalence was determined by the percentage of elderly patients with urinary incontinence; sociodemographic characteristics and comorbidities were evaluated through a standard history record, reviewed with data from medical records; cognitive function was assessed using the Mini-Mental State Examination, and functional independence was assessed using the modified Barthel scale, while the comparison between groups was made through the Student t test and the associations, through the chi-square test. Results: Nine subjects (33.33%) had urinary incontinence. There was an association between gender and urinary incontinence, with higher prevalence for females (p = 0.029). Urinary incontinence was associated with low educational level (p = 0.014), time at the institution (p = 0.004), functional classification (p = 0.003), and cognitive impairment (p = 0.001). Conclusion: Urinary incontinence is common in elderly residents in long term care facilities, with a higher prevalence in women and was associated with low education, longer time at the institution, greater dependence in performing activities, and greater cognitive impairment</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114520</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150025</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 3 (2015); 130-134</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114520/112350</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114520/112351</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114521</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T21:13:00Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Quality of life and occupational performance of people with multiple sclerosis</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de vida e desempenho ocupacional de indivíduos com esclerose múltipla</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Andrade, Valeria Sousa de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Maysa de Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Esclerose Múltipla</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividades de Lazer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Autocuidado</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Trabalho</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia Ocupacional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Multiple Sclerosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Leisure Activities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Self Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Work</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Occupational Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a neurological chronic degenerative disease with a wide range of signs and symptoms that can compromise quality of life (QOL) and occupational performance (OP) of the individuals who have it. Objective: The aim of this study was to evaluate the existence of possible correlation between OP and QOL of people with MS. Method: This is a quantitative research whose individuals attended the neurology clinics of the hospital of a federal university in the state of Minas Gerais. The OP and the QOL were obtained by the Portuguese versions of the instruments Canadian Occupational Performance Measure (COPM) and Functional Assessment of Quality of Life (DEFU), respectively. Data analysis was performed using the Pearson correlation coefficient. Results: The sample involved 24 subjects, 66.7% female with an average age of 48.3 years (SD = 10.21). The relapsing remitting type (RR) of MS was the most frequently observed (91.7%). The results of the COPM showed that most participants showed a performance ranging from moderate to bad. The activities listed as difficult were “walking down the street, up and down stairs, go to the house of family and friends, dancing and reading (score of 6.7 by around 75% of the subjects). The QOL of the participants were good, according to the DEFU, with 90% of subjects achieving a score above 72 points. The association between the total score of the DEFU with the scores of the COPM showed no statistically significant correlation. The correlation between the domain “mobility” of DEFU correlated significantly with the score of the performance of the COPM (r = 0.438, p = 0.032). Conclusion: Fatigue is one of the most common and disturbing manifestations of MS and can compromise the performance of people in different ways, being reported by 92% of subjects in the study. It can be explained by the decreased number of outbreaks observed, the RR type of the disease and a possible family and social support. It is worth noting that some research participants pointed out they get acquainted with the aspects of the disease by the Internet or meetings and associations, a fact that, according to them, led them to become aware of the evolutionary and deteriorating character of the disease. This may have led them to reflect on their life situation and influenced their opinion about its quality.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A esclerose múltipla (EM) é uma doença neurológica degenerativa e crônica com ampla gama de sinais e sintomas que podem comprometer a qualidade de vida (QV) e o desempenho ocupacional (DO) dos indivíduos que a exibem. Objetivo: Resumiu-se em avaliar a existência de possível correlaçao entre DO e QV em populaçao com essa doença. Método: Trata-se de uma pesquisa transversal e quantitativa cujos indivíduos frequentavam o ambulatório de neurologia do hospital de clínicas de uma universidade federal no estado de Minas Gerais. O DO e a QV dos indivíduos foram obtidos através da versao em português dos instrumentos Medida Canadense de Desempenho Ocupacional (COPM) e Escala de Determinaçao Funcional da Qualidade de Vida (DEFU), respectivamente. A análise dos dados foi realizada por meio do Coeficiente de Correlaçao de Pearson. Resultados: A amostra envolveu 24 sujeitos, sendo 66,7% do sexo feminino com idade média de 48,3 anos (DP = 10,21). O tipo remitente recorrente (RR) de EM foi o mais observado (91,7%). Os resultados da COPM revelaram que a maior parte dos participantes apresentou desempenho variando de moderado a ruim, tendo sido enumeradas as atividades "andar na rua, subir e descer escadas, ir à casa de familiares e amigos, dançar e ler" como mais difíceis de serem realizadas. Mais de 75% dos indivíduos obtiveram escores abaixo de 6,7 pontos. A DEFU indicou que a QV dos participantes se configurou como boa, tendo 90% dos indivíduos alcançando escore acima de 72 pontos. A associaçao entre o escore da DEFU e seus domínios com os escores de desempenho e satisfaçao da COPM nao apresentou correlaçao estatisticamente significante. A correlaçao entre a "mobilidade" da DEFU apresentou correlaçao significativa com o escore de desempenho da COPM (r = 0,438, p = 0,032). Conclusao: A fadiga é uma das manifestaçoes mais comuns e perturbadoras e pode comprometer o desempenho nas funçoes individuais de forma variada, sendo relatada por 92% dos indivíduos deste estudo. Isto pode ser explicado pelo diminuído número de surtos observados, pela predominância do tipo RR da doença, possível suporte familiar e social. Salienta-se também que alguns participantes da pesquisa mencionaram inteirar-se quanto aos aspectos da doença através da internet ou e reunioes em associaçoes, fato que, segundo eles, os levou a se tornar a par do caráter evolutivo e deteriorante da doença. Isto pode tê-los levado a refletir sobre sua situaçao de vida e ter influenciado sua opiniao sobre a qualidade da mesma.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114521</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150026</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 3 (2015); 135-140</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114521/112352</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114532</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-14T15:16:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Functional performance of wheelchair basketball players with spinal cord injury</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Desempenho funcional de jogadores de basquete em cadeira de rodas com traumatismo da medula espinal</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Fréz, Andersom Ricardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Andrezza Thimoteo de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Quartiero, Cíntia Raquel Bim</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spinal Cord Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Wheelchairs</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos da Medula Espinal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação em Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividade Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cadeiras de Rodas</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Spinal cord injuries affect people’s daily activities and limit their mobility and participation in the community. Adapted sports improve functioning because they supplement the rehabilitation of people who need a wheelchair for mobility. Objective: The aim of this study was to evaluate the functional performance of wheelchair basketball players with spinal cord injury. Method: This cross-sectional study was conducted with 12 athletes. To evaluate their functional performance the Modified Barthel Index, the adapted version of Texas Fitness test, and the medicine ball test were applied. The correlation of functional dependence with other functional performance tests was performed by the nonparametric Spearman test. Results: Six athletes were classified as moderately dependent and six as mildly dependent. The average time for the adapted version of Texas Fitness test was 27.3 ± 3.8 seconds. The average distance for the medicine ball test was 5.2 ± 0.9 meters. We observed a strong negative correlation between the Modified Barthel Index and the adapted version of Texas Fitness test (r = -0.9193, p &amp;lt; 0.0001). Conclusion: The sample group presented as mildly to moderately dependent in carrying out the activities of daily living, with upper limb strength similar to what is described in the literature, but with less agility</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Os traumatismos da medula espinal comprometem as atividades diárias e limitam a mobilidade e a participação na comunidade. A prática do esporte adaptado melhora a funcionalidade, pois ela complementa o processo de reabilitação de pessoas que precisam de cadeira de rodas para locomoção. Objetivo: Avaliar o desempenho funcional de atletas praticantes de basquetebol em cadeira de rodas com disfunções por traumatismo da medula espinal. Método: Foi realizado um estudo transversal com 12 atletas. Para avaliar o desempenho funcional foi aplicado o Índice de Barthel Modificado, o teste Ziguezague adaptado e o teste de arremesso de medicineball. A correlação do grau de dependência funcional com os demais testes de desempenho funcional foi realizada pelo teste de correlação não paramétrica de Spearman. Resultados: Seis atletas apresentavam dependência moderada e seis dependência leve. O tempo médio para percorre o teste de agilidade em zigue-zague foi de 27,3 ± 3,8 segundos. A distância média para arremesso de medicineball foi de 5,2 ± 0,9 metros. Observou-se correlação negativa e forte entre o Índice de Barthel e o teste de agilidade (r = -0,9193, p &amp;lt; 0,0001). Conclusão: A amostra estudada apresentou-se como dependente moderada e leve para a realização das atividades de vida diária, com potência de membro superior e cintura escapula semelhante aos descritos na literatura e agilidade abaixo dos valores citados na literatura</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114532</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150027</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 3 (2015); 141-144</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114532/112355</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114532/112356</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114534</identifier>
        <datestamp>2017-11-27T10:26:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Diferenças no arremesso de jogadores de basquete em cadeira de rodas e convencional</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Differences of free-throw shot in wheelchair basketball and conventional players</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Eltz, Giovana Duarte</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moraes, Enaile Farias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Stocchero, Cíntia Mussi Alvim</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rocha, Clarice Sperotto dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Matos, Mauro Gomes</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sports for Persons with Disabilities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Basketball</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Upper Extremity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electromyography</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Esportes para Pessoas com Deficiência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Basquetebol</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Extremidade Superior</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Eletromiografia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O basquete em cadeira de rodas (BCR) segue praticamente as mesmas regras do basquete convencional (BC). Objetivo: Avaliar a ativação eletromiográfica dos músculos peitoral maior (PM), deltóide anterior (DA) e tríceps braquial (TB) durante o arremesso em atletas de BC e BCR. Método: Estudo transversal, no qual onze sujeitos foram submetidos a uma avaliação eletromiográfica dos músculos PM, DA, TB no membro que realiza o arremesso. Foi utilizado um eletromiógrafo de 4 canais (Miotec/Brasil) (2000Hz/canal). Resultados: Na comparação entre os músculos, o grupo BC mostrou diferença significativa, sendo observada maior ativação do músculo DA em relação aos demais, já no grupo BCR, não houve diferença. Na comparação entre os grupos, o músculo PM mostrou maior ativação no grupo BCR, enquanto o músculo DA estava mais ativo no grupo BC. O músculo TB não apresentou diferença significativa entre os grupos. Conclusão: A partir dos resultados do presente estudo os atletas dos grupos BC e BCR apresentaram diferenças na ativação elétrica durante o movimento do arremesso. Entretanto ambos os grupos ativaram mais o DA, seguido do TB e o músculo menos ativado foi o PM, sendo estas diferenças mais visíveis no grupo BC.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Wheelchair Basketball (WB) follows almost the same rules as Conventional Basketball (CB). Objective: Evaluate the electromyographic (EMG) activation of the pectoralis major (PM), anterior deltoid (AD), and triceps brachii (TB) muscles during shooting in CB and WB athletes and to verify whether there is any difference in muscle activation between the categories. Method: Comparing two groups in a transversal study, CB and WB, in which eleven individuals submitted to an electromyographic examination, of muscles PM, AD, TB on the extremity that was doing the shooting. We used a 4-channel EMG (Miotec/Brazil) (2000Hz/channel). Results: Comparing the muscles, the CB group showed a significant difference: greater AD muscle activation compared to the others; however in the WB group, no differences were found. When comparing between the groups, the PM muscle showed greater activation in the WB group, while the AD muscle was more active in the CB group. The TB muscle showed no difference between groups. Conclusion: From these results, the athletes from the CB and WB groups showed differences in muscle activation during shooting. However, both groups activated the AD the most, followed by the TB. The least active muscle was the PM, and these differences were more visible in the CB group.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114534</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150028</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 3 (2015); 145-149</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114534/112357</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114534/112358</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114535</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-14T16:40:41Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliações que mensurem a percepção dos déficits em indivíduos com lesão cerebral adquirida: uma revisão da literatura</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Assessments measuring the perception of deficits in individuals with acquired brain injuries: a review of the literature</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Forattore, Fernanda de Sousa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro, Rafaela Larsen</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos Encefálicos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Consciência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Questionários</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Brain Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Conscience</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Questionnaires</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Through a review of the literature, to select assessments measuring the perception of deficits of individuals with acquired brain injuries who have undergone a self-awareness intervention. Method: A review in the BIREME and PubMed databases was performed going over the past 10 years. Results: In this paper, eleven articles were selected that contained assessments of self-awareness before and after a therapeutic intervention and that had sampled individuals with diagnoses of traumatic brain injury (TBI), stroke, or cerebral tumor. Conclusion: A significant number of publications were found from Australia, European countries, and the United States. The instruments mostly used in the studies were the Self-awareness of Deficits Interview (SADI) and the Awareness Questionnaire (AQ). No validated and standardized studies or evaluations were found from Brazil. Thus, development, translation, and adaptation of assessments measuring the perception of awareness in the Brazilian population are required in order to provide an evidencebased practice by the use of intervention models</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Através de uma revisão da literatura, selecionar avaliações que mensurem a percepção dos déficits do indivíduo com lesão cerebral adquirida submetido à intervenção de autoconsciência. Método: Foi realizada revisão nas bases de dados da BIREME e PubMed, referente aos últimos 10 anos. Resultados: Foram selecionados no trabalho onze artigos que incluíram avaliações de autoconsciência antes e depois de uma intervenção terapêutica e que tivessem como público indiví- duos com diagnósticos de traumatismo crânio-encefálico (TCE), acidente vascular encefálico (AVE) ou tumor cerebral. Conclusão: Observou-se um número significativo de publicações na Austrália, nos países europeus e nos Estados Unidos. Os instrumentos mais utilizados nos estudos foram o Self-awareness of Deficits Interview (SADI) e Awareness Questionnaire (AQ). Não foram encontrados estudos e avaliações padronizadas e validadas no Brasil. Dessa forma, se faz necessário o desenvolvimento, tradução e adaptação de avaliações, que mensurem a percepção da consciência na população brasileira para proporcionar uma prática baseada em evidências pela utilização de modelos específicos de intervenção</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114535</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150029</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 3 (2015); 150-154</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114535/112359</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114535/112360</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114536</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-14T16:48:23Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effect of using orthoses on prolonging ambulation in patients with Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy: review of literature</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeito do uso das órteses no prolongamento da marcha de pacientes com distrofia muscular de Duchenne: revisão da literatura</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Mariana Angélica de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cezarani, Ananda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mattiello-Sverzut, Ana Cláudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscular Dystrophy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Duchenne</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Orthotic Devices</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Distrofia Muscular de Duchenne</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Aparelhos Ortopédicos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A capacidade de marcha em pacientes com distrofia muscular de Duchenne diminui progressivamente devido ao avanço da fraqueza e encurtamento muscular. As órteses para membros inferiores são frequentemente prescritas na tentativa de prolongar a marcha nestes pacientes. Objetivo: Realizar uma revisão da literatura a fim de verificar o efeito do uso das órteses em relação ao prolongamento do tempo de marcha. Método: Foi realizado um levantamento bibliográfico nas bases PUBMED, PEDRO e SCIELO com as palavras-chave orthoses, bracing, gait, gait loss, ambulation, Duchenne muscular dystrophy. Resultados: Nos quatorze artigos selecionados foi identificada a prescrição das órteses do tipo KAFO (também chamadas de órteses longas) e AFO, sempre associada a outra intervenção terapêutica. A maioria dos estudos relatou que o uso do dispositivo prolonga o tempo de marcha. Conclusão: O uso da órtese, independentemente do tipo, prolonga a deambulação, pois retarda o avanço de encurtamentos. Assim, sugere-se o início precoce da AFO a fim de minimizar o prejuízo funcional característico da doença</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The walking ability of patients with Duchenne muscular dystrophy gradually decreases due to advancing weakness and muscle contracture. Lower limb orthoses are often prescribed in an attempt to prolong ambulation in these patients. Objective: To perform a literature review in order to verify the relationship between using orthoses and prolonging ambulation. Method: A literature review was performed in the PUBMED, PEDRO, and SCIELO databases with the keywords orthoses, bracing, gait, gait loss, ambulation, and Duchenne muscular dystrophy. Results: In 14 selected articles the prescription of knee-ankle-foot orthoses (KAFO) (also called long orthoses) and anklefoot orthoses (AFO) was identified, always associated with another therapeutic intervention. Most studies have reported that the use of such a device prolongs ambulation. Conclusion: The use of orthoses, regardless of type, prolongs ambulation, because it delays the progress of muscle contracture. Thus, the early use of AFO is recommended in order to minimize the functional impairment characteristic of the disease</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114536</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150030</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 3 (2015); 155-159</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114536/112362</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114536/112363</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/114537</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-10-14T14:41:49Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da qualidade de vida de portadores de insuficiência cardíaca congestiva e sua correlação com a Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Assessment of quality of life in patients with congestive heart failure and its correlation with the International Classification of Functioning, Disability, and Health</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zaponi, Renata Souza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Frez, Andersom Ricardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mora, Cintia Teixeira Rossato</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ruaro, João Afonso</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Daniel, Christiane Riedi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Heart Failure</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Insuficiência Cardíaca</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To evaluate the quality of life of patients with heart failure and correlate it with the International Classification of Functioning, Disability, and Health (ICF). Method: This is a crosssectional study with a sample of 19 patients, mean age of 66.28 ± 10.93 years, whose quality of life was assessed by the Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire (MLHFQ); for each question a domain of ICF was given whose results were then correlated. Results: The average MLHFQ questionnaire score was 61.21 ± 17.56. There was a positive correlation between the quality of life and left ventricular ejection fraction (r = 0.75; p = 0.0006), which was not seen when comparing the quality of life with functional class. There was a high correlation between patient outcomes and the assessment of the physiotherapist using the ICF. Conclusions: The MLFHQ questionnaire includes the requirements of the ICF, showing a high correlation between its responses and those from the ICF, and is considered global, which allows these instruments to be used in evaluating patients with congestive heart failure (CHF)</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Avaliar a qualidade de vida de pacientes com insuficiência cardíaca e correlacionar com a Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde (CIF). Método: Trata-se de um estudo transversal, com amostra de 19 pacientes, com idade média de 66,28 ± 10,93 anos cuja qualidade de vida foi avaliada através do questionário de qualidade de vida Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire (MLHFQ), sendo que para cada questão foi determinado uma categoria da CIF e estes resultados foram correlacionados. Resultados: A média do escore do questioná- rio MLHFQ foi de 61,21 ± 17,56. Verificou-se correlação positiva entre a qualidade de vida e fração de ejeção do ventrículo esquerdo (r = 0,75; p = 0,0006), fato que não ocorreu ao comparar a qualidade de vida com a classe funcional. Observou-se alta correlação entre as respostas dos pacientes e a avaliação do fisioterapeuta utilizando a CIF. Conclusões: O questionário MLFHQ contempla as exigências da CIF, possuindo alta correlação entre as respostas de ambos, sendo considerado global, o que possibilita o emprego destes instrumentos na avaliação de pacientes com insuficiência cardíaca congestiva (ICC)</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114537</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150021</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 3 (2015); 105-110</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114537/112364</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/114537/112365</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/121614</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T22:09:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Valorizando o exame clínico</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zereu, Alexandre Angelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Furlan, Andréa Dompieri</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carneiro, Armando Pereira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Antonio Cardoso dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Terreri, Antonio Sérgio Almeida Prado</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Carlos Alberto dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lourenço, Claudete</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fonseca, Gilberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Milman, Gilda de Matos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Shinzato, Gilson Tanaka</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Haziyoma, Helena Seguehi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Yeng, Lin Tehia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ikegami, Marcelo Morito</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Miazaki, Margarida Harumi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imamura, Marta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Leitão, Raimundo Edson de Araújo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imamura, Satiko Tomikawa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medicina Física e Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exames Médicos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical and Rehabilitation Medicine</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical Examination</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Nosso roteiro dé Avaliação Fisiátrica do Amputado será sucinto, visando orientar o médico na condução dos casos, de maneira segura e eficiente. Nos portadores de amputações de membros, o que mais importa é a pessoa e não o membro amputado, daí a necessidade de urna abordagem global do paciente, buscando o máximo de suas potencialidades não só, no aspecto físico, mas também psicossocial, familiar e profissional. É indispensável a memorização das principais causas e complicações das amputações para a realização da avaliação.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1995-11-18</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/121614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v2i2a121614</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 2 n. 2 (1995); 2-56</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/121614/118514</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 1995 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/121847</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-31T22:15:31Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudo da interferência dos déficits motor e sensitivo na função manual de pacientes hemiplégicos submetidos à estimulação elétrica funcional (FES)</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Miyazaki, Margarida Harumi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lourenção, Maria Inês</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro Sobrinho, José Brenha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lourenço, Claudete</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estimulação Elétrica Funcional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiplegia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O presente estudo procura identificar os aspectos fisiopatológicos que&amp;nbsp;condicionam um mau prognóstico na aplicação da Estimulação Elétrica&amp;nbsp;Funcional (FES), sendo pareados os bons e maus resultados com os déficits&amp;nbsp;motor e sensitivo. Foram avaliados 17 pacientes hemiplégicos, com praxia e&amp;nbsp;gnosia preservados, submetidos às técnicas convencionais da Terapia&amp;nbsp;Ocupacional e Estimulação Elétrica Funcional. Os eletrodos foram ajustados,&amp;nbsp;de modo a obter dorsiflexão de punho e dedos e abdução de polegar, quando&amp;nbsp;possível. Foram realizadas avaliações das sensibilidades superficial (tactil e&amp;nbsp;dolorosa) e profunda (reconhecimento de diferentes posições do membro&amp;nbsp;acometido), das preensões tipo cilindro, esfera, gancho e pinças lateral, polpa&amp;nbsp;a polpa e 03 pontos, antes e logo após 06 meses de FES. Resultados mostraram&amp;nbsp;que 13 pacientes obtiveram melhora da movimentação ativa manual. Os&amp;nbsp;pacientes que melhoraram tinham sensibilidade superficial e profunda&amp;nbsp;normal ou alterada, mas apresentavam algum tipo de movimentação manual&amp;nbsp;espontânea. Os pacientes, que não melhoraram, tinham alterações das&amp;nbsp;sensibilidades superficial e/ou profunda, mas não tinham qualquer&amp;nbsp;movimentação manual ativa. Conclui-se que a associação da Estimulação&amp;nbsp;Elétrica Funcional às técnicas convencionais de Terapia Ocupacional é um&amp;nbsp;meio eficaz de melhorar a função manual de pacientes hemiplégicos com&amp;nbsp;movimentação voluntária parcialmente preservada.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>1995-12-14</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/121847</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v2i3a121847</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 2 n. 3 (1995); 24-26</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/121847/118697</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 1995 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/122342</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T21:13:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Ansiedade, depressão e desesperança no cuidador familiar de pacientes com alterações neuropsicológicas</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Anxiety, depression and hopelessness in family caregivers of patients with neuropsychological sequelae</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Nobre, Isadora Di Natale</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lemos, Carolina dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pardini, Adriana Cristina Guimarães</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Janaína de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Salles, Isabel Chateaubriand Diniz</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Anxiety</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Depression</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Caregivers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neuropsychology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ansiedade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Depressão</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cuidadores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neuropsicologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: This article’s aim is to determine the incidence of anxiety, depression, and hopelessnessamong 54 family caregivers of patients with neuropsychological sequelae after brain injury inadulthood. Methods: This is an observational cross-sectional study and quantitative analysis,developed in a rehabilitation center (Associação de Assistência à Criança Deficiente - AACD) locatedin the city of Sao Paulo. The following instruments were applied: Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI), BeckDepression Inventory (BDI), and Beck Hopelessness Scale (BHS), along with a questionnaire tocharacterize the sample. Results: Data was statistically analyzed and 55.6% of the family caregiversshowed signs of anxiety, 20.4% depression, and 31.5% hopelessness. Conclusion: It was concludedthat the family caregivers in this study were under significant psychological distress, indicating aneed for actions aimed specifically at them in rehabilitation programs.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo:&amp;nbsp;Identificar a incidência de ansiedade, depressão e desesperança em 54 cuidadores familiares de pacientes com alteração neuropsicológica após lesão encefálica ocorrida na idade adulta. Métodos:&amp;nbsp;Trata-se de um estudo observacional com corte transversal e análise quantitativa, desenvolvido em um centro de reabilitação (Associação de Assistência à Criança Deficiente - AACD) localizado na cidade de São Paulo. Foram aplicados os instrumentos: Inventário de Ansiedade Beck (BAI), Inventário de Depressão Beck (BDI) e Escala de Desesperança Beck (BHS), juntamente com um questionário de caracterização da amostra.&amp;nbsp;Resultados:&amp;nbsp;Os dados foram analisados estatisticamente e dos familiares entrevistados 55,6% apresentou índices de ansiedade, 20,4% apresentou depressão e 31,5% desesperança.&amp;nbsp;Conclusão:&amp;nbsp;Os cuidadores familiares desta pesquisa apresentaram relevante sofrimento psíquico, apontando a necessidade de ações voltadas especificamente a eles nos programas de reabilitação.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-12-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122342</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150031</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 4 (2015); 160-165</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122342/119074</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122342/119107</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/122469</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T21:13:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da destreza manual em indivíduos com artrite reumatoide</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of manual dexterity in individuals with rheumatoid arthritis</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Armanini, Karen Kowalski</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Weber, Fernanda Matos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Muraro, Caren Fernanda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Borges Junior, Noé Gomes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Domenech, Susana Cristina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gevaerd, Monique da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Artrite Reumatoide</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Destreza Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Mãos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rheumatoid Arthritis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Skills</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hands</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Analisar a destreza manual de pacientes com AR em funçao do nível de atividade da doença. Métodos: Foram avaliados 23 indivíduos com AR, com média de idade de 54,78 ± 12,54 anos. Todos os participantes foram submetidos a uma entrevista para coleta dos dados de identificaçao e história clínica, coleta de sangue para análise da Proteína C-Reativa, determinaçao do nível de atividade da doença por meio do Disease Activity Score (DAS-28) e avaliaçao da destreza manual pelo Moberg Picking-Up Test (MPUT). Para descartar problemas de sensibilidade tátil dos indivíduos, foi aplicado o teste de sensibilidade dos monofilamentos de Semmes-Weinstein. Resultados: Foi observado que o grupo classificado em moderada atividade da doença apresentou maior tempo para execuçao do MPUT com olhos abertos na mao dominante, quando comparado ao grupo em baixa atividade. O grupo em alta atividade da doença também demorou mais para realizar o MPUT com os olhos fechados na mao dominante, em comparaçao ao grupo em baixa atividade. Adicionalmente, houve uma correlaçao positiva entre o DAS-28 e o tempo de realizaçao do MPUT com os olhos fechados na mao dominante. Conclusao: A destreza manual de indivíduos com AR pode estar prejudicada em funçao do nível de atividade da doença, repercutindo na dificuldade para a realizaçao das atividades de vida diária. Estes dados podem contribuir para a determinaçao de estratégias de tratamento visando a melhoria da qualidade de vida de pacientes com AR.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To analyze the manual dexterity of patients with RA based on the level of disease activity. Methods: The study evaluated twenty-three individuals with RA, of both sexes, aged 54.78 (± 12.54) years. All participants underwent an interview for data collection for identification and medical history, blood collection for dosage of C-reactive protein (CRP), determination of disease activity level through the Disease Activity Score-28 (DAS-28), and evaluation of manual dexterity with the Moberg Pickup Test (MPUT). The Semmes-Weinstein Monofilaments were applied to discard any problems of tactile sensitivity. Results: It was observed that the group ranked as having moderate disease activity took longer to perform the MPUT with the dominant hand and open eyes, in comparison with the group ranked as having low disease activity. The group ranked as having high disease activity also took longer to perform the MPUT with the dominant hand and closed eyes, in comparison with the group ranked as having low disease activity. In addition, there was a positive correlation between the DAS-28 and the time to perform the MPUT with the dominant hand and closed eyes. Conclusion: Manual dexterity can be impaired by the level of disease activity in individuals with RA, generating difficulties in performing activities of daily living. These results can contribute to identifying better treatment strategies in order to improve the quality of life of these patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-12-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122469</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150032</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 4 (2015); 166-171</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122469/119121</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122469/119122</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/122488</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T21:13:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores de risco cardiovasculares em pacientes com fibromialgia</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Zanetti, Hugo Ribeiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Facioli, Tábata de Paula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Furlanetto Júnior, Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Haddad, Eduardo Gaspareto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Leandro Teixeira Paranhos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Alexandre</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fibromyalgia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Risk Factors</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sedentary Lifestyle</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fibromialgia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fatores de Risco</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estilo de Vida Sedentário</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Verificar os fatores de risco cardiovasculares em pacientes com fibromialgia (FM). Métodos: O estudo foi composto por 40 mulheres diagnosticadas com FM e encaminhadas para o setor de Reabilitação Física do Hospital de Clínicas de Uberlândia. Foi aplicado um questionário do American College of Sports Medicine contendo perguntas sobre histórico familiar; tabagismo; hipertensão; dislipidemia; glicose de jejum alterada; obesidade; sedentarismo e etilismo. Resultados: O sedentarismo teve prevalência de 92,5%, hereditariedade 52,5%, obesidade 50%, hipertensão arterial 45%, dislipidemia 37,5%, tabagismo 25%, etilismo 8% e diabetes 7,5%. Além disso, 60% da amostra apresentou três ou mais fatores de risco, 30% apresentou 2 fatores e 10% apresentou apenas um fator de risco. Conclusão: Pacientes com FM apresentam vários fatores de risco cardiovasculares, desse modo, deve-se orientar tais pacientes à mudança do estilo de vida, a fim de reduzir tais fatores e consequentemente eventos cardíacos futuros, e proporciona melhora do quadro de dor.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-12-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122488</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150033</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 4 (2015); 172-175</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122488/119130</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122488/119131</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/122489</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T21:13:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Permanência prolongada na postura sentada e desconforto físico em estudantes universitários</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Caromano, Fátima Aparecida</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Amorim, Cristina Aparecida Padoin de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rebelo, Cristina de Fátima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Contesini, Adriana Maria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fávero, Francis Meire</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Frutuoso, Jecilene Rosana Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kawai, Milena Missa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Voos, Mariana Callil</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Postura</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fadiga</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estilo de Vida Sedentário</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Posture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fatigue</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sedentary Lifestyle</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A evolução do homem promoveu adoção da postura sentada por períodos prolongados, induzindo alterações biomecânicas e fisiológicas no corpo. No ensino, a adoção desta postura pode induzir distúrbios musculoesqueléticos e desconforto físico, associado ou não com aprendizagem.&amp;nbsp;Objetivo:Quantificar e caracterizar o tempo de permanência na postura sentada por estudantes universitários e avaliar relação do tempo com queixas de dor e/ou desconforto.&amp;nbsp;Método:&amp;nbsp;Estudo quali-quantitativo. Coleta dos dados feita por meio de diário. Participaram 47 universitários que registraram número de horas na postura sentada, atividades, presença de dor e/ou desconforto e responderam pergunta aberta sobre suas observações referentes ao período experimental. Foi realizada análise estatística descritiva e calculado o coeficiente de correlação de Spearman entre elas, duas a duas. As respostas à pergunta aberta foram categorizadas e agrupadas segundo a frequência e similaridade.&amp;nbsp;Resultados:&amp;nbsp;Estudantes avaliados permaneceram longos períodos sentados (13,4 DP 1,5 horas). Percepção de desconforto do mobiliário foi relevante. Queixas de desconforto e/ou dor podem estar relacionadas com a permanência prolongada na postura sentada. Os locais com mais queixas de dor foram a cabeça, região cervical, ombros e lombossacral. Quanto maior o tempo na postura sentada, maior a incidência de queixas dor. Não se pode afirmar que a dor provoque ou aumente o nível de estresse.&amp;nbsp;Conclusão:&amp;nbsp;O diário foi ferramenta útil para coleta de dados e serviu como instrumento de interferência na auto-observação e autocuidado. Este estudo contribui para o entendimento de como a postura sentada afeta universitários e fornece indicadores para futuras intervenções.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-12-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122489</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150034</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 4 (2015); 176-180</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122489/119132</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122489/119133</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/122492</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T21:13:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Associação entre desempenho funcional e quedas em idosas classificadas segundo a faixa etária</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Amarante, Thiago Rogério Padilha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gomes, Anna Raquel Silveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Flavia Pinotti dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Coelho, Rodrigo Augusto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Valderramas, Silvia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidentes por Quedas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Accidental Falls</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo:&amp;nbsp;Avaliar o desempenho funcional e o histórico de quedas de idosas.&amp;nbsp;Método:&amp;nbsp;Estudo observacional de corte transversal, onde foram selecionadas 57 idosas da comunidade, divididas em 3 grupos, segundo a faixa etária: G1- 60 a 69 anos; G2- 70 a 79 anos e G3- 80 a 89 anos. Foram avaliados: mobilidade funcional ("Timed Up &amp;amp; Go Test"); potência muscular (Teste de sentar e levantar 5 vezes); força de preensão manual (dinamômetro manual JAMAR®), histórico e prevalência de quedas. A análise das diferenças intergrupos foi realizada por meio da ANOVA One way e post hoc Tukey. As correlações foram avaliadas por meio do teste de Spearman.&amp;nbsp;Resultados:&amp;nbsp;Idosas do G3 quando comparadas aos grupos G1 e G2, apresentaram diminuição da FPM (18,08 ± 3,29 Kgf&amp;nbsp;vs.&amp;nbsp;28,10 ± 4,26 Kgf; 18,08 ± 3,29Kgf&amp;nbsp;vs.&amp;nbsp;22,92 ± 4,01,&amp;nbsp;p =&amp;nbsp;0,001), da potencia muscular (14,44 ± 2,85s&amp;nbsp;vs.&amp;nbsp;12,27 ± 2,34s; 14,44 ± 2,85s&amp;nbsp;vs.&amp;nbsp;13,16 ± 2,27s,&amp;nbsp;p =&amp;nbsp;0,04) e da mobilidade funcional (11,56 ± 3,10s&amp;nbsp;vs.&amp;nbsp;8,57 ± 2,25s; 11,56 ± 3,10s&amp;nbsp;vs.&amp;nbsp;10,30 ± 2,58s,&amp;nbsp;p =&amp;nbsp;0,004). A maior prevalência de quedas foi nas idosas do G2 (52,6%) sendo que, nos últimos 6 meses, 26% caíram 1 vez, 5% caíram 2 vezes; 10% caíram 3 e 4 vezes. As idosas do G1 e G3 caíram 1 vez. A frequência de quedas apresentou correlação com mobilidade funcional (r = -0,52,&amp;nbsp;p =&amp;nbsp;0,018). A idade apresentou correlação com a força de preensão manual (r = -0,67,&amp;nbsp;p =&amp;nbsp;0,0001), potencia muscular (r = 0,31,&amp;nbsp;p =&amp;nbsp;0,02) e com mobilidade funcional (r = 0,49,&amp;nbsp;p =&amp;nbsp;0,0001).&amp;nbsp;Conclusão:&amp;nbsp;A prevalência de quedas foi maior na faixa etária entre 70-79 anos e quanto maior a idade pior o desempenho musculoesquelético e funcional.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-12-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122492</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150035</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 4 (2015); 181-185</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122492/119124</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122492/119125</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/122507</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T21:13:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A influência da postura corporal nos parâmetros do sistema de oscilometria de impulso em crianças</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Letícia Goulart</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Renata Maba</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Assumpção, Maíra Seabra de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schivinski, Camila Isabel Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Postura</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Mecânica Respiratória</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Testes de Função Respiratória</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Posture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Respiratory Mechanics</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Respiratory Function Tests</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Oscilometria de impulso (IOS) é um método alternativo e complementar de avaliação da mecânica respiratória, mas cuja técnica de execução ainda necessita padronização.&amp;nbsp;Objetivo:&amp;nbsp;Analisar e comparar os resultados de parâmetros do IOS quando realizado em escolares nas posições ortostática e sentada.&amp;nbsp;Método:&amp;nbsp;estudo analítico observacional transversal. Escolares saudáveis de 6 a 12 anos foram submetidos à espirometria e dois exames de IOS randomizados quanto à postura (sentada e ortostática). Os dados foram analisados no SPSS 20.0. Utilizou-se o teste Shapiro-Wilk e, segundo a normalidade dos dados, aplicou-se o teste de Wilcoxon ou&amp;nbsp;t&amp;nbsp;de&amp;nbsp;Student&amp;nbsp;para comparação das posturas. Na correlação entre dados antropométricos e as variáveis oscilométricas empregou-se o teste de Pearson ou Spearman, com&amp;nbsp;p&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;&amp;nbsp;0,05.&amp;nbsp;Resultados:&amp;nbsp;participaram 72 crianças, idade média de 8,42 ± 1,26. Não houve diferença entre as variáveis oscilométricas nas duas posturas. Na posição sentada, houve correlação negativa baixa entre altura de tronco (Altronco) e variáveis: resistência a 20Hz (R20) (p&amp;nbsp;= 0,034) e a 5Hz (R5) (p&amp;nbsp;= 0,041), resistência central (Rescent) (p&amp;nbsp;= 0,018) e impedância (Z) (p&amp;nbsp;= 0,030). Em ortostatismo verificou-se correlação negativa baixa entre idade e resistência periférica (Resper) (p&amp;nbsp;= 0,011), R5 (p&amp;nbsp;= 0,014) e Z (p&amp;nbsp;= 0,009).&amp;nbsp;Conclusão:&amp;nbsp;Não houve diferença nos valores das variáveis oscilométricas entre a postura sentada e ortostática. Contudo, a resistência das vias aéreas foi influenciada pela Altronco, estatura e idade. O ortostatismo parece ser a melhor posição para análise da Resper.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-12-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122507</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150036</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 4 (2015); 186-191</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122507/119127</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122507/119128</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/122508</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T21:13:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The ICF-CY for children and adolescents with osteogenesis imperfecta: the perspective of specialists</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A CIF-CJ para crianças e adolescentes com osteogênese imperfeita: a perspectiva de especialistas</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Tatiana Vasconcelos dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Llerena Júnior, Juan Clinton</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ribeiro, Carla Trevisan Martins</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificaçao Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Osteogênese Imperfeita</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Consenso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Osteogenesis Imperfecta</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Consensus</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: A partir da perspectiva de especialistas em Osteogênese Imperfeita (OI), identificar as categorias da Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde-versão crianças e jovens (CIF-CJ) mais relevantes para avaliação de pacientes. Métodos: Três etapas de questionários enviados por correio eletrônico para cinco especialistas em OI utilizando o método Delphi modificado. Os participantes escolheram a partir de uma lista de categorias de segundo nível da CIF-CJ, as mais relevantes para avaliação da funcionalidade em crianças e adolescentes com OI. Ao final da terceira etapa, foram selecionadas as categorias escolhidas por no mínimo 80% dos respondentes.&amp;nbsp;Resultados:&amp;nbsp;Todos os componentes atingiram categorias com consenso. Os componentes com maior número de categorias escolhidas foram Atividades e Participação e Fatores Ambientais. Conclusão:&amp;nbsp;Uma lista de categorias da CIF-CJ relevantes para OI pôde ser elaborada a partir da perspectiva de especialistas. Esta é uma importante etapa na elucidação do que deve ser avaliado em crianças e adolescentes com OI.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: From the perspective of specialists in Osteogenesis Imperfecta (OI), to identify the most relevant categories of the International Classification of Functioning, Disability, and Health: children and youth version (ICF-CY) to patients. Methods: Three-stage surveys were sent by email to five OI specialists using the modified Delphi method. From a list of second-level ICF-CY categories, the participants chose the most relevant categories to assess the functioning of children and adolescents with OI. At the end of the third stage, the categories considered relevant by at least 80% of the responders were selected. Results: Categorizations of all ICF-CY components were agreed upon. Activities, Participation, and Environmental Factors were the categories with the most components. Conclusion: A list of ICF-CY categories relevant to OI could be created from the perspective of specialists. This is an important step to highlight what to assess in children and adolescents with OI.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-12-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122508</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150037</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 4 (2015); 192-198</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122508/119106</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122508/119105</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/122509</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-12-02T20:37:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">How life style has been evaluated: a systematic review</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Como o estilo de vida tem sido avaliado: revisão sistemática</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pôrto, Elias Ferreira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kümpel, Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Castro, Antônio Adolfo Mattos de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Isis Modesto de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alfieri, Fábio Marcon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Lifestyle</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Questionnaires</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estilo de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Questionários</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The term lifestyle corresponds to the set of habits and customs that can be influenced and modified and which can contribute to promoting health. Objective: This study was to make a systematic review on the subject of lifestyle, what methods have been used to evaluate lifestyle, and what is considered a healthy lifestyle. Method: This study consisted of a systematic review on the possible methods of evaluating the lifestyle and habits of what is considered healthy lifestyle. The survey was conducted in electronic databases, national and international, LILACS, MEDLINE, PubMed, and SciELO, and free search on Google Brazil, by consulting the following descriptors: "life style" associated with "healthy. Results: We found 142 articles published between 1990 and 2012, 105 of which did not meet the established criteria, 28 were considered eligible and were included in the study, 10 used randomized and pseudo-randomized samples, and 17 were not randomized. Among the articles selected, there were four proposals to validate lifestyle-assessment instruments, and one systematic review. The instruments used were not very reliable for assessing lifestyle, and their methods were not responsive. Conclusion: These studies demonstrate the importance of a healthy lifestyle and that it be started early and continued throughout life; they define the main actions related to a healthy lifestyle as well as control of metabolic parameters, physical activities, and healthy eating, but the lifestyle-evaluation instruments are still poor in responsiveness.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O estilo de vida corresponde ao conjunto de hábitos e costumes que são influenciados e modificados que podem contribuir para a promoção da saúde.&amp;nbsp;Objetivo:&amp;nbsp;Realizar uma revisão sobre os métodos que têm sido utilizados para a avaliação do estilo de vida, assim como identificar o que tem sido considerado como estilo de vida saudável.&amp;nbsp;Método:&amp;nbsp;Este estudo consistiu em uma revisão sistemática sobre os possíveis métodos de avaliação do estilo de vida e hábitos que são considerados estilo de vida saudável. A pesquisa foi realizada nas bases de dados nacionais e internacionais: LILACS, MEDLINE, PubMed e SciELO, e busca livre no Google acadêmico, como os seguintes descritores: "estilo de vida" "estilo de vida saudável".&amp;nbsp;Resultados:&amp;nbsp;foram encontrados 142 artigos, sobre estilo de vida saudável, 105 não preencheram os critérios estabelecidos, 28 foram considerados elegíveis e foram incluídos no estudo, 10 tinham amostra randomizados, e um pseudo-randomizada, 17 não havia aleatorização no processo. Entre os artigos selecionados havia quatro propostas para validar instrumentos de avaliação de estilo de vida, e uma revisão sistemática. Os instrumentos utilizados nestes estudos não eram muito confiáveis para avaliar estilo de vida, os métodos destes apresentaram baixa responsividade.&amp;nbsp;Conclusão:&amp;nbsp;Podemos concluir que o estilo de vida saudável deve ser iniciado precocemente e continuar durante toda a vida, e as principais ações relacionadas a um estilo de vida saudável, controle de parâmetros metabólico, realizar atividades física, e alimentação saudável, entretanto os instrumentos de avaliação do estilo de vida ainda são pobre na capacidade de resposta.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-12-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122509</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150038</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 4 (2015); 199-205</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122509/119103</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122509/119104</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/122512</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T21:13:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Dupla tarefa como estratégia terapêutica em fisioterapia neurofuncional: uma revisão da literatura</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Dual task training as a therapeutic strategy in neurologic physical therapy: a literature review</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mendel, Tassiana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Barbosa, Wilames Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sasaki, Adriana Campos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Executive Function</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Attention</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Neurology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Função Executiva</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia por Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atenção</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neurologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Discuss the possibilities of dual task in the ambit of neurological rehabilitation. Methods: A survey was conducted in PUBMED, MEDLINE, LILACS, and PEDro, using the keywords "dual task" associated with each of the following terms separately: treatment, physical therapy, rehabilitation, exercise, training, divided attention, executive functions, and attentional demands. We selected only clinical trials that used dual task training in adults with neurological disease. Results: From the 2,024 articles found, 1,017 were excluded because they are duplicate. Among the remaining 1,007 articles, 998 were excluded after reviewing the abstracts. Nine articles were selected that included patients with stroke, brain injuries, Alzheimer's, and Parkinson's disease. Most articles used gait as the primary task, and in six studies the second task was cognitive. The training programs ranged between a total of 9 and 48 hours of training. Conclusion: Dual task training appears to improve gait, cognition, automation skills, and transference of learning, suggesting that this may be a valuable strategy for neurological rehabilitation. Nevertheless, it is still necessary to explain which tasks are more efficient and how long the learning retention lasts.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Discutir as possibilidades de utilizaçao da dupla tarefa no âmbito da reabilitaçao de pacientes neurológicos. Métodos: Foram realizadas buscas nas bases de dados PUBMED, MEDLINE, LILACS e PEDro, com o termo em inglês dual task associados a cada uma das palavras, em separado: treatment, physicaltherapy, rehabilitation, exercise, training, dividedattention, executivefunctions e attentionaldemands. Foram selecionados apenas ensaios clínicos que utilizaram o treinamento de dupla tarefa em populaçao adulta com doença ou lesao neurológica. Resultados: Dos 2024 artigos encontrados, 1017 foram excluídos por se tratarem de artigos duplicados. Dentre os 1007 restantes, 998 foram excluídos após a análise dos resumos. Os nove artigos selecionados avaliaram pacientes com acidente vascular encefálico, traumatismo encefálico, doença de Alzheimer e de Parkinson. A maioria utilizou a marcha como tarefa primária, e uma tarefa cognitiva como secundária. Os programas variaram entre 9 e 48 horas totais de treinamento. Conclusao: O treinamento de dupla tarefa parece ter efeitos positivos na marcha, cogniçao, habilidades de automatizaçao e transferência de aprendizado, sugerindo que essa pode ser uma estratégia valiosa para a reabilitaçao neurológica. Entretanto, ainda se faz necessário explicar quais as tarefas que sao mais eficientes, o período de intervençao adequado e a extensao do período de retençao do aprendizado.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-12-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122512</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150039</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 4 (2015); 206-211</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122512/119109</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122512/119110</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/122518</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-21T21:13:38Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Ganglionopatia como manifestação inicial de neoplasia pulmonar: relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Ganglionopathy as the initial manifestation of neoplastic lung disease: a case report</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gomes, Caio Ribeiro Azevedo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Bruno Nogueira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferrão, Gustavo Carneiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nunes, Andressa Silvia Faé</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ramos, Arquimedes de Moura</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chung, Tae Mo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nunes, Lucas Martins de Exel</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Polineuropatias</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Neoplasias Pulmonares</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Relatos de Casos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Polyneuropathies</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Lung Neoplasms</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Case Reports</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Ganglionopathy is a rare condition defined by an injury to the sensory neurons in the dorsal root ganglion. This disease belongs to a group of peripheral polyneuropathies with an exclusively sensory and axonal pattern and its diagnoses can be made by an electromyoneurographic study. The association between ganglionopathy and other underlying pathologies, such as some types of cancer, autoimmune diseases, and celiac disease is often mentioned in published studies. The purpose of this report was to describe the case of a patient suffering from ganglionopathy including a detailed discussion of the electromyoneurographic study that led the attending physician to a diagnosis of neoplastic lung disease. The conclusion therefore was that it is important for the neurophysiology specialist to keep in mind the possible causes of ganglionopathy and, through this diagnosis, to help the attending physician in making an early and full workup of the patient.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A ganglionopatia é uma entidade rara que consiste na afecção dos neurônios sensitivos da raiz dorsal, fazendo parte do grupo das polineuropatias periféricas do tipo exclusivamente sensitivo com comprometimento axonal e tendo seu diagnóstico feito através de estudo eletroneuromiográfico. A associação entre a ganglionopatia e outras patologias como neoplasias, doenças autoimunes, doença celíaca, entre outras é amplamente citada na literatura. O objetivo deste trabalho é descrever o caso clínico de um paciente com diagnóstico de neoplasia pulmonar cuja manifestação inicial foi a ganglionopatia, incluindo a descrição detalhada do exame eletroneuromiográfico que auxiliou no processo diagnóstico do médico assistente. Concluímos ser importante que o médico neurofisiologista tenha em mente as possíveis causas da ganglionopatia e saiba apontar o médico assistente para que a investigação possa ser realizada de maneira completa e precoce.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2015-12-01</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122518</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20150040</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 22 n. 4 (2015); 212-214</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122518/119117</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/122518/119118</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2015 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2023-08-08T14:49:26Z" completeListSize="935" cursor="550">acdafd4605db12cde1452bbed17e20a6</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
