<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-08-07T14:49:08Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="actafisiatrica">https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102918</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T19:26:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Radiological assessment of the angular values of back-lumbar and sacral-lumbar curvature in adolescents</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação radiológica dos valores angulares das curvaturas lombo-lombar e lombosacra em adolescentes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Giovanna Barros</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pereira, João Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pinal Curvatures</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Lordosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Adolescent</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Curvaturas da Coluna Vertebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lordose</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Adolescente</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The lumbar region is of great importance in the harmony and maintenance of the erect posture and must be included in any physiotherapeutic evaluation. Due to the difficulty in measuring what is called a "normal" lumbar curvature, this study was carried out with the objective of evaluating lumbar lordosis through the angular measurement of the back-lumbar (L1-L5) and sacral-lumbar (L1-S1) curvatures, to establish the indicative values of those curvatures in adolescents. Methods: 22 asymptomatic young adults of both sexes, aged 14 to 18 years, participated in this study. All volunteers were submitted to radiological assessment in the lumbar region on the sagittal plane, performed at Hospital Doutor Joao Felício in the city of Juiz de Fora, state of Minas Gerais, Brazil. The angular measures of the lumbar curvatures were performed using the Cobb Method, directly over the radiographies. Results: No statistically significant differences were observed regarding gender for the angular values of the back-lumbar (L1-L5) and the sacrallumbar (L1-S1) curvatures. Although there is no consensus in the literature regarding the analysis and definition of the curvature angles of the lumbar column on the sagittal plane, the results have shown to be compatible with the ones reported in literature, with values that are similar to the ones found by other authors. Conclusion: The normative angular values for the back-lumbar and sacral-lumbar curvatures can be established as angular averages of 44.44º and 57.5º, respectively, for asymptomatic adolescents.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A região lombar é de grande importância na harmonia e manutenção da postura ereta e deve ser incluída em qualquer avaliação fisioterapêutica. Devido à dificuldade em definir o que pode ser chamado de curvatura lombar normal, realizou-se este estudo com o objetivo de avaliar a lordose lombar através das medidas angulares das curvaturas lombo-lombar (L1-L5) e lombo-sacra (L1-S1), para se os estabelecerem os valores indicativos dessas curvaturas em adolescentes. Métodos: Participaram deste estudo 22 jovens assintomáticos, de ambos os sexos, com idade variando entre 14 e 18 anos. Todos os voluntários foram submetidos ao exame radiológico da região lombar em plano sagital, realizado no Hospital Doutor João Felício na cidade de Juiz de Fora/MG. As medidas das angulações das curvaturas lombares foram realizadas através da aplicação do método de Cobb diretamente sobre as radiografias. Resultados e Discussão: Não foram observadas diferenças estatisticamente significativas em relação ao sexo para os valores angulares lombo-lombar (L1-L5) e igualmente para as angulações lombo-sacra (L1-S1). Apesar de não haver concordância na literatura em relação a análise e definição dos ângulos da curvatura da coluna lombar no plano sagital, os resultados mostraram-se compatíveis com as pesquisas relatadas na literatura, apresentando valores semelhantes aos encontrados por outros autores. Conclusão: Os valores angulares normativos para as curvaturas lombo-lombar e lombo-sacra podem ser estabelecidos, respectivamente, em médias angulares de 44,44º e 57,5º para adolescentes assintomáticos.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102918</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i2a102918</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 2 (2008); 92-95</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102918/101222</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102920</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T19:34:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Validação da versão brasileira da Escala de Avaliação Postural para pacientes após acidente vascular encefálico</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Validation of the brazilian version of the Postural Assessment Scale for stroke patients</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Yoneyama, Simone Minae</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Roiz, Roberta de Melo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Tiago Maia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oberg, Telma Dagmar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Núbia Maria Freire Vieira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Cerebrovascular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiparesia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Musculosquelético</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Postura</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebrovascular Accident</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Paresis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Musculoskeletal Equilibrium</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Posture</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To verify the inter-rater and intra-rater reliability, the constuct validaty and the internal consistency of the brazilian version of the instrument The Postural Assessment Scale for Stroke Patients (PASS). Method: The instrument was translated into the Portuguese Language by a bilanguage translator, based on its original version in English. Nineteen subjects with hemiparesis were evaluated by three raters using the PASS and the Fulg-Meyer Scale. Results: The ceiling effect wasn't found. Ther were correlation between the Fulg-Meyer Scale and the total PASS (r=0.79 and p&amp;lt;0.0001); excelent internal consistency for the total PASS (0.83) and its subscale Changing Posture (0.84); excelent interrater coeficient reliability for the total PASS and its subscales Maintaining Posture and Changing Posture(0.93; 0.95 and 0.87, respectively). Conclusion: The PASS showed results of constructive validity, internal consistency and reliability that allow its use in clinical practice.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Verificar a confiabilidade inter e intra-examinador, a validade construtiva e a consistência interna da versão brasileira da Escala de Avaliação Postural para pacientes após Acidente vascular encefálico (EAPA) Método: O instrumento foi traduzido para a Língua Portuguesa, com base na sua versão original em Inglês por um tradutor bilíngüe. Dezenove indivíduos hemiparéticos foram avaliados por três examinadores pelo Escala de Avaliação Postural para Pacientes após AVE (EAPA) e Protocolo de Desempenho Físico de Fugl-Meyer. Resultados: Não foi encontrado efeito teto. Houve correlação entre os instrumentos Fugl-Meyer e EAPA total (r=0.79 e p&amp;lt;0.0001); excelente consistência interna para a EAPA total (0.83) e na sua subescala Mudança de Postura [MUP] (0.84); excelente coeficiente de confiabilidade interexaminador para a EAPA total e suas subescalas Mantendo a Postura e MUP (0.93; 0.95 e 0.87, respectivamente). Conclusão: A EAPA apresentou resultados de validade construtiva, consistência interna e confiabilidade inter e intra-examinador que permitem a sua utilização na prática clínica.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102920</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i2a102920</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 2 (2008); 96-100</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102920/101223</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102921</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T19:43:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Low back pain and headache as important aspects of chronic pain in primary health care in a community of the brazilian amazon region</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Lombalgia e cefaléia como aspectos importantes da dor crônica na atenção primária à saúde em uma comunidade da região amazônica brasileira</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cordeiro, Quirino</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>El Khouri, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ota, Daniela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ciampi, Daniel</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Corbett, Carlos Eduardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Low Back Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Headache</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Prevalence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Primary Health Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Lombalgia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cefaléia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epidemiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevalência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atenção Primária à Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Pain has been described as an unpleasant sensory and emotional experience associated with actual or potential tissue damage or described in terms of such damage. In primary care health system, chronic pain reaches high levels of prevalence, mainly due to low back pain and headaches. The aim of the present study was to evaluate the prevalence of chronic pain in the primary healthcare system in the town of Buriticupu, located in the state of Maranhao, northeastern Brazil. Chronic pain disorders were the most prevalent medical diagnosis in the investigated sample, being found in 539 patients (23.02%). Musculoskeletal pain disorders were the most important etiology of the chronic pain, affecting 250 patients (10.62%), and among the musculoskeletal pain disorders, low back pain was the most prevalent one, observed in 120 (5.12%) patients. Headaches were the second most common cause of chronic pain, diagnosed in 212 (9.05%) patients. Thus, 61.6% of the chronic pain disorders were due to low back pain and headaches. The univariate statistical analysis demonstrated an association between female gender and headaches, between advanced age and all groups of chronic pain (musculoskeletal, low back pain and headaches), and between body mass index and musculoskeletal and low back pain. When the multivariate regression analysis was performed, the correlations between gender and age remained unaltered, maintaining the same patterns of association. However, body mass index no longer showed an association with any chronic pain disorder.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A dor tem sido descrita como sendo uma experiência sensorial e emocional desagradável que é associada ou descrita em termos de lesão tecidual. Na atenção primária à saúde, a dor crônica atinge altos níveis de prevalência, especialmente devido aos quadros de lombalgia e de cefaléias. O objetivo do presente estudo foi investigar a prevalência de dor crônica na atenção primária à saúde na cidade de Buriticupu, localizada no estado do Maranhão, Brasil. Dentre todos os quadros clínicos, a dor crônica foi o diagnóstico mais prevalente entre os pacientes investigados, sendo encontrada em 539 pacientes (23,02%). Dor músculo-esquelética foi o quadro de dor crônica mais comum, atingindo 250 pacientes (10,62%), sendo que lombalgia foi o diagnóstico mais prevalente entre os quadros de dor músculo-esquelética, sendo encontrada em 120 pacientes (5,12%). Por outro lado, as cefaléias foram o segundo quadro de dor crônica mais comum, depois da dor músculo-esquelética, tendo sido diagnosticada em 212 pacientes (9,05%). Assim, 61,6% dos pacientes com dor crônica apresentavam lombalgia ou cefaléia. Análise estatística univariada encontrou associação entre gênero feminino e cefaléia, entre idade avançada e os principais tipos de dor crônica que foram avaliados neste estudo (músculo-esquelética, lombalgia e cefaléia), e entre índice de massa corpórea e dor músculo-esquelética e lombalgia. Quando a análise multivariada foi conduzida, as associações observadas com gênero feminino e idade avançada não mostraram alterações, mantendo os mesmos padrões de associação. No entanto, o índice de massa corpórea não apresentou mais associação com qualquer tipo de dor crônica.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102921</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i2a102921</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 2 (2008); 101-105</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102921/101224</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102922</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T20:29:55Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Disfagia no AVE agudo: revisão sistemática sobre métodos de avaliação</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Dysphagia in acute stroke: systematic review on evaluation methods</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Marques, Charles Henrique Dias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>André, Charles</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rosso, Ana Lúcia Zuma de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebrovascular Accident</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Deglutition Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Cerebrovascular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos de Deglutição</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To critically review the literature on clinicofunctional tests used for the evaluation of dysphagia in the acute phase of stroke, with emphasis on differences between protocols usually recommended by Brazilian and foreign authors. Methods: A systematic review of published articles found in PUBMED, LILACS, SciELO and Cochrane databases was carried out, as well as of didactic texts, published reviews and reference lists of all texts for additional articles of interest. Results:&amp;nbsp;International authors tend to emphasize the importance of tests that use water, as they are relatively simple to use and present good sensitivity for the detection of deglutition disorders. On the other hand, Brazilian researchers mainly suggest the use of foods with different consistencies, focused on developing adequate feeding strategies. Conclusions:&amp;nbsp;Although instrumental exams such as the videofluoroscopy may be seen as the gold standard for the detection of deglutition disorders, they present a number of limitations in the acute stroke setting. When available, the videoendoscopy may be an option for these patients. A large number of clinicofunctional protocols have been reported for use in the evaluation of dysphagia in the acute phase of stroke. They are extensively used and practical for the evaluation of associated risks such as aspiration and, with the use of adequate techniques, should be seen as safe and effective evaluation methods.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: analisar os testes clínico-funcionais para avaliação da disfagia orofaríngea em pacientes na fase aguda do AVE e rever criticamente as referências nacionais e internacionais sobre o tema. Método: revisão sistemática através dos bancos de dados: PUBMED, LILACS, SciELO, Cochrane; de textos didáticos e revisões publicadas, além das listas de referências destas várias fontes. Resultados: Existe tendência internacional pela valorização dos testes que utilizam água, em função de sua aplicação simples e boa sensibilidade para identificação de dificuldades na deglutição. Já a literatura nacional sugere, principalmente, a avaliação do desempenho do paciente com alimentos de várias consistências. Conclusões: A videofluoroscopia é aceita como método-ouro na avaliação da disfagia. Contudo, tem importantes limitações na avaliação de pacientes no estágio inicial do AVE. A videoendoscopia da deglutição, quando disponível, pode ser uma opção para estes pacientes. Existe grande variabilidade nos métodos de oferta para o paciente entre os testes clínico-funcionais. Apesar das críticas, os métodos clínico-funcionais, são amplamente utilizados com pacientes na fase aguda do AVE, não parecendo oferecer risco significativo aos pacientes.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102922</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i2a102922</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 2 (2008); 106-110</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102922/101225</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102923</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T20:34:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The muscle fiber and the factors that interfere with its phenotype</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A fibra muscular e fatores que interferem no seu fenótipo</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Boff, Sérgio Ricardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fibras Musculares</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Músculo Esquelético</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Miosinas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fenótipo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Fibers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Skeletal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Myosins</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Phenotype</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O grande interesse atual em tirar proveito das variações na performance humana, nos levam a busca do entendimento as adaptações fisiológicas, bioquímicas e morfológicas nos tecidos envolvidos. Os resultados obtidos através de modelos experimentais fornecem informações para melhor entender a função muscular, e com isso permitir planejar um treinamento adequado ao objetivo pretendido, tendo como base adaptações fisiológicas. A performance esportiva depende de um grande número de fatores, o tipo do músculo e os estímulos a que ele é submetido e são sem dúvida parâmetros importantes para o desempenho atlético. Para cada modalidade é ideal ter um grupo de fibras predominante adequado às características específicas da atividade. Dependendo do tipo de estímulo podemos obter um aumento de força, sendo esta adaptação uma das mais importantes para a manutenção da saúde ou a melhora do desempenho atlético.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The current interest in taking advantage of the variations in human performance has led us to seek the understanding of the physiological, biochemical and morphological adaptations of the involved tissues. The results obtained through experimental models provide information to better understand the muscular function, allowing the planning of an adequate training program in order to attain the intended objective, having the physiological adaptations as the basis. The sports performance depends on a large number of factors, such as the kind of muscle and the stimuli to which it is submitted and these factors are, undoubtedly, important parameters for the athletic performance. For each modality, the ideal situation is to have a predominant group of fibers that are adequate for the specific characteristics of the activity. Depending on the kind of stimulus, an increase in strength can be obtained, being this adaptation one of the most important factors for the maintenance of health and athletic performance.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102923</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i2a102923</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 2 (2008); 111-116</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102923/101226</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102924</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T20:42:03Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Functional electrical therapy for facilitation of motor recovery in a patient with subacute stroke</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Tratamento com estimulação elétrica funcional para facilitação da recuperação motora em paciente com acidente cerebrovascular subagudo</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Plavšic, Aleksandra</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Djurovic, Aleksandar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Popovic, Mirjana B.</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Encefálico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estimulação Elétrica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebrovascular Accident</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electrical Stimulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Determinar a eficácia de um protocolo de Tratamento com Estimulação Elétrica Funcional (FET) administrado a um paciente com acidente cerebrovascular subagudo.Descrição do Caso: Paciente destro, 67 anos, sexo masculino, que sofreu infarto nas regiões occipital esquerda e frontoparietal 6 meses antes de sua admissão neste estudo e que demonstrou grau elevado de motivação para recuperar plenamente a força do braço e o controle adequado dos dedos do membro superior afetado. Intervenção: Trinta minutos de FET, 5 vezes por semana durante 3 semanas (7 ½ horas no total) além da fisioterapia convencional. Principais Medidas de Avaliação de Resultados: A Escala Modificada de Ashworth (MAS), o teste de funcionalidade das extremidades dos membros superiores (UEFT), o Registro de Atividade Motora (MAL), O teste de 6 fases de Brunnstrom, a Medida de Independência Funcional (MIF). Resultados: O paciente apresentou melhora bastante significativa nas escalas quantitativas UEFT e MAL. Ele melhorou de forma específica na atividade de escrever ao obter melhor controle dos dedos e na capacidade de controlar objetos pesados. Também, observou-se o aumento da amplitude ativa de movimento (ROM) dos músculos proximais, embora a estimulação elétrica tenha sido aplicada apenas aos músculos distais. Houve uma melhora na qualidade geral da utilização do braço, conforme mensurado pela escala qualitativa MAL. Conclusões: A terapia com Estimulação Elétrica Funcional (FET) em pacientes com acidente cerebrovascular subagudo com alta motivação para tarefas específicas pode ser um método eficaz para a melhora do funcionamento e da utilização dos braços afetados.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To determine the efficacy of a Functional Electrical Therapy (FET) protocol administered to a patient with subacute stroke. Case description: A 67-year-old right handed man who had infarct in left occipital and frontoparietal regions 6 months before study entry and who exhibited high motivation to get full arm power and fine control of fingers of the affected upper limb. Intervention: Thirty minutes of FET 5 times a week for 3 weeks (7 ½ hours in total) in addition to conventional physiotherapy. Main Outcome Measures: The Modified Ashworth Scale (MAS), the Upper Extremity Function Test (UEFT), Motor Activity Log (MAL), The Brunnstrom’s 6 stages, the Functional Independence Measure (FIM). Results: The patient exhibited substantial improvements on the UEFT and MAL amount scores. He specifically improved in the writing task by getting better fingers control and in ability of controlling heavy objects. Also, his active range of motion (ROM) of proximal muscles increased, although electrical stimulation was applied to distal muscles only. Quality of overall arm use improved, as measured by the MAL how well score. Conclusions: FET may be an efficacious method for improving function and use of the affected arms of subacute stroke patients with high motivation for specific tasks.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102924</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i2a102924</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 2 (2008); 117-121</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102924/101227</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102925</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T20:50:40Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O uso da terapia por ondas de choques radiais no ombro doloroso por subluxação após um acidente vascular cerebral: série de casos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The use of extracorporeal shock wave therapy in the painful shoulder condition due to subluxation in the stroke patient: case series</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Batista, Marcio Miranda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Caraviello, Eliana Zeraib</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Piccoloto, Paula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Milene Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Masiero, Danilo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chamlian, Therezinha Rosane</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Cerebrovascular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor de Ombro</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ondas de Choque de Alta Energia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebrovascular Accident</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Shoulder Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">High Energy Shock Waves</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">One of the main causes of the painful shoulder condition after a cerebrovascular accident (CVA), or stroke, seems to be the tractioning of the periarticular structures due to luxation or subluxation, which results in a chronic inflammatory process in these structures. The radial shock wave therapy (RSWT) has shown to be an important resource in the treatment of chronic pains, which were refractory to the conventional therapy. The present study aimed at evaluating the effect of RSWT in the painful shoulder condition due to subluxation after stroke. Nine hemiparetic patients with shoulder pain associated to subluxation that were refractory to the conventional therapy carried out for at least six months, participated in the study. The patients received three radial shock wave applications (2,000 pulses, frequency of 6 Hz), every two weeks. One patient was excluded from the study as he had been submitted to chemical blockage during the treatment. The remaining 8 patients experienced considerable pain relief (between 100% and 34%, according to the visual analogue scale), which persisted up to one month after the end of the treatment. There was an association of pain relief with active mobility improvement, joint range of motion, sleep and decrease in the use of pain medications. No adverse effects were described. The authors conclude that the radial shock waves can be an effective treatment for the control of shoulder pain in hemiplegic patients and provide further evidence for the understanding of the possible inflammatory etiology of shoulder pain in these patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Uma das principais causas de ombro doloroso após o acidente vascular cerebral (AVC) parece ser o tracionameneto das estruturas periarticulares devido à luxação ou subluxação, o que acarreta um processo inflamatório crônico nestas estruturas. A terapia por ondas de choque radiais (TOC radias) vem se mostrando um importante recurso para tratar dores crônicas, que falharam ao tratamento convencional. Este estudo teve por objetivo avaliar o efeito das TOC radias no ombro doloroso por subluxação após AVC. Participaram do estudo nove pacientes hemiparéticos com dor no ombro associada a subluxação, sem sucesso ao tratamento conservador por pelo menos seis meses.Os pacientes receberam três aplicações da TOC radiais (2000 pulsos, com freqüência de 6 Hz), com intervalos de duas semanas. Um paciente foi excluído do estudo por ter sido submetido a bloqueio químico durante o tratamento. Os oito restantes tiveram alívio considerável da dor (entre 100% e 34%, segundo a escala visual analógica) que se manteve até um mês após o final do tratamento. Houve associação do alívio da dor com melhora da mobilidade ativa, amplitude articular, sono e redução do uso de medicamentos analgésicos. Não foram descritos efeitos colaterais de qualquer natureza. Os autores concluem que as TOC radiais podem ser um recurso efetivo para o controle da dor no ombro de pacientes hemiplégicos, além de lançar mais evidências no esclarecimento da possível etiologia inflamatória da dor no ombro desses pacientes.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102925</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i2a102925</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 2 (2008); 122-126</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102925/101228</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102926</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T20:56:13Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Cart.+Editor</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effect of music and physical exercises on a group of rheumatic patients: pilot study</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeito da música e de exercícios físicos num grupo de pessoas reumáticas: estudo piloto</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Noordhoek, Johanna</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Jokl, Lieselotte</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Musicoterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia Ocupacional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doenças Reumáticas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Music Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physiotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Occupational Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rheumatic Diseases</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The association of therapies with music and physical exercises was studied in a group of rheumatic patients (n = 17). During each of the combined therapeutic sessions, the participant was interviewed about his physical (feeling of pain and capacity to move freely) and emotional conditions. In general, after 8 sessions, the participants improved the evaluated aspects. It was considered that the interaction of these therapeutic areas is not only possible, but particularly positive. Consequently, new perspectives were opened in the therapeutic field, mainly due to the existential dimension attained by the process, as it simultaneously interacts with the emotional, physical and social aspects of the rheumatic patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A associação de terapias com música e exercícios físicos foi estudada com um grupo de indivíduos reumáticos (n = 17). Em cada sessão das terapias conjugadas, o participante era entrevistado quanto ao seu estado físico (sensação de dor e facilidade de se movimentar) e emocional. De modo geral, após 8 sessões, os participantes melhoraram nos aspectos avaliados. Considerou-se que a interação dessas áreas terapêuticas não só é possível, mas sobretudo, positiva. Desta forma, foram abertas perspectivas no campo terapêutico, principalmente, pela dimensão existencial que o processo alcança, uma vez que interfere, ao mesmo tempo, nos aspectos emocional, físico e social das pessoas reumáticas.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-06-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102926</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i2a102926</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 2 (2008); 127-129</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102926/101229</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102937</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T14:01:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Use of radiotherapy in immature heterotopic ossification in patients with spinal cord injury</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Uso da radioterapia na ossificação heterotópica imatura em pacientes com lesão medular</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Taricco, Luciana Delboni</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Araujo, Isolda Ferreira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Juliano, Yara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ares, Marcelo de Jesus Justino</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cristante, Adriana Rosa Lovisotto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Ossificação Heterotópica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos da Medula Espinal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Radioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Ossification, Heterotopic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spinal Cord Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Radiotherapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A incidência de ossificação heterotópica (OH) nos pacientes adultos com lesão raquimedular é de aproximadamente 20%. A OH costuma ter evolução benigna, mas pode causar redução da amplitude do movimento articular e dificultar o processo de reabilitação. Existem poucos estudos que mostram o uso da radioterapia no tratamento da OH em pacientes com lesão medular. O objetivo deste estudo é avaliar se há progressão da ossificação imatura em pacientes com lesão medular submetidos à radioterapia como tratamento primário. Foram selecionados os prontuários de pacientes da clínica de lesão medular da Associação de Assistência à Criança Deficiente (AACD) que apresentaram OH imatura e que receberam tratamento com radioterapia, sendo este o único tratamento em todos os casos. É um estudo tipo coorte histórico. Para análise da evolução da ossificação foram utilizados como parâmetros a comparação da amplitude de movimento da articulação afetada, medida com goniômetro, e a imagem radiográfica, graduando a ossificação de acordo com a classificação proposta por Brooker et al. O tempo de seguimento do estudo foi de 23,3 meses. Quatorze das 15 articulações estudadas não apresentaram piora clínica ou progressão da ossificação heterotópica. Não foram observados efeitos colaterais à radioterapia. Concluímos que os pacientes tratados precocemente com radioterapia não apresentaram progressão significativa da OH e que a radioterapia é um método seguro e de fácil aplicação.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The incidence of heterotopic ossification (HO) in adult patients with spinal cord injuries is roughly 20%. HO usually has a benign development, but can reduce the range of joint motion and hinder the rehabilitation process. Few studies have shown the use of radiotherapy in the treatment of HO in patients with spinal cord injuries. The objective of this study is to assess whether immature heterotopic ossification progresses in patients with spinal cord injuries submitted to radiotherapy as the primary treatment. The medical records of patients attending the spinal cord injury clinic of AACD (Associação de Assistência à Criança Deficiente) with immature HO and who were treated exclusively with radiotherapy were selected. This is a historical cohort-type study. Ossification progress was determined by analysis of the range of motion of the affected joint, measurements with a goniometer and radiographic image. Ossification was classified according to the classification proposed by Brooker et al. The study follow-up period was 23.3 months. Fourteen of the 15 studied joints did not worsen clinically, nor did the HO progress. None of the patients had side effects from radiotherapy. We conclude that patients treated early with radiotherapy do not present significant HO development and that radiotherapy is a safe and easy-to-use method.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102937</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i3a102937</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 3 (2008); 144-148</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102937/101238</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102937/101239</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102938</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T15:52:21Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Study of sexual function alterations in women with spinal cord injuries in the city of Ribeirao Preto, state of Sao Paulo, Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudo sobre as alterações da função sexual em mulheres com lesão medular resistentes na cidade de Ribeirão Preto/SP</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Sodré, Paula Canova</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Faro, Ana Cristina Mancussi e</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spinal Cord Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Women</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sexuality</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Reabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos da Medula Espinal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Mulheres</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sexualidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">É sabido que qualquer pessoa que sofreu algum dano na medula, além de comprometimento da sensibilidade, locomoção, funções intestinais e urinárias, independente da região lesionada, também acomete a função sexual. Cada pessoa reage de maneira diferente por mais semelhante que seja a lesão. O presente estudo exploratório, descritivo, transversal, aplicado de campo, de natureza quantitativa, foi realizado em três hospitais e duas clínicas de fisioterapia na cidade de Ribeirão Preto, SP, com a finalidade de conhecer as mulheres com lesão medular atendidas no período compreendido entre 1º de janeiro de 2000 a 31 de julho de 2004. A população foi composta por 81 mulheres. Deste total, foram excluídas 30 que não atenderam os critérios de inclusão, 12 delas com diagnósticos não relacionados à lesão medular, 11 não localizadas, seis que faleceram e uma que se recusou a participar da pesquisa. A faixa etária que predominou a lesão medular é dos 18 aos 37 anos (38%). Após a lesão, 27% permaneceram solteiras, 28% com seus companheiros, escolaridade nível de ensino fundamental (49%), analfabetismo (9%). Apresentaram etiologia traumática (100%), nível lombar (53%), seguido do cervical (27%), torácica (16%) e sacral (4%,). Das causas externas constatamos acidente automobilístico (29%), 12% de queda, em terceiro encontra-se o ferimento por arma de fogo (FAF), levantamento de peso, atropelamento e acidente de motocicleta 8% cada, mergulho em águas rasas e espancamento, com 2% cada, ferimento por arma branca (FAB), práticas de atividades esportivas e queda de objeto sobre a cabeça, práticas de esportes radicais, queda da própria altura somaram 16% das mulheres, e dentre estas mulheres 94% são idosas. Quanto à escala CSFQ, 90% da amostra apresenta disfunção sexual em relação à variável prazer, disfunção do orgasmo (90%) disfunção do desejo/freqüência (76%) e 72% disfunção do interesse sexual, excitação 92%. Neste estudo podemos confirmar que a paciente com lesão medular, apresenta complexidade e peculiaridades específicas. E que a escassez de estudos sobre sexualidade especificamente feminina da portadora de lesão medular, não oferece um cuidar específico que permeie as diferentes dimensões sociais, psicológicas e físicas, não assegurando um cuidado holístico e a continuidade deste cuidar em domicílio estabelecendo um processo de reabilitação sem qualidade.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">It is known that a person who has suffered a spinal cord injury, in addition to sensitivity, locomotion, intestinal and urinary function impairment, regardless of the injury location, must also face sexual function impairment. Each person reacts differently, no matter how similar the injuries can be. The present study, which was an exploratory, descriptive, transversal, applied field study of quantitative nature, was carried out in three hospitals and two physical therapy clinics in the city of Ribeirao Preto, state of Sao Paulo, Brazil, with the objective of evaluating women with spinal cord injuries treated from January 1, 2000 to July 31, 2004. The study population consisted of 81 women. Thirty women were excluded as they did not meet the inclusion criteria: 12 of them had diagnoses that were not related to spinal cord injury, 11 could not be located, 6 died and one refused to participate in the study. Age range in which the spinal cord injury predominated was 18 to 37 years (38%). After the injury, 27% remained single, 28% remained with their partners; regarding the degree of schooling, Grade School predominated (49%) and 9% were illiterate. They presented traumatic etiology (100%) at the lumbar level (53%), followed by cervical (27%), thoracic (16%) and sacral (4%) levels. Of the external causes of the injury, car accident (29%) was the most prevalent, followed by falls (12%), firearm injury, weight lifting, being hit by a car, and motorcycle accident (8% each), shallow-water diving and being beaten up (2% each), and knife injury, sports activities, fall of object on the head, practicing radical sports and fall from one’s height added up to 16% of the women and among them, 94% are elderly. The “Changes in Sexual Functioning Questionnaire” (CSFQ) scale showed that 90% of the sample presented sexual dysfunction regarding the sexual pleasure variable, orgasm dysfunction (90%), desire/frequency dysfunction (76%), sexual interest dysfunction (72%) and arousal dysfunction (92%). This study confirmed that the patient with spinal cord injury presents specific complexities and particularities and that the scarcity of studies on the specific sexuality of women with spinal cord injuries does not offer a specific care that encompasses the social, psychological and physical dimensions, as well as the continuing homecare, establishing a rehabilitation process without quality.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102938</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i3a102938</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 3 (2008); 149-155</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102938/101240</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102938/101241</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102939</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T16:03:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio corporal e exercícios físicos: uma investigação com mulheres idosas praticantes de diferentes modalidades</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Corporal balance and physical exercises: an investigation in elderly women who practice different exercise modalities</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Teixeira, Clarissa Stefani</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lemos, Luiz Fernando Cuozzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Luis Felipe Dias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rossi, Angela Garcia</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mota, Carlos Bolli</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Balance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Posture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Postura</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Life expectancy has been progressively increasing, which implies in an increase in the number of elderly individuals. As a consequence, several types of physical activities are offered to this population, aiming at improving some physical qualities. One of those qualities is corporal balance, which has been largely studied due to its association with many diseases that can affect the elderly. Thus, this study compared a group of elderly women that regularly practiced hydrogymnastics with sedentary ones. Fifty-one (51) elderly women with a mean age of 63.26 ± 9.63 years participated in the study group. Balance was evaluated through kinetic assessment, using an AMTI OR6-5 force platform (Advanced Mechanical Technologies, Inc.) at a frequency of 100 Hz. The analyzed variables were the amplitude of the force center displacement and the mean force center displacement in the anteroposterior and midlateral directions. The statistic analysis used the descriptive statistics, the Shapiro-Wilk’s test and the Kruskal-Wallis test with a level of significance of 5%. The results showed statistically significant differences in the midlateral direction, both in range and the mean force center displacement between the groups. Thus, it is possible to conclude that there were differences regarding the balance in the midlateral direction and less instability was observed in the group of elderly women that practiced physical exercises.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Atualmente a expectativa de vida vem crescendo ano após ano, caracterizando um aumento no número de idosos. Com isso, diversos tipos de atividades físicas são ofertadas para essa população objetivando melhoras em algumas qualidades físicas. Uma dessas qualidades é o equilíbrio corporal, que vem sendo bastante estudado, em virtude de estar relacionado com diversas doenças que podem afligir os idosos. Com isso, esse estudo comparou mulheres idosas praticantes de hidroginástica, ginástica e mulheres idosas sedentárias. Fizeram parte do grupo de estudo 51 mulheres idosas com idade de 63,26 ± 9,63 anos. O equilíbrio foi coletado através da avaliação cinética, sendo utilizada uma plataforma de força OR6-5 AMTI (Advanced Mechanical Technologies, Inc.) a uma freqüência de 100 Hz. As variáveis analisadas foram a amplitude do deslocamento do centro de força e o deslocamento médio do centro de força na nas direções ântero posterior e médio-lateral. Para análise estatística utilizou-se a descritiva, teste de Shapiro-Wilk e o teste Kruskal-Wallis com nível de significância utilizado de 5%. Os resultados mostraram diferenças estatisticamente significativas nas direções médio-lateral, tanto na amplitude quanto no deslocamento médio do centro de força entre os grupos. Conclui-se deste estudo que ocorreram diferenças no equilíbrio na direção médio-lateral, sendo que menores instabilidades foram encontradas nas idosas praticantes de ginástica.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102939</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i3a102939</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 3 (2008); 156-159</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102939/101242</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102939/101243</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102942</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T16:16:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Escalas de controle de tronco como prognóstico funcional em pacientes após acidente vascular encefálico</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Trunk control scales as functional predictors for stroke patients</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Aguiar, Paula Teixeira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rocha, Talitha Nery</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Elisandra Silva de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Cerebral Vascular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiparesia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Paresis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">De acordo com a Organização Mundial de Saúde (OMS), o acidente vascular encefálico (AVE) é considerado uma síndrome com desenvolvimento rápido de sinais clínicos de perturbação focal ou global da função cerebral, com possível origem vascular e com mais de 24 horas de duração. Além de o AVE causar déficits no movimento dos membros, marcha e linguagem, o déficit de controle da mobilidade do tronco é também um problema muito importante. O Objetivo deste estudo foi identificar a relação entre a alteração no controle de tronco, através de escalas, e incapacidade funcional de pacientes hemiparéticos após AVE. Foi realizado um estudo de revisão de literatura através do acesso aos indexadores de produção científica, sendo selecionados oito artigos clínicos, longitudinais e descritivos. Todos os autores observaram relação prognóstica entre o controle de tronco e habilidades funcionais. As escalas utilizadas foram a Trunk Control Test (TCT), Postural Assessment Scale for Stroke Patients (PASS-TC) e Trunk Impairment Scale (TIS) (Fujiwara e Verheyden). Concluiu-se que a avaliação clínica do controle de tronco, através das escalas, constitui uma ferramenta importante para o prognóstico das habilidades funcionais de pacientes hemiparéticos após AVE, e para o planejamento de um tratamento específico e diferenciado para esses pacientes. Entretanto, há poucos estudos comprovando esta relação, sendo que estes utilizaram diferentes escalas, não havendo um consenso entre os autores. Além das escalas, não há concordância nos dados para a avaliação do balance e marcha.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">According to the World Health Organization (WHO), stroke is considered a syndrome with a rapid development of clinical signs of focal or global disturbance of cerebral function, of which origin is possibly vascular and lasting more than 24 hours. In addition to deficits in limb movement, gait, and language, the stroke may also cause impaired control of trunk mobility, which is an important issue. Therefore, the aim of this literature review was to identify, through the use of scales, the association between trunk control impairment and functional disability in hemiparetic patients after a stroke. A literature review was carried out and eight clinical, longitudinal and descriptive articles were selected. All the studies showed a prognostic association between trunk control and functional abilities. Trunk Control Test (TCT), Trunk control items of the Postural Assessment Scale for Stroke Patients (PASS-TC) and Trunk Impairment Scale (TIS) (Fujiwara and Verheyden) were used in the assessments. It was concluded that the clinical evaluation of trunk control, through the use of scales, is an important tool for the prognosis of the functional capacity of hemiparetic patients after a stroke and for the planning of a specific and differentiated treatment of these patients. However, there few studies proved this association, as different scales were used and there was no consensus among authors. Additionally, there is no agreement on the data regarding the evaluation of balance and gait.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102942</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i3a102942</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 3 (2008); 160-164</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102942/101244</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102942/101245</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102943</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T16:23:08Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effects of the pulmonary rehabilitation program on the quality of life of asthmatic children and their parents</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeitos da reabilitação pulmonar sobre a qualidade de vida: uma visão das crianças asmáticas e de seus pais</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rezende, Ivana Mara Oliveira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moura, Ana Luisa Dália</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Bibiana Carolina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Faria, Juliana Machado de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Crisciane</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bolina, Ingrid de Castro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Coelho, Cristiane Cenachi</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Asthma/rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Asma/reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The assessment of quality of life in asthmatic children and adolescents is important, as severe asthma, or its uncontrolled symptoms, prevents the participation of these individuals in sports activities, disturbs sleep and, consequently, the regular school performance. However, the disease does not have an impact only on the patients, but it also affects the quality of life of their parents. Objective: To evaluate the quality of life of asthmatic children and the perception of their parents/tutors regarding their children’s quality of life before and after a Pulmonary Rehabilitation Program (PRP). Patients and Methods: 5 male children, with a mean age of 8.16 ±1.83 years, were studied and 6 parents/tutors, before and after a 24-session PRP. All the children had a clinical diagnosis of mild and moderate asthma. The Pediatric Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire was applied to the children, whereas a second and specific questionnaire was applied to the parents. The absolute scores of the questionnaires before and after the PRP were compared by Wilcoxon’s test with p&amp;lt;0.05. Results: There was no significant difference in the comparison of the results of the children’s questionnaire, before and after PRP. However, absolute improvement was verified in the majority of the questions in both questionnaires. Conclusion: The quality of life questionnaires applied to the asthmatic children and their parents did not detect any significant variation regarding the analyzed questions. However, the absolute variations in several items, involving the two instruments, suggest a clinical improvement in the quality of life shown by both questionnaires.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A determinação da qualidade de vida de crianças e adolescentes asmáticos é importante, pois a asma grave ou com sintomas mal controlados, impede a participação desses indivíduos em esportes, prejudica o sono e, conseqüentemente, o rendimento escolar. Entretanto a doença não tem somente um impacto sobre os pacientes, mas também afeta a qualidade de vida de indivíduos ligados a eles. Objetivo: Avaliar a qualidade de vida das crianças asmáticas e a percepção dos pais/responsáveis quanto à qualidade de vida de seus filhos antes e após um programa de reabilitação pulmonar (RP). Materiais e Métodos: Foram estudadas 5 crianças, sexo masculino, com idade média de 8,16 ± 1,83 anos e 6 pais/responsáveis, antes e após um programa de reabilitação de 24 sessões. Todas as crianças tinham diagnóstico clínico de asma leve e moderada. Foi aplicado o questionário Pediatric Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire (PAQLQ) para as crianças e um segundo questionário específico para os pais. As pontuações numéricas dos questionários pré e pós RP, foram comparadas pelo teste de Wilcoxon, sendo considerado um p &amp;lt; 0,05. Resultado: Não houve diferença significativa, na comparação dos resultados pré e pós RP Entretanto, verificou-se melhora absoluta na maioria das questões em ambos os questionários. Conclusão: Os questionários de qualidade de vida aplicados às crianças asmáticas e aos seus pais/responsáveis, não detectaram variação significativa. Contudo, as variações absolutas em vários itens envolvendo os dois instrumentos sugerem uma melhora clínica na qualidade de vida em ambos os questionários.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102943</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.5935/0104-7795.20080002</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 3 (2008); 165-169</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102943/101246</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102943/101247</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102944</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T16:28:35Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Prevalência de queixas urinárias e o impacto destas na qualidade de vida de mulheres integrantes de grupos de atividade física</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Prevalence of urinary complaints and their impact on the quality of life of women that participate in physical activity groups</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Mourão, Flávio Afonso Gonçalves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Luciana Napoleão</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Vasconcellos, Natália de Paula Carneiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Maria Beatriz Alvarenga de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Urinary Incontinence</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Women</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Incontinência Urinária</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Mulheres</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Sociedade Internacional de Continência define incontinência urinária como qualquer perda de urina relatada pelo paciente. É uma condição que afeta a população mundial, principalmente feminina, levando a diversas implicações. O objetivo deste estudo foi verificar a prevalência de queixas urinárias e o impacto destas na qualidade de vida das mulheres, integrantes de grupos de atividade física. Métodos: Participaram do estudo 50 mulheres, com idade a partir de 40 anos, participantes de grupos de atividade física conduzidos pela Fisioterapia em um Centro de Saúde de Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais. As voluntárias foram submetidas a uma anamnese uroginecológica, e aquelas que apresentaram queixas urinárias nos últimos meses responderam o questionário “King’s Health Questionnaire” para avaliação da qualidade de vida. Resultados: A prevalência de mulheres com queixas urinárias foi de 42%. Os sintomas mais predominantes foram: urgência (95,24%), freqüência (90,48%), incontinência de esforço (85,71%) e noctúria (80,95%). Quanto à intensidade, os sintomas de urge-incontinência (49%) e urgência (46%) apresentaram os maiores índices. De acordo com a análise dos domínios, o impacto da incontinência (53,96 ± 26,83) sobressalta-se quando comparado a outros resultados, seguido pelo domínio medidas de gravidade (43,78 ± 23,01). Conclusão: A população estudada apresentou elevada prevalência de queixas urinárias e o impacto da qualidade de vida encontrado não descarta a influência negativa do quadro patológico.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The International Continence Society defines urinary incontinence as any loss of urine reported by the patient. This is a condition that affects the world’s population, mainly the female sex, leading to several implications. The purpose of this study was to assess the prevalence of urinary complaints and their impact on the quality of life of women that participate in physical activity groups. Methods: A total of 50 women, aged 40 years and older that participated in physical activity groups, participated in the study carried out by Physical Therapy Department of a Basic Health Unit in Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais, Brazil. The volunteers were submitted to urogynecological anamnesis and the ones that had presented urinary complaints in the recent months answered the “King’s Health Questionnaire” to have quality of life evaluated. Results: The prevalence of women with urinary complaints was 42%. The most predominant symptoms were: urgency (95.24%), frequency (90.48%), stress incontinence (85.71%) and nocturia (80.95%). Regarding the intensity, the urge-incontinence (49) and urgency (46) symptoms had the highest rates. According to the analysis of the domains, the impact of incontinence (53.96 ± 26.83) is striking when compared with the other results, followed by the measure of severity domain (43.78 ± 23.01). Conclusion: The studied population had a high prevalence of urinary complaints and their impact on the quality of life does not rule out the negative influence of the pathological picture.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102944</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i3a102944</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 3 (2008); 170-175</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102944/101248</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102944/101249</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102946</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T16:34:47Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Reprodutibilidade, validade e responsividade da escala de Medida de Independência Funcional (MIF) na lesão medular: revisão da literatura</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The Functional Independence Measures (FIM) reliability, validity and responsiveness in spinal cord injury: literature review</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Barbetta, Daniela de Campos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Assis, Marcos Renato de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos da Medula Espinhal/reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da Deficiência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Literatura de Revisão como Assunto</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spinal Cord Injuries/rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disability Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Review Literature as Topic</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A escala de Medida de Independência Funcional é um dos instrumentos mais utilizados na avaliação da capacidade funcional dos indivíduos com lesão medular. O registro da evolução funcional desses indivíduos é fundamental no processo de reabilitação. Este estudo teve como objetivo revisar na literatura científica a reprodutibilidade, validade e responsividade dessa escala em indivíduos com lesão medular. Os resultados encontrados mostraram alta concordância interna e reprodutibilidade inter-avaliador; validade e responsividade, exceto para avaliação da dimensão cognitiva e do domínio locomoção.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The Functional Independence Measures scale is one of the most frequently used tools for the assessment of functional capacity of individuals with spinal cord injuries. Measurements of the functional outcome in these individuals are essential in the rehabilitation process. This study aimed at reviewing the scientific literature regarding the reliability, validity and responsiveness of FIM in individuals with spinal cord injuries. The results showed good internal consistence, inter-rater reliability, validity and responsiveness, except for the assessment of the cognitive dimension and the locomotor domain.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102946</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i3a102946</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 3 (2008); 176-181</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102946/101250</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102946/101251</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102947</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T16:38:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação na Esclerose Lateral Amiotrofica: revisão da literatura</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation in Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis: literature review</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Xerez, Denise Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Review Literature as Topic</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Esclerose Amiotrófica Lateral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Literatura de Revisão como Assunto</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis is a motor neuron pathology that results in a high degree of impairment. There is a worldwide tendency to create standardization manuals regarding the approach of this population, mainly on the subject of rehabilitation and quality of life. We conducted a review of the published guidelines related to this issue in a strict, non-systematic way and based on this published material, created a proposal for an up-to-date, comprehensive and simple manual adapted to the Brazilian reality.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Esclerose Lateral Amiotrófica é uma patologia do Neurônio Motor que traz um grande grau de incapacidade. Em todo o mundo existe uma tendência a elaborar manuais de uniformização na abordagem desta população, principalmente no que se refere à reabilitação e qualidade de vida. Levantamos os guidelines publicados para este fim, de maneira não sistemática estrita, e elaboramos a partir destes, uma proposta de manual adaptado a realidade brasileira, atualizado, abrangente e simples.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102947</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i3a102947</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 3 (2008); 182-188</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102947/101252</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102947/101253</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102949</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T16:46:58Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Bloqueios com fenol para tratamento de espasticidade</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Phenol block for spasticity management</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Trevisol-Bittencourt, Paulo Cesar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tournier, Marcelo Benedet</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fenol</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Espasticidade Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Bloqueio Nervoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Phenol</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Spasticity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Nerve Block</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">No tratamento da espasticidade focal, os bloqueios periféricos com toxina botulínica (TB) e com fenol são os preferidos. Os bloqueios com fenol são os assuntos de interesse desta revisão, que mostra alguns aspectos históricos, princípios de ação, principais indicações e a aplicabilidade clínica desta substância. Ela tem o propósito de relembrar que o fenol, quando respeitada suas indicações, tem mostrado boa relação entre eficácia e segurança. Desde que é uma droga de baixíssimo custo, deveria ser considerada como agente ideal para uso em larga escala nos serviços de reabilitação carentes de recursos econômicos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Peripheral blocks with botulinum toxin (BoTN) and phenol are the treatment of first choice in the management of focal spasticity. This review will focus on phenol blocks, presenting some historical aspects, principles of action, main indications and the clinical applicability of this substance. The purpose of this review is to remind that, when its indications are respected, phenol has shown a good balance between efficacy and safety. Since it is an extremely low-cost drug, phenol should be considered as the ideal agent for large-scale use in resource-poor rehabilitation centres.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102949</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i3a102949</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 3 (2008); 189-191</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102949/101254</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102949/101255</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102950</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T16:52:10Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Benefícios do condicionamento físico como tratamento da claudicação intermitente</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Benefits of physical conditioning in the treatment of intermittent claudication</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Barbosa, Érica Carvalho</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dalle, Rafael Diniz Mascarenhas</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Intermittent Claudication</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Peripheral Vascular Diseases</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Claudicação Intermitente</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doenças Vasculares Periféricas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Claudicação Intermitente (CI) é um sintoma patognomônico da doença arterial obstrutiva periférica, caracterizado por dor muscular ao exercício físico que cessa ao repouso. A Claudicação Intermitente tem um caráter potencialmente benigno, devido ao baixo risco de evolução para isquemia grave e perda do membro, e também por uma boa possibilidade de melhora dos sintomas. Assim, o tratamento clínico é considerado adequado e normalmente empregado como primeira alternativa terapêutica, sendo que esse tratamento deve ser baseado no controle dos fatores de risco modificáveis da arteriosclerose, principalmente o fumo. Associa-se ainda um tratamento farmacológico e um não farmacológico, onde o tratamento não farmacológico primário para a claudicação intermitente é um programa formal de exercícios físicos que pode ser realizado pelo paciente baseado apenas na orientação médica (sem supervisão) ou sob a orientação de um profissional. O mecanismo pelo qual o paciente melhora da claudicação com a atividade física ainda não está totalmente esclarecido, e vários fatores são atribuídos à melhora dos sintomas, como a formação de novos vasos, liberarão de oxido nítrico, ação sobre as lipoproteínas, entre outros.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Intermittent Claudication (IC) is a pathognomonic symptom of obstructive peripheral arterial disease, characterized by muscle pain during physical exercise that ceases at rest. IC has a potentially benign nature, due to the low risk of progression to severe ischemia and limb loss, as well as a good chance of symptom improvement. Thus, the clinical treatment is considered appropriate and usually employed as the first therapeutic alternative; the treatment should be based on the control of the modifiable risk factors of arteriosclerosis, especially the habit of smoking. Treatment consists of the association of a pharmacological treatment and a non-pharmacological one, and the primary non-pharmacological treatment for intermittent claudication is a formal exercise program that can be performed by the patient based only on medical guidance (without supervision) or under the supervision of a professional. The mechanism by which the patient improves claudication through physical activity is yet to be fully clarified, and several factors are attributed to symptom improvement, such as the formation of new blood vessels, release of nitric oxide and action on the lipoprotein, among others.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i3a102950</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 3 (2008); 192-194</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102950/101256</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102950/101257</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102951</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-27T18:58:04Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Pusher syndrome after cerebrovascular accident: a case report</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Síndrome de Pusher após acidente vascular encefálico: relato de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cecatto, Rebeca Boltes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Cristiane Isabela de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Cerebral Vascular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paresia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos da Percepção</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Paresis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Perceptual Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O termo Síndrome de Pusher refere-se a uma alteração no controle postural de pacientes portadores de hemiparesia após lesões encefálicas. Objetivos: descrever o caso de uma paciente portadora de hemiparesia após Acidente Vascular Encefálico (AVC) e sintomas clínicos sugestivos da Síndrome de Pusher promovendo uma discussão sobre a etiologia, a fisiopatologia, a evolução clínica e o prognóstico da Síndrome de Pusher em pacientes portadores de lesões encefálicas. Métodos: Este é um relato de caso retrospectivo de uma paciente do sexo feminino, de 62 anos, portadora de hemiparesia esquerda após AVCH de tálamo, com score de 13 na National Institute of Health Stroke Scale, Medida de Independência Funcional (MIF) de 56 e sinais clínicos da Síndrome de Pusher. Um programa interdisciplinar de reabilitação foi instituído ainda na fase aguda, além de um programa domiciliar de adaptações arquitetônicas e fisioterapia motora para o treino do balance, alinhamento de tronco e cinturas, postura e verticalidade. Resultados e discussão: Apenas quatro meses após o ictus, os sinais da Síndrome de Pusher haviam desaparecido e a paciente apresentava MIF de 99, apesar da manutenção da hemiparesia, da disartria, da hipofonia e do humor deprimido. Conclusão: Este relato de caso sugere que a Síndrome de Pusher isoladamente pode influenciar a evolução e o grau de independência após o AVC, retardando a alta hospitalar e os ganhos do processo de reabilitação. Mais estudos são necessários para compreendermos a fisiopatologia, a evolução e o prognóstico da Síndrome de Pusher.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Pusher syndrome is a disorder of balance in patients with brain injury. Aim: to report the case of a patient with hemiparesis after thalamic stroke and clinical signs suggesting Pusher Syndrome to promote a discussion about the etiology, pathophysiology, prognosis and clinical evolution of this syndrome for neurologic impaired patients. Method: Retrospective evaluation of a female inpatient aged 62 who developed mild hemiparesis and severe contraversive pushing behavior after acute hemorrhage affecting the right thalamus with NIHSS = 13, FIM = 56 and clinical signs of Pusher Syndrome. Following standard motor physiotherapy and architectonic adaptations, the pushing behavior completely resolved 4 months after the onset with a FIM of 99 although, at that time, left hemiparesis was still present. This case report illustrates that pushing behavior itself may be severely incapacitating, may occur with only mild hemiparesis and affected patients may have dramatic functional improvement and delayed hospital delivered and rehabilitation gains. More studies are crucial for better understanding Pusher Syndrome.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-09-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102951</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i3a102951</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 3 (2008); 195-201</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102951/101258</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102993</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T16:25:39Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Asthma impact on body posture in children aged 8 to 14 years analyzed by biophotogrammetry</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Impacto da asma sobre a postura corporal de crianças entre 8 e 14 anos analisada pela biofotogrametria</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ricieri, Denise da Vinha</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Jecilene Rosana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rosário Filho, Nelson Augusto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Postura</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Asma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Fotogrametria</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Posture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Asthma</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Photogrammetry</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Comparar a postura do tronco entre asmáticos e nao-asmáticos medidos em fotogramas digitais. Método: Angulos referentes aos principais eixos posturais de nivelamentos e alinhamentos do tronco de 50 crianças entre 8 e 14 anos, nas vistas anterior e posterior, foram medidos sistematicamente no programa Corel Draw-12. Os resultados foram tratados num estudo descritivo geral, comparando gêneros/GR, e num estudo caso-controle, comparando a postura entre asmáticos/AS e nao-asmáticos/NA. Na vista anterior mediu-se o nivelamento da pelve/NP e ombros/NO, e alinhamentos do tórax/ATX e onfálico/AXO; na vista posterior foram registrados o nivelamento das escápulas/NE, e alinhamentos da coluna superior/CS e inferior/CI. Os resultados foram interpretados a partir de corolários específicos, e considerados significantes resultados para p&amp;lt;0,05. Resultados: A constataçao estatística de uma distribuiçao normal dos registros permitiu a aplicaçao de testes paramétricos. Nao houve diferença entre gêneros (GR = p&amp;gt;0,05), mas o perfil postural global do grupo AS mostrou-se melhor que para NA (p&amp;lt;0,05). Conclusões: A abordagem pela Rotina Postural Biofotogramétrica/RPB mostrou-se instrumentalmente efetiva. Sugere-se uma coorte prospectiva entre sujeitos de AS para esclarecer a suspeita de que, na asma, a persistência da sobrecarga muscular e padrao respiratório vicariante perpetuam-se em compensaçoes posturais, mais evidentes numa fase mais adulta.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To compare trunk posture between asthmatic and non-asthmatic children by digital image assessment. Methods: the angles of the main postural axis for trunk alignment and leveling of 50 children, aged 8 to 14 years, at the anterior and posterior views, were measured in Corel Draw-12 software. Results were statistically treated in a descriptive study comparing genders, and a case-control study, which compared trunk posture between asthmatics/AS and non-asthmatics/NA. At the anterior view we measured the pelvis/PL and shoulder/SL leveling; at the posterior view we recorded scapula leveling/SL and the upper/UC and lower/LC spinal column alignment. The final data were interpreted based on previous and specific corollaries, and all results with p&amp;lt;0.05 were considered significant. Results: the normal distribution of data allowed parametric tests to be applied. There was no difference between genders (p&amp;gt;0.05) but the global profile of the AS group was better than the NA group (p&amp;lt;0.05). Conclusions: The Biophotogrammetric Postural Routine/BPR was instrumentally effective. A prospective cohort for NA subjects should clarify the role of muscular overload persistence and an inadequate respiratory pattern in asthma on postural compensations, which are more evident in the adult phase of life.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102993</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i4a102993</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 4 (2008); 214-219</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102993/101278</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102994</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T18:25:12Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Task-orienting and biofeedback: effects on weight-bearing in hemiparetic subjects</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Tarefas orientadas e biofeedback: efeitos na transferência de peso em hemiparéticos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Trípoli, Fernanda</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moreira, Sofia Rael</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oberg, Telma Dagmar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Núbia Maria Freire Vieira</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Paresis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Body Weight</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Cerebral Vascular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paresia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Peso Corporal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Indivíduos hemiparéticos apresentam assimetria na distribuiçao do peso corpóreo em ortostatismo, limitando-os em suas atividades de vida diária. O reconhecimento desta assimetria e capacidade de redistribuiçao de peso constituem um importante aspecto para reabilitaçao. O objetivo foi analisar a transferência de peso durante tarefas orientadas e após feedbacks em hemiparéticos. Foram recrutados 28 indivíduos hemiparéticos, sendo avaliados por 2 balanças digitais nas tarefas com pés afastados 20 cm e olhos abertos, membro inferior afetado à frente, membro inferior afetado atrás, privaçao visual, feedback auditivo e feedback visual. Houve aumento de 11.36% do peso no membro afetado na tarefa de membro para trás, 4.54% após uso do feedback visual, 45.45% após feedback auditivo. Em contraste, houve reduçao da transferência de peso no membro afetado de 4.54% na tarefa de privaçao visual e 6.81% na posiçao de passo à frente (p&amp;lt;0.001). Observou-se que a utilizaçao de feedback externo (espelho e comando verbal do terapeuta) e a tarefa de membro parético para trás foram efetivas na redistribuiçao de peso entre os membros inferiores na hemiparesia.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Hemiparetic individuals display asymmetric weight-bearing in the orthostatic posture, which limits the performance of daily living activities. The recognition of this asymmetry and weight transference capacity constitutes an important aspect of rehabilitation. The objective was to analyze the weight transference during the oriented activity and after feedback in hemiparetic subjects. A total of 28 hemiparetic individuals were enrolled in the study. They were assessed by two digital scales during the activities with their feet placed 20 cm apart, with their eyes open, with visual deprivation, with the affected lower limb forward and backward, and auditive and visual feedback. There was an increase of 11.36% in the weight-bearing on the affected lower limb, backward; 4.54% after visual feedback and 45.45% after auditive feedback. In contrast, there was a decrease in the weight-bearing of 4.54% after visual deprivation and 6.81% in forward weight-shift on the paretic limb (p&amp;lt;0.001). It was observed that the use of external feedback (mirror and verbal command by the therapist) and forward weight shifting with the paretic limb were useful for weight redistribution between the lower limbs in stroke patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102994</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i4a102994</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 4 (2008); 220-224</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102994/101279</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102995</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T18:32:18Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Correlation of balance deficit, motor impairment and functional independence in patients with chronic hemiparesis</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Correlação do déficit de equilíbrio, comprometimento motor e independência funcional em indivíduos hemiparéticos crônicos</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Azevedo, Eliza Regina Ferreira Braga Machado de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Macedo, Lydianna Silveira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Paraízo, Marcelo Fabiano Novaes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oberg, Telma Dagmar</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Núbia Maria Freire Vieira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cacho, Enio Walker Azevedo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Paresis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Musculoskeletal Equilibrium</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Movement Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Personal Autonomy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Cerebral Vascular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Hemiparesia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Musculosquelético</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos Motores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Autonomia Pessoal</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To verify the correlation between the balance deficit and motor impairment in functional activities of patients with chronic hemiparesis after stroke. Methods: 24 patients with chronic hemiparesis after stroke were selected and evaluated by Functional Independence Measure (FIM), Berg Balance Scale (BBS), Dynamic Gait Index (DGI) and Fugl-Meyer Assessment (FMA).Results: BBS showed moderate correlation with FIM (r= 0.6457, p= 0.0007), balance section (r= 0.5070, p= 0.0114) and lower limb section of FMA (r= 0.5728, p= 0.0034) and DGI (r= 0.6453, p= 0.0007). The FIM also showed moderate correlation with DGI (r= 0.5449, p= 0.0059) and balance section of FMA (r=0.6107, p=0.0015). However, a weak correlation was observed between the FIM and lower limb section of FMA (r= 0.1515, p= 0.4797). Conclusion: The balance deficit correlated with the functional independence level in chronic hemiparesis. Nevertheless, there was no correlation between the motor impairment and functional independence.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Verificar as correlações entre o déficit de equilíbrio e o comprometimento motor nas atividades funcionais de pacientes hemiparéticos crônicos após AVE. Metodologia: 24 pacientes hemiparéticos crônicos após AVE foram selecionados e avaliados através da Medida de Independência Funcional (MIF), da Escala de Equilíbrio de Berg (EEB), do Índice do Andar Dinâmico (IAD) e do Protocolo de Desempenho Físico da Fugl-Meyer (FM). Resultados: EEB apresentou moderada correlação com a MIF (r= 0.6457, p= 0.0007), subescala de equilíbrio (r= 0.5070, p= 0.0114) e extremidade inferior da FM (r= 0.5728, p=0.0034) e IAD (r= 0.6453, p= 0.0007). A MIF também apresentou moderada correlação com IAD (r=0.5449, p= 0.0059) e subescala equilíbrio da FM (r= 0.6107, p= 0.0015). Entretanto, foi observada fraca correlação entre a MIF e a subescala de extremidade inferior da FM (r= 0.1515, p= 0.4797). Conclusão: O déficit de equilíbrio se correlacionou ao nível de independência funcional na hemiparesia crônica. Entretanto, não houve relação entre o comprometimento motor e a independência funcional.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102995</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i4a102995</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 4 (2008); 225-228</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102995/101280</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/102997</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T18:40:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação da funcionalidade dos trabalhadores com LER/DORT: a construção do Core Set da CIF para LER/DORT</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of the functionality of workers with Repetitive Strain Injury (RSI)/ Work-related musculoskeletal disorders (MSDs): the construction of the ICF Core Set for RSI/MSDs</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Lima, Mônica Angelim Gomes de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Neves, Robson da Fonseca</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tironi, Márcia Oliveira Staffa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Nascimento, Ana Márcia Duarte Nunes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Magalhães, Francesca de Brito</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Transtornos Traumáticos Cumulativos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Trabalhadores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cumulative Trauma Disorders</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Workers</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">This study presents the ICF Core Set for Repetitive Strain Injury (RSI)/ Work-related musculoskeletal disorders (MSDs) and its construction process. The ICF Core Set for RSI/MSDs was created through successive consensuses among specialists in the workers' healthcare area throughout six phases, which involved from the assessment and the study of the ICF, followed by its reading and discussion, to the establishment of codes and comparison with the core sets of generalized pain and depression. For the "body functions" component, the chosen codes were related to the following aspects: mental, sensory, pain and neuromusculoskeletal functions, as well as movement functions. For the "body structures" component, the chosen codes were related to the following aspects: nervous system structures and those related to movement. For the "activity and participation" component, the chosen codes were related to: mobility, personal care, domestic life, interpersonal relations and interactions and the main areas of life. For "environmental factors", the codes chosen were related to: support and relationships, attitudes and services, systems and policies. The environment component was the most limited for the description within the work context. This study represents the effort of constructing a core set based on an interdisciplinary approach, viable to be applied during the treatment and rehabilitation process of workers presenting RSI/MSDs and can contribute to bring Brazil into the international discussion that deals with the consequences of human disease from a social-medical model, displacing the scientific debate and the creation of public policies from the context of disability/incapacity into the health context.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O presente artigo apresenta o Core set da CIF para LER/DORT e seu processo de construção.&#160; O Core set da CIF para LER/DORT foi elaborado por meio de consensos sucessivos entre especialistas do campo da saúde do trabalhador em seis etapas, que envolveram desde a aproximação e estudo da CIF, leitura, discussão até a eleição de códigos e comparação com os core sets de dor generalizada e de depressão. Para o componente ‘funções do corpo’ foram escolhidos códigos relacionados aos aspectos: funções mentais, sensoriais, de dor e neuromusculoesqueléticas e relacionadas ao movimento. Para ‘estruturas do corpo’ foram escolhidos códigos relacionados aos aspectos: estruturas do sistema nervoso e relacionadas ao movimento. Para ‘atividade e participação’ foram escolhidos códigos relacionados à: mobilidade, cuidado pessoal, vida doméstica, relações e interações interpessoais e áreas principais da vida. Para ‘fatores ambientais’ foram escolhidos códigos relacionados à: apoio e relacionamentos, atitudes e serviços, sistemas e políticas. O componente ambiente foi o mais limitado para a descrição dentro do contexto do trabalho. Este artigo apresenta o esforço de construção de um core set, a partir de uma abordagem interdisciplinar, viável à aplicação no processo de tratamento e reabilitação de trabalhadores com LER/DORT e poderá contribuir para inserir o Brasil na discussão internacional que trata das conseqüências do adoecimento humano a partir do modelo sócio-médico, deslocando o debate científico e a produção de políticas públicas do contexto da deficiência/incapacidade para o contexto da saúde.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102997</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i4a102997</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 4 (2008); 229-235</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/102997/101281</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103000</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T18:44:54Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Efficacy of acupuncture in pain relief and function improvement in ankylosing spondylitis: a randomized controlled trial</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efetividade da acupuntura para alívio da dor e ganho funcional em espondilite anquilosante: ensaio clínico controlado e randomizado</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Jorge, Liliana Lourenço</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imamura, Marta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sugawara, André Tadeu</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fen, Chien Hsin</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spondylitis Ankylosing</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Acupuncture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Espondilite Anquilosante</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acupuntura</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A espondilite anquilosante (EA) é uma doença inflamatória crônica que acarreta seqüelas osteomusculares, déficit funcional e dor. Apesar do crescente número de pacientes buscando acupuntura como opção terapêutica para analgesia, há poucos trabalhos verificando sua eficácia em ensaios controlados. O objetivo deste estudo é avaliar a eficácia da acupuntura para alívio da dor espinhal em pacientes com EA. Estudo piloto randomizado duplo-cego, placebo-controlado na Divisão de Medicina Física e Reabilitação do Hospital das Clínicas da Universidade de São Paulo. Dez portadores de dor espinhal secundária à EA foram estudados para se verificar o efeito de dez sessões de acupuntura clássica, duas vezes por semana, contra eletroacupuntura placebo. A avaliação da intervenção antes e após incluiu medida da dor espinhal, mobilidade espinhal (teste de Schober, distância dedos-chão, distância occipício-parede e expansibilidade torácica), inflamação (BASDAI, proteínas de fase aguda), avaliação subjetiva do paciente e função (BASFI). Acupuntura clássica não foi melhor que placebo nas medidas de saída. Contudo, o Effect Size para alívio da dor foi 2,04 para acupuntura e 1,09 para placebo, ambos considerados comparáveis aos tratamentos padrão para EA. Pelo teste do Sinal, ambas as intervenções mostraram resultado significante. Acupuntura não é melhor que placebo para o alívio da dor em pacientes com EA. A resposta relevante no grupo placebo fornece evidência do efeito benéfico da relação médico-paciente no alívio da dor em pacientes com EA. O estudo está registrado com o número ISRCTN02971192 em http://isrctn.org</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Ankylosing Spondylitis (AS) is a chronic disease that leads to musculoskeletal sequelae, functional impairment and pain. In spite of a crescent number of patients seeking acupuncture as an analgesic therapy, only a few studies verified the acupuncture efficacy in controlled trials The objective of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of acupuncture for spinal pain relief in AS patients. Double-blind randomized placebo-controlled pilot from the Division of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, University of Sao Paulo. Ten AS patients suffering from spinal pain were studied to evaluate the effect of ten sessions of classic acupuncture, two times per week, against sham electrical stimulation. Before and after intervention assessment included spinal pain, spinal mobility (Schöber test, Fingers-to-floor distance, Occiput-to-wall distance, and chest expansion), inflammation (BASDAI, acute-phase reactants, number of drugs taken), subjective patient assessment, and function (BASFI).Results: Classic acupuncture was no better than sham electrical stimulation in all outcome measures (p = 0.0625). However, the effect size for pain relief was 2.04 for acupuncture and 1.09 for the sham, both considered comparable with the standard treatments for AS. If evaluated by the Sign test, both acupuncture and sham interventions showed significant results (p = 0.0313). Acupuncture does not seem to be better than sham acupuncture for relieving pain in patients with AS. The relevant response in sham group may provide some evidence of a beneficial, subjective effect as an important component of pain relief in AS patients. The trial is registered under the number ISRCTN02971192 at&amp;nbsp;http://isrctn.org</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103000</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i4a103000</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 4 (2008); 236-240</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103000/101282</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/103001</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-11-26T18:50:14Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Musculoskeletal pain in primary health care in a town of the Mucuri Valley, northeastern Minas Gerais, Brazil</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor musculoesquelética na atenção primária à saúde em uma cidade do Vale do Mucuri, nordeste de Minas Gerais</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Cordeiro, Quirino</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>El Khouri, Marcelo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Corbett, Carlos Eduardo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epidemiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde Pública</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Public Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A dor musculoesquelética é um problema de saúde pública, devido à sua alta prevalência, alto custo e impacto negativo que pode causar na qualidade de vida dos pacientes e também de seus familiares. A dor musculoesquelética é um quadro clínico importante no atendimento aos pacientes da atenção primária à saúde. Assim, o objetivo do presente estudo foi investigar a freqüência de dor musculoesquelética como razão para consulta médica na atenção primária à saúde, na cidade de Serra dos Aimorés, localizada na região nordeste do estado de Minas Gerais, no Vale do Mucuri, Brasil, e tentar correlacionar tal quadro clínico às variáveis de gênero e idade. Dentre todas as queixas clínicas referidas como razão para consulta médica, a dor musculoesquelética foi a mais prevalente entre os 1.306 pacientes investigados, sendo encontrada em 139 deles (10,64%). A análise estatística dos dados encontrou associação significante entre gênero masculino e presença de queixa de dor musculoesquelética. Em relação à faixa etária, pôde-se observar um aumento na freqüência de queixa de dor musculoesquelética, conforme a idade avançava. No entanto, não foi encontrada diferença estatisticamente significante, quando a população, dividida por faixa etária, foi analisada. Tais achados reforçam a importância de adequada avaliação e tratamento dos quadros de dor musculoesquelética pelas equipes da atenção primária à saúde. Importância especial deve ser dada a algumas populações específicas, como os idosos. Ademais, há que se atentar também para a diferença existente entre pacientes do sexo masculino e feminino.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Musculoskeletal pain is a public health problem due to its high prevalence, high cost and negative impact on the quality of life of patients and their relatives. Musculoskeletal pain is an important clinical feature in the context of the primary health care. Thus, the aim of the present study was to investigate the prevalence of musculoskeletal pain as the reason for seeking medical assistance in primary health care in the town of Serra dos Aimores, located in the Northeastern region of the state of Minas Gerais, in the Mucuri Valley, Brazil in an attempt to correlate such clinical picture to gender and age variables. Among all the clinical diagnoses, musculoskeletal pain was the most prevalent reason for seeking medical assistance in a total of 1,306 investigated patients, being found in 139 of them (10.64%). The statistical analysis of the data found a significant association between male gender and the presence of musculoskeletal pain. Regarding the age variable, the frequency of musculoskeletal pain increased with age. However, there was no statistically significant difference when the groups, divided according to age range, were compared. Such findings reinforce the importance of the evaluation and treatment of musculoskeletal pain by the primary health care staff. Special importance must be given to specific populations such as the elderly. Moreover, the differences related to gender must also be taken into account.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2008-12-09</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v15i4a103001</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 15 n. 4 (2008); 241-244</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/103001/101283</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2008 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2023-08-08T14:49:08Z" completeListSize="935" cursor="275">ad8fff58f56c702e4f31ad6713dc0dda</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
