<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.revistas.usp.br/lib/pkp/xml/oai2.xsl" ?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-08-07T14:49:39Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="ListRecords" metadataPrefix="oai_dc" set="actafisiatrica">https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/oai</request>
  <ListRecords>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/169835</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-01T13:27:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effects of a physical exercise program based on the soil Pilates method on physical activity, locomotor capacity and quality of life in men with lower limb amputation</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeitos de um programa de exercícios físicos baseado no método Pilates solo sobre a atividade física, capacidade locomotora e qualidade de vida em homens com amputação de membro inferior</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rudolpho, Sara Maria Soffiatti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Luza, Lisiane Piazza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pires, Greicy Kelly Wosniak</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Franciele Cascaes da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lima, David Braga de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Laiana Cândido de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Caviquioni, Thamara</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Rudney da</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disabled Persons</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Amputation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Postural Balance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pessoas com Deficiência</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Amputação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício Físico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Postural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: &#160;Avaliar os efeitos de um programa de exercícios físicos de 12 semanas baseado no método Pilates Solo sobre atividade física, equilíbrio, capacidade locomotora e qualidade de vida em homens com amputação unilateral de membro inferior. Método: Participaram do estudo 14 pessoas com amputação unilateral de membro inferior, divididos em 2 grupos: Grupo Intervenção – GI (participantes expostos ao protocolo de exercícios baseados no método Pilates Solo) e Grupo Controle – GC (participantes não expostos ao protocolo de exercícios baseados no método Pilates Solo). Foram aplicados os seguintes instrumentos: a) ficha para caracterização dos participantes; b) Physical Activity Scale for Individuals with Physical Disabilities (PASIPD); c) Escala de Equilíbrio de Berg; d) Medida Funcional para Amputados (MFA); e e) Short Form Health Survey (SF-36). Os dados foram analisados por meio da estatística descritiva e inferencial sendo considerados significativos os resultados com p menor ou igual a 0,05. Resultados: Com base nas análises foi possível observar diferença significativa no equilíbrio após o período experimental (p=0,008), a favor do grupo intervenção. Além disso, pode-se observar diferença significativa na média do grupo intervenção para equilíbrio e para aspectos físicos na qualidade de vida (SF-36), assim como o d de Cohen mostrou efeitos de grande magnitude sobre essas variáveis. Conclusão: Logo, os resultados apresentam efeitos positivos na prática do programa de exercícios físicos sobre o equilíbrio dinâmico e estático e na qualidade de vida de pessoas amputadas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Evaluate the effects of a twelve week physical exercise program based on the Pilates Solo method about physical activity, balance, locomotor capacity, and quality of life in men with unilateral lower limb amputation. Method: The study included 14 people with unilateral lower limb amputation, divided in two groups: Intervention Group - IG (participants exposed to the exercise protocol based on the Pilates Solo method) and Control Group - CG (participants that were not exposed to the exercise protocol based on the Pilates Solo method). The following instruments were applied: a) form to characterize the participants; b) Physical Activity Scale for Individuals with Physical Disabilities (PASIPD); c) Berg's Balance Scale; d) Amputee Functional Measure; and e) Short Form Health Survey (SF-36). The data were analyzed using descriptive and inferential statistics, with results with p less than or equal to 0.05 being considered significant. Results: Based on the analysis, it was possible to observe a significant difference in balance after the experimental period (p=0.008), in favor of the intervention group. In addition, a significant difference can be observed in the mean of the intervention group for balance and for physical aspects of quality of life (SF-36), as well as Cohen's d showed effects of great magnitude on these variables. Conclusion: Therefore, the results show positive effects in the practice of the physical exercise program on the dynamic and static balance and on the quality of life of amputees.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/169835</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i3a169835</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 3 (2021); 133-141</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/169835/176464</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/170112</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-06-28T17:50:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação postural: avaliação quantitativa da postura estática de crianças de seis a dez anos de idade</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Postural evaluation: quantitative evaluation of static posture in children from six to ten years of age</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Tiago Gomes de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Valle, Ian Mazzetti Rodrigues</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Batista, Ingrid Thaiane Soares</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gomes, Lara Elena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carvalho, Rodrigo Gustavo da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Postura</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doenças Musculoesqueléticas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Desenvolvimento Infantil</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Software</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Posture</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Musculoskeletal Diseases</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child Development</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Software</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A avaliação da postura corporal estática de crianças permite identificar e prevenir desordens musculoesqueléticas no estágio inicial. Objetivo: Avaliar a postura estática de alunos de uma escola pública, comparando a postura entre as faixas etárias e entre os sexos. Métodos: A amostra foi composta por 130 escolares (62 do sexo masculino e 68 do sexo feminino), os quais tinham entre 6 e 10 anos de idade. Cada escolar foi fotografado nas vistas anterior, posterior e lateral direita, e o registro fotográfico foi analisado por meio do Software de Avaliação Postural (SAPo). Resultados: Somente foi encontrada diferença entre os sexos no ângulo do tornozelo, além de interação entre sexo e faixa etária. Em relação à idade, o alinhamento horizontal dos acrômios e o alinhamento horizontal da cabeça foram diferentes entre 6-7 e 9 anos. O alinhamento horizontal da cabeça, o alinhamento horizontal das espinhas ilíacas ântero-superior (EIAS) e o alinhamento sagital do membro inferior também apresentaram interação significativa entre sexo e idade. Conclusão: Em média, a maioria dos resultados demonstra que há um alinhamento vertical e uma simetria horizontal nos ângulos analisados, com exceção do alinhamento sagital do membro inferior, do ângulo do tornozelo e do alinhamento sagital do corpo que não demostraram um alinhamento próximo do ideal. Logo, os escolares avaliados apresentam uma boa saúde musculoesquelética.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Static postural evaluation of children allows identifying and preventing musculoskeletal disorders in early stages. Objective: To evaluate the static posture of students of a public school, comparing the posture between age groups and between genders. Methods: The sample consisted of 130 school children (62 males and 68 females), who were 6-10 years old. Each student was photographed from the anterior, posterior and right lateral views, and photographic records were analyzed using the Software Postural Assessment (SAPo). Results: Only the angle of the ankle was different between the genders and this variable also presented interaction between gender and age group. In relation to age groups, the horizontal alignment of acromions and horizontal alignment of the head were different between 6-7 and 9 years. The horizontal alignment of the head, the horizontal alignment of the ASIS and the sagittal alignment of the lower limb also showed a significant interaction between gender and age group. Conclusion: On average, most of the results show that there is a vertical alignment and a horizontal symmetry in the analyzed angles, except the sagittal alignment of&#160; the lower limb, angle of the ankle and sagittal alignment of the body that did not show a close alignment of the ideal. Therefore, the evaluated students&#160; presented a good musculoskeletal health.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/170112</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v29i1a170112</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 29 n. 1 (2022); 18-24</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/170112/181087</dc:relation>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/170112/180938</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/170355</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-04-17T17:41:07Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação muscular do joelho e funcional de membros inferiores de jovens atletas de voleibol do sexo feminino</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Knee muscle evaluation and lower limbs’ functional evaluation of young female volleyball athletes</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Ana Paula</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fabian, Geiziane de Fátima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cecconi, Matheus Pauletti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Eberle, Elias Franzoi</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Balbinot, Guilherme Faria</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Viecelli, Andressa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Tadiello, Gerson Saciloto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Bonetti, Leandro Viçosa</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Functional Performance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Strength Dynamometer</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Athletic Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Knee</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Volleyball</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Desempenho Físico Funcional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dinamômetro de Força Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos em Atletas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Joelho</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Voleibol</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Os desequilíbrios musculares e funcionais são analisados na tentativa de prevenir lesões e melhorar os desempenhos de atletas. Objetivo: Analisar o desempenho muscular de extensores e flexores de joelho e o desempenho funcional dos membros inferiores de atletas de voleibol. Métodos: Quinze atletas da categoria sub-16 de voleibol feminino da Universidade de Caxias do Sul foram avaliadas. Para análise do desempenho muscular, as variáveis pico de torque de extensores e flexores de joelho, e razão convencional de extensores/flexores, foi utilizado o dinamômetro isocinético. Já para a análise funcional dos membros inferiores, foram utilizados os testes Hop tests e Y balance test (YBT). Resultados: Na comparação entre membro dominante (MD) e não dominante (MND), não houve diferenças estatisticamente significativas na análise do pico de torque; já na razão flexores/extensores foi encontrada diferença significativa apenas à 240°/s. Entretanto, os valores médios da razão flexores/extensores encontrarem-se abaixo dos valores sugeridos pela literatura. As avaliações funcionais também não mostraram assimetrias entre os membros; no entanto, a pontuação composta do YBT apresentou-se abaixo dos valores normativos. Conclusão: A excelente simetria entre os membros pode ser justificada pela especificidade do esporte, pois os gestos esportivos do voleibol apresentam carácter simétrico durante as exigências físicas dos membros inferiores. No entanto, os baixos valores da razão flexores/extensores e da pontuação composta do YBT talvez não estejam diretamente relacionados a um risco maior de lesões já que os valores de referência utilizados são de atletas adultos.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Muscle and functional imbalances are analyzed in order to try prevent injuries and improve athletes' performance. Objective: To analyze knee’s muscular performance of the knee extensors and flexors and lower limbs’ functional performance of volleyball athletes. Methods: Fifteen female volleyball, athletes under the age of 16 from the University of Caxias do Sul, were analyzed. For analysis of muscle performance, the variables peak torque of knee extensors and flexors, and conventional flexor/extensor ratio, the isokinetic dynamometer was used. For the functional analysis of the lower limbs, the Hop tests and Y balance test (YBT) were used. Results: In the comparison between dominant (MD) and non-dominant (MND) limbs, there were no statistically significant differences in the analysis of peak torque; and in the flexor/extensor ratio analyzes, just one significant difference was found at 240°/s. However, the mean values of flexor/extensor ratio are below to the values suggested by the literature. Functional assessments also did not show asymmetries between members; however, the YBT composite score was below to the normative values. Conclusion: The excellent symmetry between the members can be justified by the sport’s specificity, as the volleyball’s gestures have a symmetrical character during the physical demands of the lower limbs. However, the low values of the flexor/extensor ratio and the YBT composite score may not be directly related to an increased risk of injuries since the reference values used are for adult athletes.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-12-28</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/170355</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v29i4a170355</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 29 n. 4 (2022); 251-259</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/170355/190493</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/170815</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-11-24T18:59:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Redução da força de preensão manual entre idosos longevos</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Reduction of handgrip strength among the oldest old</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tavares, Darlene Mara dos Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Nayara Gomes Nunes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Marchiori, Gianna Fiori</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Lara Lacerda Soares</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso de 80 Anos ou mais</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força da Mão</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Sarcopenia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Enfermagem Geriátrica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged, 80 and over</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Hand Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Sarcopenia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Geriatric Nursing</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivos: Descrever as características sociodemográficas e de saúde dos longevos, identificar a ocorrência da redução da força de preensão manual dos longevos e verificar os fatores associados à redução da força de preensão manual dos longevos. Métodos:&amp;nbsp;Estudo transversal e analítico, com abordagem quantitativa, desenvolvido com 313 idosos longevos da comunidade de uma Macrorregião de Saúde do Estado de Minas Gerais. Na coleta dos dados aplicaram-se: Miniexame do Estado Mental; Questionário estruturado elaborado pelo Grupo de Pesquisa em Saúde Coletiva; Questionário Internacional de Atividade Física; versão brasileira do Short Physical Performance Battery; Teste de força de preensão manual; Índice de massa corporal e questão referente à ocorrência de queda. Procederam-se às análises: descritiva, teste Qui-quadrado e regressão logística múltipla (p&amp;lt;0,05). Resultados:&amp;nbsp;Houve predomínio de longevos do sexo feminino (64,2%); com 80-90 anos de idade (86,6%); 1-5 anos de estudo (53,0%); renda ≤1 salário mínimo (55,3%); viúvos (63,3%); que moravam acompanhados (75,7%); inativos fisicamente (51,4%); com desempenho físico moderado/bom (55,9%); sem ocorrência de quedas nos últimos 12 meses (68,4%); eutróficos (39,9%) e com cinco ou mais morbidades (62,9%). A maioria dos longevos (60,4%) apresentou redução da força de preensão manual que se associou à ocorrência de quedas nos últimos 12 meses (p=0,042) e à inatividade física (p&amp;lt;0,001). Conclusão: A redução na força de preensão manual dos idosos longevos foi relacionada à ocorrência de quedas e inatividade física, tais fatores contribuem para planejamento do cuidado gerontológico na prática clínica. &amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To describe the sociodemographic and health characteristics of older adults aged 80 or over, to identify the occurrence of reduced handgrip strength of older adults aged 80 or over and to verify the factors associated with reduced handgrip strength of older adults aged 80 or over. Methods: Cross-sectional an analytical study, with a quantitative approach, developed with 313 older adults aged 80 or over from the community of a Health Macro-region of the State of Minas Gerais. In data collection, the following were applied: Mini-Mental State Examination; Structured questionnaire prepared by the Collective Health Research Group; International Physical Activity Questionnaire; Brazilian version of the Short Physical Performance Battery; Handgrip strength test; Body mass index and question regarding the occurrence of falls. Results: There was a predominance of older adults aged 80 or over females (64.2%); with 80 -90 years of age (86.6%); 1-5 years of schooling (53.0%); income ≤1 minimum wage (55.3%); widowers (63.3%); who lived accompanied (75.7%); physically inactive (51.4%); with moderate/good physical performance (55.9%); no falls in the last 12 months (68.4%), eutrophic (39.9%) and with five or more morbidities (62.9%). Most older adults aged 80 or over (60.4%) showed a reduction in handgrip strength, which was associated with the occurrence of falls in the last 12 months (p=0.042) and physical inactivity (p&amp;lt;0.001). Conclusion: The reduction in the handgrip strength of older adults aged 80 or over was related to the occurrence of falls and physical inactivity, such factors contribute to planning gerontological care in clinical practice.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/170815</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i1a170815</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 1 (2020); 4-10</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/170815/162696</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/170876</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-07-31T18:14:45Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Instrumentos de avaliação do ajuste psicossocial à amputação, uso e satisfação com a prótese: uma revisão sistemática da literatura</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Instruments for evaluation of psychosocial adjustment to amputation, use and satisfaction with the prosthesis: a systematic review of literature</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pires, Greicy Kelly Wosniak</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Luza, Lisiane Piazza</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rudolpho, Sara Maria Soffiatti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Paula Lopes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Rudney da</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Amputation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Artificial Limbs</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Psychosocial Impact</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Patient Satisfaction</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Amputação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Membros Artificiais</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Impacto Psicossocial</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Satisfação do Paciente</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">O ajuste à amputação envolve tanto questões físicas quanto psicossociais e a satisfação com o membro artificial. Objetivo: Revisar sistematicamente a literatura acerca dos instrumentos que avaliam o ajuste psicossocial à amputação e uso da prótese e a satisfação com a prótese em pessoas com amputação de membro inferior. Métodos: Fonte de dados: Medline via Pubmed, Web of Science e Scopus. Critérios de elegibilidade: estudos originais que utilizaram questionários para avaliar o ajustamento psicossocial a amputação e uso da prótese e a satisfação com a prótese. Participantes: pessoas com amputação de membro inferior. Métodos de avaliação e síntese dos estudos: todas as análises foram realizadas por três avaliadores, de forma independente, sendo os resultados apresentados de forma descritiva, em tabelas. Resultados: Foram encontrados 239 artigos na busca inicial, sendo incluídos 12 artigos ao final da revisão. Nestes, foram identificados 14 questionários que avaliam o ajuste psicossocial e a satisfação com a prótese, porém, somente 5 são validados especificamente para a população amputada. Conclusão: A Trinity Amputation and Prosthesis Experience Scale (TAPES) e o Prosthesis Evaluation Questionnaire (PEQ) são os instrumentos mais utilizados, sendo sempre importante uma seleção criteriosa dos instrumentos a serem utilizados nas pesquisas e intervenções a fim de se obter dados válidos, confiáveis e comparáveis. Número de registro da revisão sistemática: CRD42019097279.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The adjustment to amputation involves physical and psychosocial issues and the satisfaction with the artificial limb. Objective: To systematically review the literature about the instruments that assess psychosocial adjustment to amputation and use of the prosthesis and satisfaction with the prosthesis in people with lower limb amputation. Methods: Data sources: Medline via Pubmed, Web of Science and Scopus. Study eligibility criteria: Original studies that using questionnaires to evaluated the psychosocial adjustment to amputation and prosthesis use and about prosthesis satisfaction. Participants: people with lower limb amputation. Study appraisal and synthesis methods: all analyzes were performed independently by three evaluators, and the results were presented descriptively, in tables. Results: Were found 239 articles in the initial search, with 12 articles included at the end of the review. In these, 16 questionnaires were identified that assess the psychosocial adjustment and satisfaction with the prosthesis, however, only five are validated specifically for the amputated population. Conclusion: The Trinity Amputation and Prosthesis Experience Scale (TAPES) and the Prosthesis Evaluation Questionnaire (PEQ) are the most used instruments, being always important to carefully select the instruments to be used in research and interventions in order to obtain valid, reliable and comparable data. Systematic review registration number: CRD42019097279.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2023-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/170876</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v30i1a170876</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 30 n. 1 (2023); 47-54</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/170876/193133</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2023 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/171038</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-02T14:48:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Medo de cair em idosos classificados como vulneráveis de um centro de referência à atenção da saúde do idoso</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Fear of falling among elderly people classified as vulnerable in a referral center for elderly health care</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Ferreira, Miguel Jânio Costa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>França, Júlio César Queiroz de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lobos, Juan Carlos Costa Mata</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santana, Roseanne Maria Silva Barbosa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moraes Júnior, Juarez Belmiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Carneiro, Andréa Santana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Monteiro, Silvio Gomes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Maria Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Serviços de Saúde para Idosos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidentes por Quedas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Medo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Services for the Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Accidental Falls</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Fear</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Correlacionar o medo de cair com a vulnerabilidade em idosos. Método: A vulnerabilidade foi avaliada por meio da Pesquisa sobre Idosos Vulneráveis (VES-13) e o medo de cair pela Escala de Eficácia de Quedas - Internacional – Brasileira (FES-I-BR), participaram idosos de ambos os sexos e idade (60-85 anos), foram excluídos voluntários com limitações cognitivas e os que não participavam do grupo de convivência. Foram aplicado os testes de Kolmogorov-Smirnov, de Mann-Whitney, de Spearman, de regressão logística binária e para análise de sensibilidade e especificidade da FES-I-BR, empregou-se a curva da característica do operador receptor (ROC), a análise foi realizada em 95% nível de confiança e p&amp;lt;0,05 foi adotado.&#160; Resultados: Entre os n= 123 idosos, foi observado que (33,3%) são vulneráveis, n= 120 (97,6%) apresentaram alguma preocupação em cair. Entre as atividades analisadas na FES-I-BR, 21,1% estão extremamente preocupados em cair ao andar em superfícies escorregadias e foi observada uma correlação positiva e significativa entre a pontuação do VES-13 com a pontuação da FES-I-BR, a FES-I-BR foi um previsor significativo para a vulnerabilidade.&#160; A FES-I-BR de forma aceitável mostrou-se capaz de discriminar o medo de cair de vulneráveis de não vulneráveis em uma área de 0,656 (p&amp;lt;0,005), sensibilidade de 53,7% e especificidade de 69,5%.&#160; Conclusão: O medo de cair está correlacionado com a vulnerabilidade, os idosos vulneráveis apresentaram mais medo de cair, o medo de cair é fator preditor de vulnerabilidade e a FES-I-BR foi capaz de discriminar o medo de cair de idosos vulneráveis e não vulneráveis.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Was to correlate the fear of falling with vulnerability in the elderly. Method: Vulnerability was assessed using the Vulnerable Elderly Survey (VES-13) and the fear of falling using the Falls Efficacy Scale - International - Brazilian (FES-I-BR), elderly people of both sexes and age (60- 85 years old), volunteers with cognitive limitations and those who did not participate in the coexistence group were excluded. The Kolmogorov-Smirnov, Mann-Whitney, Spearman, binary logistic regression tests were applied and for the sensitivity and specificity analysis of the FES-I-BR, the Receiver Operator Characteristic Curve (ROC) was used, analysis was performed at 95% confidence level and p &amp;lt;0.05 was adopted. Results: Among the n = 123 elderly, it was observed that (33.3%) are vulnerable, n = 120 (97.6%) had some concern about falling. Among the activities analyzed at FES-I-BR, 21.1% are extremely concerned about falling when walking on slippery surfaces and a positive and significant correlation was observed between the VES-13 score and the FES-I-BR score, FES-I-BR was a significant predictor for the vulnerability. In the present study, the FES-I-BR in an acceptable way proved to be able to discriminate the fear of falling from vulnerable to non-vulnerable in an area of 0.656 (p &amp;lt;0.005), sensitivity of 53.7% and specificity of 69, 5%. Conclusion: Fear of falling is correlated with vulnerability, vulnerable elderly people were more afraid of falling, fear of falling is a predictor of vulnerability and FES-I-BR was able to discriminate between the fear of falling of vulnerable and non-vulnerable elderly people.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171038</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i2a171038</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 2 (2020); 82-88</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171038/167759</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/171118</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-25T14:48:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Association between walking and strength of lower limbs after chronic stroke</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Associação entre velocidade de marcha e força de membros inferiores após acidente vascular encefálico crônico</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Brenno Belchior Cordeiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Faria-Fortini, Iza de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Costa, Pollyana Helena Vieira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Torriani-Pasin, Camila</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Polese, Janaine Cunha</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscle Strength</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Walking Speed</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Força Muscular</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Velocidade de Caminhada</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudos que investigam a associação entre a força média de membro inferior e a velocidade de marcha em indivíduos pós AVE são escassos. Logo, é importante determinar se a força muscular média pode explicar o desempenho na marcha, visto que os músculos agem em grupo. Objetivo: Investigar a associação entre velocidade de marcha e força muscular de membros inferiores, e identificar se um grupo muscular individual ou a força média de membros inferiores poderia predizer a velocidade de marcha e a velocidade de reserva (VR) em indivíduos pós AVE crônico. Métodos: 64 indivíduos deambuladores comunitários pós AVE crônico passaram por avaliação de força isométrica máxima (flexor/extensor/abdutor de quadril, flexor/extensor de joelho e flexor plantar/dorsoflexor de tornozelo) e velocidade de marcha habitual e máxima (Teste de Caminhada de 10 metros). A VR foi considerada a diferença entre velocidade de marcha máxima e habitual. Resultados: A força média do lado parético foi responsável por 19% e 20% da variância na velocidade de marcha habitual e máxima respectivamente. A força de flexor plantar do lado parético e flexor de quadril e joelho do lado não parético explicaram 27% da VR e força de flexor plantar do lado parético explicou 15%.&#160; Conclusão: A força média do lado parético contribuiu para a velocidade de marcha habitual e máxima. a força de flexor plantar do lado parético, flexor de quadril e joelho do lado não parético contribuíram para a VR de indivíduos pós AVE crônico.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Certain muscle groups strength directly influence walking speed (WS), and the lower strength of the paretic side is significantly associated with lower WS of individuals after stroke. Studies that have investigated the association between the average of lower limb strength and the WS in individuals are scarce. Therefore, it is important to determine whether the strength could explain walking performance due to some muscle weakness could be compensated by the strength of others, mainly because all muscles act in group, not isolated. Objective: To investigate the association between WS and lower limbs muscle strength, and to identify whether an individual muscle group or the average strength of lower limb would best predict WS and walking speed reserve (WSR) in individuals with stroke. Methods: Sixty-four community-dwelling individuals with chronic stroke have their maximum isometric strength (hip flexors/extensors/abductors, knee flexors/extensors, and ankle dorsiflexors/plantarflexors) and self-selected and fast WS (10m walk test) measured. WSR was considered as the difference between the fast and self-selected speed. Results: Average strength of the paretic limb accounted for 19% and 20% of the variance in self-selected and fast WS, respectively. Plantarflexor strength of the paretic, knee and hip flexors of the non-paretic side explained alone 27% of the WSR scores and plantarflexor strength of the paretic side alone explained 15%.Conclusion: Average muscle strength of the paretic side contributed to self-selected and fast WS. Plantarflexor strength of the paretic side, knee and hip flexors of the non-paretic side contributed with the WSR of chronic stroke individuals.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171118</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i3a171118</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 3 (2020); 131-138</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171118/167880</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/171150</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-11-24T18:59:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeito agudo da estimulação elétrica nervosa transcutânea (TENS) na lombalgia</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Acute effect of transcutaneous nerve electric stimulation (TENS) on lombalgy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Rosa, Bruna de Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Borba, Bruna Albani</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Taiana Boeira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lumertz, Milena</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Josué Nascente dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dohnert, Marcelo Baptista</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Daitx, Rodrigo Boff</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electric Stimulation Therapy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Low Back Pain</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy Modalities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Terapia por Estimulação Elétrica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Dor Lombar</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Modalidades de Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A lombalgia é um problema extremamente comum, que afeta mais pessoas do que qualquer outra afecção. Acarreta em um quadro de dor, perda de função e redução da qualidade de vida. Isto posto, o tratamento conservador é de suma importância para a reabilitação de pacientes com lombalgia. Objetivo: Avaliar o efeito agudo da estimulação elétrica transcutânea (TENS) em portadores de lombalgia. Métodos: Série de casos, no qual participaram 66 pacientes. Foi realizado uma única intervenção com TENS no modo acupuntural, frequência de 70 Hz, tempo de pulso de 150 us, com duração de 40 minutos. Foram avaliados o nível de dor, flexibilidade de isquiotibiais, força muscular e estabilização do complexo lombopélvico pré, imediatamente após e 24 horas após a intervenção.&amp;nbsp; Resultados: O nível de dor, flexibilidade de isquiotibiais e força muscular dos extensores de tronco apresentaram melhora imediatamente após intervenção (p&amp;lt;0,05). Após 24 horas, houve aumento significativo da dor em comparação ao pós intervenção (p&amp;lt;0,05), porém ainda se verificou um efeito analgésico e de melhora da flexibilidade em comparação a avaliação pré. A força muscular melhorou de forma significativa pós intervenção e manteve-se 24 horas após (p&amp;lt;0,05). Os testes de estabilidade apresentaram maior tempo de manutenção da postura imediatamente após a aplicação da TENS, porém com redução deste feito pós 24 horas (p&amp;lt;0,05). Conclusão: A TENS demonstrou redução do quadro álgico, melhora da força de tronco, flexibilidade de isquiotibiais e da estabilização lombopélvica imediatamente após a intervenção. Estes efeitos se mantiveram 24 horas após, porém não com a mesma intensidade.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Low back pain is an extremely common problem that affects more people than any other condition. It causes pain, loss of function and reduced quality of life. That said, conservative treatment is of paramount importance for the rehabilitation of patients with low back pain. Objective: To evaluate the acute effect of transcutaneous electrical stimulation (TENS) in patients with low back pain. Methods: Case series, in which 66 patients participated. A single intervention with TENS was performed in acupuncture mode, frequency of 70 Hz, pulse time of 150 us, lasting 40 minutes. The level of pain, hamstring flexibility, muscle strength and stabilization of the lumbopelvic complex pre, immediately after and 24 hours after the intervention were evaluated. Results: The level of pain, hamstring flexibility and muscle strength of the trunk extensors improved immediately after intervention (p &amp;lt;0.05). After 24 hours, there was a significant increase in pain compared to the post-intervention period (p &amp;lt;0.05), but there was still an analgesic effect and improved flexibility compared to the pre evaluation. Muscle strength improved significantly after the intervention and was maintained 24 hours later (p &amp;lt;0.05). The stability tests showed a longer posture maintenance time immediately after the application of TENS, but with a reduction of this done after 24 hours (p &amp;lt;0.05). Conclusion: TENS demonstrated a reduction in pain, improvement in trunk strength, hamstring flexibility and lumbopelvic stabilization immediately after the intervention. These effects were maintained 24 hours later, but not to the same degree.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171150</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i1a171150</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 1 (2020); 34-40</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171150/162680</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/171245</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-02T14:48:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Rel.+Caso</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Intensive rehabilitation protocol for neuropsychomotor development in a child with microcephaly: a case report</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Protocolo intensivo de reabilitação para o desenvolvimento neuropsicomotor em uma criança com microcefalia: um estudo de caso</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Tavares, Amanda Braceloti</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sant'Anna, Junior Augusto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Borges, Nathalia Cristina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santiago, Hildemberg Agostinho Rocha de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Junior, Ivair Matias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Menezes-Reis, Rafael</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Microcephaly</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child Development</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Skills</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Psychomotor Performance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Physical Therapy Modalities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Microcefalia</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Desenvolvimento Infantil</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Destreza Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Desempenho Psicomotor</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Modalidades de Fisioterapia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A microcefalia é uma doença de origem multifatorial podendo ser desenvolvida de forma congênita ou por causas ambientais.&#160; Ela atinge os ossos da calota craniana, causando o fechamento prematuro das fontanelas, no qual restringe o espaço interno do crânio, que em consequência afeta o crescimento e desenvolvimento normal do encéfalo, levando a disfunções neuropsicomotoras leves, moderadas ou graves. Desta forma, este estudo tem como objetivo avaliar o desenvolvimento neuropsicomotor de uma criança com microcefalia, antes e após um protocolo fisioterapêutico intensivo. Trata-se de relato de caso no qual foram avaliados os marcos motores e os níveis de função apresentados pelo paciente, antes e após um protocolo fisioterapêutico intensivo, realizado por um período de 30 dias consecutivos. Foram obtidos importantes resultados no controle de cervical, alinhamento de cabeça em linha média, manuseio de objetos, elevação das mãos à boca e alinhamento postural. Desta forma, conclui-se que o protocolo fisioterapêutico intensivo é uma alternativa eficaz que auxilia e potencializa o desenvolvimento neuropsicomotor da criança.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Microcephaly is a multifactorial disease that can be developed congenitally or due to environmental causes. It affects the skullcap bones, causing premature fontanelles closure, in which it restricts the internal skull space, which consequently affects the growth and normal development of the brain, leading to mild, moderate or severe neuropsychomotor disorders. Thus, this study aims to evaluate the neuropsychomotor development of a child with microcephaly, before and after an intensive physical therapy protocol. This is a case report in which the motor milestones and function levels were evaluated before and after an intensive physical therapy protocol performed for a consecutive 30 days period. Important results were obtained in cervical control, midline head alignment, object handling, lifting hands to mouth and postural alignment. Thus, it is concluded that the intensive physical therapy protocol is an effective alternative that helps and enhances the child's neuropsychomotor development.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171245</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i2a171245</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 2 (2020); 120-124</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171245/167771</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/171383</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-04-26T13:11:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Comun.+Breve</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Situational diagnosis of Specialized Centers in Rehabilitation and Orthopedic Manufacturings: CERBrasil Project</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Diagnóstico situacional dos Centros Especializados em Reabilitação (CER) e Oficinas Ortopédicas: Projeto CER-Brasil</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Castaneda, Luciana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dantas, Diego Sousa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Antônio Tadeu Ribeiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Castro, Shamyr Sulyvan</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pessoas com Deficiências</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Pesquisa sobre Serviços de Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Centros de Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação em Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disabled Persons</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Services</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation Centers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">In Brazil, the attention to people with disabilities has increasing in recent years, with the creation of the Care Network for People with Disabilities, as well as with ministerial initiatives to assess the current situation of the network and specific services in rehabilitation. In this sense, it is intended, through this brief communication, to present the CERBrasil project that aims to carry out the situational diagnosis of Specialized Centers in Rehabilitation (SCR) and orthopaedics manufacturings. The CER-Brasil project is a multicenter study with the national articulation of researchers from the five Brazilian federal regions. Through a multi-methodological approach, the project is being carried out in different stages, which include the Delphi method, documentary research, evaluation of health services, and interviews with managers, professionals and patients linked to SCR in different regions of the Brazilian territory. &#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A atenção a pessoa com deficiência no Brasil vem ganhando destaque nos últimos anos, com a criação da Rede de Cuidados à Pessoa com Deficiência, bem como com iniciativas ministeriais para avaliação da situação atual da rede e dos serviços específicos em reabilitação. Nesse sentido, pretende-se por meio dessa comunicação breve, apresentar projeto de pesquisa nacional de avaliação da atenção especializada em reabilitação. O projeto intitulado CER-Brasil objetiva realizar o diagnóstico situacional dos Centros Especializados em Reabilitação (CER) e Oficinas Ortopédicas. Trata-se de um estudo multicêntrico com a articulação nacional de pesquisadores das cinco regiões federativas brasileiras. Através de uma abordagem plurimetodológica, o projeto está sendo realizado em diferentes etapas, que incluem método Delphi, pesquisa documental, avaliação de serviços de saúde, e entrevista com gestores, profissionais e pacientes ligados aos CER em diferentes regiões do território brasileiro.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-12-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171383</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i4a171383</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 4 (2020); 256-259</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171383/170091</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/171415</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-25T14:48:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Comun.+Breve</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Peripheral oxygen saturation is not influenced by the use of face masks in exercise</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">A saturação periférica de oxigênio não é influenciada pelo uso de máscaras faciais em exercício</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Natália Cristina de Oliveira Vargas e</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alfieri, Fabio Marcon</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Oxygen Level</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Masks</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Coronavirus Infections</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício Físico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Nível de Oxigênio</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Máscaras</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Infecções por Coronavirus</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">In many cities worldwide the use of face masks in public spaces became mandatory to prevent dissemination of COVID-19. The closure of public parks, gymnasiums and other areas designed for the practice of physical exercise may contribute do inactivity. Objective: The aim of this experience report was to evaluate peripheral oxygen saturation with the use of different face masks at rest and at outdoor exercise. Methods: A single healthy female subject (41 years old, body mass index 18.5 kg/m2), experienced in outdoor jogging, was subjected to running sessions with 4 different types of face masks (surgical, double cloth, triple cloth and N95) and without mask, in 5 non-consecutive days. Sessions lasted 50 minutes, where 5,8km were covered at an average speed of 7km/h. Peripheral oxygen saturation (SpO2, %) and heart rate (HR, bpm) were registered at rest, at every 5 minutes of exercise and after 5 minutes of recovery. Results: Data revealed that no desaturation occurred at any moment with any mask, even at high intensity. There were no differences in mean SpO2 or HR with either type of face mask during exercise when compared to the use of no mask. Conclusion: Setting aside the discomfort of training with face masks and the possible interference of this in performance, face masks seem not to prevent adequate gas exchange during exercise in healthy subjects.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Em muitas cidades do mundo o uso de máscaras faciais em espaços públicos tornou-se obrigatório para prevenir a disseminação da COVID-19. O fechamento de parques públicos, academias e outras áreas destinadas à prática de atividade física podem contribuir para o sedentarismo. Objetivo: Avaliar a saturação periférica de oxigênio com o uso de diferentes máscaras faciais em repouso e durante exercício ao ar livre. Método: Uma única participante (41 anos, índice de massa corporal 18.5 kg/m2), experiente em corrida ao ar livre, foi submetida a sessões de corrida com 4 tipos diferentes de máscaras faciais (cirúrgica, tecido duplo, tecido triplo e N95) e sem máscara, em 5 dias não consecutivos. As sessões tiveram duração de 50 minutos, onde 5,8km eram percorridos em uma velocidade média de 7km/h. A saturação periférica de oxigênio (SpO2, %) e a frequência cardíaca (FC, bpm) firam registradas em repouso, a cada 5 minutos de exercício e após 5 minutos de recuperação. Resultados: Os dados revelaram que não ocorreu desaturação em nenhum momento com qualquer das máscaras, mesmo em alta intensidade. Não houve diferença nas médias de SpO2 ou FC com nenhuma das máscaras durante o exercício quando comparadas com o uso de nenhuma máscara. &#160;Conclusão: Deixando de lado o desconforto de treinar com máscaras faciais e a possível interferência disso na performance, as máscaras faciais parecem não impedir uma adequada troca gasosa durante o exercício em indivíduos saudáveis.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171415</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i3a171415</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 3 (2020); 190-192</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>eng</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171415/168003</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/171458</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-04-26T13:11:28Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Validation of a skill assessment instrument wheelchair management</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Validação de um instrumento de avaliação de habilidades de manejo de cadeira de rodas</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Amorim, Minerva Leopoldina de Castro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Kathya Augusta Thomé</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Batista, Luiz Henrique Rufino</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ponce, Keegan Bezerra</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spinal Cord Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Wheelchairs</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Validation Study</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Delphi Technique</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos da Medula Espinal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cadeiras de Rodas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estudo de Validação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Técnica Delfos</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Wheelchair management skills are essential for the functional independence of people using wheelchairs. Teaching them requires professionals to assess the initial condition of the apprentice, allowing them to verify their evolution during the intervention process. Objective: Validate an HMCR evaluation protocol, with criteria within existing concepts and scientific knowledge of psychometry. Method: For construction and validation of the instrument, we used the Delphi Survey method and content validity. The research participants were six specialists in the area of wheelchair activities with a master's or doctor's degree. We used Cronbach's alpha (α), content validity index (CVI), correlation coefficient to measure the internal consistency of the instrument intraclass (ICC) and T test of a sample with a 5% significance level. Results: 17 items we obtained for the criteria of clarity (CVI= 0.865 ± 0.059; α= 0.834; ICC= 0.828; P &amp;lt;0.05), relevance (CVI= 0.902 ± 0.071; α= 0.774; CCI= 0.779; P &amp;lt;0 , 05), simplicity (CVI= 0.918 ± 0.054; α= 0.705; CCI= 0.694; P &amp;lt;0.05), objectivity (CVI= 0.888 ± 0.067; α= 0.856; CCI= 0.850; P &amp;lt;0.05) and accuracy (CVI= 0.922 ± 0.060; α= 0.742; CCI= 0.721; P &amp;lt;0.05). Conclusion: Items in the construction of the assessment instrument demonstrate, by means of psychometry, to be valid and guarantee to measure what it is proposed to measure. Internal consistency of the items ensures that the development of a scale is necessary for the evaluation of people with SCI who use CR, which proposes new studies of application of the test to conclude the validation process.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Habilidades de manejo em cadeira de rodas são fundamentais para independência funcional de pessoas usuárias de cadeira de rodas. Ensiná-las, requer dos profissionais instrumentos que possam aferir a condição inicial do aprendiz permitindo verificar sua evolução durante o processo de intervenção. Objetivo: Validar um protocolo de avaliação de HMCR, com critérios dentro de conceitos e conhecimentos científicos existentes da psicometria. Método: Para construção e validação do instrumento, utilizamos o método Delphi de Survey e validade de conteúdo. Os participantes da pesquisa foram seis especialistas na área de atividades em cadeira de rodas com titulação de mestres ou doutores, usamos para medir a consistência interna do instrumento o alfa de Cronbach (α), índice de validade de conteúdo (IVC), Coeficiente de correlação intraclasse (CCI) e teste T de uma amostra com nível de 5% de significância. Resultados: Nos 17 itens obtivemos os critérios de clareza (CVI= 0,865±0,059; α= 0,834; CCI= 0,828; P&amp;lt;0,05), pertinência (CVI= 0,902±0,071; α= 0,774; CCI= 0,779; P&amp;lt;0,05), simplicidade (CVI= 0,918±0,054; α= 0,705; CCI= 0,694; P&amp;lt;0,05), objetividade (CVI= 0,888±0,067; α= 0,856; CCI= 0,850; P&amp;lt;0,05) e precisão (CVI= 0,922±0,060; α= 0,742; CCI= 0,721; P&amp;lt;0,05). Conclusão: Os itens na construção do instrumento de avaliação demonstram por meio da psicometria ser válido e garante medir aquilo que se propõe medir. A consistência interna dos itens garante que o desenvolvimento de uma escala se faz necessária para avaliação de pessoas com LM que utilizam CR, o que propõe novos estudos de aplicação do teste para concluirmos o processo de validação.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-12-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171458</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i4a171458</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 4 (2020); 220-224</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171458/170080</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/171459</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-02T14:48:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Influence of the use of Wii Fit on static balance and gait in Parkinson disease</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Influência do uso do Wii Fit sobre o equilíbrio estático e a marcha na doença de Parkinson</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Belchior, Luciana Dias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Almeida, Lícia Maria Belchior</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Parkinson Disease</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Video Games</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Simulation Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Postural Balance</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait Analysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doença de Parkinson</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Jogos de Vídeo</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício de Simulação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Equilíbrio Postural</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Análise da Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Doença de Parkinson (DP) caracteriza-se, especialmente, por bradicinesia, instabilidade postural, reflexos reduzidos e alteração de marcha, aumentando o risco de quedas. Objetivo: Avaliar a influência de exercícios protocolados sobre equilíbrio estático e marcha com Wii Fit na DP. Métodos: Trata-se de artigo original que analisou alterações estáticas e marcha em dois pacientes com Parkinson, submetidos ao Nintendo Wii® e avaliados antes e após o protocolo. A avaliação deu-se mediante análise do equilíbrio estático e da marcha, no início e ao final de 6 semanas após o protocolo de três jogos: Penguin Slide, Plataforms e Balance Bubble, 2 vezes semanais, abordando a mesma sequência. A pesquisa foi realizada no Laboratório de Análise do Movimento Humano, vinculado à Universidade de Fortaleza, de fevereiro a setembro de 2015. Resultados: Os dados baropodométricos, referentes à variação da superfície, mostraram valor menor após intervenção. A variável velocidade média aumentou após atividade. As distâncias entre 2º e 3º passo e entre 3º e 4º passo também aumentaram, após intervenção, exceto esta última para o primeiro paciente. Com o protocolo de Nitendo Wii Fit, participantes relataram maior agilidade e segurança nas passadas, podendo ser comprovado pelo aumento da velocidade média dessas. Os pacientes evidenciaram uma melhora no equilíbrio estático e na marcha. Conclusão: Os exercícios protocolados em realidade virtual nos pacientes com DP melhoraram o desempenho do equilíbrio estático e da marcha, o que tende a favorecer a estabilidade ortostática e a deambulação. &#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Parkinson Disease (PD) is characterized, especially, by bradykinesia, postural instability, reduced reflexes and changes in gait, increasing the risk of falls. Objective: To evaluate the influence of protocol exercises on static balance and gait with Wii Fit in PD. Method: This is an original article that analyzed static changes and gait in two patients with Parkinson who were submitted to Nintendo Wii® and evaluated before and after the protocol. The evaluation took place by analyzing static balance and gait, at the beginning and at the end of 6 weeks after the protocol of three games: Penguin Slide, Platforms and Balance Bubble, twice a week, covering the same sequence. The research was carried out at the Laboratório de Análise do Movimento Humano, linked to the Universidade de Fortaleza, from February to September 2015. Results: The baropodometric data, referring to the variation of the surface, showed a lower value after intervention. The average speed variable increased after activity. The distances between the 2nd and 3rd step and between the 3rd and 4th step also increased after the intervention, except for the latter for the first patient. With the Nitendo Wii Fit protocol, participants reported greater agility and safety in their strides, which can be proven by increasing their average speed. Patients showed an improvement in static balance and gait. Conclusion: Exercises protocoled in virtual reality in patients with PD improved the performance of static balance and gait, which tends to favor orthostatic stability and walking.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171459</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i2a171459</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 2 (2020); 107-112</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171459/167760</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/171476</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-02T14:48:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação de sintomas na distrofia muscular de Duchenne: uma estratégia de cuidado paliativo</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Evaluation of symptoms in Duchenne muscular dystrophy: a palliative care strategy</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pavão, Josiane Rosires</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lizzi, Elisângela Aparecida da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza, Mariana Angélica de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Sobreira, Cláudia Ferreira da Rosa</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Chaves, Thais Cristina</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Mattiello-Sverzut, Ana Claudia</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Distrofia Muscular de Duchenne</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cuidados Paliativos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação de Sintomas</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Muscular Dystrophy, Duchenne</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Palliative Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Symptom Assessment</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A avaliação de sintomas na distrofia muscular de Duchenne (DMD) permite o adequado manejo terapêutico e o Edmonton Symptom Assessment System (ESAS) possui esta função: avaliar simultaneamente múltiplos sintomas de pacientes em cuidados paliativos (dor, cansaço, sonolência, náusea, apetite, falta de ar, depressão, ansiedade e bem-estar). Objetivo: Verificar se pacientes com DMD entendem os termos do ESAS e são capazes de graduar seus sintomas por este instrumento. Métodos: 10 pacientes com DMD foram avaliados transversalmente em relação à: compreensão dos itens do ESAS, caracterização dos sintomas (pelo ESAS e Escala de Faces) e medida da função motora. A graduação de sintomas do paciente, pelo ESAS, foi realizada também pelo avaliador. Os dados foram analisados descritivamente e por meio do coeficiente de correlação de Spearman. Resultados: Todos os pacientes compreenderam os sintomas dor, cansaço, sonolência, depressão (tristeza) e bem-estar, já os sintomas náusea, apetite, falta de ar e ansiedade não foram compreendidos por todos. A média geral de todos os sintomas avaliados pela escala ESAS foi abaixo de 5 pontos. Entre os resultados da escala ESAS e Escala de faces, houve correlação forte para os sintomas “depressão” (r= 0,64) e “ansiedade” (r= 0,65). Houve correlação perfeita (r= 1,0) entre ESAS preenchida pelo paciente e pelo avaliador para os itens “depressão” e “ansiedade” e correlação forte (r= 0,82) para “sonolência”. Conclusão: Pacientes com DMD entenderam os termos do ESAS e graduaram seus sintomas por este instrumento, portanto, não há necessidade de alteração dos termos do ESAS para avaliação de pacientes com DMD.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Symptom assessment, in Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy (DMD), allows an adequate treatment, and the Edmonton Symptom Assessment System (ESAS) assess it:&#160; evaluating clinical problems of patients in palliative care (pain, tiredness, drowsiness, nausea, appetite, shortness of breath, depression, anxiety, and well-being). Objective: To verify if patients with DMD understand the terms of the ESAS and if their symptoms could be assessed using this instrument. Methods: Ten patients with DMD were cross-sectional&#160; evaluated in relation to the understanding of the ESAS items, capacity to describe symptom (using the ESAS and the Faces Scale) and the Motor Function Measure. The patient’s symptom by ESAS was also classified by evaluator. A descriptive and correlation (Spearman's correlation coefficient) analysis of data was performed. Results: All patients understood the symptoms of pain, tiredness, drowsiness, depression (sadness), and well-being. However, some patients did not understand the symptoms of nausea, appetite, shortness of breath. The general mean of all symptoms assessed by the ESAS was below 5 points. For the symptom ‘depression’ and ‘anxiety’, a strong correlation was found between the results of the ESAS and the Face scale (r= 0.64, and r= 0.65, respectively). Additionally, a perfect and strong correlation, respectively, was found between the ESAS completed by the patient and the evaluator for the items '‘depression’," and ‘anxiety’ (r= 1.0)" and a ‘drowsiness’ (r= 0.82). Conclusion: DMD patients understood the ESAS terms and graded their symptoms using this instrument. Therefore, it is not necessary to change the ESAS terms to assess patients with DMD.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171476</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i2a171476</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 2 (2020); 89-94</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171476/167761</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/171505</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-02-01T13:27:52Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Registros de absenteísmo-doença: o que os conteúdos revelam sobre a funcionalidade de trabalhadores da higienização?</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Absenteeism-disease records: what do the content reveal about the functioning of hygienization workers?</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Bárbara Cordeiro</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lopes, Jaqueline do Carmo Machado</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Scharan, Karoleen Oswald</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moser, Auristela Duarte de Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Occupational Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Absenteeism</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde do Trabalhador</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Absenteísmo</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To use sickness absence data of cleaning workers from an educational institution to establish an initial content subsidy with the categories of the International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF). Method: Quantitative, descriptive and retrospective study. It was analyzed 2881 medical certificates during 2010 and 2014, classified according to ICD-10. Variables studied: sex, admission and dismissal date, start and end of the certificate, number of days off and ICD-10 codes. Based on the linking rules proposed by Cieza, 2016 and in a process carried out by three researchers, the content of the absenteeism-disease records with the ICF was established. The data were processed by IBM SPSS 2.0 program. Results: It was identified 29 meaningful concepts of ICD-10 referring to the six most common chapters. Twenty-six of them were related to 17 categories of ICF, mostly to the functions and structures of the Body, followed by 1 category of Activities and Participation. One was classified as health condition and 2 as not covered by ICF. The available data did not allow relate meaningful concepts of ICD-10 to the categories of Environmental Factors component of ICF. Conclusion: The content of the absenteeism-disease records allowed to subsidize the selection of ICF categories, reflecting the biophysical aspects contemplated in ICD-10. However, in order to consider the biopsychosocial aspects of the ICF and the worker's health policy, it will be important to include in the absenteeism-disease records contents referring to Activities and Participation and Environmental Factors, in which workers experience their functionality.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Utilizar os registros de absenteísmo-doença de trabalhadores de limpeza do setor de higienização de uma instituição de ensino superior para estabelecer um subsídio inicial de conteúdo com as categorias da Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde (CIF). Método: Estudo quantitativo, descritivo e retrospectivo. Foram analisados 2.881 atestados médicos, de trabalhadores de limpeza durante o período de 2010 a 2014, classificados de acordo com a CID-10. Variáveis estudadas: sexo, data admissional e demissional, início e fim do atestado, número de dias de afastamento e códigos da CID-10. A partir das regras propostas por Cieza et al. 2016, em um processo efetuado por três pesquisadoras, estabeleceu-se o conteúdo dos registros de absenteísmo-doença com a CIF. Os dados foram tratados pelo programa IBM SPSS Statistics 2.0. Resultados: Foram identificados 29 conceitos significativos da CID-10, referentes aos 6 capítulos mais frequentes. Vinte e seis deles foram relacionados a 17 categorias da CIF, majoritariamente às funções e estruturas do Corpo, seguido de 1 categoria de Atividades e Participação. Um conceito foi classificado como condição de saúde e 2 como não cobertos pela CIF. Os dados disponíveis não evidenciaram categorias do componente Fatores Ambientais. Conclusão: O conteúdo dos registros de absenteísmo-doença permitiu subsidiar a seleção de categorias da CIF, refletindo os aspectos biofísicos contemplados na CID-10. Porém, para considerar os aspectos biopsicossociais da CIF e da política de saúde do trabalhador, será importante contemplar nos registros de absenteísmo-doença conteúdos referentes as Atividades e Participação e, Fatores Ambientais, nos quais os trabalhadores experenciam sua funcionalidade.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-09-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171505</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i3a171505</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 3 (2021); 142-148</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/171505/176465</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/172051</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-11-24T18:59:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Inquérito populacional sobre a funcionalidade das pessoas com lesão medular no Brasil: estudo de protocolo</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Population survey on the functionality of people with spinal cord injury in Brazil: a protocol study</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Utiyama, Daniela Mitiyo Odagiri</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Alfieri, Fabio Marcon</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Battistella, Linamara Rizzo</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos da Medula Espinal</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Inquéritos Epidemiológicos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spinal Cord Injuries</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Surveys</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">An International Spinal Cord Injury survey was developed to describe health and to be well subject to spinal cord injuries in relation to the local community. The objective of this study will be well subject to spinal cord injuries in relation to the local community. The objective of this study will be to describe how personal resources, environmental, health, quality of life, work conditions of individuals who suffer from spinal cord injury in Brazil and data comparison with other countries participating in the research. This study must be of an observational cross-sectional character. Individuals will be recruited at the Institute of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation of the Hospital de Clínicas of the Faculty of Medicine of the University of São Paulo, the Lucy Montoro Rehabilitation Network&amp;nbsp; and the Fluminense Rehabilitation Association. Participate in the study 400 individuals with both sexes aged 18 years or older diagnosed with traumatic spinal cord injury whose injury time is longer than 3 months. The volunteers will carry out an initial evaluation through a questionnaire with 125 questions about health problems, activity and participation, independence in activities of daily living, work, environmental and personal factors, health services and quality of life. Variations between variables can be made using Pearson or Spearman correlation. Simple linear or logistic regression models can also be used according to the data obtained. The procedures for processing and adjusting data obey the recommendations of the Intercultural Research of Guidelines and the strengthening of the Report on Observatory Studies in Epidemiology.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A pesquisa InSCI (International spinal cord injury) foi desenvolvida para descrever a saúde e o bem-estar de indivíduos com lesão medular (LM) em relação à comunidade local. Por isto, objetivo deste estudo será descrever as características pessoais, fatores ambientais, de saúde, de qualidade de vida, de trabalho dos indivíduos que vivem com lesão medular no Brasil e comparar os dados com outros países participantes da pesquisa. Este estudo deverá ser de caráter transversal observacional. Os indivíduos com LM serão recrutados no Instituto de Medicina Física e de Reabilitação (IMREA) do Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo, na Rede de Reabilitação Lucy Montoro (IRLM) e na Associação Fluminense de Reabilitação (AFR). Participarão do estudo 400 indivíduos de ambos os sexos com idade igual ou superior a 18 anos com diagnóstico de lesão medular de origem traumática cujo tempo de lesão esteja superior a 3 meses. Os voluntários realizarão uma avaliação inicial por meio de questionário com 125 perguntas sobre problemas de saúde, atividade e participação, independência nas atividades de vida diária, trabalho, fatores ambientais e pessoais, serviços de saúde e qualidade de vida. As associações entre as variáveis serão feitas testes de correlação de Pearson ou Spearman. Modelos simples de regressão linear ou logística também poderão ser usados de acordo com os dados obtidos. Os procedimentos de processamento e ajuste de dados obedecerão às recomendações das Diretrizes Cross-Cultural Survey (CCSG) e ao fortalecimento do Relatório de Estudos Observatórios em Epidemiologia (STROBE).</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/172051</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i1a172051</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 1 (2020); 11-19</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/172051/162697</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/172216</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-25T14:48:20Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Funcionalidade e qualidade de vida de pessoas com esclerose lateral amiotrófica e percepção da sobrecarga e apoio social de cuidadores informais</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Functionality and quality of life of people with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis and perception of overload and social support of informal caregivers</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Gomes, Crystian Moraes Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Zuqui, Aline Caus</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Schiavo, Kellen Valladão</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Jonaina Fiorim Pereira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Quality of Life</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Caregivers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Social Support</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation Centers</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Esclerose Amiotrófica Lateral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Qualidade de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cuidadores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Apoio Social</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Centros de Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: This research aims to measure the functionality and quality of life of Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS) patients and provide evidence about the potential excessive burden of care generated for their informal caregivers. Method: This is a quantitative, exploratory and descriptive study,&#160; and cross sectional investigation. The study sample was 24 participants, being 12 patients with ALS and 12 informal caregivers, recruited at a Specialized Rehabilitation Center. Individuals with ALS were administered the following instruments: Demographic Information Questionnaire; Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis Functional Rating Scale-Revised (ALSFRS-R); Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis Assessment Questionnaire (ALSAQ-40) and caregivers: Informal Caregiver Burden Assessment Questionnaire (QASCI); Medical Outcomes Study Social Support Survey (MOS). Results: Strong correlations were found between ALSFRS-R and ALSAQ-40 (r = - 0.709 p &amp;lt; 0.010), between the Daily Living Activities domain and ALSFRS-R (r = - 0.877 p &amp;lt; .001), between the domains of QASCI and MOS, Efficiency and Control Mechanism and material support (r = - 0.598 p &amp;lt; 0.040), Role and Family Satisfaction and Affective Support (r = - 0.604 p &amp;lt; 0.037), and Family Support and Interaction Positive Social (r = - 0.683 p &amp;lt; 0.014). Conclusion: The functionality and quality of life of the patient with ALS influence the provision of care, the perceived social support was a moderating variable of the caregivers' stress burden.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Esta pesquisa tem como objetivo mensurar a funcionalidade e qualidade de vida de pacientes com Esclerose Lateral Amiotrófica (ELA) e fornecer evidências sobre a possível sobrecarga de cuidados gerados aos seus cuidadores informais. Método: Trata-se de um estudo descritivo exploratório do tipo quantitativo, com delineamento transversal. A amostra do estudo foi composta por 24 participantes, sendo 12 pacientes com ELA e 12 cuidadores informais, recrutados em um Centro Especializado de Reabilitação. Foram administrados aos indivíduos com ELA os instrumentos: Questionário sobre Informações Demográficas; Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis Functional Rating Scale-Revised (ALSFRS-R); Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis Assessment Questionnaire (ALSAQ-40) e aos cuidadores: Questionário de Avaliação da Sobrecarga do Cuidador Informal (QASCI); Escala de Apoio Social do Medical Outcomes Study (MOS). Resultados: Foram encontradas fortes correlações entre ALSFRS-R e ALSAQ-40 (r = - 0.709 e p &amp;lt; 0.010), entre o domínio Atividades de Vida Diária e a ALSFRS-R (r = - 0.877 e p &amp;lt; .001), entre os domínios da QASCI e MOS, Mecanismo de Eficácia e de Controle e Apoio material (r = - 0.598 e p &amp;lt; 0.040), Satisfação com o Papel e com o Familiar e Apoio Afetivo (r = - 0.604 e p &amp;lt; 0.037), e Suporte Familiar e Interação Social Positiva (r = - 0.683 e p &amp;lt; 0.014). Conclusão: A funcionalidade e a qualidade de vida do paciente com ELA influenciam na provisão de cuidados, o suporte social percebido foi uma variável moderadora da sobrecarga de estresse dos cuidadores.&#160; &#160;&#160;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-02-02</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/172216</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i3a172216</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 3 (2020); 167-173</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/172216/167981</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/172364</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-02T14:48:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Association between the classification of functional ambulation classification and gait speed after stroke</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Associação entre a classificação da deambulação funcional com a velocidade da marcha após acidente vascular cerebral</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Júlio, Cíntia Elord</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cardoso, Ariadne</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pereira, Gabriela Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Corrêa, João Carlos Ferrari</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Soraia Micaela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Marcha</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Caminhada</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação de Processos e Resultados</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Gait</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Walking</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Outcome and Process Assessment, Health Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The choice of the appropriate instrument is decisive for the success of functional assessment and rehabilitation. In view of this, it is necessary that the professional has extensive knowledge of the instruments available so that he can choose the most effective, least costly and quickest assessment. Objective: To analyze whether the classification of ambulation obtained by the Functional Ambulation Classification (FAC) is associated with the performance obtained in the 10-meter walk test (TC10m). Methods: Cross-sectional study in which 61 individuals affected by stroke were evaluated. TC10m and FAC were used. To verify the normality of the data, a Kolmogorov-Smirnov test was used. One-way ANOVA was used to check whether there was a difference between dependent and independent walkers according to FAC with gait speed using the TC10m. A post hoc test and the Scheffe method were performed, considering p≤0.05. To analyze the association between the categorization of walking and gait speed, the chi-square test of independence was used. Results: There was a significant difference at each FAC level in relation&#160; to gait speed. There was an association between the classifications obtained by the FAC and by the TC10m [x2(9) = 145.335; p= 0.001]; and in 48% the variables are correctly associated. Conclusion: The findings indicated that the FAC levels were associated with walking speed. This finding expands the knowledge about gait assessment measures and helps clinical practice, considering that it facilitates the choice of the best instrument to assess gait after stroke.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A escolha do instrumento adequado é decisiva para o sucesso da avaliação funcional e reabilitação. Diante disto, é necessário que o profissional tenha amplo conhecimento dos instrumentos disponíveis para que possa optar pela avaliação mais eficaz, menos onerosa e mais rápida. Objetivo: Analisar se a classificação da deambulação obtida pela Functional Ambulation Classification (FAC) se associa com o desempenho obtido no Teste de Caminhada de 10 metros (TC10M). Métodos: Estudo transversal no qual foram avaliados 61 indivíduos acometidos pelo Acidente Vascular Cerebral (AVC). Utilizou-se o TC10M e a FAC. Para verificar a normalidade dos dados foi utilizado teste Kolmogorov – Smirnov. Foi utilizado o ANOVA de uma via para verificar se houve diferença dos deambuladores dependentes e independentes conforme a FAC com a velocidade da marcha por meio do TC10M. Foi realizado um teste post hoc e o método de Scheffe, considerando p≤0,05. Para analisar a associação da categorização da deambulação com a velocidade da marcha, foi o utilizado o teste do qui-quadrado de independência. Resultados: Houve diferença significante de cada nível da FAC em relação a velocidade da marcha. Houve associação entre as classificações obtidas pela FAC e pelo TC10m [x2(9) = 145,335; p=0,001]; sendo que em 48% as variáveis estão corretamente associadas. Conclusão: Os achados indicaram que os níveis da FAC apresentaram associação com a velocidade da marcha. Este achada amplia os conhecimentos sobre medidas de avaliação da marcha e auxilia a prática clínica, considerando que facilita a escolha do melhor instrumento para avaliar a marcha após AVC.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/172364</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i2a172364</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 2 (2020); 95-99</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/172364/167766</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/172431</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-02T14:48:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Effects of virtual reality in children and teenagers with cerebral paralysis based on International Classification of Functionality, Disability and Health: a systematic review</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Efeitos da realidade virtual em crianças e adolescentes com paralisia cerebral baseada na Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde: revisão sistemática</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pereira, Gabriela Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Heyriane Martins dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brandão, Thayane Correa Pereira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Jéssica Lima da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kaczmarek, Mara Cristina Dias</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Pinheiro, Vanessa Viana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fonseca Junior, Paulo Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Soraia Micaela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Cerebral Palsy</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Virtual Reality</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Adolescent</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Paralisia Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Realidade Virtual</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Adolescente</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Abordar os efeitos da terapia com realidade virtual em crianças e adolescentes com Paralisia Cerebral de acordo com a Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde (CIF). Com intuito de reunir dados que elucidem como a aplicação da CIF pode resultar em melhor compreensão das características apresentadas em uma situação de saúde. Métodos: Os artigos foram pesquisados nas plataformas MEDLINE (Pubmed), PEDro, LILACS e SCIELO, publicados até maio de 2019. A escala de qualidade PEDro (Physioterapy Evidence Database) foi utilizada como método de avaliação de qualidade dos artigos, sendo incluídos artigos com nota ≥ 6 (seis) no PEDro. Resultados: Seis artigos foram incluídos nesta revisão. De maneira geral, observou-se resultados significantes quanto às “Funções corporais” relacionadas à melhora da função de membros superiores e inferiores, após intervenção com RV, quando comparados a terapia convencional. No domínio “Atividade” observou-se resultados na marcha, equilíbrio e habilidades motoras globais de crianças com PC após intervenção com RV. Conclusão: Os efeitos da Realidade Virtual em crianças com PC relacionados a CIF são positivos, mas foram encontrados mais resultados associados ao domínio “Funções corporais” e “Atividade”, assim, sugere-se que sejam feitos mais estudos para verificar os efeitos da RV quanto à “Participação” e “Fatores ambientais”.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: This review aimed to address the effects of therapy with virtual reality in children and adolescents with cerebral palsy according to International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF), with the intention of gathering data that elucidate how the application of ICF can result in better understanding of the characteristics presented in a health situation. Methods: The articles were searched in the MEDLINE (Pubmed), PEDro, LILACS e SCIELO platforms, published until May 2019. Physiotherapy Evidence Database - PEDro was used as a method for evaluating, was included articles with a score ≥ 6 (six) in PEDro. Results: Six articles were included in this review. In general, significant results were observed regarding “Body functions” related to the improvement of upper and lower limb function after intervention with VR when compared to conventional therapy. In the “Activity” domain, we observed results in gait, balance and overall motor skills of children with CP after VR intervention. Conclusion: The effects of Virtual Reality in children with CP related to ICF are positive, but more results were found associated with the domain "Body functions" and "Activity", so it is suggested that further studies be done to verify the effects of VR on “Participation” and “Environmental Factors”.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/172431</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i2a172431</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 2 (2020); 113-119</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/172431/167769</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/172965</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-11-24T18:59:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Physical activity as a protective factor for extreme low weight in elderly assisted by a health care operator</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividade física como fator protetor para o extremo baixo peso em idosos assistidos por uma operadora de saúde</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Deborah Lorenzo Gomez</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>D'Oliveira, Rafaela Ramos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Kim, Beatriz Myung Jin</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Ana Flávia de Lima</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva Junior, Eduardo Antonio Barros</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Henrique Souza Barros de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Manso, Maria Elisa Gonzalez</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Services for the Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Nutritional Status</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Activity</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Life Style</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Serviços de Saúde para Idosos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estado Nutricional</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Atividade Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estilo de Vida</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Investigate the influence of factors related to multidimensional aspects of aging in a group of elderly assisted by the private health sector. Methods: Cross-sectional study conducted with 243 elders with a body mass index &amp;lt;23 kg/m² assisted by a health plan in the city of São Paulo, SP, Brazil, with them being allocated into two groups: low weight and extreme low weight. For data collection, a survey developed by the researchers themselves containing information related to multidimensional aspects of aging was employed. The obtained data were submitted to a descriptive analysis of the variables and a subsequent comparative analysis through Student’s t-distribution, Chi-squared or Fisher’s exact tests, when necessary. For variables with statistical significance, logistic regression was applied and the odds ratio, with a 95% confidence interval, was calculated. Results: It was observed that advanced age (p=0.044), mobility difficulty (p=0.011) and low levels of physical activity (p=0.021) significantly influence the elderly in extremely low weight nutritional status. Moreover, through the logistic regression model, it was found that, for this group, every hour of physical activity practiced by underweight elders, the risks of evolution to an extreme low weight status decrease by up to 14%. Conclusion: The regular and oriented practice of physical activity by the elderly with some degree of nutritional deficit is able to prevent and/or delay unwanted outcomes in susceptible groups.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Investigar a influência de fatores relacionados aos aspectos multidimensionais do envelhecimento em um grupo de idosos com baixo peso assistidos pelo setor privado de saúde. Métodos: Estudo transversal conduzido com 243 idosos com índice de massa corpórea &amp;lt;23 kg/m², todos assistidos por uma operadora de planos de saúde, no município de São Paulo, SP, Brasil, alocados em dois grupos: baixo peso e extremo baixo peso. Para a coleta dos dados empregou-se inquérito contendo informações relacionadas aos aspectos multidimensionais do envelhecimento. Os dados obtidos foram submetidos a análise descritiva das variáveis, com posterior análise comparativa através dos testes t Student e Qui-Quadrado ou exato de Fisher, quando necessário. Para variáveis com significância estatística, aplicou-se regressão logística e calculou-se as Odds Ratio, com intervalo de confiança de 95%. Resultados: Observou-se que, a idade avançada (p=0,044), dificuldade de mobilidade (p=0,011) e baixos níveis de atividade física (p=0.021) influenciam significativamente os idosos em estado nutricional de extremo baixo peso. Por meio do modelo de regressão logística, verificou-se que para cada uma hora de atividade física praticada pelos idosos deste grupo, os riscos de evolução para extremo baixo peso diminuem em até 14%. Conclusão: A pratica regular e orientada de atividade física praticada por idosos com algum grau de déficit nutricional é capaz de prevenir e/ou retardar desfechos indesejados em grupos susceptíveis.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/172965</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i1a172965</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 1 (2020); 41-44</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/172965/162679</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/172968</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-02T14:48:29Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Speed and accuracy of movement in individuals after stroke</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Análise da velocidade e acurácia de movimentos em indivíduos após acidente vascular encefálico</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Araújo, Gabriela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rossini, Nataly</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Ferrari, Aline Sanchez</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Monteiro, Carlos Bandeira de Mello</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Talita Dias da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Massetti, Thais</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fernani, Deborah Cristina Gonçalves Luiz</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dantas, Maria Tereza Artero Prado</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Stroke</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Skills</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Task Performance and Analysis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Acidente Vascular Cerebral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Destreza Motora</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Análise e Desempenho de Tarefas</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The Stroke might cause alterations in movement control due to the sequels of this process. Objective: Analyze the speed-accuracy trade-off of upper limb movement in individuals with sequels of Stroke through a computer software. Method: It is about a cross-sectional study, the sample was composed of 46 individuals divided into two groups: individuals post-stroke, between the ages of 35&#160; and 83 years old, in which 10 were women and 14 were men; and 22 healthy controls aligned by age and sex, in which 8 were women and 14 were men, evaluated through the instruments: Mini mental state examination, Orpington prognostic scale, Fugl-Meyer Assessment Scale, dynamometer, box of blocks and throught the software “Fitts Reciprocal Aiming Task v.2.0. (Horizontal)”, that seeks to understand the motor control of the upper limb, verifying the speed and accuracy of movement through a computer task. Results: The individuals with sequels of Stroke showed a loss in the strength of the palmar grip and manual function. Besides, they showed a longer time in movement in all index of difficulty compared to Control group. However, they showed a similar behaviour to the healthy individuals throughout the execution of the index of difficulty. Conclusion: Thus, it can be concluded that the individuals with sequels of Stroke showed a deficit of the motor control of the upper limb, compared to the healthy individuals, however, these showed the same behavior, with a bigger deficit in the accuracy of movement.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">The Stroke might cause alterations in movement control due to the sequels of this process. Objective: Analyze the speed-accuracy trade-off of upper limb movement in individuals with sequels of Stroke through a computer software. Method: It is about a cross-sectional study, the sample was composed of 46 individuals divided into two groups: individuals post-stroke, between the ages of 35&#160; and 83 years old, in which 10 were women and 14 were men; and 22 healthy controls aligned by age and sex, in which 8 were women and 14 were men, evaluated through the instruments: Mini mental state examination, Orpington prognostic scale, Fugl-Meyer Assessment Scale, dynamometer, box of blocks and throught the software “Fitts Reciprocal Aiming Task v.2.0. (Horizontal)”, that seeks to understand the motor control of the upper limb, verifying the speed and accuracy of movement through a computer task. Results: The individuals with sequels of Stroke showed a loss in the strength of the palmar grip and manual function. Besides, they showed a longer time in movement in all index of difficulty compared to Control group. However, they showed a similar behaviour to the healthy individuals throughout the execution of the index of difficulty. Conclusion: Thus, it can be concluded that the individuals with sequels of Stroke showed a deficit of the motor control of the upper limb, compared to the healthy individuals, however, these showed the same behavior, with a bigger deficit in the accuracy of movement.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-06-30</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/172968</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i2a172968</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 2 (2020); 100-106</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/172968/167768</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/173126</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-06-28T17:50:22Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Possibilidades de utilização da Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde (CIF) na saúde da criança: uma revisão sistemática</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Use of the International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF) in child health: a systematic review</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Pereira, Gabriela Santos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Santos, Heyriane Martins dos</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Gonçalves, Thais Nogueira Simões</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Brandão, Thayane Correa Pereira</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Fonseca Junior, Paulo Roberto</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Soraia Micaela</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">ncapacidade e Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Saúde da Criança</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Avaliação em Saúde</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">International Classification of Functioning</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Disability and Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Child Health</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Health Evaluation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: Synthesize the possibilities of using the International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF) in children's health. Methods: The review process followed the recommendations of PRISMA (Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyzes). The review was carried out in the MEDLINE (Pubmed), LILACS and SciELO databases, comprising studies in English, Portuguese or Spanish, published until 2018. Results: 2375 studies were identified, of which 1145 were excluded due to duplication, leaving 1230 for analysis. In the end, 29 articles were chosen for the elaboration of this study. It was possible to observe a great diversity of use of the ICF, from use as outcomes of clinical trials, use of the biopsychosocial model and use of ICF concepts and categories. All components of the ICF were mentioned among the studies, with greater emphasis on the component of bodily functions and activity and participation. Conclusions: ICF is an important and useful tool for the classification of children's functionality holistically in clinical trials, observational studies and in clinical practice. In addition, it is possible to monitor child development on the basis of ICF qualifiers.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Sintetizar as possibilidades de utilização da Classificação Internacional de Funcionalidade, Incapacidade e Saúde (CIF) na saúde da criança. Métodos: O processo de revisão seguiu as recomendações do PRISMA (Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses). A revisão foi realizada nas bases de dados MEDLINE (Pubmed), LILACS e SciELO, compreendendo estudos em inglês, português ou espanhol, publicados até 2018. Resultados: Foram identificados 2375 estudos, destes, 1145 foram excluídos por duplicidade, restando 1230 para análise. Ao final, 29 artigos foram eleitos para a elaboração deste estudo. Foi possível observar grande diversidade de utilização da CIF, desde uso como desfechos de ensaios clínicos, uso do modelo biopsicossocial e uso de conceitos e categorias da CIF. Todos os componentes da CIF foram citados dentre os estudos, com maior ênfase para o componente de funções corporais e atividade e participação. Conclusões: A CIF é uma ferramenta importante e útil para a classificação da funcionalidade de crianças de forma holística em ensaios clínicos, estudos observacionais e na prática clínica. Além disso, é possível fazer acompanhamento evolutivo do desenvolvimento infantil a partir dos qualificadores da CIF.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2022-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/173126</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v29i1a173126</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 29 n. 1 (2022); 56-66</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/173126/180945</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2022 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/173136</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-11-24T18:59:27Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Esp.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Nursing homes during the pandemic COVID-19 crisi: SOBRAMFA strategies, an efficient models</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Residenciais de idosos durante a crise do COVID-19: a gestão SOBRAMFA, um modelo eficaz</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Blasco, Pablo González</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Levites, Marcelo Rozenfeld</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moreto, Graziela</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Janaudis, Marco Aurelio</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>De Benedetto, Maria Auxiliadora Craice</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Residential Facilities</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Medical Care</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Coronavirus Infections</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Aged</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Instituições Residenciais</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Cuidados Médicos</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Infecções por Coronavirus</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Idoso</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A atual pandemia pelo COVID-19 nos faz viver tempos difíceis e inéditos. Os esforços de todos os profissionais de saúde, cada um nas suas competências, são essenciais. Enquanto pesquisadores e cientistas se debatem procurando recursos terapêuticos eficazes, aqueles que estão na linha de frente devotam seus melhores esforços no cuidado clinico dos pacientes afetados. A cada dia que passa mostra-se imprescindível o cuidado da própria equipe de saúde. Não apenas o cuidado físico (para o qual se tomam todas as providências possíveis em cada caso) mas também da saúde mental. Um elemento da equipe de saúde desanimado, pessimista, sem perspectiva é também um fator de crise, provoca insegurança nos pacientes e nas famílias&amp;nbsp; -mais ainda da que lhes chega habitualmente da mídia - e&amp;nbsp; nada ajuda na equipe de saúde. Torna-se preciso levantar o moral dos que lidam diariamente com esta ameaça de proporções antes nunca vistas.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">The current pandemic for COVID-19 makes us live difficult and unprecedented times. The efforts of all health professionals, each in their own competencies, are essential. While researchers and scientists struggle to find effective therapeutic resources, those on the front line devote their best efforts to the clinical care of affected patients. With each passing day, the care of the health team itself is essential. Not only physical care (for which all possible measures are taken in each case), but also mental health. A discouraged, pessimistic member of the health team, without perspective is also a factor of crisis, it causes insecurity in patients and families - even more than what usually comes to them from the media - and nothing helps the health team. It is necessary to raise the morale of those who deal daily with this threat of proportions never seen before.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2020-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/173136</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v27i1a173136</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 27 n. 1 (2020); 1-3</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/173136/162670</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2020 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/173469</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-23T18:11:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Orig.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiological profile of patients with amiotrophic lateral sclerosis accompanied in the Associação de Assistência à Criança Deficiente</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">Perfil epidemiológico dos pacientes com esclerose lateral amiotrófica acompanhados na Associação de Assistência à Criança Deficiente</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Silva, Rafael Santos Ferreira da</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Lira, Letícia da Silva</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Freitas, Simone Ferreira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Dylewski, Viviana</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rocco, Fernanda Moraes</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Oliveira, Clarissa Barros de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Rodrigues, Nádia Baggio Barreto</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Motor Neuron Disease</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Epidemiology</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Doença dos Neurônios Motores</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Esclerose Amiotrófica Lateral</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Epidemiologia</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS) is a neurodegenerative disease characterized by irreversible loss of motor neurons in the spinal cord, brainstem and cerebral cortex, leading to muscle atrophy, spasticity and consequently death. Objective: To verify the prevalence of ALS in the Associação de Assistência à Criança Deficiente (AACD) – Ibirapuera’s unit and to characterize the individuals affected by the disease during the rehabilitation process, in order to draw an epidemiological profile of this population. Methods: This is a retrospective study, based on information contained in medical records, referring to a study conducted during the period from January 2008 to January 2018, being a data search guided by a resource developed for this study. Results: The prevalence of patients with ALS in the treatment of neuromuscular diseases is 11.6%. The profile of these patients is slightly higher in white females, with a mean age of 59 years, with systemic arterial hypertension being the most common comorbidity. The most common ALS was sporadic, and Riluzole was the most commonly used drug. There was great variability of physiotherapeutic objectives and an increase in the use of non-invasive mechanical ventilation. There was no association between the presence of gait in the last evaluation and the time of the patient in physical therapy. Conclusion: The objectives are in agreement with the literature, as well as it cites the importance of knowing the population better to have a multidisciplinary approach more suitable for these patients.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">A Esclerose Lateral Amiotrófica (ELA) é uma doença neurodegenerativa caracterizada por perda irreversível dos neurônios motores da medula espinal, tronco encefálico e córtex cerebral, levando à atrofia muscular, espasticidade e consequentemente à morte. Objetivo: Verificar a prevalência da ELA na Associação de Assistência à Criança Deficiente (AACD) – Unidade Ibirapuera e caracterizar os indivíduos acometidos quanto à evolução da doença durante o processo de reabilitação, a fim de traçar um perfil epidemiológico desta população. Métodos: Trata-se de um estudo retrospectivo, baseado em informações contidas em prontuário, referentes a pacientes que realizaram reabilitação durante o período de janeiro de 2008 a janeiro de 2018, sendo a busca pelos dados guiada a partir de formulário desenvolvido exclusivamente para este estudo. Resultados: A prevalência dos pacientes com ELA em tratamento na clínica de doenças neuromusculares é de 11,6%. O perfil desses pacientes é ligeiramente maior do sexo feminino de cor branca, com uma média de idade de 59 anos, sendo a hipertensão arterial sistêmica a comorbidade mais encontrada. A forma de ELA mais frequente foi a esporádica, e o medicamento mais utilizado foi o Riluzole. Houve grande variabilidade de objetivos fisioterapêuticos e aumento do uso da ventilação mecânica não invasiva. Não houve associação entre a presença de marcha na última avaliação e o tempo do paciente em fisioterapia. Conclusão: Os objetivos estão de acordo com a literatura, bem como demonstram a importância de conhecermos melhor a população para termos uma abordagem multidisciplinar mais adequada para estes pacientes.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/173469</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i1a173469</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 1 (2021); 30-35</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/173469/171810</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:revistas.usp.br:article/173528</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-23T18:11:16Z</datestamp>
        <setSpec>actafisiatrica:Art.+Rev.</setSpec>
        <setSpec>driver</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
          <dc:title xml:lang="en-US">The effect of non-pharmacological intervention on bone mineral density in patients with spinal cord injury: a systematic review</dc:title>
          <dc:title xml:lang="pt-BR">O efeito da intervenção não farmacológica na densidade mineral óssea de pacientes com lesão medular: uma revisão sistemática</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Moreira, Rickella Aparecida Alves</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Paiva, Natália Silveira de</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Cichon, Flavio Rodrigo</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Imamura, Marta</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Souza , Daniel Rubio de</dc:creator>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Osteoporose</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Densidade Óssea</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Estimulação Elétrica</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Traumatismos da Medula Espinal/reabilitação</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="pt-BR">Exercício Físico</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Osteoporosis</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Bone Density</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Exercise</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Electric Stimulation</dc:subject>
          <dc:subject xml:lang="en-US">Spinal Cord Injuries/rehabilitation</dc:subject>
          <dc:description xml:lang="pt-BR">Objetivo: Avaliar os efeitos das medidas não farmacológicas na prevenção de perda ou no aumento da densidade mineral óssea de pacientes com lesão medular. Método: Revisão sistemática usando as bases de dados Medline, Embase, Cochrane Library e Lilacs com pesquisa entre 2009 e junho de 2019. Resultados: Foram encontrados 801 artigos dos quais foram selecionados, de acordo com os critérios de inclusão e exclusão, 15 artigos: 8 Estudos Clínicos Randomizados (ECR), 5 Estudos de Intervenção e 2 Revisões Sistemáticas. Conclusão: As evidências do uso de terapias não farmacológicas para prevenção e tratamento da osteoporose em LM são fracas e seus estudos contêm inúmeros vieses impossibilitando conclusões definitivas. O FES é a modalidade mais estudada e seu uso pode ser benéfico tanto para prevenção como para o tratamento da perda de massa óssea. Os resultados são observados com um uso frequente (5 sessões semanais) e associado a atividades físicas em especial as que promovam maior resistência muscular. Destacamos também que o retardo na perda de massa óssea está circunscrito ao período de aplicação, cessando após o término do mesmo. A associação de eletroestimulação e exercícios parece potencializar a ação medicamentosa, mas mais estudos são necessários para ratificar esta impressão. Intervenções não farmacológicas como o ortostatismo, atividades físicas, treino de marcha e a eletroestimulação são estratégias de baixo custo, baixo risco, poucos efeitos colaterais e com inúmeros outros benefícios na reabilitação de lesados medulares. Por isso, ainda que não tenhamos evidências consistentes de ação na massa óssea, estão fortemente recomendados.</dc:description>
          <dc:description xml:lang="en-US">Objective: To evaluate the effects of non-pharmacological measures (exercise, orthostatism, electrical stimulation, gait training, vibrating platform and physical activity) in preventing loss or increasing bone mineral density in patients with spinal cord injury. Method: Systematic review using the Medline, Embase, Cochrane Library and Lilacs databases with research between 2009 and June 2019. Results: 801 articles were found from which 15 articles were selected, according to the inclusion and exclusion criteria: 8 Randomized Clinical Studies (RCT), 5 Intervention Studies and 2 Systematic Reviews. Conclusions: Evidence of the use of non-pharmacological therapies for the prevention and treatment of osteoporosis in SCI is weak and its studies contain numerous biases making definitive conclusions impossible. FES is the most studied modality. Its use can be beneficial for both prevention and treatment of bone loss. The results are observed with frequent use (5 weekly sessions) and associated with physical activities, especially those that promote greater muscular resistance. The delay in the loss of bone mass is limited to the application period, stopping after the end of the application. The association of electrostimulation and exercise seems to enhance the medication action, but more studies are needed to confirm this impression. Non-pharmacological interventions such as orthostatism, physical activities, gait training and electrostimulation are low-cost, low-risk , have few side effects and a numerous other benefits in the rehabilitation of SCI. Therefore, although we do not have consistent evidence of action on bone mass, they are strongly recommended.</dc:description>
          <dc:publisher xml:lang="pt-BR">Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo</dc:publisher>
          <dc:date>2021-03-31</dc:date>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/article</dc:type>
          <dc:type>info:eu-repo/semantics/publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
          <dc:identifier>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/173528</dc:identifier>
          <dc:identifier>10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i1a173528</dc:identifier>
          <dc:source xml:lang="pt-BR">Acta Fisiátrica; v. 28 n. 1 (2021); 54-65</dc:source>
          <dc:source>2317-0190</dc:source>
          <dc:source>0104-7795</dc:source>
          <dc:language>por</dc:language>
          <dc:relation>https://www.revistas.usp.br/actafisiatrica/article/view/173528/171799</dc:relation>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">Copyright (c) 2021 Acta Fisiátrica</dc:rights>
          <dc:rights xml:lang="pt-BR">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0</dc:rights>
        </oai_dc:dc>
      </metadata>
    </record>
    <resumptionToken expirationDate="2023-08-08T14:49:39Z" completeListSize="935" cursor="750">53a95be81fb77266768c9a4b49fbd9c0</resumptionToken>
  </ListRecords>
</OAI-PMH>
